And the last thing I was going to talk about, but I'm now at the end is some advanced
scenarios, which are brand new to DebugPX and you guys can take a look at and ask questions about if you want
to dig into them, in particular, to what you were talking about setting that debugger hidden attribute.
If it's on code you don't own, but you want to set that, you can do it with this.
So I have this Set-CommandDebug mode and I can turn it on for an entire module.
So if I'm debugging and calling code that calls other modules that I don't want to debug, I can basically say
turn the debugging off for that module, so then I can set breakpoints whether they're command breakpoints or
variable breakpoints and steps through only my stuff and take the other stuff as if it's a black box and
don't touch it. So it's very handy as well because you're often consuming, especially with PowerShell gallery,
you download script modules, you run them, and you don't want to debug those, you want to debug your code
that's running those, hopefully, unless they're not very well written modules.
So that's all I've got today. If you guys have more questions, I will be around all week.
I'm happy to pull, go aside, and talk about some of things in more detail or you can contact me through
on my slide deck, which you will receive. This is a link to the modules I talked about and
this is my contact information for reaching out to me, so feel free to contact me any time.
I'm happy to help.