So debugging PowerShell is an interesting thing because debugging PowerShell often starts, well always pretty
much starts with dealing with errors. And when dealing with errors,
it doesn't really matter who or what level of experience the people who are using PowerShell have.
Most people get really hung up on the notion of red error text where you'll find very seasoned people working
in the industry for a long time, maybe even have done scripting, they run a command that you gave them,
and they say it's red and that's all that they give you. They just it's errored, it's red, and in the error text,
if they look at it, the actual solution the text is right there in front of them it tells them specifically
what was wrong and so you walk over to the screen and you tell them how to decipher that error text as part
of the debugging steps and then you kind of start getting them beyond that, but some people like to actually
change the color by default through GPOs and what not, scripts, profile scripts just because it can make
things easier for people. So I'm just going to
load a helper function here first and you're going to see me flip back and forth a lot between this view and
the other one as I run stuff, so if you want me to jump back to something that you want me to explain or detail,
let me know. So here's just a simple example showing a typical error.
There's a lot of detail in here that's really useful, in particular, this is the kind of example where
somebody might just come to you with an error because it failed and says it can't find the path and you go
over to the machine and you say well it can't find the path because it says it can't find the path,
and so this is the kind of thing that you can run into even when working with seasoned pros.
So changing up the color is easy. If you're working in ISE, there's psISE.Options.ErrorForegroundColor,
so you can change the color to something that you like a little bit better and I mean that's blue on blue
so that's not a great example. Here's another one. You've got a wide variety with
System.Windows.Media.Colors to pick the color that you want makes it a lot easier, and actually just even
being experienced with PowerShell and reading through the texts through many, many years now,
switching the color makes a difference for me too. It's a small thing, it's seems silly, but it makes a
difference throwing this in your profile script and just using it for a little while, you might start
realizing that the text that's in the error message does pop out more and you start noticing more things that
are in it, so it's a cool technique to follow. Now something else you can do with error messages is so how
many people here are aware that there's more than one error category view or error view, I guess, one more way
that you can view error messages, only---I saw one person half raise their hand, so not many people.
So by default, when you look at error messages and you see text like this and the green down here, this is the
normal error view where you're going to see some detail text messages and some line and character positions
inside of the script that ran category information. You can also change the view to what's known as a
CategoryView, which is a much more terse view. So if I get that exact same error message in this CategoryView,
you can see here, all it's showing me is what's hidden inside of category info in the view above.
So if I select this text right here on this line, this is what it's showing me in the CategoryView and all
you do is you set this global variable to ErrorView = CategoryView and you get a more terse format, which is good
if you're experienced because it can get to the point more quickly sometimes and especially
if you're looking at the entire error variable a many, many errors one after another, this can just give you
a line by line, so you can scan it for things. So that's a good tip; however, the CategoryView and the
category information isn't always descriptive enough to tell you what's going on.
I mean, in this case, it's pretty simple because the error type is ItemNotFoundException.
You can see that the error message contains the path, so it really tells you, but there are cases where it's
more obtuse trying to figure out what's going on from the CategoryView, in which case, you can just flip it
back to ErrorView = NormalView, or technically, you can do ErrorView = Anything at all and anything at all,
it'll go back to the, let me run that command again, it goes back to the normal view for anything beyond CategoryView.
So inside of this logic that PowerShell uses, it's basically just searching for this string else NormalView,
so it doesn't really matter what you set it to. If you forget NormalView, just that it's something other
than CategoryView and you'll be good. If you're so inclined and you want to take a round with more error views,
there really should be more, I had written more. Small side story, I was installing software on my laptop
one day, running out of space quickly as I was installing Visual Studio.
Rather than cancelling the installation, which would have been the smarter thing to do and cleaning things
up and then installing the product afterwards, I decided I'll frantically go around and clean up some stuff
while it's installing. And so then I found myself holding down Shift+Delete on my keyboard while I was looking
at my Windows Explorer with my Modules folder selected. Ask myself, what do I do now?
And pressing Escape didn't dawn on me in that moment, and so I let it delete and tried using some delete recovery
tools to pull stuff back and I was able to get back 95% between that and things I'd emailed other people,
but I lost a little bit of content that way. So that's one argument for using version control.
But one of the things I lost was I had a module that allowed me to define some more error views and I had
some cool stuff and I haven't yet pulled that back in yet, but I intend to.
If you have things that you would like to see in error text by default that aren't there, let me know because
it's on my to do list to I don't know where I'll get to it, but it's in my short list of things I think about,
and so I think there really should be more views, so just please let me know.
My email address is right here. And by the way, all these scripts, I will share them so you don't have to
jot stuff down directly from here if you don't want to because you're going to get the content afterwards,
as well as the slides, as limited as they are. Beyond ErrorViews and the color, and this is going to sound
silly, but has anybody heard the expression talk to the bear? (Audience comment)
Yeah, same idea. So you've got a rubber duck, or your bear, or your Xamarin monkey, or whatever other stuffed
animal you keep hidden in your office put it on your desk when you have a problem and explain that problem
to it because a large percent of the time, you're going to find the solution to that problem by just
reiterating it yourself. So people who talk aloud, it actually does work.
So there's a reason why people talk to themselves and that's one.
And it's surprising. I mean how many people have had a question related to an issue and you go walk over to
a coworker an you're asking that question and as you're asking them, the light bulb comes on and you know the
answer to that question right? That's what the talking to the bear is.
So it's just about verbalizing what's in your mind already, so that you can release it and put it in front of
yourself by saying it and finding the solution.