Okay, so some debugging with breakpoints. Let me show you something really quick here.
I'm going to put a breakpoint and I run this. Okay, so I'm on a breakpoint right now and the breakpoint I'm
on is the first line in my script on Get-Service. When you're dealing with breakpoints, most people think of
in ISE these visual breakpoints where you go to a line and you just hit F9 to turn on a breakpoint and then
F5 to run your script and you work with the breakpoint from there.
And that's really useful and there are some things that you should know that you can do, so once you're on a
breakpoint, excuse me, and these work for on the PowerShell native console, as well, so if you're in server
core where you don't have ISE or just in some environment where you are working on the command-line,
you can still have breakpoints and look around and do debugging without it.
So you can use L to take a look at where you are and you can see the asterisk on the left-hand side showing
you where you're at. You can do, what are the other commands I want to show, K, the call stack, in this case,
there's only one call, but it's very useful to figure out which commands were invoked to get me to this point.
You can run H to see a list of all the commands I can run while I'm in the debugger and these are good to
learn and practice, especially stepInto, stepOver, and stepOut, knowing how those work.
StepInto will go into a function if you're calling the function, so you debug inside that function.
StepOut will if you're in a function because you stepped in accidentally, and you think I'm done debugging here,
I want to go up one level, it'll just run the rest of that code and then continue debugging at the next line
after the function call outside of the function. And stepOver is basically saying I don't want to go in this function.
I'm debugging something at the level I'm in right now, so that's where you stepOver.
So those are really useful, as well as continue basically says let it running or quit, I'm done debugging and
I want to stop debugging altogether. So learning how these commands work can be really helpful when you're debugging.
And there's also shortcuts, so if you're in ISE, you can learn shortcuts up here in the Debug menu,
F10, F11, Shift+F11, all of these, or of course, you can use the menu items if you like.
Yes. Have you heard of any way to automatically skip over like certain funky calls that you always wanted more?
Like say you have a log line and you log XML, but you never want to actually step into that and debug it,
you just want to always skip over that? So there is a property or it's an attribute.
So inside of a function, do you own the code? Okay, so if you own the code, at the very top of your function,
put System.Diagnostics.DebuggerHidden open bracket, close bracket inside of square brackets because it's an attribute.
You put that at the top and the debugger is going to totally ignore it.
It won't step in if you want it to. Thank you. You're welcome.
So, great question. So alright, working with debugger on these breakpoints is useful, but there are other
things you can do beyond the built-in breakpoints support in PowerShell that are kind of fun.
So I have this module called DebugPX, so I'm going to import it.
And now that I've imported it, I can just run Enter-Debugger and I'm in the debugger.
Or I can use BP or breakpoint because those are aliases for the command.
So I can now, maybe I've been working on a system where I don't have PowerShell ISE, but I have Notepad
because I'm on server core and I'm debugging something and I don't want to do line breakpoints because I don't
want to count where lines are, but I have the code. I can crack open my ps1 file in Notepad, type in breakpoint,
and then save the file, and then run it, and that'll be the debugger on that breakpoint.
And that's only if you're using DebugPX because that's part of the code that I've written and I've managed my own modules.
And it's the same the debugger as everything, right. So I can still look around, I can still get the help
information, it's just another way to enter the debugger. So now let me quit out of the debugger.
So yeah, BP's an alias. This one's kind of cool. It works in pipelines.
So if you're debugging something in the middle of it and you want to stop during the pipeline process,
you can just inject this breakpoint or enter debugger command right in the middle and that'll do it,
and you can also do it conditionally. So in this line right here, breakpoint, I'm going to stop when I'm on
the Windows update service in this pipeline. So I can run that and it runs through all my what ifs and then
when I hit Windows update, it stops. So if you're looking for some obscure conditions that happen in a pipeline,
this can be really useful in figuring out and stopping at that point in time because something actually
happened that you were waiting for. Oh, and they can also have reminder texts.
So sometimes you might have a situation that happens once in a while, really, really weird.
You can't figure it out. It's just a bug that shows up on three or four machines in your environment and
it's really, really just infrequent and you don't know what's going on.
Well you can put in those scripts if you wanted to, you can put a breakpoint with the condition basically
being that weird condition that you're looking for, and some message saying just notifying the person when it actually happens.
So if I run this, then I get this text BREAKPOINT ZOMG, it happened, to let me know.
You know, it could be call Kirk Munro because it's the issue he was looking for and then I can actually
troubleshoot and debug and see what's going on. So for weird stuff, that's kind of handy.
I don't use that often, but once in a while it can help.
Oh, and also all these breakpoint commands work in unsaved files.
They work if you're using F8, and of course, this is all PowerShell V3 or later.
PowerShell V5 has a wait debugger command, which is slightly different from this Enter debugger command that
I wrote a while back. There are some pros and cons to both. They do some things I don't do with jobs.
I do some things they don't do with conditional breakpointing, and messaging, and pipelining, and stuff,
so they both are complimentary and you can zoom both with version 5 if you like, as well.