A few more quick things. So I already talked about try/catch and why they're important.
I'll skip over that. This is interesting. If you're working with arrays, this one bites people all the time.
If you're working with arrays and you're doing comparisons, make sure the thing you're comparing the array
with is on the left-hand side unless you explicitly want to be comparing the items in the array with or any
collection for that matter. So for example, looking at this code, I create an array and it's empty, so I'll do that.
And now I'm going to say $X = null to see if my array is null and I get back nothing.
I don't get back true and I don't get back false, I get back nothing because PowerShell reads this and says okay,
I'm going to take every item that is in the collection called X and I'm going to compare it with null,
and if it matches, I'll give it to you. But there was nothing there, so I get nothing.
So these kind of things that seem like they should work, don't, and it's a common source of problems in scripts.
But if I do it the other way, $Null = X, then it actually tells me if the X variable is null or not.
So understanding that difference with collections is key because you need to think about are you comparing
the content of the collection, or the collection itself, and what you want to do with it.
There are a few more examples of that right here that you can run through, more of the same thing, just showing
how that works. And I talked about if something returns more than one value and you're trying to---oh yeah,
so actually I talked about what particularly figuring out where stuff comes from and I'll show you this
example as well. When you run commands in PowerShell, this is especially true in PowerShell V3 and 4 because
5 does some stuff that makes this not so much an issue, but it still is there.
If I run a command that I want to have the results stored in an array, I will always, always, always wrap that
in array enclosures 100% of the time because it's the only way you're guaranteed it's always going to be an array.
If I call Get-VM and there's only one VM, the results come back, I have a single object not in array.
In PowerShell V5, I could do .Count and it'll work because they put stuff in to handle that, but not in 3 and
I don't think it's in 4. I don't remember when they added that, but just it's worth making sure if you want
an array, explicitly wrap in array. It doesn't cost anything. You just wrap it with, so I just do array
enclosures and that tells me that I'm getting something and if it's one, if it's many, I want an array.
So it's good to know that tip. And some of these are comments that you guys can read over here on your own
since I'm running out of time. The only other thing I'll talk about here, yeah so preference variables,
so Get-Variable-Name* Preference. Being aware of these is really important when you're debugging to figure
out how things, to control the flow of what's going on. ErrorActionPreference, in particular, can be really useful.
But with ErrorActionPreference, this is okay, ErrorActionPreference = Stop.
That's basically saying in my command, treat any error as a terminating error and stop running immediately or
this using PSDefaultParameterValues to do the same thing, but don't do this.
People will do this in commands and it's not the right thing to do, ErrorActionPreference = Continue because
you're telling PowerShell, I don't care what the error is even though this weird error is happening that I
know is okay, so that's why I'm doing this. Any other error out of the sun that comes up is going to go by,
unless it's an actual terminating error because of being wrapped inside a try/catch and it'll just continue execution.
So don't do that in your scripts. Make sure you're controlling it, either turning it, this is okay,
turning errors on a more strict scenario, not the opposite, or use -ErrorAction line by line for the
commands that you run.