So enough about some lighter weight techniques and changing colors.
When you're dealing with errors, it's really important to be able to identify what the source of the error is,
and so I'm going to go through a few techniques to help identify what sources of errors are.
This first thing, I'm just priming the pump by putting an error in the system, so let me just run this,
and so I've got 20 errors that I just through into my Error array and you can look at errors inside of $Error.
It's just an array list, so if I run that, it flies by pretty quick and there's 20 errors there, a few different
types thrown in with a randomizer just to make it interesting. And so, when you're dealing with this,
how many people have written a script and you
run it and then you get error, error, error, error, error, error because they're not necessarily all terminating right?
There's a notion of terminating errors, which is an error that when your script or your module hits it, stops dead.
You've got one error, which is great for a focus because you know exactly where you've got to look,
but it also masks other errors that are going to show up probably afterwards as you go through the debugging
techniques and steps to work stuff out. So a lot of times though, a lot of errors you get in PowerShell are
non-terminating and when you're dealing with it, it can be challenging from a large list.
Where do you start?
So you can use PowerShell itself to help prioritize what the errors are.
And so generally speaking when I do talks, I don't use aliases and what not.
Here I am because we're talking about debugging and since we're talking about debugging, I'm assuming a
certain base knowledge of PowerShell. If you see an alias that you don't understand up here, raise your hand,
let me know, I'll explain it,
but most of these are pretty boarder plate. I mean, some people might not know that you can use short hand
for parameter names, so -Des is short for description and since it's unambiguous in the Sort Object cmdlet,
it'll find it. But the for the most part, I'm just using a few aliases.
So one thing that's great when you have a whole lot of errors is to group them, so this command is going to
take all my errors, group them together, sort them in descending order by count, and then give me the count
and name, so I can prioritize. So you run a command like that and all of a sudden, that list of 20 errors
because much more digestible. So I can prioritize by what's most common and very quickly figure out what are
things I want to fix first according to how frequently they're happening.
I mean, the numbers can be a bit misleading, right, because you could be doing it inside of a loop and you
could have one bug that's much higher priority versus something that happens 50 times because you ran it
inside of a loop, but it still helps just in terms of digesting stuff and that mental blockage of getting rid
of 50 errors at once because of this, you sort of think it is by group, so you can start breaking down the
barriers and getting to the end solution more quickly, can be very helpful.
So leverage PowerShell's sorting and grouping capabilities when you're processing large amounts of errors to
really see what's going on. And the other thing that's cool here too
is this is pulling out all the source code, all of the line references, and the character references,
and just giving me the text, which is really useful in terms of just reading what's going on, there's nothing red
up there and I might be able to figure out from that exactly what's going on.
If I can't, I can go into $Error and see what line numbers things happened on and figure things out from there.
Questions so far?
Okay. So beyond processing large quantities of errors, there are a lot of details in errors that are very
worthwhile looking at when you're troubleshooting. So if I run this, okay, is that a good example?
Yeah, that's fine. So let me go back again. So we're at this again.
So here I'm looking at some error details for one of the particular errors and actually let me do one more
thing first that I didn't have in my script. So I'm going to pass the entire collection out to FormatList *
because I want to highlight something. (Scrolling) Now they're actually all showing the details, so I must
have a load---I've got a module called DebugPX that makes it so when I pipe to FormatList *, I don't have to
do -Force because typically when you run and that might still be loaded, let me just, bear with me one second.
No, it's not there. So typically when you pipe to Format List * from the error,
you're just going to see the exact same text that you see when the error shows up on screen.
You're not going to see properties on the left column with values on the right.
Typically when you run error and pipe the format list, you just won't see that because the way the PowerShell
team has implemented error formatting, it basically says I don't care what you told me you want,
unless you force it, I'm not going to give it to you, which is a bit silly and I think it's a bit of a design flaw.
So in one of the things I worked on is this module called DebugPX and I will get to that, but DebugPX makes
it so I don't have to, or sorry not DebugPX, FormatPX, that's why because FormatPX is loaded.
I have a bunch of modules and when I load them, they do work for me that I forget about because I load them
underneath my profile, so I forget to clear my profile afterwards.
So go back to this. Here's what you typically see, Error 0 format list* shows the exact same thing I would
have got when the error came up. There, glad I figured that out.
And if I want to see it, the whole thing, I have to pipe it to Format List * -Force and that's because of what
I was talking about, it would help PowerShell just implicitly think that I'm only going to give you this
error text, but it really is for the look of the properties
because when you're dealing with errors, you're often dealing with exceptions, and so there's an exception
property that you can dig into to figure out what's going on, if it's coming from internal code in PowerShell,
or a binary cmdlet, or a DLL, or something in .NET that you called, well that's going to come in often in the
form of an exception, and so getting out that exception detail is important.
Target object. That's important because what object was being referenced when this error came up.
Was it a file on my system? Was it a string path? So when the error path does not exist comes up,
that target object should be set to the path that didn't exist so I can figure out what's going on.
The category info, you see that by default. Other useful things are your StackTrace, ScriptTrackTrace,
and I'll get into that in a second, and InvocationInfo, but there's a lot of interesting hidden stuff that's
there that by default you don't get unless you pipe to force. So you use the force when you're looking at
errors or now I'll load the module that I had forgotten I had loaded and wait.
I have a load order that's required for one of my modules. Now I'm back normal.
And so yeah, with FormatPX loaded, FormatPX recognizes that when you pipe from an error to FormatList * or
FormatTable * for some format cmdlet, that you probably really wanted it to give it to you that format,
and so it respects that and just works around this one little quirk and FormatPX is up in the gallery.
All the modules I work on I put up in the gallery. And so now I get by default all of these full information
from my error messages when I wipe the FormatList *. So when you're looking at that, I mentioned there's
exceptions, right, so you can do, they're objects, .NET objects, same as everything else, so I can ask for
the exception and that again shows me text, not properties. And so I have to pipe that to FormatList and
again I would normally have to use the force if I was not using FormatPX to take care of it for me and then I
can gather all this information inside of my exception. And sometimes, there are inner exceptions,
and so certain times you can run into an error. This doesn't happen all that often, but it does happen
where the error happens several layers deep through a whole bunch of logic and DLLs and so you go from your
top level error to your exception, which had an inner exception, which may have another inner exception,
and so be aware of this inner exception property on exceptions because if the error that shows up is not
obvious to you off the top, what's going on,
it may be because the text that's exposed at the outside of the error is not descriptive enough to what
actually happened under the covers and you have to dig in. So yeah, just go
through looking at your error messages and look at these inner exceptions, in this case, there is none for this
particular error, but make sure you're aware of the .InnerException and that can recourse to multiple inner
exceptions and sometimes,
you dig through a few layers and you look at the text that's there and it's clear as day what went wrong,
but because of details of code and how logic works and how things don't necessarily always bubble up to the
top in the right way, it's just hidden from you. So dig through and you can find a lot of
interesting things. Leveraging the StackTrace. So I showed you in the FormatList * there is a
ScriptStackTrace and that's great for locations that are inside of PowerShell functions or scripts or modules
that are script modules because it will show you the StackTrace of the logic that went through to get to that
error, which can be very helpful in debugging and figuring out what's going on and there is also a StackTrace
that is for when you're dealing with compiled locations and cmdlets and DLLs that's on the actual exception,
or InnerException,
or InnerException.InnerException, and so on. So you can dig through and you can look at logic, and so this
is a bigger StackTrace because this particular error came from binary code and less from PowerShell code.
I mean there was one line in my ScriptBlock that really didn't tell me anything, but I can see, I look at this
from the, it's about, right, so the most the call the actually through the exception wasn't lookup
command information at the very top, System.Management.Automation.CommandDiscovery.LookUpCommandinfo.
So you look at this from a top-down from that's where the error happened to that was the first call in the
binary code that I invoked and it can be helpful just to figure out what logic was happening, what things went
through when the actual error came up.
This is by the way, this can be intimidating to people dealing with StackTrace is and going through the stuff,
but don't be afraid to roll up your sleeves, try it, if you can't figure something out, and need some help,
you can email me, ask a coworker, go to powershell.org on the forums, people can now help you figure these
things out, and you start knocking them off one at a time and working with this stuff, and it becomes a lot
easier relatively quickly.
The other thing, when you're dealing with a large quantity of errors, rather than leaving them lying around
in your $Error variable, I personally like to clean up my error variable because
when I like to just be lazy and do $Error and look at everything that's in it, but if I leave it around for a
long time, then I have a whole lot of stuff that I don't care about that I already dealt with a while ago,
so it's just a collection. You can clean things up.
So if you dealt with an error, you can remove that particular error just by .Remove with the actual error
itself or you can use index, so that removes just the particular topmost item in the error stack or I can
remove an entire range. This is going to remove from 0 to 10. Or I can clear the whole thing.
And so these are useful as you go through and deal with errors that you have just so you don't always have
older things you've dealt with kicking around because then you can be lazy and do $Error and see you did a
catch anything and no nothing came up, so good. So that's dealing with error details.