Okay, hi everybody. Thanks for coming. I did already push the button, so you don't have to ask to make sure.
I want to talk to you guys today about something that I spend a lot of time doing, which is debugging PowerShell.
I've been working with PowerShell for 10 years now and I worked on, in past lifetimes, Power GUI as an evangelist
and then later on as an architect and as a product manager
and I used to work on Power WF and Power SD, so I've been working on PowerShell and PowerShell tools for
quite a long time, especially in the past with the tool side of the fence.
And so through all that work, I've done a lot of debugging and I've come up with a lot of tips and tricks
that I use and I'm constantly, I guess the curious side of me is always creating, I think looking for ways to
create new tools that make debugging even easier and tinker around with how things work under the covers and
finding cool solutions that weren't necessarily readily available before.
So the talk I want to give today is about sharing of that back with you.
All of the content that I'm sharing here works on PowerShell V3 and later, so this is not bleeding edge
latest and greatest, you have to have V5, otherwise it's no good to you.
If you're using version 3 or later, anything I talk about here, you guys are going to be able to use,
unless I call it something and specifically from a new version, in which case I'll highlight that, but in general
that's the way that I'm going to roll with this.
So who am I? My name's Kirk Munro. I go by the nickname, Poshoholic.
If you want to contact me, that's my Twitter handle, poshoholic.com, poshoholic@gmail.com,
poshoholic@hotmail.com, you kind of get the drift. If you want to look for me somewhere around the web,
just look for that handle and then you can find me and reach out to me.
I work for, these days, by the way, I work for a company called Provance Technologies, which is we specialize
in IT solutions management and I'm a technical product manager there still doing a lot of PowerShell in that space.
I've been with them for the past three years and just doing PowerShell as well on the
side as a hobby and passion at home.
So the agenda is just talking about a collection of PowerShell modules that I've written that help make
debugging and defensive scripting easier, some tips and tricks, recommendations, best practices,
things you can avoid, and hopefully, you'll come out of this a bit more enlightened in some of the things you
might run into in debugging your own work, and so that it'll ring a bell when you run into it later and maybe
think of some of these solutions and ideas and be able to get through your issues more quickly.
And because it's about debugging, I can't really teach about debugging PowerShell from a slide deck,
so all the content that I'm going to do from here on is going to be in PowerShell ISE and doing demos because
it's going to make learning it a lot easier to see firsthand.
By the way, any questions that anybody has, don't feel you have to save them for the end.
Interrupt me at any time. If I don't see you, just speak up and grab my attention.
I don't have this scripted down to the wire and timed to the last minute.
I leave breathing room for working with the audience and if there are particular things you want me to drill in
deeper on or have questions about, bring it up and I'll see where I can fit it and how I can handle it.
And if I can't handle it here or can't answer the questions here, I'll be happy to do research and figure out
or talk to you after the fact in one of the side rooms or in the hall and see what I can do to help as well.