There's a lot of error management and error troubleshooting that happens without necessarily dealing with
running through a debugger and putting breakpoints and stepping through code.
A lot of stuff could happen just from using tooling to do work for you.
So dealing with historical information. I mean I put this in here just kind of as a joke.
This isn't really, this is just from my TypePX module where I can do all sorts of interesting things on numbers
and relative dates and what not, it's one of the modules I work on, but the module I'm talking about for
debugging purposes is HistoryPX. So let me make sure I don't have it loaded.
No, I don't. Good. So historical information. I've read a lot of commands inside this session here and I
can hit h, actually let me do with the latest 10. So there's the 10 most recent messages, which just shows
me what I ran and not even fully because it's truncated with … and it gives me some id numbers so if I want to
re-run something, but that's not really that useful, so let me just, I'm going to give you an example here.
Let me clear the history, no leave the history that's there because I want to go to number three soon.
I'm just going to prime the pump here and I want to throw a few things in that are interesting about historical commands.
So this code does the same thing twice, right? The first thing is it calls, it does 1 divided by 0,
which is divided by 0 error, it's going to throw an exception, and then it calls just put some string will it blend.
And on the second part, which is the try/catch block, does the exact same thing inside of a try/catch handler
and it's an important detail to follow when you're dealing with error handling because if you look at the way
those two things ran, so the codes all up at the top there and then you see the first error shows up and you
see will it blend the text because that text still ran. So even though, 1 divided by 0 resulted in an exception,
when I ran it, everything that happened afterwards after my semicolon still ran and went through.
But then look at the second example. So after the will it blend, then there's an attempt to divide by 0
exception and there's no string. Why not? Anybody know? (Audience Answer)
Exactly. So divide by 0 is a terminating exception, unless you don't put it inside of a try/catch block,
which is a gotcha in PowerShell because there a lot of places where an exception terminates and it's meant
to terminate, it's an exception basically saying hold on, you're doing something really wrong here, but if you
don't wrap it in try/catch, then it's not going to terminate. So if you write functions that have an
exception that is terminating exception, but you don't wrap it in try/catch, it'll do everything afterwards
and it'll just continue running. It won't stop your function from executing the rest of the code,
which may have unexpected consequences depending on what it does.
So as a rule of thumb, even though I might sound cumbersome, I try/catch everything.
Every begin process and end block in my functions have a try/catch at the top-level.
Every single one. Every script I write, try/catch. Absolutely everything because that's the only way when
you're writing PowerShell that you can guarantee that you get the same behavior every single time.
If you don't, somebody else may put try/catch around it calling your function or your script and get different
behavior because theirs is going to stop on an exception that yours let go through and just generate an
error, which you may think is just benign and you think, okay, well that's fine.
It's generates an error, but still does all this other stuff, except that other stuff doesn't run because
they called it inside a try/catch block, which is a bit of a challenge, and so it's better to write your
code so that it is robust and runs the same way every single time, so I try/catch absolutely everything.
But when you do that, and I go, so I just ran that and I got you different examples, now I'm going to look
at this history and this time I'm going to pipe it to from that table.
So if you look at the last two entries here 41 to 42, they're doing the same piece of code right?
Starting at 41 and 42, oh that's right, wait a second. Because I ran it as a block, it treats it as one command.
So I'm going to run it twice, each piece by itself. So I'll run that and then I'll run the other one.
Now when I look at the history, there, so 44 and 45, and pipe that to FormatTable, this tells me,
it gives me a better example of what actually happened, right. So 44 completed, even though it was a
terminating exception that completed because it kept on running versus 45 failed.
So by using try/catch, it will also be detectable in your history to see where something actually had a
terminating exception versus not.
Even though these commands completed, they may have generated errors.
You can't see that from this. This is the built-in history. So the only thing you can get here is
terminated with error or not from the execution
status state, but I've come up with a solution to help work around that.
So I'm going to import HistoryPX, that's also in the gallery, and now I'm going to just create a bunch of errors.
I think I can run all these together. Yeah, we'll run those ones.
So there I just generated a bunch of different error messages and now let me show you the count of the most
recent commands I've ran. So now, actually sorry again because I ran them all at once, I've got to do this
one at a time. It's one of the hard parts about when you're just demonstrating debugging and you want to run
commands one at a time is you have to do it one off. So now that he did that, there.
So, HistoryPX takes history and extends it. It will calculate the duration, so if you're doing any kind of
benchmarking around your scripts and your commands and you want to see how long one run had verses another and
you tweak your code here and there and you want to automatically detract things, well you can just have version
A, B, C of a script, for example, and run each one and then look at the durations and figure out which one
took the longest. It'll show you success or failure. It'll show you the number of errors.
It gives you output, so if you had a command that you ran that generated certain amount of output, how many objects
were output, so the number assign at output. The number of signs source is how many commands, how many lines
in that command that I ran generated output, and I'll get to that one in a minute.
It can be really useful because sometimes you run a command that's unexpecting, so that generates unexpected output.
So here's an example. Look at this function, New-ArrayListWithOneItem.
It's pretty straightforward, right. I just go in and create a new array list, add integer and value to it,
and return the array list to the caller. So I'll load that, and now I'm going to run it, and now when I look
at the results, I get two records.
Anybody know why? Nope. (Audience comment) Yes. So
ArrayList.Add returns the index of the value that was added to the array list and there are methods like this
all over .NET.
You call into some method and it does the work you want and returns a value that you don't need,
but you might not know that unless you look at the method signature and when you're dealing with this kind of
a thing in a very large command that you run and goes and gets, maybe it pulls the list of the virtual
machines from all of your Hyper-V servers and your infrastructure and outputs one and you're trying to figure
out where that comes from, that can be really challenging.
so that's where the number of sources is useful because I can run that same command,
New-ArrayListWithOneItem. I get the two results back and then I can take a look at the history.
So if I, well actually yeah, I'll show you the properties I'm working with first.
So inside of my history extension from HistoryPX, there are errors and error counts so you can go and look at
those collections in the default output. You only see the counts, but you could actually look at the errors
for any particular command after it ran. You can look at the output after it ran.
So you ran a command, you forgot to capture the output and it went across the wire and did something,
it took a while, and you think oh shoot, I meant to put that in a variable, it's got it for you.
Output sources and output sources count. That's what I wanted to talk about with respect to this particular command.
So I already ran it, so now I can look at, actually going to do it again here because I want to have it in
the right sequence, so I'm going to get the most recent history entry, Get-History-Count1 and look at the output source.
And so look at the top one in the text property, al.Add 1 returns something, so it tells me what line
returned it, the line number, the starting column number, and so that's all the metrics about where it was
inside of my command that I ran, what was actually returned, which is
really cool when you're trying to find these kind of issues because it just can be a challenge when you have
that needle in the haystack returning something that you didn't expect and you don't want to do a lot of
commenting and uncommenting of code to figure it out and try to figure out where that particular piece is.
And you don't have to think about turning it on. I mean, as long as you have HistoryPX loaded, which by the
way, you have to load manually because HistoryPX contains a lot of commands that are proxies for existing
commands, so natively is not going to, when you're on Get-History it's not going to say oh you want to load
HistoryPX because Get-History is on the box. So if you want to use HistoryPX and you like this,
then download install the module and put import module HistoryPX in your profile and you're good,
and it'll always track the data for you.
Let's see. Oh, so you can also manage the configuration, so if I run this command.
So one of the concerns with HistoryPX that I have heard in the past is that what about if I go and get thousands
and thousands and thousands of records. I don't want you storing that all on my session inside of the history
variable so that you're building up my memory in my PowerShell session and consuming my resources on my system.
So it, by default, takes a fairly light tactic for memory, yeah, for making sure it doesn't consume too much
memory, so it'll only store the extended history information for the last 200 commands you ran and a maximum
of 1,000 output items per command so that you don't end up having too much of a huge memory footprint,
but you can call Set-ExtendedHistoryConfiguration and change this.
So it's up to you to figure out how much you want to store, if you want to store more and you can do that,
as well, in your profile. Another thing I put in, and this is kind of experimental this one, so when you're
dealing with history and you have commands that you ran and you forgot to get results, and it's great that it
captures it for you, but there's also, you may have seen Lee Holmes put out a I think it was Tweet or a blog
post talking about something about variable for capturing output automatically and that works some of the time,
but not in every case, and so HistoryPX takes that a bit further and builds it in.
So if I run this command, Get-Service, now I can do $__ because we didn't have enough $__.
$__ basically says take the last collection of stuff that you got and show it to me again,
which is really cool when you're doing interactive, I'm in the command-line running commands,
figuring out where properties are, and modifying my script at the same time, back to the command-line doing
some more work, back to my script adding the code because I can do things like look at the values in $__,
so I can look at the names and notice that the $__ doesn't change.
I'm still working with the same collection of services, but when I'm referencing properties in $__,
HistoryPX is smart enough to think well you're just digging around, so I'm not going to take those values
and overwrite what I stored, I'll just let you dig around and go on your way.
If I call Get-Help, it's not going to store that because who wants to store Get-Help and $__.
So it has a collection of things that it tracks and other stuff that it says oh, I'm not going to worry with that.
And so, even after I run Get-Help, I still have that same collection I had from before keeping track of things.
And so the way that works is I have this Get-CaptureOutputConfiguration because it's all about capturing
output, and in capturing output, there is excluded types, oh and also there's capture value types and capture
null, so those are both turned off by default because value types are things like ints and strings,
so it's just going to ignore those altogether and not store them because, again, it's not really saving any time.
But for collections and actual .NET objects that are rich, it'll store them, but you can configure that and
you can change how that works. So if I look at the ExcludedTypes, then I can see these are all the types that
it's going to ignore by default. It's a system of strings in there, helping if we're short,
MamlCommandHelpInfo. It's going to ignore results from Get-Member and Get-Command and Get-Variable
because those are things we very frequently call just to go and look stuff up that we don't necessarily want
to store and overwrite something that we're working in as I'm doing this rapid back and forth on the command-line
figuring out some properties and methods and then off on my script running the work.
So I like this a lot because it helps me switch back and forth without always having to think about putting
something into a variable to do the work I needed to do, and you can configure this, you can remove things
from this, exclude type lists, or add things if you want to, and it'll track or not track accordingly.