Now data is a liability. You might be thinking what does that mean?
So there was a very recent breach, a very interesting breach from the Ashley Madison website.
So they're an adultery website. They probably thought that their most precious resource, their most precious commodity
was like the PayPal information that was inside their databases, credit card information, but realistically,
people are used to those things getting breached and they get their notifications and they're like oh that
sucks, I've got to change these things again. Their most precious commodity was trust.
When you're doing a website that's all about flying under the radar, the minute you lose trust, you're done.
The Ashley Madison site got breached. All of that sensitive data that really was not crucial to the Ashley
Madison business then became a liability that leaked and within 6 months, they had lost 80% of their business.
I checked again
a couple days ago and it's gone down again, so their now down to more like 90% of their business.
The 10% that remains, if you take a look at the web traffic, is from countries that don't speak English.
They just weren't part of the news cycle.
So data is clearly a liability. If you don't need the data, then you shouldn't store it, right.
This comes true when you talk about storing customer data. If you don't actually need access to this data, encrypt it.
Let the customers be the only people who have
access to the data. That solves you from the dangers of an attacker coming and stealing a bunch of personal
information that you don't actually need access to. A perfect example of this is just the way that's appropriate
to do with passwords. When people create login systems for websites, well you don't store literally the
usernames and passwords, you used to, but if that database gets breached, now you have everybody's usernames and passwords.
So that the technique there is instead to store their username or whatever and then a hash of their passwords.
Now the hash of their passwords that you prove that they knew the password without ever storing the password itself.
So there's an example of treating data as a liability.
Now success. Don't let success be your downfall. Some interesting things to ask yourself, right.
So what if every host in my entire network had this bit of software?
What if every person in the world was connected to my service and was subject to the same rules or whatever else.
A good example would be think about some obscure Android distribution that has a picture taking application to
share it up to Twitter
and maybe they hit a bug that was including the GPS information of where the person was when they took the picture.
That person might be like, that distribution might be like, well that kind of sucks, we'll send out Apache at one point.
If this was Instagram on iPhone, and if all you had to do was go to Instagram and you could find out the GPS
coordinates of everybody and everybody's picture, that would be a recall class vulnerability.
The only difference there is success. Don't let success be your downfall.
Design your systems in such a way. A great example is cryptography, right.
So cryptography, everybody assumes that everybody knows the algorithm.
If you're writing something that requires some secrets like ooh, if this DLL ever got into the public or this
implementation ever got into the public, it'd be game over. You need to design systems that don't have that issue
and that's kind of what drives things like cryptography.
Now that's been a lot of like here don't do this, don't do this.
People talk about the way to get around these things is threat modeling.
So they kind of look like this. You've got dashed lines for trust boundaries and boxes for servers and that
kind of stuff. What a threat model is not is a big effort that you spend in Visio.
That's not the benefit of threat modeling. Threat modeling is talking through your architecture,
talking through your design. A lot of times, this is what they look like.
You sit in front of a whiteboard, but the important part is that you have structured discussion with peers
about, well what happens if this thing gets popped, what happens if this thing gets popped,
thinking through those is what helps you create a secure design.
So the threat model template itself, what does it look like when you actually sit down and start doing threat modeling?
This is the thing that everybody can do, it just takes directing your thoughts.
So the first thing you start off with is just a diagram. This can be in Visio.
It kind of feels like you've made an official corporate document once it's done in Visio, but it can be absolutely
on a whiteboard. The important point is that you've identified the components, the hosts, the data stores,
being able to talk to these things and talk about them one at a time.
The one thing I would point out there is
in this ideal threat model, the traditional approach is called a stride model.
So for each one of these little arrows, you talk about spoofing, what happens if the person isn't who they
say they are. Tampering, what happens if somebody changes his data in transit?
Repudiation, so what happens if they say didn't do it. Information disclosure, which is what happens if
this connection is sniffed on or whatever. D, denial of service.
What would happen if somebody killed this connection or made it impossible to use?
And elevation of privilege or what would happen if somebody stole credentials and managed to become not the
user we thought they were. Wouldn't you start taking that systematic stride model over every one of these things?
You just feel like you're caught in a hamster cage
And there's a much more structured way. So we talked about take a diagram, talk through the components,
what do they do? Now this is a thing that you if you're at all involved in the infrastructure,
you're able to do this, right. So somebody points you at this web server here.
I come up to you, I sit at your desk or your cube or whatever and I point at that web server, I go what does that do?
You don't need to be a security expert to say well, that's our web server.
It serves up pages for the campus website. People can enter their course descriptions and search for things.
Like this doesn't need to be a terribly complicated engineering exercise.
This is you talking to a peer, but just taking a security aspect to it.
Now the data stores are very important. We talked about all those dangers of when people are compromising
infrastructures, usually, they're after some potentially of gold at the end of the rainbow.
A great example is a data store of when people a little while ago breached RSA, company RSA to make all those
secure ids, it's likely that they worked. Their end goal wasn't to breach RSA itself.
They wanted to use basically the token generation seeds to then breach Lockheed Martin and then steal real
IP because Lockheed Martin was using these two-factor authentication codes.
They wanted to breach Lockheed Martin so that they could get access to crazy fighter jet stuff.
So the data stores. You take a look through your diagrams and you go okay this is a data store.
What's in it? If there's some things as you're talking through your data stores and you say this is a
combination of people's favorite colors and their dog's names and the day of the week, and also their social
security numbers and credit card numbers, maybe you have a good opportunity there to start splitting your
data stores where one, you realize that it's incredibly sensitive, you can protect that differently than you
might protect something that's less sensitive. Now so you've got the components, you've got the data stores,
then you starting talking through, how do they actually interact among each other?
So this is what an attacker does, right. They say okay I got the web server, what do I have connections to?
What things can I start to go off and so these connections, so they talk to each other.
How do they do it? This is a thing that we can all answer. Well it uses PowerShell.
Well what's the identity being used during that connection? Did I hardcode a credential somewhere?
Is it like a service account? These are things where you can help decide, you know what it turns out that
this connection is being done as an account that's trusted across the entire domain.
So if somebody steals one of these credentials, now they're able to steal it and use it across my entire infrastructure.
So that's a bad idea. You can start to see what happens when these things are breached.
So there's identity, right. That's a very, very important thing.
Windows has a lot of great options for proving identity that aren't necessarily a danger when those things are stolen.
So a great example is group manage service accounts.
Those are domain identities that you can register in AD that make the identity only work from a specific
machine that you've declared as trusted. So that machine can go off and fetch the current identity of this
group manage service account. It can be that domain user across your whole network.
Somebody steals that credential. The minute that one machine is done with the credential, the password is just rotated.
So somebody steals that credential. It's no longer useful across the rest of your infrastructure.
So there's a great example of how you can compartmentalize identity.
You start talking about protocols, so when I've got one node talking to another, if you're doing anything
fancy, if you're doing a custom binary protocol blah, blah, blah, blah, blah, that's where you start having
some things you've got to really be concerned about. If you've implemented a protocol parser on one side of
the fence, well then an attacker might just start chucking bad data down that protocol.
If you're doing something regular like I'm just using PowerShell or I'm just using HTTP over SSL and that
SSL is like real SSL. I went off and got a good cert from a PKI.
It's not like homegrown self-signed certificates. The danger with self-signed certificates, if some people
will do this in their infrastructures as they'll set up some SSL communication with self-signed certificates
and then they'll set all these flags on the one side that says just ignore SSL errors because I know this is self-signed.
So it turns out, that's not a security boundary anymore. It's not a security prevention because an attacker
doing this interception can absolutely just give it a new self-signed certificate and they have complete access
to that entire communication. So if you're doing regular stuff like regular protocols, you don't need to
spend much time here. But when you're talking through your design and if you start, people say oh yeah we've
got this custom, that's when you know your questions should start rising up where you know you need to start
dialing into that a lot more.