Alright. Everybody, I'm Lee Holmes if we haven't met before. I've been an engineer on the PowerShell team
since the beginning and always been involved deeply in security.
So how many people here are involved in some degree of creating, creating any infrastructure,
creating any software, creating any websites, do any of that DevOps stuff.
Okay, so everybody, you know, we're involved with creating stuff.
That's what we do day to day. Now when you start talking about creating stuff, you're going to be really
happy at the end of I created this thing, it's beautiful, put it up on the web, it's so shiny, and you call
your mom, it's like hey mom take a look at this. I've got stuff on the web and she comes and takes a look at
it and she goes why does it say hacked by Russia? So the thing is, as happy as we are to create new stuff,
other people are just as happy of breaking new stuff. When we're creating new stuff, we've got to keep in
mind that there's another side than just the glorious creating of new things.
There's also making sure that the new stuff that you create doesn't become the next newspaper headline.
So we're going to talk about how you define and how you design software infrastructures and components and
designs that are robust and able to prevent some of these attacks that you keep on hearing about.
Now the key for doing this is called assume breach. If you were at Jared's talk just before, he talked about
part of his job is customers. He comes in and helps them find attackers on their network.
Now we used to be in this place of designing software where we said we're going to set up this really strict,
strict wall on the outside. We're going to put up a web server and we're going to have like people with AKs
like watching for everybody to come and were going to just like lock that down and that's about where we
think we're done. Where we have to move, it is absolutely impossible to truly, truly defend that boundary.
Where we have to move when it comes to software design is assume breach.
Assume that people will come in and then take steps to design your architecture in such a way, design your systems
in such a way that you can limit the damage that happens from that breach.
Now you're saying Lee, you've got cars up here, so let's talk about cars.
There is a company or there this is an institute out there, a non-profit institute called the Institute for Highway Safety.
It's actually driven by insurance companies. It's non-profit and they look at real data in the real world
about how people are getting impacted in terms of collisions and everything else, so they obviously work to
reduce the number of collisions, so making day time running lights and that kind of thing.
But what's important is that they also constitute and they consider the crash scenarios.
They want to make sure that when the crash actually does happen that you're more safe than you were before,
that you're more likely to survive one of these crashes. So they were funded in 1959 and they've been doing
some work since then.
Now they have a couple tests. So you tend to see the straight head-on crashes, two cars smashing together.
They found through data that that's not really the kind of crash that happens.
What often happens is they call it the overlap test, so you really have two cars, maybe they're going head on,
but at that last minute they swerve and they only crash 40% of the bumpers.
They've found also that there's another type of crashes where people just like drift a little bit in their
lanes and they have a very, very small overlap in their crash, so 25%.
Maybe they hit a telephone pole or a tree. They, of course, they do side crashes, rear impacts, things like that.
So these are the kind of things that they test for and see how well vehicles survive.
Now in 2009,
they marked their 50 year anniversary. They crashed a 1959 Chevrolet Bel Air, which was a regular car at the
time, with a 2009 Chevrolet Malibu, which was a pretty good performing car in terms of crashes.
So this is what 50 years of assume crash brings you in a world where people's lives are in danger.
So you got the red team at the left, crash! This looks brutal. You never want to see this.
Both cars look like they've been destroyed. You see the front ends completely crumbling, bits and pieces everywhere.
This is going to be a bad traffic day. What you see here on the right, the Bel Air, this is where it gets interesting.
Not only the front crumple zone collapse, but so did the entire passenger compartment.
Now if you take a look from the side of the driver, no seatbelts, no airbags, steering column comes right at him.
He's not being protected by anything in the assume crash mentality.
If you take a look at this, they think that this probably would have been a fatal collision.
This is a 40 mile an hour collision. This is not that much. Now you're taking a look at the Chevrolet Malibu.
This is a very controlled crash. You see the airbag deploys, the persons impact and recovery within the car
is very well controlled. What they found is that this person probably suffered a minor foot injury.
So when you take the assume breach mentality, so the assume crash mentality, when you go from just this idea
of hardening the outside to you know what crashes are going to happen,
we need to take steps to make our systems and our cars capable of remediating this.
Then you get from a situation of a life-ending collision at 40 miles an hour to somebody getting a minor foot injury.
We can do the exact same things with our systems.
So you see here, just cosmetically at the top, they look pretty bad, but take a look at the passenger compartments.
The Malibu, like the door opens still. The Bel Air, you know, you're completely crushed.
Now an interesting thing too is they just started the small frontal overlap testing, 2012 they introduced
this getting new data that these are very dangerous collisions. There were some poor performers.
When they started crashing cars with the small overlap, a lot of fatal injuries.
In only two years, they started doing some research. What are some of these cars doing that are making these
crashes more recoverable? So in 2014, they had a journal publication taking some common design practices
from the auto industry for people who had been very successful at this small frontal overlap testing.
They called it the stop car crash journal and it's actually the guy's name.
I think he was born for this because you don't want to start the mess for sure.
So here we're at some of the techniques they used. So nearly everybody did a bunch of reinforcement around the doorframe.
So obviously, when you've got a small frontal overlap, the doorframes and the car frame takes a lot of load.
A lot of people added a side frame that was also kind of very strict and rigid.
The ones that did the best integrated well with the doorframe so that there was an additional load path
during an impact to spread it throughout the whole frame, rather than just crumpling that front corner of the wheel well.
They added engagement extensions here you see at the bottom left.
Now the trick for these things is that these things were actually more robust to a crash than the rest of the car.
So this thing engages first, sends the car kind of more sideways and more of a spin, and what that ends up
happening is you don't have as rough of a deceleration frontally and it gets kind of sent into some side spin.
So everybody who was successful at this had to make sure that the side spin didn't send you out of the way
for avoiding the airbags themselves, but a couple kind of design principles that people could use and now
you started being able to see these design principles coming into other car models and doing a great job at
vastly improving their ability to survive one of these attacks.
Now we're not here obviously, we're not the auto industry. We're talking about cyber, right, cyber threats,
cyber intrusions, all that kind of stuff. So the Verizon Enterprise Data Breach report is really good.
I find it really good reading to understand the context of the industry and what are the kind of attacks that we're seeing.
A lot of times you're going to notice here down in the near the bottom there's the professional column.
That's kind of the stuff that we'll be involved with a lot. What you'll see here is cyber espionage is
getting a ton of the types of attacks. You also see crimeware is being used in a ton of ton of the attacks.
So this is kind of the thing. This is kind of like your small frontal overlap and your large overlap and
your side crashes. What can we do to start preventing some of these cyber-attacks and some of these crimeware attacks?
Now when somebody finally gets in with crimeware, what does it look like?
Crimeware is a pretty big thing. We call it malware, but malicious stuff ultimately get used for something else.
Now when somebody clicks on a malware, they get infected by malware, the malware is most commonly going to be
used for further command and control within that infrastructure.
Maybe it'll be used for a commanding control infrastructure for another attack, but it's likely that you're
going to have persistent interaction with an attacker. Sometimes it's used just as a denial of service,
bot, or a host for something else.
Another one here is cyber espionage. So this is like the APT kind of stuff, right, the bad actors from Canada.
So mostly what they're after are secrets. They get into your enterprise and they're going to be looking for
credentials, databases, all that kind of stuff. So we can take a look at the kind of attacks that are
happening in the industry and start to let this inform the way that we talk about our systems and the way we
consider our systems.