So the point here is that people say that threat modeling doesn't work and they really get stuck on that
document-driven approach. It's structured thinking about security that works.
Go back, put these things on a whiteboard. We'll be releasing this as a threat modeling template to help you
think through the different aspects of your system. Think it through.
Think through the different dangers of your components and your data stores and what you can do to help
restrict these and prevent any issues in the future.
Now what I wanted to do is talk a little bit about if people have questions about hey I'm designing,
I've got this system, obviously make it generic or whatever, but I wanted to sort of talk here about what do
people, what challenges are they running into? What are some opportunities for restricting a thing that
you're nervous about? Any takers? Yes.
(Audience question) Yeah, so the question was when you start going down this path and somebody goes well
I'm like 14 layers in and if somebody abuses this API, bad stuff happens.
Ultimately, you're going to be constrained in the implementation effort.
And so, it's really important to be pragmatic about it. The way we like to focus it on what are your top five
worries and what are your top five unmitigated vulnerabilities, and then you just start prioritizing.
So you can say you know what, we've got like 10 issues that are way huger, let's not dig too much into this
first, let's start looking for things that we kind of in our guts know are higher priority, higher impact.
So that's kind of the way that I found it really helpful to just be pragmatic on the threat modeling,
rather than diving down to like kind of API levels and that kind of stuff.
Anything else? Yes. So the company that I was working for has had all there…
Yeah, so the question was, when you have two components that are communicating over PowerShell remoting,
should we be doing that over SSL? And that's a good example of somebody saying I've got two components
interacting, what is a danger, what are the information disclosure risks and everything.
On that perspective, we're actually working at releasing a PowerShell Remoting Whitepaper soon.
It's SSL is almost always better, it's almost always better. When it comes to PowerShell remoting,
we've taken enormous steps to ensure that PowerShell remoting, even without SSL, is a completely safe thing to do.
That's because PowerShell remoting uses Kerberos, which does the authentication mechanism in such a way that
you can't really snoop it or sniff or anything else. It's the same thing as talking to SMB shares or anything else.
From then on, everything else in PowerShell remoting is encrypted by the protocol itself, and so SSL is important
to enable when you're using a basic authentication, for example, connecting to a WinRM endpoint over HTTP,
like something off in Azure, that's a good example where you're not within a domain environment.
Yeah, that's what I thought. But they were under the impression that…
Correct. You notice when you're about to do a bad thing with PowerShell remoting, you get so many error
messages about allow unencrypted connections and all these kind of things.
But that said, they had a valid concern that we didn't have it documented well enough, and so we're working
on that to get that out there so that you can just give them a document for them to kind of geek out on it
and understand the context. (Audience question) Yeah, the whole thing has got just tons of subtly.
It's really hard to keep them all in mind, especially when you're talking to somebody who is completely
involved in the risk mitigation department, and so it's a thing that we're going to work on making sure that
there's just kind of a document that people can read through. We're going to put it up there on TechNet.
We're going to continue to tweak it and make sure that these kind of concerns can be addressed so that we
don't feel like we have to individually fight the good fight. Cool.
Well, thanks for your time. Go out and think about your systems and make them secure.