Now this is the fun part. You get to think about the system from the eyes of an attacker.
So we've identified a bunch of hosts, a bunch of data stores, now you take a look at a host and you think
okay so I've got the web front-end. What's the worst that could happen if this thing got compromised,
like just let your spin for a while, half of threat modeling is brainstorming and creating new things.
Now here are some good things to get you started, right. So people will sometimes use that host as
a way to exfiltrate data. Maybe if sometimes that host is being used as a bridge between two things and they
can embed some stuff that intercepts that bridging capability. Maybe this host is now interacting with some
other custom infrastructure, like maybe this is a place where you're bridging two networks and they can use
this as a jumping point into another network. So just kind of thinking creatively about if I was an attacker,
what would I do with this host?
Data. We talked about some of the data attacks from the Verizon Data Breach report.
When you have data, people like to do things like hold it for ransom.
You've got a database that's storing your backups in an infrastructure that you created, what happens if an
attacker takes that over, encrypts everything, and then tells you I'll give you back the key after you give
me a million dollars.
You don't need to necessarily defend against everything, but thinking through the attacks, what would happen,
and as you're going through these things, you're just writing them down, putting them on the whiteboard,
bit better if you put them into a document to this thing. Now the thing here that's interesting about value
of data is sometimes it can be used to leverage other things. So this is the situation I was talking about
where people were taking the RSA seeds in the key seeds, then potentially able to use those for other attacks.
Then when you get into there, you start talking about mitigations.
So for all these attacks, what are some of the things that you can do to mitigate the attacks?
Now the mitigations, you're not always going to have a very clean answer.
Sometimes you go, you know what if somebody steals all this data like I'm literally losing my business.
If this data goes away, that is an end of business event. That's not a situation you want to be in.
This is a very quick thing. These threat models when you sit down and think through in this sort of structure
a lot of times, you get the majority of the innovative, interesting ideas in an hour discussion.
If you can't spend an hour on your security discussion, you're probably wasting your time on other things.
This is a very, very important thing to do.
Then you get to detection and response. So the mitigations. If you found a situation where if this breach
happens, it's a business ending disaster. Even just acknowledging that this happened would be complete loss
of trust or something like that. That's when you set it upon yourselves to change the design in such a way
that you no longer have that vulnerability. So there's an interesting distinction between threat and vulnerability.
So a threat is kind of a danger of a bad thing happening, and so there's a threat, for example,
of somebody compromising your database and stealing all of the data and selling it on the black market.
That's a threat.
A mitigation would be well that's fine, it's all encrypted. The customers have all the keys.
I don't even know what's in there. So there's your mitigation is encryption.
So when you have a threat with the mitigation, it's no longer a vulnerability.
If you have threats that you think are concerning and you don't have a mitigation, then now you have a vulnerability.
Now sometimes, you're not going to be able to completely mitigate all your threats.
You're going to have a situation where hey this bad thing, I'm really worried about maybe this server being
compromised, maybe it's going to be abused to do some other attacks against this other thing.
Now sometimes these things you can solve by just doing some detection.
So for example, if one of your servers is making REST calls into another server and you know that it's
always going to be the same two calls and you know, you can start to know which maybe accounts are being used
or which storage account ids, something like that. If you can figure out a good pattern that these are going for,
you don't necessarily need to write massive, massive remediations for these, you can just say that's fine.
What we'll do is we're going to start setting up auditing and logging on the way that these communications
are happening and we'll create a rule that detects anything that's outside of what we consider normal.
That's a valid way to operationally get around some of these threats you might have.
But some of the mitigations, they're not going to be there unless you're designing your infrastructure to help,
especially when it comes to the detections. We're kind of accustomed to Windows how it's got such great
event logging, you know you can see which processes are launching, what were the command-lines,
what PowerShell was being used, what was the ScriptBlocks being used.
That didn't come for free, right, this was everybody in the infrastructure that we're using said what
additional detail would people like to know operationally about how this system is working.
Now if we're the ones in charge of writing new software, creating new systems, doing the DevOps thing,
we also want to make sure that our systems are equally as security transparent.
So you should be able to set up rules that say when somebody is connecting over here to this system using
this application, whoa hey let your application or your service start generating event logs and audit logs
based on the things that you think are interesting in your application.
When you use PowerShell or where they use the ETW events built into Windows, Windows makes it very, very easy to
write structured logs into the event log. You can create your own event log channel, just do all this kind of
cool, cool stuff. If you were doing custom logs like a text file somewhere, you want to make sure that thing
is parsable by machines. You don't want
to say hey Joe, when you're trying to detect a breach here, read through every line of this text file and hope
you just happen to be awake and an attack happens. You want to use the machines to help you, make it machine
parsable, and be very explicit about what that format is. If you need to, write your own parser so that
these things now you can go off and write the splunk alerts or whatever you want to do for when some of these
events are happening that you want to start detecting. Now for each of these components too it's important
to think through, as hard as you try, there will probably be a system where, there'll probably be a situation
where you're going to get breached. You did all this assume breach work, this defensive work, there'll be a
situation where you get a call from a government agency and they say just thought you'd like to know we saw
one of your web servers involved in attacking another customer. That's generally how people find out that
they've been compromised. Now absolutely, if you don't have in-house incident response staff, you'll end up
calling a company to help out. There's a bunch that do a great job.
What you don't want to do is to say I don't know actually how you recover from this.
They'll help do a great job of like scoping the breach and everything else, but they're not going to know
your application internals. So if you know that one of your hosts have been compromised, they'll help you
detect one of these hosts have been compromised. There'll come a point where you say, they'll say
this thing needs to get remediated. What does that mean? How do you actually clean the breach off of that system?
Sometimes it means, well if it's DFC, fine, I'll just nuke the machine, reapply the configuration,
figure out how they got in, make sure that it wasn't from the software I put on, but sometimes it means,
oh actually this system is storing a lot of live data, so what we're going to have to do is capture the data,
take it off, maybe create an offline image, then bring it back on.
You might have a more complicated remediation story. Sitting in front of the whiteboard and talking through
these situations helps you be a lot more clear when the situation is actually happening, instead of when you're
paying some consultants however many dollars an hour to figure it out on the fly with you.
You don't want to sit there and go I don't know how to remediate this.
There's an attacker here, our business is down, we don't know how to actually recover it, and then they'll
help you talk about data stores. So proactively thinking through the remediation story is very, very, very useful.