So now it's our turn. We're actually the ones who are sitting up here defining new infrastructures,
creating new software, defining new networks. This is us, right.
It's our job to figure out how we defend against these attacks.
Now what's the solution? Is it going to RSA and going shopping at the vendor floor?
You could try
it. Everyone loves to sell their genie in a bottle that solves all your problems.
The answer is hard work. Just get out there, put in some elbow grease, and think.
That's my daughter welding, by the way.
Now the key is to realize that breach, it's not a binary state. You don't go from like happy, happy days,
the suns out, the suns shining to like oh I'm breached, it's all over, things happen in stages.
You have, for example here, let's talk through one. You've got an initial attack.
Somebody gets a suspicious email, they double-click it, they open it.
A regular phishing attack. They're just brutally, brutally effective.
Maybe they have some access to some test infrastructure, so this is they take the attacker now who's got
control of the account that they just phished, takes those credentials, and accesses some test infrastructure you have.
Now maybe that infrastructure once they've compromised that, they've got administrative access to this test
infrastructure, maybe somebody else coming into this infrastructure has administrative credentials to the production infrastructure.
So now they steal those credentials, start to deal with the production infrastructure.
So now they transition to production off of those stolen credentials, right.
Now they're into production. This is where they're starting to get close to their endgame.
Now they start stealing data, they have to collect it, zip it up, do whatever.
They're searching through your infrastructure for sensitive things.
Exfiltration. They're finally taking that data, sending it to somewhere that's important, maybe they're doing
this through, you see a bunch of outgoing web traffic from a host that's never done it before, they've got to
get the data out of your system somehow. And then finally, even still, once they have the data, it's not game over.
They do have an endgame. The data that they steal, maybe they're going to use this for intellectual
property rights, maybe it's a patent that you're about to file and then they can beat you to market with it,
maybe it's a user database, maybe it's some other sensitive information.
So you see here that the breach goes from a very, very early stage.
You have the ability to write software and architecture that can very, very, very much slow these down at all phases.
Now when you're starting to take a look at how do I design my systems to be protective against these kind of issues,
you see a couple common themes. Now successful architectures, they follow the principles of least privilege,
least capability, so only let your systems do what they should do.
Data that you store is a liability, really, like when you start taking a bunch of data.
If you don't need it, don't store it. And the other thing is don't let success be your downfall.
Now if you think about what are some situations where what if everybody was doing it?
That's a good thing to put what if every host had this or what if every company in the world had this.
People tend to when they're creating their own unique snowflakes not think that this at scale could be a very,
very big danger.
So least privilege and least capacity. The idea here is that these attacks as we showed in that kind of
breach diagram, people aren't just running through and like get in, do one thing.
They're compromising some bit of your infrastructure, then they get that, then there's kind of checking other
parts of your infrastructure and they're getting that. They're taking this and they're snaking their way through everything.
They could only do what your infrastructure is capable of doing.
If your infrastructure, if you've, for example, set up network lockdowns that prevent your web server from
ever hitting your back-end databases, you know if that needs to go through a malware layer, then an attacker
can't take over your back-end databases from the web server. If you're limiting your own functionality,
they can't do what your architecture can't do, what your systems can't do.
Now we're well aware in the kind of PowerShell community of just enough administration.
That's another great example here. When you're having systems talking to other systems, don't do it over
unconstrained protocols like straight raw WMI or anything else, do it over just enough administration
endpoints where your system's connecting to other systems can only do the commands that they're supposed to do.
Now an attacker takes over any of those systems and then they've got a restricted set of things that only
that service was supposed to be able to do anyways.