So comparison, before DevOps, your recovery and response took a long time.
The reason most companies are so fearful of failure is because when something does fail, it fails for a long time.
Right. Most of us can handle a stubbed toe because it heals in five minutes or so.
It's the broken leg that's a real pain because then you're in the chair for 10 weeks.
After DevOps, the recovery and response can be really fast. Failure becomes less serious because it's less impactful.
Before DevOps, everything was mission critical. How many of you have been told that email is mission critical?
That's bull.
I know it's inconvenient when email isn't up, but no one died. Okay.
There are places where nearly every application is mission critical and those places are called hospitals
because people die when things break. If no one's going to die, then you can handle a failure for a few
minutes or an hour or whatever. I know it's inconvenient, but if you move over to a DevOps model, you can start
to realize that yeah not everything is so mission critical. We can afford to be down for a little while.
We can stomach a little inconvenience. What we couldn't stomach was yeah email is down, it's going to be down
for several hours and when it comes back up, everything's gone, right.
That's why everyone said oh it's mission critical. They didn't actually mean it is critical to our mission.
They meant I know when this fails, it's going to be biblical and we can't handle that.
Before DevOps, we know that change breaks things, so let's just not change, ever.
Let's implement a management framework that has an entire committee who sits down once a month to discuss how
they're not going to approve anything and we call that ITIL. After DevOps though, change is fine.
You can be more agile.
We have to change. We know we have to change. How many of you have organizations who from a business
perspective are just pressing IT to do it faster? Yeah. Maybe don't outsource your VM management to a
company that has a six-month spin up SLA, just as a suggestion. But they're pressing us because we need to
be more agile and we can because change becomes less scary because we have a recovery plan that's fast and that'll work.