You are going to need tools though. You will either have to buy tools or build tools.
This is where the concrete implementation starts to come in because PowerShell it turns out is a great way to
build tools to help you achieve some of these goals and we'll talk about that.
Some DevOps facts. Puppet labs today a state of the DevOps report in 2015 and talked to a bunch of different
companies who are really, really all in with this approach, 60 times fewer failures, 60.
I want you to think of all the software deployment fails that you have had over the past year and if you're
thinking, yeah, it was about 60, well they just took it to 0. Sixty times fewer failures.
A hundred and sixty-eight times faster recovery when there is a failure.
Do that math.
If you had a failure that took 168 days to recover from, they just took it down to one day.
That's a hugely important fact because part of DevOps is accepting the fact that you will have failures.
You are going to screw something up just like you have always screwed things up.
This is just acknowledging it and getting to a point where you can recover fast enough that it's not so painful
when you fail. It's called fail with style. Okay.
They got 30 times more deployments in the field, 30 times. That means instead of deploying something once
per year, you deployed it once every couple of weeks, which means you're now moving features,
you're removing bugs, you're getting code out to where it needs to be, you've massively improved the agility
of the business and the businesses ability to respond to changing conditions because you can react much faster.
Two hundred times shorter lead for deploying.
If it used to take you 200 days to get completed code out into the field, now it takes you 1 day.
If it used to take you 200 hours, now it takes you 1 hour. These are a big, big deal.
I mean, this is a massive change and there's a lot of benefits, but you have to acknowledge a few things,
so let's run through a quick example. How many of you are familiar with Amazon Web Services Elastic Beanstalk?
Okay, just a few folks. Go read up on it. Now if your, oh my company will never, I don't care.
I'm not telling you to buy it. I'm telling you to go read up on it because this is the ideal text book definition
of what DevOps actually should look like. Amazon themselves has taken on the role of ops, they are the IT
operations department, and they have managed to remove almost all human interaction from the software
deployment process while still making it safe, fast, reliable, and predictable.
Here's how it works.
I'm a dev, okay. I'm writing my little web app that's going to get run in Amazon.
Let's say it's in a PHP or whatever goofy crap kids use these days.
As part of that,
in a little folder, I have a text file and the text file describes the type of environment that I want my app
to run in. Whatever packages I need, whatever add ins, whatever DLLs, or blah, blah, blah, blah, blah,
right, I need this much RAM, I need this type of processor, I need this type of OS, I need these things in it.
One of the biggest places where we fall down in deploying software, is that the damn developers never tell us
what's supposed to be running when we put it in production, right.
They sit in their little ivory tower world and are like oh wow my code didn't compile, oh I was missing this package,
I'll just install it. Look, it compiled and they don't ever clue us in the fact that package has to be there
for the code to work, right. And that's when we run into failure.
We push that sucker out live and it blows up into a million pieces because nobody actually wrote down what it
was we were supposed to deploying and when they do write it down, what's that deployment document look like?
You get like a Word doc, right, yeah it needs this and this and this or maybe it's a ticket.
It's not something we can consume easy. It's too easy for us to screw that up.
So in this model, the devs put a text document as part of their project and it's a text document I could read
and it's a text document that the computer can read. In Microsoft terms, we might call this a MOF, right.
So what happens is,
somebody says okay, let's deploy the app maybe to a test environment.
Maybe that's what we're going to do first. Amazon sucks in all the project code including that file,
it sets up the environment, it compiles the application, it injects the code into the virtual machine,
and then it starts running whatever automated tests you've set up.
This is key because the code only runs in an environment that was set up by the automation engine.
So if the developer forgot to specify something, his tests are going to fail and he can't just run in here
and oh yeah right, I forgot such and such a package. He's got to go back,
he's got to modify his configuration document to indicate what package was missing, he's got to
push the button again, the deployment engine will spin down the old environment and spin up a new
one that meets the new criteria, so by the time he gets it working, we know we've got this nailed.
So what Amazon literally does is you can ping their REST API or you can go into their dashboard and you can
say update app. It spins up however many virtual machines, sucks the source code into them,
configures those virtual machines, sets their memory, sets the processor class, installs whatever packages
you need, sets environment variables, registers those with the load balancer, deregisters the old ones,
and then destroys the old ones. Everything that we're used to doing manually, they just got as a bunch of Python scripts.
We might do that with a MOF.
Maybe we just tell the developer look I'm going to teach you how to write DSC configuration scripts and you're
going to draw up a DSC configuration script in as part of your project.
And we go to deploy your project, I'm going to take that and I'm going to use it to create a MOF and that's
how I'm going to configure the environment.