This is not for everyone. There are some of you in this room and there are people in the room every time I
talk about this who are going to think to yourself, you know, this makes sense.
I'd like to work in this type of organization. Our organization will just absolutely never do this.
You need to recognize if that's the case so that you do not start just banging your head into a wall.
I get into a lot of conversation with folks. I had a great one with a young lady who works for a company that
they do not have any internal software developers, and that's fine, lots of us don't.
It's a smaller company. But how do I do this DevOps stuff with my vendors?
You can't. They're not going to be complicit in this and she kind of got into this loop of no how can I make it work?
You can't. You can't make it work, right. That's like saying I really, really want to drive this car on the
ceiling upside down, so how do I make that. No, you don't. It's not what it's for, that's not how it works.
So this isn't for everybody. You can definitely, even if it's not for you, there might be some nice pieces
you can take from it. And maybe for certain projects it's for you, but recognize when this is not the right tool.
So speaking of that, DevOps is not a collection of tools. You will need tools to do this.
But DevOps is not something that you can go buy. DevOps is an approach to managing IT.
It is an approach to software delivery. You guys know where this kind of came from, this whole DevOps movement?
It came from Agile. Software developers started adopting these project management methodologies like Agile
where they could really iterate very quickly and produce new builds of software every day, every week,
whatever their cycle was and then they would hand it off to ops and we're like maintenance window not scheduled
until next Tuesday when the moon is full, and so they would have this huge pipeline of software that they
were ready to deploy and we're off over here implementing ITIL which is essentially about stopping all movement
in all molecules ever, right. Who works in an ITIL shop? Yep, right.
And everybody goes. Yes, we went to the DMV and said how should we run our shop.
It's essentially what we did. So DevOps came as kind of a reaction to that, which is, we need to make ops more
agile and you'll actually hear it taught. You'll hear about Agile ops or Agile IT and you'll kind of hear
those terms thrown around as well. DevOps has become a little bit more popular.