It's not marketing. It really is about dev, developers, and ops, operations, working together for a common
goal and that goal is to smooth out the path between the coder and whoever's consuming that code whether that's
users or it's a service or something else. That is a really, really, really, really important statement that
you almost can't go any further until you embrace that.
Let's look at what's involved in getting an application or a service from a coder out to its user.
For one, you have to start by coding it, right, and about the only way to code is to push your fingers against buttons.
That is a creative process. It's an artistic process. We can put a lot of tools in place to help make developers
more efficient, but at the end of the day, code comes from the human mind.
And so you can only do so much to smooth that part of it out. So now the coder has finished, the coder has
hit compile, a miracle has occurred and now we have code. That's when ops traditionally takes over to get
the code wherever it's going to be. We're deploying it to a server, we're deploying it out to client
computers wherever it is. We are almost nothing but a hurdle, right, any effort that is greater than 0 means
we are slowing things down. In an ideal world, the coder would just be able to close his eyes and squint
really hard and then the code would appear wherever it was supposed to be, right, that's ideal.
That's impossible because developers don't have the psychic deployment powers like we do.
So anytime we get involved, we are automatically creating a barrier, so our goal is to work with the devs to
lower that barrier as much as possible given some reasonable things like we don't want the universe to blow
up every time this happens. So, that's kindof what that is.