DevOps is not just one thing. It's going to look different in every single organization.
It's going to look different in nearly every single project, but let me just give you kind of a quick example
of how this probably will change your IT organization.
How many of you have separate dev and ops and maybe even like a network infrastructure team like fairly siloed IT?
That goes away. It has to. And this is where we have to look at whether our organization is willing to do this.
What it needs to be is not, how many users have walked into the office and said man, looking forward to
getting that IP address today? Never happens. We even fool ourselves.
Remember we went down this whole virtual desktop infrastructure?
How many users come in and say oh I love my desktop. Love it! They want their apps.
They want their services. And so, we have to reorganize IT. If we're going to do DevOps, we've got to be
organized around apps and services. So what it can look like, for example, is here's the corporate application team.
It's got 10 developers and 2 ops guys and a network infrastructure guy and they work together on that.
And incidentally, those same two ops guys are also on this other project team because their lending their ops
expertise to that team and telling the developers look in order for us to really smooth this out and we're
all on this boat together, so let us help each other make it happen.
If you could put these two things into your code, we're going to be able to make it much quicker and easier
for everybody else, so let's do that. And they have access to that in real time and those guys float to
whatever projects they're assigned to. And then all the ops guys and all the infrastructure guys and all the
developers have a guild and that doesn't have anything to do with the project.
That's just where the network infrastructure guys all get together for lunch every month or so and say so
how's it going on all the projects? And one of them go yeah, you know what we really found out that this one
brand of switch that we're trying out, rocks. It's a little easier to manage, so as you guys start moving
into other projects, you might look at that. That was really successful.
And somebody else can say yeah, you know what, we figured out that router over here blows up every Tuesday
and all of our problems have been stemming from this one place, and so they share their domain knowledge with
each other, but they're not organized that way. You don't just have a bunch of people who are disconnected
from reality managing IP addresses in an Excel spreadsheet. You organize around what is delivering to the business.
And if you're going to do DevOps, even for a small project, the team has to look like that.
Everybody who's contributing to it needs to be in the boat. It's the only way you can make it work because
otherwise what do you end up with? You get these walls, you get these communication walls, you get these
direct report-to hierarchy org chart walls. It's not healthy. It's not conducive to getting the job done.
One thing you'll probably start noticing too is that the projects that fail is run by the same --- project.
Can we start cutting the fat?
Projects that fail all the time that have a common human resource element, you can start to look at that.
(Audience comment)
You do have to change how you think about this.
So where do you begin? Small.
Do not go home and say hey you know that one giant project that actually makes the entire company run every
single day, let's DevOps that sucker. Go find something little.
Find something low stakes because there's going to be a learning process.
You're going to have to build some tooling. You're going to have to experiment, see what works for your organization.
Experiment somewhere lower impact, less mission critical. Start small and then grow from there.
And if you're, yeah I know, I work for a bank, we can't do, actually most of the companies that are really
leading DevOps right now are financial services companies because they're under such pressure to push out
websites and mobile apps and all this other stuff and this is the way they're actually getting it done,
so you can do it. How many of you are thinking yeah but my company is a little different?
No, you're not. All the companies are different. All of them. You're all equally weird in different ways
and that's why you're probably going to be building a lot of your own tools.
You might start with building components that somebody else that you buy, but you're going to glue everything
together on your own. You might go get a box of Legos, but you're going to put them together in your own way
and that's how you accommodate for your differences. That's why DevOps is not something that you can just
go buy at, do we have software stores anymore? Amazon, you can't buy DevOps at Amazon unless you're buying
it from Amazon Web Services who does it quite well.