What about failure? This is the Twitter fail whale. You're going to fail.
You've always failed. Like I said, this is just a way of codifying that failure and making sure that what
you learn from that failure can't happen again because you've got a process in place that's coded.
So one more thing. It's fun to talk about all this, but a lot of folks will get a little bit stuck on okay
let's say I don't have software developers, that means I don't really need to do this, right?
Well, yes and no.
You guys have all heard the term infrastructure is code, right. I hate that.
It's syntactically wrong. Infrastructure from code is fine. Infrastructure from code.
How many of you have a vision, even if you're not doing it, have a vision of having all of your servers
managed via something like DSC or Chef or Puppet? Well boys and girls, that's code.
That DSC document, that configuration script, and the MOF that comes from it, that's code.
This exact same pipeline applies to you.
Here is my DSC configuration script. Push the button, compile, here's the MOF, let's spin up a virtual machine,
let's inject the MOF into the VM, let's let the LCM do its dance, and then when it's done, we're going to run
a bunch of automated tests to make sure the environment is configured the way we wanted it to be, and if it is,
then that code, that DSC configuration script is approved for use in production and we can push the other button
and start spinning up new servers with that thing. Okay, times change.
You know what, we're switching AV vendors now, we're going to use different antimalware on our servers,
so I'm going to go change my DSC configuration script to remove the old stuff, make sure it's not there,
make sure the new stuff is there, make sure it's configured correctly, deploy it to the test environment,
spin up the VMs, run the tests against it, looks good, push it to production, all my servers reconfigure
themselves consistently every single time. Infrastructure from code means that we are developers, sorry,
probably didn't think that was going to happen when you came out this week, but you're a dev now.
So infrastructure from code means we can use this same pipeline to manage our infrastructure and this is way
better than
well how did it use to be, right. Let's say you changed management agents and now you've got to go around
and uninstall the old one and install the new one on how many servers do you have, 500, 1000.
You have two ways of doing that. You could do it yourself manually by running around and doing it, right,
actually a couple of way, more than two. You could do it manually.
You sitting in this room probably would have written a script to do it, but scripts in that kind of situation
can be a little delicate, right. Anybody ever script something like that in the past?
Did it work perfectly on every single machine? No because you've always got those little specials ones out
there that are broken. And then you're third option is that new thing, the intern net where you go to a
college and you get a couple of kids, pay them, and they run around and do it manually.
But wouldn't it be better if you could have a policy-driven infrastructure where you just say look this is
what you need to be today, and if that ever changes, I'll let you know, and you can run all that through this
DevOps pipeline where we are both dev and ops and we automate the ops piece of it and we focus on that
creative human part, the dev piece, our code, our configuration.
Could you see yourself running things this way? See DSC, Chef, Puppet, all of them, they're scary as Hell if
you're not doing this. If you're not pushing things through test and testing and building it as a pipeline
where it goes from a successful test out into production. Just whacking out MOF files, that's scary.
But this automates all the ugly bits, the testing and everything else.
How many of you have played with DSC to provision a machine? Okay.
So you wrote your configuration script, yeah, you ran it so you get a MOF, right.
When you were just starting to do this, did you just push it out to the node first time?
Yeah, yeah -Verbose -Wait right just to see what happened and when it ran, the first time you got it to run
without errors, remember that? Remember how good that felt? What did you do next?
It ran without errors. What's the very next thing you did?
Source control.
You did not put it into source control next. You RDPd into the server, didn't you, to see if it worked.
Yeah, of course you did because you don't believe it. All we're doing is talking about automating that piece.
Instead of you RDP-ing into the server and looking around with your human eyeballs, we want the
machine to do it. Have the machine go check. Did you do this? Did you do this?
Did you do this? Did you do this? Is this true? Is this true?
You write a little script for it. We've got testing frameworks, but if you just wanted a little script,
you could even do that. And once the machines could because the machine is going to be able to check all
those things a lot faster than you and it's going to do it every time.
It's not going to forget. Make sure it's in the domain. That's important.
Make sure it's got an SSL certificate. Make sure it's got an HTTPS listener for remoting.
Make sure the HTTP listener is turned off, right. You're going to forget at least one of those things at some point.
The computer will never forget. So you build those checks. You don't RDP into the server please for the
love of all that's holy stop RDP-ing into your servers. Alright.
Not an option with Nano, so we're going to have to figure out how to automate this anyway.
So you automate it, let it check it. And if it says thumbs up, you've got to believe it.
And it might be wrong, you might have forgotten to test something and that's fine, you'll figure it out,
but then go back and add it to the test.
Create that confidence in your code and that's really what DevOps is.
Failure is always an option here. It was always an option. We always failed.
You know, one of the reasons, so Puppet labs if you dig into that state of DevOps, I think that number 200 times
shorter lead time to deployment. You know why? Because they eliminated all this human QA effort where it
was, okay here's the code, now we're going to have some monkeys sit here and just pound on it.
They're going to run through scenarios, they're going to try and break stuff, it's going to be a little random,
they're not really going to collect data, so the developers are going to get frustrated and we're going to go
back and forth and fight with each other and the devs are going to say it's fixed and then we're going to do
the whole cycle again and they're going to find something different and they're going to send it back and they
don't have enough data. That's why it took so long because that QA process was too random,
too not automated, too inconsistent. All this does is it flights all that a lot faster.
It's consistent. You're still going to fail. How many of you have ever seen a big code deployment go out
with 0 bugs? No. That's not true. They all go out with 0 bugs.
It's not until the users touch them and infect them, right. You know that's where bugs come from, they're infected.
Users infect code. Well it happens all the time. It's always happening.
It's always going to happen, but at least this way, we can get a less screwed up version a lot quicker.
Here's why a lot of developers like this. Rather than deploying one giant thing every year that has 800
moving parts because when something breaks, not if, when something breaks, you've got 800 moving parts to look at.
They would, most of them, much prefer to ship out something every week than only change one or two things
because if they break it, they're pretty sure what they broke. Right, the other problem you get with these
long release cycles, these let's work on it for six months or a year or a year is by the time you get to the
end and you ship the code. The guy who started the code doesn't work for your company anymore.
Right, either his brain has changed because he's lived through 6 or 12 months of life or he's quit and gone
on because he can't believe you can't deploy software any faster than that.
But you do these things quickly and constantly and small, tiny, tiny bits, then when something does break,
yeah, pretty sure I know what that was because we only changed that one line that said Y2K don't touch,
we touched it. We should go put that back. So it's really easy to recover a lot faster.
And so us letting them ship more stuff because who are your best beta testers, who's really going to find all your bugs?
Users.
Your users because they're infecting the code. So you might as well shorten up the path for getting the code out
to your users because that's where all the testing happens anyway and if you can do it in small bits.
And again, this is the same with infrastructure, infrastructure from code.
Don't save up all the changes you want to do to your servers for a once every five-year nightmare cluster.
Alright, change one little thing at a time. Okay, we're just going to push this out.
Oh, that went well. Great. Okay let's do the next thing. Let's push that out and we can do it constantly
and iteratively and evolve things rather than having massive revolution all the time.
This is one of the reasons Microsoft is trying to shift their own model over to this so that they can just
ship small little bits and gradually evolve the operating system, rather than having to come up with a brand
new user interface and rearrange the entire control panel every five years, right, which is all Windows has ever
done, right, new UI, new control panel.