So low sodium, right, cloud, fat loss, right, there's all these marketing terms that get thrown around at us
all the time and it becomes really easy to become immune to them.
I mean, we're constantly having marketing stuff tossed at us. When cloud first kind of became a word in the
IT industry right when we ripped it off from the telecoms, it had a real concrete useful technical meaning
for about 10 minutes and then marketing people got a hold of it and ran away with it and suddenly everything
was a cloud. You can get your own personal cloud, no that's a hard drive.
It's not, it's hooked up to the internet sure, but that doesn't make it a cloud.
So everybody kind of ran away with it and the same thing happened with DevOps.
DevOps
as a term has actually been around for quite a while. It didn't really start to catch on until a couple of
really, really good books about it like the Phoenix project was kind of the definitive book that really got
people's attention on it in a big way, I guess. A lot of .coms, startups in the current era of startups
started using this type of an approach, so DevOps actually meant something
and then the marketing people got a hold of it. And all of a sudden, it's we're DevOps, here's DevOps in a box
and we being who we are and what we do for a living immediately started ignoring the word, justifiably, I think.
And so I wanted to do this talk to kind of just it's a real thing.
DevOps is not a marketing word. I want people to pay attention to this because it is a real thing; however,
it isn't something you can buy in a box. It's not shrink wrapped, you can't just wake up one morning and go
we should do DevOps, let's just do that. It's a massive cultural change.
It's a massive philosophical change and how you decide to do IT.
You can apply DevOps principles to one tiny project within your organization if it's got some certain
boundaries around it that allow that. You can run your entire IT organization according to these principles.
But you have to understand what it's supposed to achieve and you have to understand the tradeoffs that you
have to agree to make if you're going to go down this route.
And so, I've done a keynote a couple of times about really at a high level what DevOps is supposed to mean,
what it's supposed to be, but I don't often talk about what it actually looks like in terms of a concrete
what is this, if I'm doing this, how will I know, what's it look like, what buttons do I press to make DevOps turn on.
And so that's what I wanted to do today. Talk about DevOps.