So the model you're describing so far my understanding you can bring node oriented and during Dekens talk about
VMware, it would be in that, Oh he had to instantiate a system to use its LCM to manage the rest of
the environment, so when you compare it to _____ software, the whole infrastructure had this scripted thing
talking about it wasn't just one node, it was all sorts of things.
How does DSC have it mapped to---?
So yeah, so this does not really talk about just one node. Take Elastic Beanstalk, for example, if you work
for a large company and you've got an enormous website, that push the button might be spinning up 300 VMs,
some of those might be a database, some of them might be front-end servers, it's the whole application.
Same thing here. Same thing here. You usually try to segment your environment into functional chunks,
which we kind of do that anyway, right. I mean if you've got a three-tier application, you kind of have its
back-end and its middle tier and we try at least not to cross things, right, we want one server to basically
do kind of one role in the environment. Yeah, you might have machines that are AD and DNS and DHCP, but we call
those infrastructure servers and that's a role and we try not to put anything else on those, right.
And so, you can have multiple things happening as part of an operation.
You just try to put some role boundaries around it so that you can manage those things as a unit and I use
the virtual machine a lot. Might not be a VM, might be a container, might be client machines.
How many of you have ever screwed up a Group Policy? Because you're live editing the stupid things.
There's not a save button. I wonder what happens if I click, what's the screaming all about?
So I mean we could absolutely apply these types of things to the existing infrastructure the way we already do things.
Remember, this is an approach, this is sort of a guidance on how to go about this.
It's not a fixed set of tools, it's not a fixed set of scenarios.
We can use examples using concrete things like DSC or Elastic Beanstalk, but those are just examples of the
philosophy and that's really what this is. You can apply the philosophy to anything.