So let's dig into that a little bit more.
Setting up that environment. Tools like DSC, Chef, Puppet, Ansible, Salt, SCVMM, this is designed to read
the application's environment needs from that document and then set up the environment appropriately,
including dependencies like packages or DLLs or whatever other dependencies might exist.
We're now documenting those things in a way that can be automated.
Now it sounds hard when you just talk about it, but really think about it, how many of you think you could
probably rig this up at least in like a trial situation using something like maybe DSC or Chef or Puppet, yeah.
The technologies all exist at this point. We can actually do this.
We don't have like a complete pipeline product that we can just go buy that will magically do all this,
but all the pieces exist and we'll talk about some of those pieces.
So setting up the environment is straightforward. How many of you think you could automate the creation of
a VM if I pushed you to it?
I already have.
Yeah, and a lot of you already have.
If you've got something like DSC or Chef or Puppet or whatever, how many of you think you could automate the
provisioning of that environment once the VM is up. Of course you could.
Absolutely. How many of you think you could have a developer give you a PowerShell configuration,
a DSC configuration script, you can run that, produce a MOF, but then you could also have your own
operational concerns configuration script, which you could run and produce a MOF.
So now you've got the stuff the developer needs, but you've also got the stuff you need, the security,
the firewall, the things the developer might not necessarily care about, getting your management agents
installed or whatever else and you just hand both of those to the LCM.
Okay, I'll do that. I'll configure it. I'll set it up boss. Right.
We have all this. We have the pieces. So once the environment is up, standard compilers just get called to
compile your code or you can take it out of a checked in source control repository, right, when someone says go,
you just get the latest check in from source control that's passed whatever validation it has.
That code gets injected into the new VM. Tools like TeamCity can help you do this.
These exist, they're out there. And then if it's a test environment, once it's up and running,
you run automated tests against it. Now the exact tools you use to create those tests are going to depend on
your software dev environment. Right, if you've got Microsoft developers who are doing .NET, then you're going
to use the tools that are part of Visual Studio to create these automated tests.
If you're pushing PowerShell code, you're going to need something like Pester.
If you're pushing Python code, they've got automated test engines as well.
So you're going to use the matching testing framework. You run the test against the code.
If the tests fail, you bounce it back to the developer, you decommission the environment, you destroy it,
they've got all the evidence they need to go try again.
This isn't any effort on your part. It's all automated. It happens when the developer sits in their Visual Studio
and they say go. A miracle occurs. We create the miracle and then we just watch it lovingly from afar.
If the tests pass, then you repeat the entire process in the production side of the environment because the tests passed.
Alright, where's the weak spot here? Just because the tests pass, am I guaranteed that this is going to work
perfectly in production?
No.
No, I'm not. This is where you have to be willing to accept failure.
You get to production, Oh God, we missed something. Fine, roll back, do the whole process again with the last
known good version, which is still in source control, which is why we use source control, kids.
Go get the last known version, repeat the whole process. How long do you think it would take for most applications?
From the time you go oh crap, it's not working, push the abort button, how long do you think it would take to
go get the old version of the source code, spin up the environment, and get the old version running in production again?
Seconds to minutes. Quick, quick like a bunny. Quick, quick, quick, quick, quick, quick.
Because we've automated it all and we know it's going to work because the last time we did it with that version,
it worked fine. There's no reason it shouldn't work fine this time.
So
now that you know it failed in production, you know you forgot to test something in your automated tests.
Now production is back up and running, everybody can breathe easy, go fix your tests.
Right, okay well that didn't work out so well, so let's make sure that we're going to test for that situation
again next time and we'll catch it. So you failed, but you recovered quickly and the learning process,
right, because we're supposed to learn from failure. Most places are supposed to have the attitude that it's
okay to fail so long as we learn and we don't do it again. Your learning process is going and updating those tests.
That's code. The next time you run those tests, the computer is going to do it exactly the same way every
single time, and so you have learned and you have improved your automated environment's ability to resist
error the next time. And you were only down for a few minutes. Small price to pay because what we do now is
we ship it out after spending a ton of time wasted trying to ensure we will have no failure, we have failures
anyway and our learning process is everyone standing in a room screaming at each other hoping to God the
developers remember to test it the next time, so it doesn't happen again.
Well this is a much more codified form of failure. It's a form of failure that leads to improvement.
You can point to it. You can chart the number of failures you have and you can chart the number of things you're testing.
That's why people like this. Managers can get behind this because they can see the gradual improvement over time.
Make sense? So we run our automated tests, and like I said, Elastic Beanstalk is the perfect example of this.
You're shaking your head. In disbelief or?
No, I don't know anything (inaudible).
Oh, Elastic Beanstalk is just that. It's an Amazon service. You point it at your Git repo and your project
needs to have a configuration file, not unlike a MOF, different because they have their own format, and you say
okay deploy it, go. They spin up some VMs, they read your configuration file, they install packages,
they do whatever, they suck your source code over, they put it where it's supposed to go, they register the
VM with a load balancer, and they make it available to the public. It takes about 10 seconds.
It's magic. And it's the perfect implementation of DevOps and a lot of people will look at that and go well
that can't be DevOps because there's no ops, it's just the dev deploying stuff.
Yeah, now it's awesome. There is ops. Amazon is the ops. They've just automated human beings out of that sequence
because we don't scale well and we make mistakes. And this way, we've taken the one piece of the pie we
cannot automate coding and we've made that the highlight feature and everything else is automagic after that.
Yeah, but does that mean developers can deploy stuff straight to production?
It means that depending on how you set up your pipeline, developers can deploy directly to a test environment,
and if all the tests pass, does that mean it automatically goes to production?
Well no. It's how you set it up. Maybe if the tests pass, it logs a help desk ticket and says we're ready
for deployment and then during your next maintenance window or your next release cycle, after you've had a
chance to let your users know this is coming, whatever your process is, you push the button and it all
happens automatically from there. So you can still have business process cutouts and for some projects
you're going to want that and for other projects you're not going to want that.
You're just going to want it to sail automatically through. It's going to depend on the situation and your business needs.
So ops still exists, right. People make this mistake that DevOps is no ops and that's not the case.
We're still there. We've just automated all of the finicky bits and we've become decision makers because
that's what people do well. Right, we're really good at processes and making decisions about those processes.
Where we suck is when things get boring. Alright, and we're deploying the app again.
And we're just typing, throw that package, and that, oh crap I missed two things and that exploded.
Alright, we're not good at consistently doing repetitive things over and over and over and over, but we're really
good at those decisions, and so we just take on a human role. Now I've got a couple of companies that I talk
to that do this and there's a lot of companies that do it, a couple I talked to that do it really well,
and what they found is they've basically removed most of their second tier of IT.
They've got a help desk to unlock people's passwords, right, because you do, and then they've got engineers
high level, tier three folks who write all this. They write all the code necessary to automate all this and
that's about it. That's all they have.