Now when you guys, don't worry, when you guys get the code for this, I'll wait for it, it's going to look like this.
You're going to download this thing called DSC, boy that's really irritating, sorry guys, DSCPreCon and you're
going to have all of these sections under there of code. The section that we're starting
at is section seven. So you got six earlier sections of wonderful code just for you.
Okay, don't be so happy about it. Section seven is the pull server, so I'm going to go in there and I'll
show it to you. And here's how I construct everything. You have a demo file.
This demo file walks you through the entire process. Ready? Say yes.
Yes. Wow, you guys are tough.
I'm going to set my directory here. Now here's what I did. I wrote the entire process
down for you in a short list so that you can see what the whole process is and then I demo and create the
entire thing for you. So here's what I want you to know. Don't panic about this thing flashing.
Just get the
concept that I'm trying to convey to you because you
have the code and I've written it all out for you. Are we good so far?
Good so far. So relax. I'm relaxing. Okay, good. I like that.
So one of the first things
you're going to need is you are going to need a couple of things right out the bat to make a secured pull server.
You're going to need a certificate. Now this pull server is an internal pull server.
You can use your own internal PKI to put an SSL cert on it. I never recommend wildcard certs, but if you
must, you must. So you can put an SSL cert on the box that's going to be the pull server.
In my case, I'm going to use a box called DC,
which happens to also be a domain controller, don't do that in real life, but you can do it in lab,
that we're going to turn into a pull server. This gets a little bit complicated because it's not you making
a website and putting a certificate on it. We need some special services in there.
Microsoft has bundled this for us to make life easier. So the first thing I'm going to do
is I'm going to create a DNS record for the pull server. This DNS record is what I'm going to teach all my
nodes how to use, how to get to, to find their configs. I'm going to forget what this is,
but it's DSC.Company.Pri, so I'll just add the DNS record. And here's what I want to show you as soon as
he's done with that. We need a DSC resource module off of the gallery.
The DSC resource module
that we need to get is called, and don't write this down because I have it written here, it's called
XPSDesiredStateConfiguration. This module gives us a couple of capabilities and some documentation that I
want to show you. Now do you want me to give you the truth or the story?
Truth. Aww. Because see the story is a nice, easy polite thing and the truth is painful.
Okay, truth it is. Blame him. Blame him. So look,
let me show you how to find this module. You can find this module, and I've written it out for you, of course.
I'll show it to you. Oh, yes please. NuGet, NuGet, NuGet. Come on, Come on.
Snap to it, snap to it, baby. At least I think we're going to find the module.
There it goes. That's awesome. No, that's not awesome. There it goes.
There. So here's the module XPSDesiredState. I want you to notice the version numbers 3.9.
Friday of last week, it was 3.8.
Wednesday of last week, it was 3.7. I'll get back to that in a moment.
But so they're updating it. But you need this on the pull server and the box you're writing the config to
make the pull server, so your author box and your target. So
here's what I'm going to do. I'm going to get rid of this right now.
No, I can't get rid of that. Oh, this is going to cost me... Oh, that's okay, I'll fix it.
So here's where, how am I going to do this, I'm going to use install module to install XPSDesiredState.
I need another resource module because the way I like to write my configs, install it on my author box,
and then I need to install it on the box that's going to become the pull server.
The resources must exist there. So you can see the next command I'm going to run is Invoke-Command on DSC
to do that exact same thing. Are you with me so far? Yeah. Yeah, okay.
So we'll do that.
In here, I want to show you something. One of the best things about DSC resources is Microsoft gives you
some documentation to help you learn how to use the resource. So what I wanted to show you was right here
Where that module is getting installed, out here, and I have to change this to 3.9, out here underneath
examples, there's a sample of how to set up a pull server. This is really nice of them, right?
Don't you think that's nice they give you a sample? Okay, you don't seem all excited.
Let me show you a sample. We're not going to do it this way, but.
So they give you a sample. This is a configuration of how to set up a pull server.
And here are a couple of things that we need. First of all, we need to have a special Windows feature called
DSC service that has to be installed first. When that's installed, now we can start to set up our pull server
and I want to show you some of the configuration settings here.
These are things that we have to tell the pull server how to configure its website.
I want you to do me a favor and look at, the endpoint name is going to be the website name, what I want you
to do is look at port, Port 8080. This is the port that the websites going to run on.
Now I want a secured website, so what port should this be?
Four four three. Four four three. Does it have to be 443? No. See SSL works on any port.
Why do we usually set it for 443 though? (Audience Answer) Yeah because users don't know how to type in
colon for whatever and there's no way to communicate, so we make it easy because the browser makes it
easiest for us. Here's what I don't like to do. I don't like to set pull servers up on 443 and there's a
reason for this. I can teach the LCMs, the nodes, how to get to the pull server by giving them the port number,
but I might on this pull server want to set up something else on this pull server like a self-service portal
or PowerShell web access, things that I need users to access that are on 443.
And here's why and some people will go, do I have any Exchange guys in here?
When you set up a KAS box, are you allowed to put any other websites on that KAS box?
No, sir. No sir. Don't call me sir. No! I want to tell you something.
I want you to think about this. Configurations that you put on this pull server are little tiny text files.
Even if you have a 1,000 or 6,000 configurations, they're little tiny text files, do you know what a web server
dishes out really well? Little tiny text files. Little tiny text files!
You know how well it dishes it out? That millions of people can get little tiny text files from a web server.
So I want you to, I want you to, this web server you're building is never going to be doing any real work
because your nodes are going to ask for a text file and it's going to go…
One of these can handle everything you've got. Everything. So I want you to just kind of think about that
for a second because he's not working hard, so I like to put other things, management things, on him to use
up that resource a little bit more. Does that make sense? Yeah.
So if you take a look up here, I'm going to leave it at port 8080.
Here's how we're telling it, though, to be a secured website.
We need to give it this information. The Certificate ThumbPrint of the certificate and I'm going to show you
how I get that to fill that in. Now I want to point out a couple of other things.
ModulePath and ConfigurationPath. This is the physical location on the pull server where you will put your
configs and your DSC resource modules.
You can change this. I do not recommend it. In other words, why are you changing it?
If you don't have a really good reason, don't do it. I also want to point something else out here.
I skipped over the physical path to where the website files reside and when this comes back up, it's missing something.
This is wrong. The documentation is wrong. And I don't know if you'll stay lit long enough,
but the documentation is wrong. Does anybody find that funny? No.
Oh, I find it funny. I find it typical. Oh, typical. It says iNetPub, but it should say iNetPubwww is the
location where the physical files are. Don't worry about it. I'm going to give you a config that's correct.
The state is going to be started, other than that, let me show you my config, and we're going to run it,
and make a pull server.