Let me show you my config, and we're going to run it, and make a pull server.
Does that sound like a plan? Yes. Alright, I'm not going to show you the simple one,
I'm going to give you the advanced one, why, because I think you're advanced.
You get both, but it's the advanced one. I'm a web guy, so I'm real anal about web servers
and web servers are under constant attack. So here's what I do is I want to configure my pull server,
which is a web server, with the most minimal components possible.
I also want something that nobody else seems to like to set up. My boxes are all core.
There's occasionally when a web server needs to be managed from the iNet management tools like a developer or
something like that. You have to turn on and enable remote management on web servers.
On core, you can't do it because you can only do it through the graphical.
I need you to think that through. You can't turn on remote management because it requires the graphical on
the box to turn it on. Well why can't I turn it on remotely with the graphical?
Because it's not turned on. Well how am I going to turn it on? I wrote you the PowerShell code in DSC
format that does it. I figured it out. So I'm going to show you how to turn on remote management.
Nobody's pull server configs has this in it, so here's what happens.
You can't manage the damn thing after you get it set up. Isn't that stupid?
So do you want me to give you the good code or the bad code? Good code.
Okay, I like that. I'm up for good code. So here's what we do.
This is called the config data. I separate my configuration data from my actual configuration.
So what I'm allowed to do here is I can put in all of those things as properties right here at the top if I
want to change them. If I want to have multiple pull servers, which we'll talk about in a minute, I can just
have multiple hash tables here with different computer names in it.
Now what I'm setting up is roles. I've got a web role and then a pull server role.
So here's all my configuration data. Take a look at this, this is how I get the certificate thumbprint.
I Invoke-Command to the box that has the certificate, Get-Childitem to the store, I find the certificate with
a Where clause if it stays lit, and then I grab the thumbprint. This is a great piece of code, man.
You want this code. This is a great piece of code. So down here, here's how this works.
This is the actual configuration itself and I want you to take a look at the line, I import the DSC resources
that I need, but I want you to look at the line AllNodes.where Role -eq Web.
That's how you separate your configs for the
different roles that you want. This makes it real convenient because once I've written this correctly,
I never want to touch this code here again. The only thing I ever want to touch are the values in the config
data at the top. So I made this much better for everybody. And here's the other thing I did, and I'm not
going to make you try to watch the blinky thing.
I'll tell you about it and you'll see it here. When you install a web server,
you install a Windows feature web-server. It installs a limited set, a matter of fact, just enough stuff so
that you can have an HTML Page. No code will run all that kind of thing.
Microsoft thought that would be a brilliant idea and they're absolutely correct.
So what I do is I do that, but you still need some components for the pull server, so I install those,
but here's the thing, that basic set that it installed, there are things in there I don't want on my pull server
and I want to reduce the attack surface as much as possible. So not only do I have Windows feature resources
that are adding in individual components, I'm also removing the stuff I don't want that the default installed.
This gives me the tightest web server with the least amount of tax surface possible.
They don't do this if you use their sample documentation. They just go blah and it just barfs out.
I'm anal about this because I know it will be a and also this web role is what I use for all my web servers.
It's always the most minimum cut down for them and just the application components like ASP.NET 4, 5,
that it needs to run the applications. So what I here as this thing is blinking on and off is
a list of each one of those. So it's a detailed list, it'll come back, don't worry, you're not missing anything.
So pretty long list, but really cool. Let me get to the cool part.
GUI remote management, as soon as it comes back up. See the light?
Oh, no, of course you don't because it's not up long enough. I just give you…
So what I did is I figured out, I did this actually a long time ago through just regular PowerShell scripting.
I figured out how to enable and configure the remote management piece on IIS without being on the box.
You can do it in a script, but I put it in DSC format. So you have to install the window, the web management service.
The problem with this is that once you install the service, you still have to enable remote management and
then configure it. Those are done through the registry keys. I figured out the registry keys.
Now the registry keys don't exist until you install the management service, but then they exist, so you have
to make sure you get them in the right sequence. Please
flip back on. You can look at the code when you download it. There's the remote management stuff when it
flips back on and the registry keys for it to enable it, get it set up.
The other thing is with remote management on IIS, there's a service that has to be started called the WMSVC service.
There's a problem. I love this problem. This problem makes me so happy.
The service is not started. You guys know how to start a service.
You can remotely do a Start-ServiceWMSVC. But here's the problem.
The service is set to manual, so when the box reboots,
guess what isn't working. The remote management stuff doesn't work and you can't get to it again.
I love that! So what I did is I used a service resource to set it to run and configure it for automatic.
Yeah. So that way it will always be there. Okay, cool. Well let's run this.
Oh, let me go just show you down here. Here's the pull server and what I did is I replaced all those properties
I did in the config data as variables down here, so I never have to touch this code again.
This code is good code. It puts things in the right place, unlike the sample that's out there.
So you should applaud that I gave you good code instead of bad code because Richard Siddoway gives you bad code.
No, I'm just kidding. Okay, so let me run this and what'll happen here is it'll create a MOF and I'm going to
push this to the pull server. Well why can't you pull it to the pull server?
Because I don't have a pull server yet. And I'll show you, I'll let you see this as it runs.
I'm going to, I'm also going to change the LCM on the pull server.
You don't actually need to see this. This is just because I'm weird.
(Audience comment) Yeah, shut up. But here, let me… I'm going to kick off the configuration, so I'm going
to hit this and it's going to push it out, it's going to run the config.
It's only going to take it a couple minutes, but what's going to happen here is I want you to notice what I'm
doing right now. What am I doing right now? Talking to us, jazz hands.
Jazz hands! That's awesome! Nothing. In other words, I'm a big fan of I don't like to work hard,
so I'm going to let this thing do it. Now here's the best thing about it.
If I need a second pull server, what am I going to do? (Audience Answer)
Yeah. I may not even really, other than the name, I may not even need to change anything else, just push it out.
If I need 50 pull servers, which you would never need, I could just fire it to 50 machines all at once if I wanted to.
This is a beautiful thing, man. It's beautiful! It's really, except you can't see it, but it's getting to be beautiful.
And once this pull server comes up, he'll be in full operation. Now all you need to do is start putting your
configs and resources up and that's the hard part and that's my session that I hope the screen stays on the
entire time on I think Wednesday.