But I want to talk about high availability.
This pull server, as you'll see he'll come up, he'll be a working pull server.
It'll be nice. Is this machine critical? Yes. This pull server is going to hold all of the configurations
for all your nodes. Is it mission critical? It might not be because…
Well that's a way to split in the middle and not have a viewpoint.
If the pull server's not available, it won't get updates to the config, but it's already got a cache puppy if
the _____ node. Here's the thing. You're absolutely correct. All the nodes, when they get a config,
they copy that config to themselves. They run that configuration.
The only time they actually pull anything down from the pull server again is if you made a change up here.
So I want you to think about it. If this pull server dies, everybody is still doing what they're supposed to do,
you just can't get any changes out. So is this mission critical?
Absolutely not. So how many pull servers do you actually need?
Yeah, thanks for putting up the right finger on that one. I appreciate it.
Now here's the thing. In production, not lab, in production, I'm a high availability freak, so I'm going to
set up another pull server and make it highly available and let me tell you why.
It's not for performance. It's not because it's mission critical.
It's because of two things. I'm lazy and it's cheap. So since it's cheap, if one pull server dies, I don't want
to have to care at that moment. I might be out drinking, I might be having fun, and I don't want to care about it.
It's so cheap, it's free. Yeah. Anybody here ever set up a load balancer?
Yes. Load balancer website. That's all you're doing. So what you do is you bring up another pull server,
you put a load balancer. Now what kind of load balancers can you use?
Well first of all, how many of you have heard of Microsoft Network Load Balancing?
How many of you like to use NLB? Well that's a sorry site. NLB doesn't suck?
NLB is actually a great load balancer, but it's a layer three load balancer, which means the entire nick has
to die before it fails over. When I come to the websites, I want, if the app pull dies, I want it to be able
to failover, so I need a layer seven load balancer. I need a big IPF5.
Yes. Yes! So I'm going to spend a 100 grand on two of those because you want to load balance the load balancer
for a cheap, dirty pull server. That kind of sucks, doesn't it? Now look, if you've got a spare hardware
load balancer lying around that you're not using, go ahead, and use it.
There's nothing wrong with that, but I'm thinking it's kind of overkill.
This isn't a commerce site for my customers. This is my internal pull server.
So I'm going to give you a free piece of software. How much did I say it cost?
Free. That works as well as a big IPF5 and here's the deal, I use this in production on commercial websites.
I see confused looks. Okay, here's what I need you to do. Stand up.
How much time do I have? Stand up! I don't have a lot of time.
Come on! Come on! You sit all damn day! Get up! Richard Siddoway is, of course, he's too much of an
English gentleman to participate in all of this. I want you to do me a favor.
I want you to put your foot upon your chair. I want you to go like this.
Put your hand on over one eye, oh come on, put your hand over one eye, and go arr.
Arr. Arr. Arr. Alright fine. Now sit back down. Now you'll never forget it.
ARR. A-R-R, Application Request Router. ARR is one of the greatest load balancing products in the history
of the world and you don't even know that it exists and I'll tell you why.
You're going to yell at me too when I tell you why it exists and who it exists from.
It Microsoft made it. Was it the IIS team that made it? Yes.
It was the IIS team that made that. I'm very, yeah, we're not going to talk about that, okay.
We're not going to go through that whole scenario because I'll say the wrong thing again.
You know what's going to happen. There'll be tweets and it will be bad.
Application Request Router. Here's how you get it. You go into the iNet Config Manager, you go out to the
web platform installer, you search for ARR, you install it, you get a new icon or a new folder in your web
management tools and you drop servers in there, and it'll load balance them just like that.
You can change the algorithms, all that if you want to play with that stuff or you can just drop servers in there
and it'll automatically load balance them and it's faster than gas and it works perfectly.
I can't believe it was written by Microsoft. No, that's a joke!
That's a joke! I was just lightening up. So a free load balancer that doesn't cost you money, that's the one
to go through. So to make this highly available, bring up two pull servers, easy to do
with this config, and then give it a shot. I'm going to show you how to test the pull server, what it looks like.
Now I might need to reboot this because I was removing software in my config.
Oh, it worked. Okay, fine. Yes. When you install
ARR, ARR, would you install it on one of the pull servers or would you keep that on a…
Great question. No, great question. I'm glad, I should've, so let me answer your question.
This is a great question. Where do you put ARR? You treat it like you need a box that you're going to treat
like a load balancer, so what you do is you have a separate Windows VM or whatever with IIS on it,
that's where you install ARR. That becomes your load balancer. The pull servers are behind that.
Those are the things you put into the little folder, their names, and your DNS address points to this guy.
Now some people will get ridiculous like me and go well I need to load balance the load balancer.
You put in a second ARR box and then use NLB between them is the best way to go.
Then it's free, it's awesome, and it works. Yes, sir. (Audience Question)
Yeah, you'll change the IP address to the IP address of the ARR box, you got it.