So here's the thing. We're DSC is for configuration management.
I've got two sessions during this week. This is on how to make a pull server for your infrastructure where
you will put your configurations and your resources.
The next session that I'm doing is how to package your configurations and your resources.
These sessions have nothing to do with writing configurations in your resources.
That was yesterday. Now do you want the good news or the bad news?
Bad news. Oh, pessimist. Bad news is this, if you don't know anything about DSC, this is the deep end of
the pool, sorry. Now do you want the good news? Yes. Good news is this, you want the code from yesterday?
Yes. I'm going to give you the code from yesterday. Yay! Which includes the code that I'm using today and
the code that I'm using later in the week and all of the code that we did yesterday, which could show you how
to do DSC.
So first of all, guys, when this thing decides to come back on, look 10 years of PowerShell, yeah!
You're going to see some of these people walking around here and there's going to be Microsoft blue badges
everywhere, so say hi and talk to people. Alright, look fast for when it blinks,
what's going to come is there's the link to the code. It's GitHub at the powershell.org.
There it is, get it quick. Use your camera. Also, you want Steven Murawski's reading list on DevOps.
It's an excellent reading list.
Okay, you don't look impressed. Alright, let's talk about pull servers.
Here's what we want to do. We want to have a configuration that we want to be able to send out to other
nodes that are going to automatically configure our boxes for us.
We do not want to push this to them because that means I have to manage that.
I don't want to manage anything. I want to sit at home in my underwear and drink coffee or whatever and I
want it managing itself. So we want to bring up a server that we can put our configs on that all of our nodes
that are using DSC can go to grab the config for them and automatically do it themselves.
Are you with me so far? Yes. Good. Give me feedback just like that, so I know that you're alive and well.
And don't worry about the flickering screen. We'll get through it all.
So does that kind of make sense? I want to have this pull server.
Now there's three kinds of pull servers that you're allowed to have.
Three kinds.
I only got three more slides, guys, and then we'll… So you can have an SMB pull server.
Here's what an SMB pull server is.
Hey, you know what? You guys ever build a file server? Yeah. Do you guys ever create a share on a file server?
That's an SMB pull server. Oh, come on. That's all it is. It's a server with a share.
So you use though the PowerShell command New-SMBShare to create the share and assign the permissions to it.
You can configure the client LCM, which is the local configuration manager to go to that share for the configs,
then delete it and do the right thing. Do not use an SMB pull server.
You don't have all the features that you need.
There's another type of pull server called an HTTP pull server.
This is a web server. Yeah. It's an HTTP web server, which means all communications go across the wire like what?
Plaintext. Plaintext. Not good. Here's why not good. You don't want somebody sniffing those configs
and understanding how you're configuring your boxes. That's not good.
So you can configure an HTTP
pull server, but then delete it and do the right thing.
Are you ready for the right thing? You only have one right option.
HTTPS. There you go! Oh, man
I love it when you play along. So what this means is, has anybody here ever set up
a website with a certificate on it. Awesome! That's all we're going to do.
Now, the cool part about this is, you have some help in making this work and we're going to go to code here
in a minute and I'm going to show you how this sets up. It's not difficult and I'm giving you all the code,
so there's no reason why you can't do this at home. Here's what I recommend and I recommend this all the
time when we talk about DSC. I do not develop DSC by pushing it those configurations to machines.
The reason is that I need to see the whole process. If you come to my next session on this, it gets complicated
fast, and so I always, even in a lab environment, set up a pull server, an HTTPS pull server because it's free,
and in my lab environment, I go through the whole process of development, so it's always correct.
So I'm going to give you how to build this pull server. It's really easy.