So ask whatever questions you want to ask in the few minutes that we have remaining
before you get fed. Well, in there just when you all were setting up the modules on the pull server,
the pull server actually went out and got the modules off the internet themselves.
Well in my company, IIS servers, unless their customer facing, cannot be web connected.
Yep, absolutely. So what you do is you take your workstation, you bring the modules down, and then you just copy them.
So I can just pick a folder off of my workstation and drop them in.
I work with a lot of government agencies that are in the same way, right.
They can't have their machines can't directly access the internet.
So all you need to do is bring down your copy and you copy it out the program files modules folder on that pull server.
Now I don't want you guys thinking you're going to be deploying resources all the time.
The whole point to this pull server is going forward with all your nodes, you're going to put all of your
resources, custom resources, all that onto that pull server, those nodes will then pull them down from the
pull server, so the nodes don't need internet access. It's just this initial set you'll need to go out and
grab, right, and then put them up there yourself. You can just manually copy them.
I've got a script that does that for a customer, just updates versions and boom, boom, boom, so because they
have that situation. What else? Oh, come on. Do you want to do Desired State stuff?
Do you want to do configuration in Azure? Did you gloss over the certificate that uses certificates on the box?
Yeah, in this situation, the certificates on the box; however, I did give you code to do the certificate request
from your PKI if you wanted to. If you have ADCS set up and you have the policy stuff set up on your ADCS,
I gave you the code, it's commented out, but you can actually just run code to go request the certificate
automatically and put it on the box. A lot of people manage their certificates, though, a different way,
so I don't usually automate that for a customer because they have some other piece in place.
Their security team does it a different way. The idea is to get a certificate on the box and then we can
pull its thumbprint and go. In your other talk, don't you have the ability to encrypt the configurations themselves?
Are you going to cover that in here? We actually did that yesterday and it was about credentials.
I missed it. You missed it; however, you got the code for it if you download it.
And if you want to ask me questions about it offline, I'm happy to talk to you about it.
The code takes you through, don't do this because here's your result, plaintext password, don't do this like
they say on the internet because here's your plaintext password.
Then it says here's how you encrypt it. You're never going to find this on the internet because they changed
how to do it. They added in a document encryption type, you have to make a new certificate, you have to add
a new EKU for the document encryption type. If you don't do exactly what I have in there, it never going to work.
But I wrote it out all for you, so and I'm happy to talk to you about it and take you through it, that kind of thing.
It's changed in WMF5 than what we had in WMF4, so if you see older stuff, I did a lot of older stuff on
credentials and all that kind of stuff. It just doesn't work the same way.
The process is the same, but you've got to make a change to the certificate.
Yeah, but yeah, we do all the credential stuff. Alright guys. Well, you know, I'll hang here and answer
questions, but if you want to go potty, pee, or lunch or something like that, please feel free, but I'll stand
here for 15 minutes and chit-chat. So you're officially done. Go.
Thank you.