Now guys I want to show you this because I'm just proud of this.
This is what it looks like when it works. I know it looks like it doesn't work, but that's what it looks like
when it works. And if you come to the next session, you'll actually see it work as we do configurations on it
and all that kind of stuff, but I just want to show you just the remote management because I'm so happy that,
come on light up long enough on the screen, wait a minute it'll light up, you'll see it, hold on.
Connect. Hey, I got management. Oh, come on I got remote management to the web box!
And your pull server, that's that endpoint website pull server
on port 8080. Now you will teach the LCMs or the nodes how to get there and I will show you that in the next session.
Yes, sir. (Audience question) It has an AD binding. If you have a, you should be building this on your own
new box, so don't build it on somebody that's already messed with the ports.
What I do is I want to tell you this. In the configuration, what we usually do with web servers is we turn
off the default site because we're going to make our own stuff. People will say to me why don't you just
delete the default website. That's not good. Sometimes we like to bring that guy back, so I just turn him off.
I do not turn off the default website if it's a pull server or if it's an ADSC server, if it's a certificate server.
Because if it's a certificate server, now you can't get any, and your pull server, there might be reasons
for us to use that default website. Now I need to give you some good news, oh no, I can give you that news
in the next session, that's when it applies. So let me check the time.
Awesome. I know it didn't look like much, but you get all the code to make your own pull server, so you can
start your own infrastructure. Does that look cool? Yes. Okay, come to the other session I'm doing because
now we'll go through how to put all your configs on there and you'll see it all run because there's some
tricky parts to getting all the configs and the resources onto the pull server.
Once you have that done, you now have the infrastructure you need for DSC, both for lab and for scalable
stuff out there. Now I do want to point a couple of things out.
Right now, if you especially come to the next session or if you were in the session yesterday, right now there
are a few things that we are, that the team is working on with the pull servers.
You notice how I said we're at diversion XPSDesiredState 3.9 and we were at 3.8, that's because they're
working on some issues that we might have in situations. So if you come to the next session,
we have an issue with configuration names that I'll show you a work-a-round for until that gets fixed.
I want you to keep something in mind. When you go back to your office, you should try this and build this.
Use my code, whatever, make your own code for this, but follow along what's going on with these version updates
on XPSDesiredState because you might run into something that you don't need to fight because it got fixed.
If you come to my next session, you'll see exactly what that is and how it's getting fixed and we'll just
move on from there. So just want you to know, this is work in progress, but I use this in customers,
in their infrastructure. It is a stable, usable pull server. It's a great product.
Now if this pull server does not provide you, and I say this about anything in DSC, if you're working with DSC,
we assume you're going to start building your own tooling for a while because this is a platform,
it's not a whole product, but I have a tendency to say this, if you came to yesterday's and you'll see him
walking around here, Steven Marowski, he's a chef guy. He's the chef guy, right, the chef guy wearing an apron
and a chef hat. Other options are like Chef and Puppet and Ancible, stuff like that.
I have a tendency to go to Chef. When I work with customers that cannot build their own tooling today,
I'll direct them towards Chef. If I'm working with customers that already have developers and IT guys that
are PowerShell capable like you guys are, that can build their own tooling, building the tooling you need is easy
and the types of tools. Well I want to inventory everybody to see what configs they're running and stuff
that into a database. That's easy to write! In the future, I can't tell you this for sure because I don't
know for sure, but I would assume that probably Microsoft at some point is going to have some more tooling
around this, but right now, you can easily write anything that you need.
Now if you were here yesterday, you saw a lot of that. You saw somebody writing a lot of tooling and some
of the stuff I gave you I've done some additional tooling about it, but this is a really good product to
start with and what we see a lot of people doing, even if they think they're going down the Chef path,
they're doing the DSC path alongside it. A matter of fact, I'm working with somebody right now that's doing both.
How many hypervisors do you guys use? Oh, so you only use Hyper-V, that's good, good answer.
(Audience comment) Yeah, use one. So a lot of companies, you have VM, you have Hyper-V, so some companies
are doing multiple configuration management systems and that's not always a great idea, but if you haven't
gotten into DSC, this is the thing to get into. This product rocks.
And configuration management is the most important thing and on Wednesday, I think it is, Michael Green is
going to go through all the DevOp stuff. You want to see that. Marowski's going to talk about DevOp stuff.
You want to see that.