So what I did was to do what Adam Platt calls help-driven development.
I started with my help file, right. I used my help file as my spec for my code.
Okay. It's just an easy way to do it and it means that I always have a spec.
But what I did was I realized that my help examples are my contract with the user about the behavior of my
code, right, and by code I mean scripts or modules. Okay. And when I make that behavioral contract,
I as part of that behavioral contract, when I write my examples, I show sample output.
That's my expected in my test. We're comparing actual to expected.
So I show an example of running my code and showing expected output.
So it's very easy to use the help examples as the test spec and the test as the code spec, of course,
it supports behavior-driven development and there's a feedback loop because it makes my help better.
So for this, I picked what I thought was the simplest possible little example.
I used Windows PowerShell profiles, but when I'm testing or doing demos or writing shared code, I disable them
because I don't want something in my profile to affect my test or my code.
So I had little snippets of code all over the place that disabled my profiles and re-enabled them and then
would get the disabled profile, so I didn't freak out and that's the little module we're going to be testing with.
So I actually started with a help file. Let me show this to you.
We're going to switch around here. Okay. This is PowerShell HelpWriter.
I showed it last year. And I started with a help file for a Get-Profile, Disable-Profile, and Enable-Profile
cmdlets and they all have these nice examples. Okay, and then I went over here to PowerShell Studio.
Do I need to use zoom it, can you guys see? Okay. And I did New, New Module from Help File, I went to my
Help Files, and there's my module. Okay. And so what PowerShell Studio did for me was it just mocked up little
functions for my help file. Okay. It used the output type because I was careful to specify that and it gave
me a little export module member statement at the end and a module manifest, and quite soon, it will also
give you a test file. Okay. So that's basically where I started.