So welcome to Real World Test-Driven Development with Pester. My name is June Blender.
I'm a technology evangelist at SAPIEN Technologies in Napa, California.
I spent some time writing help with the PowerShell team and I'm now honored to a Windows PowerShell MVP.
Thank you. So this is really different than most of the talks that I give, which tend to be sort of I know
all about this. Here's the syntax, here is how you do this, here is some examples, right.
Instead, I'm going to talk about my experiences learning Pester, which is really a different view and I hope
that this will help those of you who don't know Pester to learn it and those of you who are teaching Pester
to have some insight into what it's like to learn it and this is real world stuff.
So I tested the code and information on the slides to these versions of Windows and these versions of
PowerShell and particularly Pester 3.4.0. When I started putting together this talk it was Pester 2 and
they're ready to release Pester 4 now. The versions will vary, so this one is 3.4.0.
So we talked a little bit in the pre-session about why test and I'm going to call it moot.
Alright, I'm going to say that folks who are here understand why we test, but I'm always happy to entertain discussions.
But for a while, even those who wanted to test did not have a professional framework to do so.
And then along came Pester. And Pester is really an extraordinary contribution to PowerShell because it's a
professional test environment that's built as part of the academic discipline of code testing.
The people who built it really knew what they were doing and rather than developing some helter skelter test system,
they built on the academic discipline of test-driven development and it's a huge contribution on,
when you learn the domain-specific language in pester and by domain, I don't mean like domain controller,
right, I mean the academic discipline of testing, and you go to another language and look at its test
framework, it will look very similar and familiar to you. So when you see the folks who contribute to Pester,
thank them, buy them a beer, right. It's really an extraordinary contribution.
So it says up there that Pester is a BDD style testing framework, so let's talk about that a bit.
Test-Driven development is decades old. It is certainly not as old as programming, but people like Kent Beck
and others decided that the way to approach testing is to write the test before writing the code and this was
pretty revolutionary, okay. They said that you write a test, you write only the code that you need to pass
the test, and then you go onto the next test. The first time you test that code, run the test, it should fail
because there's no code, right. But you write only the code that you need to pass each test.
And in theory, the code is simpler because you've only written enough code to pass the test, everything is tested,
sort of a priori, and the developer can be a little more bold because they don't have to worry about regression errors.
They can put in a new feature and if they accidentally break something, the test will pick it up.
Behavior-driven development grew out of test-driven development and it's the theory that you write tests that
describe the behavior, not the implementation of your code, right.
So that way, you can change the implementation and do novel things without having to rewrite your test suite.
It is a really hard thing to do in practice. I failed. You'll see.
But in addition, your tests should be independent of the environment in which they were written, right,
it doesn't have to, you know the it works on my machine is not a good excuse, right, and they're also
independent of each other. You're testing the code segments in isolation.
You should test all of the features and you ship your tests. Your tests become part of your code.
But that didn't answer the question of which tests do I write? Right, I'm supposed to write my test before my code.
How do I figure out which tests to write? Yet, a lot of the tests that I've seen are so easy,
right, they're so simple to pass that of course the code looks great when you test it and then hand it to a
real user and it breaks all over the place, right, so there's a real art in writing tests.
And it was about this time last year that I heard Dave Wyatt's talk about Pester and this was the first question
that I hit that I could not solve. So this is where this talk will start.