Then I create a test for every example. Now I'm going to take you through about seven minutes of syntax.
Are we good so far? Everybody happy? Okay. I'm going to take you through about seven minutes of syntax
where we're going to discuss the Pester syntax and its natural language.
You've often heard these called DSL, or Domain Specific Language, right.
It's just its natural language for comparing actual to expected values.
So my hint to those of you who are learning Pester is to either learn the syntax if that works for you and
forget it or don't even learn the syntax, just go with the natural language.
Okay and I threw, these slides go up on GitHub, and they're available to use, so I threw in a little glossary
for those of you who are unfamiliar with the terms. They're not defined in help files.
Okay. So Describe is a container, okay, and I consider it the naming container.
If you look up in the upper right-hand corner, there's going to be a little breadcrumb trail and that's a
good thing to watch for. You'll see how these pieces interact with each other.
Okay. So describe, I considered describe to be the naming container because when you run Invoke-Pester to
run your tests, there are TestName and Tag parameters and they always refer to the test name and the tag on
the Describe block, right. There are other containers in Pester and they have names.
The names are always required and they are almost always arbitrary, but when you use TestName and Invoke-Pester,
it only looks at the names of the Describe blocks, so it's my naming container.
Oh, it creates a scope for both mocking and TestDrive and we'll talk about those in a little more detail,
and again, the name is required and arbitrary. One more thing and this gets everybody, see the curly brace
that's on the same line as the Describe keyword, that curly brace, regardless of your favorite curly brace
style, is required to be on the same line as Pester because that ScriptBlock is the value of a positional parameter, right.
So if you did put it on the next line, you'd have to use that awful back tick, right, hopefully without a space
following it, right. Okay. But there's a
wonderful error message and I think when you see it, remind yourself of the value of excellent error messages.
There's an error message in Pester. If it can't find the ScriptBlock, it said did you put the curly brace on
the next line. Okay. It's great.
It's wonderful. The other thing is that if you omit the required name parameter, it assumes that this script,
well PowerShell, so it's looking for a string followed by a ScriptBlock, these are all positional parameters,
that's how it does the natural language, so if you happen to omit the name, PowerShell converts the
ScriptBlock to a string and then it can't find the ScriptBlock. Okay.
So if you omit the name, you'll get one of those errors that said did you put your curly brace on the next line,
right, even if you didn't. Context is also a container. Look, keep your eye on the breadcrumbs.
It's a container inside Describe. It's an optional container. You don't need to use this one, right.
They added it for organization, but it's very important because context is the smallest container that creates
a mocking scope. There are smaller containers, but they will not contain a mock in Pester 3.4.0.
Okay. The name again is required and arbitrary.
The next container is It. It is a required container inside either describe or context.
It encloses your tests. It is the smallest test container, but it does not contain mocks.
It does not create a mocking scope. It also has a name that's required and arbitrary.
Should is not a container. Should is actually a function. It compares actual to expected values.
You always pipe to it and it does that comparison based on the value of the B operator that follows it,
so this is a very typical should format.
And these are all the wonderful comparison operators. Okay. They change, so keep an eye on them.
Not all of them are documented. I noticed last night, BeOfType, which is one that I use frequently is not
documented, but I owe those guys some favors, so I'll probably throw that in.
These are fantastic. Learn these and use them. They will help you in your tests.
Oh, and then mock, which is my absolute favorite part of Pester.
It lets you fake the input to the cmdlet that you're testing, right.
It is absolutely invaluable. I heard some people say that they're using Pester, but they're not using mocking.
This is the way that you make your code independent of your environment and independent of code that it interacts with.
Okay, and what it does is it fakes the input to the command that you're testing.
Okay, so the command that you mock, does not run. And instead, you provide the fake output so that when the
command that you're testing runs, it gets the output that you specify instead of running that command.
So you do not mock the command that you're testing, right, because it won't run.
You mock the command that provides input to your test command. So in this case, you see my cursor?
Good, okay. So in this case, we're testing new user, right, but we're mocking a helper function that it
calls, Get-UserType. Okay, and we're going to mock it with admin so that when New-User creates its object,
it gets admin. I could put anything in there and one of the things I'd want to test is all the valid values
and at least one invalid value. Okay. Let's see, oh and in unit test, you mock all calls to other cmdlets,
that's the isolation feature. Oh, we're doing pretty well
on time. Good. Mock does not scope to It blocks. Okay. So the mock that's done the mock of Get-ChildItem
in the first It block, also affects the output in the second one.
The smallest mocking context is, oh sorry, the smallest mocking scope is context.
Okay. Boy, did I learn that the hard way.
And then TestDrive, which creates basically a virtual file system just for tests.
This is something that the Pester team could've made us do as testers, but instead, they handled it
themselves and it was a brilliant decision. Here's how it works.
Whenever I answer a Describe block, I get a brand new test file system.
That's just for my tests. I can write files in it, I can read files from it, I can change them without
affecting the file system on my machine, and more importantly, without being dependent on the contents of my
personal file system so that it works on my machine. Okay, and what's really going on is that it's creating
a temporary drive in ENV temp, right. But so you refer to TestDrive by as TestDrive: like C: right,
always with a colon or the TestDrive variable holds the fully-qualified path to the current TestDrive.
Okay and you'll see me using this when I create paths. You answer a Describe block, you get a brand new
TestDrive, you leave the Describe block, that TestDrive is gone, you open a new Describe block, you get a
brand new one. Okay. So there's no pollution between tests. It was a brilliant move.
Again, if you see these guys, pat them on the back. This is a huge facility.
Okay.
There's some scoping stuff and we can
talk about that if we have some time. In module scope is an Uber container just for testing modules and what
it does is it creates all of the test elements in module scope, which means that the test has access to all
of the elements of the module including elements that are not exported, right, like variables and like those
helper funs that you need to mock. Okay. So when you're testing a module, this is almost a required thing to use.
This one has a required name, but the name is not arbitrary and it must match the actual module name.
Okay. And then the final thing is the wonderful
Invoke-Pester cmdlet and let's get to some code.