So when you test modules, as opposed to scripts, you use the InModuleScope container, which means that you
can mock any function. It can't handle multiple versions, so make sure to use that Get-Module Remove-Module.
Oh, if you just use Remove-Module without Get-Module and there are no modules in there, it throws a non-terminating error.
Okay, but if you use Get-Module and then Remove-Module, it doesn't.
Yeah, it's nice. And then write separate tests for all of your nested modules because they're not
automatically tested, right, but you just give it the fully-qualified path to the module.
So a couple of conclusions. It took a really long time to do this.
It was my first one. I have since written more tests for things that I actually have in production code and
it went much snippier. Okay. So it took a really long time, but so did my first decent script.
Okay. It's a learning process and I think you really need to look at it in the long run, not in the short run,
right, so you
don't base how many times, how much time a test takes on somebody who's doing it for the first time.
Right? That's a ridiculous measure of efficiency. So I think that in a year or so when people get really
good at writing tests, we'll have better metrics for how efficient this process is.
It was much too easy for me to assume when I hit a bug in my test that it was a Pester bug.
This is a system in development and I did find a couple of Pester bugs.
They were pretty minor. Most of the time they were my bugs, they were logic bugs.
In this code, I have a for loop, right, and my for loop would not run.
You can debug these files too. Just run the test files, run them through your debugger, and I could watch
in my debugger, watch it skip that for loop. So I went up to Dave Wyatt and I said your code doesn't have a for loop.
I had set my for loop up to run while the value of a certain array, right, the index was less than the value
of a certain array and it was nothing in my array, okay. So really, don't assume that these things are Pester bugs.
Take responsibility. I found them to be most valuable for regression testing.
So in production, I have a system that runs fairly frequently and gathers some files and I change it a lot
because my boss always wants me improving my code, right, and this is wonderful for catching unintended side effects.
So normally, when you test a new feature, you test to make sure the feature works and this automatically
tests to make sure that your new feature didn't break other features that your users depend on.
The output type became really important to me. I have learned to use that output type attribute and to
include it in my documentation and it makes my writing, mocking, and tests much simpler.
It avoids a lot of mocking and test errors. Amen! Yes. The error should be explained in the help file.
Okay. That's a really important thing that I didn't realize how important it was for me to document errors
and not have my users try to figure out what errors they might encounter.
Okay, and then the final thing is that every module should have at least one test file.
This talk was reviewed by Dave Wyatt twice. He looked at all the tests and all the code and all of the slides
and I owe a huge debt of gratitude to the people who went before me including Jakub Jares and Mike Robbins
who wrote great articles about Pester.
We're celebrating 10 years of PowerShell and these are the people on the PowerShell team who've been there
all 10 years at Microsoft.
And this was Real World Test-Driven Development with Pester, so thank you for coming.