Okay, so some time pass and I continue to write these tests and I realized that I might because this is the
files, the Windows file system, I needed to do integration tests in addition to my unit tests, and this is just
because I didn't trust my own funny mocking of the file system, okay.
So what I did was I took the test file that I've been working on and I just renamed it to .Unit.Tests, okay,
and then just to make it easy for myself, when I wrote my Describe blocks, I changed it to
Get-ProfileUnitTest and Get-ProfileIntegrationTest and I added a UnitTest or IntegrationTest tag so that I
could run those separately. Okay, these are just structural. The code was the same.
And then I wrote some integration tests and I want to show these to you, okay?
I got rid of that great big function that creates that virtual world for me and here's that Get-ProfileTest,
but its integration test, so I use the real Enable-Profile to enable the profiles.
I have a Get-ExpectedProfile that goes and looks for profiles on the system.
I'm actually running Get-Profile and Disable-Profile on real profiles in the real file system.
Okay and this made me feel a little bit better. It did not follow the academic model, but it satisfied me
that the things that I'm doing actually work in the real file system with admin permissions and without.
And the other thing I did on these integration tests was that I put a #Requires -RunAsAdministrator at the top
so that I could test the admin parts. Okay. I'm testing the non-admin parts in my unit test.
Any questions about this or the structure? Yeah, Adam. The #Requires -RunAsAdministrator, does anything parse
that or is that just a comment? Oh, I'm sorry. That's part of PowerShell.
And you can put it on any script. Yeah, there are a couple of different #Requires.
In my version chaos talk, I was talking about
#Requires -Module, right, and it does, there's #Requires -Version for the PowerShellVersion.
There's #Requires -Module for dependent modules and you can, this is a different talk, you can actually use
a module specification object in your #Requires -Module to require a specific version of a specific module
with a specific GUID. So yes, very cool stuff. So now I have integration tests as well as unit tests and I
can, let me run them actually for you. I'm going to copy the file path and run as administrator.
Okay. Never trust yourself to type when you're doing a demo at a major conference.
Okay. And it should run them all. Have I forgotten anything? I don't think so.
Okay. Look at all of those tests for the simple little cmdlets.
Now one of the reasons that there are this many tests is that for each thing I did, I did an enumeration of
the files of the file paths that it returned and then I did a count
to make sure that I got all and only the ones that I expected and that's because PowerShell doesn't do a
great job of comparing arrays with arrays, right. Anyone who's ever used Get-Unique, right, will recognize that
and Pester, because it's PowerShell, doesn't do a great job of comparing arrays to arrays.
But in version 4 of Pester, there's going to be new array comparison features and I should be able to cut the
number of tests here in half, right, and just test, be able to compare arrays to arrays and that will be a huge change.
But again, that's why I specified that I'm doing 3.4.0, Pester 3.4.0.
Okay and fortunately everything passed. Okay and now what I'm going to do is I'm going to do, oh I'm going
to do it on a different set. I'm going to grab this next set. Let me show you.
We have a couple of extra minutes, so I'm actually going to show you something cool.
I didn't think I would get to show this to you, so I'm a little jazzed.
This is a great lesson and this is actually real life. So I'm going to do Invoke-Pester, whoops, do not type
during major talks at conferences. Copy the folder path will do it.
Okay. Great. And now I'm going to use the code coverage parameter, which is fantastic and it shows you code
that did not get run during the tests, so it helps you write your tests because it tells you where you've
missed code and it requires a file name and you always want to run it against your script file or modular file,
not against your test file. You don't want to test the code coverage in your test file.
You want to test the code coverage in your module file. So this actually happened to me.
This is real life. Okay, I had my unit tests and my integration tests and I thought I was really covered.
So let's see what happens. The output is at the very end. Okay.
And it shows here that my code coverage was 97.5%, which for people like me is a failing grade.
Okay, and what it showed me is that I'm missing a right warning, I'm missing what I interrupted to be a test
for a warning that I put in, right, and I cheated.
There's no example for that warning, but I put the warning in because I kept forgetting that when I change my
profile in one session, because those profiles are loaded when the session starts, I need to remember to
restart the session to make the profile changes effective, but I did not put that in my examples and I didn't
test and I thought I got caught, okay, but I didn't. Let me show you what was actually happening.
Note that this is on Line 172. Okay, and I'll go back to my code and I'll go to Line 1, whoops, delete, 172.
You see what's going on here? I'll scroll up just a little bit.
I did a cut and paste. No one ever does that. And I pasted my code outside of my function.
Of course it wasn't running. Okay. But if I grab this code and paste it back inside the function and save,
and I run that same test again, (Running) sadly, I get 100% and I don't deserve it, okay.
Code coverage means the code ran. This parameter does not say test coverage.
It's code coverage, right.
So a code coverage of 100% means that during those tests every line of code ran.
It does not mean that every line of code was tested. Okay, big lesson, important one.
Does that then mean that the code coverage is really making sure that you end up mocking something and then
never actually not mocking. That would be one way to look at it.
Yeah, so JB very brilliantly suggests that what we do is use code coverage to make sure that we're mocking
things so that it should show up in code coverage, to use it in a positive way, so I should see like a
if I'm mocking Get-Profile and I'm running only my Disable-Profile tests, that Get-Mocking doesn't run.
And I think the only thing I need to test that, the only thing that might happen is that if I only run my
Disable-Profile test, it might not look at Get-Profile at all, and also, it might recognize that it mocked.
Right, there's a great command called Assert-MockVerified, which means that even if the mock doesn't do
anything obvious, it lets you know that it was called.
Okay.
So there's my little CodeCoverage slide in case we didn't get to do this demo.