So here's the little module that I created. There is no code in here.
This is empty. This is the one that I created from my help file and here is my first test for it.
I'm going to go all the way up here. The rest of this talk is going to be looking at code, so I should
probably watch the time. Come on, June. Okay. So let me show you what one of these things looks like.
Pester, very reasonably, cannot handle multiple versions of your test module in the session at the same time.
So when you're running, you can use Pester for version 2.0 and later, but when you're running on PowerShell 5,
this is absolutely critical. And even if you are not running on PowerShell 5, you're users might be, right.
So you need to get and remove the module, any, all versions of the modules from the session, so that's the first line.
And then the second line is to import the version of the module that you actually want to use and to do this
I always use the required version parameter. Your experience may vary.
Other people might want to do this in a different way. And then I, because Import-Module returns a
non-terminating error, I use ErrorAction Stop because if it can't find my module, I don't want it to run the test.
Make sense? Okay. And if you are developing outside of PSModulePath, the alternative to all of this Get-Module
and Import-Module is to use Import-Module with a full-qualified path to the module manifest.
Right, that works too. But again, I use ErrorAction Stop just to make sure that, and your tests, test this.
Your test will run and you don't even have your module or the version of your module that you want.
Import-Module imports the first version of the module that it encounters, which is usually the first path in
PSModulePath, right, it's a discoverability issue. I do a whole talk about this.
Okay. Here's my InModuleScope. Let's get rid of this. Here's my InModuleScope keyword and it has the name
of my module. Okay. Structure make sense? Cool. So the first thing I did, actually that's a lie,
the first thing I did was to try to put all of this setup in my It blocks and that was just a total mess.
So if you have setup to do, you've heard that tests are arrange, assert, and act, right.
I do the arrange in a big function. Okay. And so basically what I'm doing here is I'm setting up the
TestDrive and I'm setting up fake profiles in the TestDrive. And so here are fake profiles paths.
You can see that there's no $ before PSHome because I'm fooling around in a TestDrive.
I provided a way for me to grab groups of those files that I needed for testing and at its heart, I take this
TestDrive path, I append one of those phony profile paths, and do a New-Item command on that TestDrive,
again with ErrorAction Stop. Make sense? So that's what I'm doing and it's much easier to do that in a
single function than to try to do that in my It blocks. So I'm going to go back to my help file for a second
to the Get-Profile cmdlet that gets profiles and I'm actually going example by example.
Okay. So my first example gets all profiles. It's pretty simple.
So here are my tests for it and you can see that I even used the example name so that I can associate each
example with my help file. It just gives me some guidance so that I know which sorts of tests to write.
So here's my Describe block and I usually use the name of the command that I'm testing in the Describe block.
That's just a style thing. Okay. Here's my Context block. And this is the little internal function that I
just showed you that I'm running. I want to test all profiles, so I test All and it returns a string because
I need to compare strings.
One of my experiences was that my tests were breaking because my types did not match.
Right. I would say this input is a file info object and I expect it to be this string.
Well it fails, right, or vice versa, right. I'm giving you a string, I expect it to be this file info object.
And one of the ways that I was able to get around constantly making these errors were to make the output type
on the functions that I'm testing explicit by using the output type attribute
so that I always know what the output type is. So in this case, I needed a string.
So I'm testing Get-Profile and I'm mocking a helper function that does not exist at this point.
I have no code. That file is empty, but I realize that if I want to mock the paths, I need to have a helper
function or something that provides those paths to the function that I'm testing.
Okay. So normally, when I test, I end up with more helper functions than I normally would if I wrote the code
without using the test-driven development process, okay, but it makes the code very modular.
It's actually very nice. So I'm mocking something that doesn't exist.
Here's my Get-Profile call. And so the first part of it gets all profiles and the second part gets only profiles.
Okay. And this is a pattern that I use a lot. I'm creating some fake stuff that's similar to those.
I'm trying to make it hard for myself, and I make sure that they're not there by doing some counting.
Okay and when I run this, I'm just going to run it in the console here, it will fail because I have no code.
Okay. Yeah. It looks like your test may be requiring something that you're not wanting, that you're not specifying.
You're required by this particular sorted order. Right, I sorted them.
Okay. Yeah, they're sorted. See the Sort-Object on Get-Profile?
Okay. Yeah. Yeah, good point. Thanks. Okay. So this failed because there was no code.
So I'm going to close this and grab the next version. The test file is virtually the same.
I'm going to put it over here. It helps me to have my code and test side by side.
Okay and here is my little Get-ProfilePath helper function and only the code that I needed in Get-Profile to
pass that test, which was a call to the Get-ProfilePath helper function and a Get item.
Okay. So this time when I go back and run that test, it passes.
Can you see that? I'm going to do that again. I'm going to restart the shell and run it again.
Okay, so that's basically the process. I take my examples, I convert them into tests, I run the test,
the test fails, I write the code. So let me show you what happens after a little while when it gets a little more complicated.
So here's my test code for the Disable-Profile cmdlet. Let's take a look at the examples for just a sec.
Okay. My first example gets the CurrentUser CurrentHost profile.
That's really easy because it's not in the System32 directory. My second example is the tougher one and this
is a decision, this is a design decision that I needed to make when I wrote my spec or my help file.
What do I do if there's something that I want to disable that I can't disable because it's in system32, right.
And so the design decision that I made was that it should disable what it can and write a non-terminating
error if it can and this is the example that shows that. Okay and you'll see the test that show it as well.
And then the last one just shows that if you have no profiles, there's no output and no errors.
And here are the tests that I wrote. You'll get all this code, but here are the tests that I wrote to test that.
This is the ones for Get-Profile. Let's close this. And here they are for Disable-Profile.
Okay. Notice that when I'm testing Disable-Profile, I'm mocking Get-Profile, okay.
Disable-Profile is going to call Get-Profile to get the profiles to disable and I never want a problem in
Get-Profile to make my test for Disable-Profile fail. Okay. So I always want to mock any cmdlet that's in
my module, okay. So the first one disables all the user profiles and then the second one turns out to be quite tricky.
Okay. So in the first case, I have multiple contexts for this because I'm using multiple mocks, but the first
test I tested with system32 profiles in a non-admin session and you'll see that I ran Disable-Profile,
I converted my non-terminating error to a terminating error with ErrorAction Stop and I used the Should Throw
operator to test it because it should generate an error. Now in the modular when I run it, it's a non-terminating
error, but here, in order to use Should Throw, I just made it a terminating error.
Okay? Good trick. Okay, then I tested the same system32 profiles in an admin session.
It should not throw and it should disable them. And then in the third case, I used all profiles in a non-admin
session and you'll see that some of them should error out and some of them should actually be disabled.
And here's that last test case where it's no profile, so I'm mocking Get-Profile with null, and when I run
Disable-Profile, my output should be null or empty and it doesn't write an error, even if I use ErrorAction Stop,
it should not throw. And I'll run this and I promise you that it works, unless it's a demo.
Okay. Any questions about the structure or content
of these tests? Yeah. So you probably should not throw. Is that applied in the throw when and you hadn't
sent that and it totally passed. Uh-huh. Well, so I would see the non-terminating errors, but unless I
was watching the test run I wouldn't see it, right, because it's going to go to the error stream instead of
the output stream. Right, so if I'm taking my test results and saving them somewhere in a file, I would miss that.
Questions? Other questions? How are we doing on time? Pretty good.