and let's look at some magic here. Now even though I'm running PowerShell 5 on Windows 10,
everything I'm doing should run on Windows or PowerShell 3 even or later.
I tend to put a requirement of at least version 4 because I think everyone should be at least at version 4
at this point for anything running on your desktop. Yeah, there's nothing that I'm doing that is version 5 specific.
So if you're not at v5 yet, you don't have to worry about anything.
So let's kind of walk through all of this process. And let's just run Get-Command.
It's alright. So you all know Get-Command retrieves a command info object
about whatever command you specify. It can be either a cmdlet name or an alias or a function, in this case,
I just
am going to use the full cmdlet name. So we're going to start off by kind of looking at this proxy approach.
So I'm going to get the command Metadata for $C and that $cmd, that object now, is pretty rich.
There's a lot of actual useful stuff here that I think a lot of people skip.
Now I'm going to go through manually through a lot of these steps and then I'll show you my cheat,
my automation tool, which will
speed up the entire process. How different is the output from the command's metadata than just what you do
when you've looked at all the properties up in the service? Oh, back up at the command default.
It's the same information, but this object,
this automation command metadata, has some additional methods. Thank you.
Which we're going to take advantage of here. Right, so it's more than just the properties.
There are some methods to this object that we will invoke to make the magic happen.
So like any object, of course, you can drill down, so you can look at the parameters to get a hash table.
This will be the same type. You can get the same type of information by doing Get-Command and looking up the parameters.
It's still there. We're just looking at it at a different way.
And I'm showing you all of this so that you can understand where, when I get to copying and pasting,
where the data is coming from. Okay, so it's coming from objects
like this. And the, no actually, I'm going to take that back. I may have misspoken.
Let's pipe $cmd, Get-Member -Force. So actually the methods we're going to use are for a different class.
I misspoke. I'm an IT pro veteran. Not a developer veteran. So we're going to take advantage of the
System.Management.Automation.Proxy class and that has a static method called GetParamBlock and the parameter
we're going to specify is our command metadata.
So this is going to be another way of parsing that hash table of parameter information.
Let's see what that looks like.
Yet, you know, and if you have a laptop, you can follow along with some of this.
I'm not going to go really fast. So now we can see. Question.
Is this all going to work for homemade of cmdlets and modules, and well if I hook one up, to get that same
sort of result? Yeah. It should. If you have. I assumed it did, but I wanted to make sure.
I think the only thing I would make sure of, if you wanted to copy one of your functions, is I would make sure
that you are using a cmdlet binding attribute. All the advanced functions.
Right. Yeah, so but if you have an advanced function, but if the Get-Command doesn't really care,
it's going to still find the same information. Yeah and Get-Command works on simple functions also.
Right. I don't know, but the command metadata will work unless you're using that cmdlet.
I always use cmdlet binding attribute in my functions.
Anyway. So there is the parameter information. That's the parameter block.
Now there are some things there, we're going to copy this later and eventually you'll see how I fix this,
I'm not a big fan, for example, of the way that they layout the parameter names.
So instead of being $name, it's $ and then in curly braces and then name.
It works fine and I'm sure there's
a legitimate .NET reason for them to do that. I know one reason is if you have a parameter name with a space
you have to do that, but you don't build parameter names with spaces, right?
If you do. Then you get exactly what you deserve. Yeah, yeah.
But you can see I have all of the parameter attributes and the aliases, that's the type, so all the
information is right there. We can also use this class, and again, looking at the command, to get the
different blocks of the command. Now every cmdlet and advanced function is going to have three blocks,
right, your begin process and end ScriptBlock. So I can use this magic here and say what's in the begin ScriptBlock?
Remember, what we're looking at here is what is then going to end up in a proxy function.
Once we get to this in an ISE tab, I'll go through it in a bit more detail.
But there is the begin block. We then have the process block, which is really just running the command.
We'll come back to this in a moment. And of course, the end block.
We're just ending the pipeline. What's also nice is that we can get the help for the command.
We're going to again use this proxy command object, this class, and there was a method called GetHelpComments
and the parameter has to be the help content. So I'm just having kind of nested Get-Help command for Get-Service
and you could certainly use variables and when you see my acceleration tool that's what I'm doing.
What this will do is, well let's select that, run that, this gives you all of the help, basically, in a text format.
You see where this is going because I can now start getting the pieces I want and in essence copying and
pasting them into a new command. So if I'm. Yeah. Does this work with the commands with .NET?
No. No, this is only going to work for a cmdlet or a function. This won't work with any native .NET class like
the math class, for example. For something like that, you could look to classes in v5 and build something
new around that. If we have time, I have something that we can at least get a peek at to give you an idea
of what that might look like, but that's kind of we'll see how quickly we get through this.
Yeah, everything I'm showing you assumes that the command you are copying is just that, it's a command.
It's not a .NET class. So then if we wanted to, we could go ahead and create the actual proxy command.
This is the second line that I had in my slide and I'm just, I'm actually, I should change that because
actually I am using v5. I have some clipboard cmdlets now. (Audience Comment)
Yeah or you could just pipe it to clip, number of ways you could do it.
So now, if I come here do New, paste it in. So there's the proxy command that basically took, I wanted you to
see the different little pieces because eventually I'm going to break those out.
But if you just create the whole proxy command like I did there, then you get all of that.
So now all you have to do is just start whittling away or adding in what you need.
Okay. You okay June? Well I, so I've been writing proxy functions for years and I did not know this and
I've just been copying all this stuff. Yeah, thank you. Wow. Okay, okay.
It's the only way I know to create a proxy function. Now granted though, it's not necessarily documented very well.
Well not a lot of people know about it.