So we're supposed to spend roughly two hours talking about a topic that I've called Accelerated Toolmaking:
Copying PowerShell Commands. I do a lot of scripting and I have built my own set of tools to help me
Build tools faster. I'm assuming most of you have written a PowerShell scripter tool.
Is that correct? Okay. And it can be kind of a tedious process.
We're always looking for shortcuts and other ways to do that. So that's kind of the premise for my talk today
is what can you do to kind of speed up this process and I'll go into this in a bit more
detail. Again, for those of you just here, you've seen this slide many times.
It's kind of amazing that I've known a number of these people for 10 years.
That's really kind of hard for me to get my head around sometimes.
Alright, so those of you who don't know me and there are people who don't.
I was at a bar last night and
someone recognized Adam Bertram and then he turned to me and he said who are you.
I loved it. That's perfectly fine and made Adam's night. So,
I am a grizzled IT Pro veteran. Not quite as grizzled as Richard Siddoway or Mark here, but I'm up there.
Well you know if
someone's got to be the old alpha IT pros and I've been around, I've seen a lot of things, and I try to bring
all of that experience to the work that I do and the books that I write, the classes that I teach, the sessions,
the blog articles, all
of that. I'm a long time PowerShell MVP, oh cloud and data center now, but
I don't know, I'm still always going to call myself a PowerShell MVP.
The whole cloud and data center, that's just too much
to say. I am a PowerShell teacher, author, I've written a few books, I do some consulting and project work,
so some of you know me and have seen me, I've been around a bit.
I do a lot of my writing at petri.com, I do courses for Pluralsight, and I am pretty active on Twitter.
I've got a slide at the end that has all my contact information.
Alright, so getting into this here. So what's the problem? Well, you have some sort of PowerShell scripting
or toolmaking requirement. Someone has come to you and said
hey we need a tool or a script to do X.
And you look around and go oh well you know we have this one PowerShell command and it does almost everything
that we need it to do. Almost. If we just
had like maybe one more parameter or maybe if it didn't have a particular parameter or if I could just
combine this with another command, it would be perfect. Now I could, me, I'm talking in your stead, say I'm a
PowerShell expert, yeah, I could sit and I would know what to type, but often you're building stuff for other people.
You don't want them to have to rely on knowing what to type, how to plug stuff together.
You want to build braindead simple tools, right. So how do we
get there? You may also need a tool or script or something for delegation.
You're building a server. You may have a constrained endpoint.
You want to put something on there that you're going to delegate to the help desk, or junior IT admin,
or an end user or perhaps you're even using JEA. And again, you want to have some sort of tool in place that is
based on something that is there now, but more customized to do exactly what you need to have done.
Now instead of reinventing the wheel, just build a better wheel.
Now fortunately, I'm going to show you some gimmicks, or tricks, or hacks, or
tools that I have built to help speed up this process of building a better wheel because like you, the last thing
I want to do is open up Visual Code, or ISE, or PowerShell Studio, whatever tool you're using, #Requires S version
4.0 and type everything out. I'm assuming most of you use things like templates and have other snippets and
all these other tools to help speed up the process. Well what I want to talk about today
is some other ways that we can speed up this process of building tools.
So I have this little kind of a copy-a-command concept and this idea of copying a command, you can go down
two paths and we're going to look at both paths. I've got
lots of demonstrations of this is the command I started with, this is what I ended up with, and we'll walk
through it and look, and so you can see the changes that I made. Everything I'll show you, I will share at some point.
Follow me on Twitter because that's probably where I'll announce where to go to get the download link.
So we can create a proxy version. A proxy version is a way of creating kind of a copy of the command,
but you actually are still running, when you get to running it, the actual command and you'll see that.
Anyone here ever build a proxy function? A few. Okay. Was it easy to do?
In some ways it's kind of easy. I'm going to try to show you
how to speed up that process. I mean, it actually is easy because it's really almost a two-step process.
You run this command and then Get-Foo will be whatever command you want and that will create an object that has
command Metadata, basically, the parameters and the ScriptBlocks and all the stuff that defines that command.
You then create a new proxy function. I think I've got more code examples here.
And then you edit, take away what you don't need, add in what you do need, and when you're done, you have a new command.
Your proxy command can have a totally new name or you
can reuse the name. Personally, I always come up with new names.
I'm not. The only reason you would create a proxy command with the same name is if you were going to be
doing some delegation probably with JEA. For the most
part though, the tools that I build I'm building to help me do my work and help other people.
I don't really do a lot with delegation right now. Maybe once JEA really
matures in v5, I'll move into that more and look into that, but and you'll see all these in action in a moment.
The other approach I take is to create what I call a wrapper function and probably many of you have built
things like this. It's a function Get-Foo that at the very heart of it, then call some other PowerShell command.
Those can be kind of tedious to write because you have to generate the help.
How many of you just love writing comment-based help? Yeah. So hire June and she'll write your comment.
Use Visual Studio to right-click your function and click Generate in PowerShell.
You have a question or you like writing help? I like writing help.
Okay. So we've got a few people who like writing help.
You'll see that I don't write help. I copy it. And but you also then assume multiple same parameters for
your underlying function or an underlying command that you are calling, but you have to type, do a lot of typing,
or manual copying and pasting. And when I build my wrapper functions, I leverage splatting
because I'm going to assume that the parameters for my wrapper function are mostly the same parameters for
the underlying command, which makes it really easy to just splat PSBoundParameters right to that command,
so it makes my code really simple to look at and I'm all about having really simple-looking code.
Alright, so that's really all the slides I have, so I'm going to go into PowerShell, walk through lots of demos.
We'll come back to the slides, ask questions, give you a few references,