Question. Well, I'll just have to show you.
I was curious if you've ever seen this. Oh, you'd be surprised.
So one of the things that I tried to do a while ago is try to duplicate the behavior of the dir command you
see in .exe in PowerShell then a bunch of people who have absolutely not used PowerShell solely because they're
used to dir and all the weird-ass ways you could use it in a cdn.exe and of course that was just like an unending...
Is it because they wanted to use a slash instead of the dash? They wanted a slash.
They wanted to put a space between the slash between dir/. Yeah, there's no way you can to,
PowerShell's parameters are going to expect a dash, and so there's no way around that.
But I haven't seen anything that comes close like those people had.
I don't know. Has anyone else seen anything like that? One way to do it is to open up PowerShell and start
with the cmd. (Audience comments) Yeah, I thought that I had written some other directory.
I know I have a number of commands, scripts, and functions to get better results for the dir command,
not necessarily as a complete replacement, although I thought I had something.
I'll look. It was a case where we were finding ourselves having to write this in the scripts, intern developers
and both things were conceived DWDSC and PowerShell. They just need to get over it.
Sometimes is easier to fix the person.
Easy to say, harder to do. Other questions, yeah.
This is mainly more of a comment than a question. What you're doing here is really exciting, by the way.
It fits into the general category of code generation, right, to automatically generate code.
One of the knocks against code generation has always been that you've made this new copy of a bunch of code
and then you tweak it here, you tweak it there, but now you're sort of stuck.
So if the original mechanism by which you generated that copy changes like you showed how you could, erases
were made, so you're now stuck and you have to reapply all that stuff.
Yeah, if you build a command that's built on say a Microsoft cmdlet and Microsoft and the next version of
PowerShell introduces a breaking change, yeah, you may have to go back and absolutely.
The only note is that the more of these automatic tweaks you can build into your original script and the less
you have to tweak afterwards, the better off you are to have to rerun this thing later.
And that would be a situation where using a proxy command is maybe a better approach because you're not
relying so much on the command. You're going to just send it the parameters.
Your changes go in modifying that script CMD ScriptBlock. So if you are, if that is a concern, then a proxy
approach would probably be the better way to go. But certainly. And I write stuff like this primarily
because a lot of IT pros don't like to type, they're not very good at it, they know they should write a script,
but you guys are all crunched for time. You want, and this is from people that post in a forum, I need a
script to do X. Well we're not going to write a script for you, but let me give you something that will help
speed up the process. So I'm always trying to find shortcuts and ways to take the pain away and the grunt
work so that you will put in comment-based help because you don't have to do anything.
It's just going to copy. You just have to then edit what's already there and editing is a whole lot easier
than typing it from scratch, right? So I'm assuming everyone here's basically IT pros and you're crunched
for time, you needed this yesterday, and I don't have time to sit and write a complete thing from scratch,
I don't, I'm still learning. You still need to know PowerShell and understand some of the things, but you could
run my command to generate the new version of your wheel and hopefully then have enough information or if you
get stuck then you post in the forum and say I've got this version of my, I'm building this script that basically
is wrapped around Get-ADUser and I'm running into a problem. How can I get around that?
So then you just focus on the little pieces that you want to change and not worry about the rest of the stuff
that you need. There's another question over here. Somebody just stretching their arm.
Here. When you brought the dynamic parameters over, any logic associated with those dynamic parameters was maintained there?
Oh, that's a good question. Because if you've got something like Get-ADUser, it doesn't have any parameters
associated with that. No, that's a good point. The and I'll have to test that, for example, the dir command
has dynamic parameters for a file and directory. If you're in the file system, you get those parameters,
but not if you're in say the registry. So if I were to build a well let's just ah, how much time do we have here?
I'll work on that. The include dynamic parameters is at least getting the name.
It's not actually building a true dynamic parameter, which a true dynamic parameter has logic, has some sort
of code to say if this condition is met, then bring this along. The main reason I had the include dynamic
was to get around the Active Directory issues because for whatever reason those cmdlets are, and I don't know
why, well because I know what they're doing, but I don't know what logic is saying make this dynamic because
it's not dynamic in the way like I'm in the file system, so make this parameter available.
They've decided that all of their parameters were just going to be defined as dynamic, which is a little bit different.
But you're right. I don't know if my copy command, I know it doesn't make a true dynamic parameter, it just gets
the name, identifies it. So you could still make it dynamic if you need to.
You'd have to go back and add that piece back in. That's a very good point.
Other questions? Is any of this useful or magical?
As I said I do all my writing and pretty much at petri or on my blog.
PowerShell in Depth, 2nd Edition. Oh we know, I guess people brought books, which is kind of a good thing
because this is one of the few times that Don, and Richard, and myself are all in the same time zone and the same location.
So if you've brought books for people to sign, I meant to tweet that out, do it because this is the time.
And this is you know other people should've told them like bring your Mark books and he'll sign.
I see some books down here. So this is a great time. So
PowerShell Deep Dives, I've going to give a plug here for this book.
This is also published by Manning. I was the editor, which I will never do again, a variety of PowerShell MVPs,
Microsoft people, people very active in the PowerShell community.
This book grew out of some of the original PowerShell deep dives in summits.
This is a book that is basically this conference, but in a book.
So the chapters are all written by someone active in PowerShell.
They're all little niche topics. You will not find that information anywhere else and what made this kind of
special is no one got paid for this. All the proceeds for this book go to charity, so you should buy two copies.
If you go to Manning and order and buy the book there on the Manning website, you can get the, I believe,
you get all the eBook versions for free. So don't go to Amazon if you want the eBook versions.
Anyway, so a plug for that because it's for charity and you will stuff about PowerShell that you won't learn anywhere else.
And then my contact information. If you need me, I'll be here the rest of the day and all day tomorrow.
That's where I blog. You're welcome to email me. I have some business cards if you need that sort of thing.
I'm pretty active on Twitter. You can kind of find me on Google+ every other day or something.
On Twitter, let me also mention this,
Adam Bertram and I on the first Friday of every month host, "host" kind of a PowerShell chat on Twitter.
That's first Friday of every month 1pm Eastern time to 2pm, for about an hour.
So we just get online. We use the PS Tweet chat hashtag and we just kind of answer questions or chat and
find out what people are working on.
So if you want to hand out or even just kind of lurk and see what people are working first Friday of every month.
I try to send out some tweets before that to remind people, but something else to think about.
Alright. Thank you very much.