So there's some things here that you would probably
want to get rid of or fix. For example, this is all just right now a script.
So let's say I was building, this is for a Get-Service, right, so I'm going to define my new function.
Let's call it Get-Myservice. Alright, so let's look at some things we would have to fix manually
and you're so welcome to kind of go through mam because maybe this will be mostly what you need.
Because this is going to be my version of Get-Service, I don't really want the help link for online to go to Microsoft.
You can, I suppose, but I'm going to delete that. I'm going to delete because I really don't need remoting
capability, but I do like that it gives me, if the command has parameter sets that it concludes all of that
parameter set information for me,
including the default. That's good. I may go and add additional parameters or parameter sets, but at least
what I'm starting with is good.
I can then come here and I'm a big, and this is just a personal preference, I would prefer this to look like $Name
without the curly braces. So you could go through and modify all of the parameters.
If I'm building this and let's say, you know what, I don't want to have the required services parameter,
I can just delete it. If I want to add a parameter, I can go through and add a parameter.
When we get to some of my before and after, you'll see how I do that.
I'm just going to kind of give you a feel for how this proxy function works.
The main part is here in the begin block. So this line here is basically going to build a wrapped command
that's going to call the underlying command. So the assumption is that wherever you're going to run this,
whatever that underlying command is, it exists on the machine where you're running this, right?
So we're going to take that wrapped command and this is basically just kind of
a ScriptBlock that we're going to build here with $ScriptCmd. This line here.
This ScriptBlock, it's really quite simple. All it's saying is take the underlying command, which is the wrapped
cmd, invoke it, and then splat whatever comes through PSBoundParameters, which is just a hash table.
You get that every time you have a parameter defined when they run the command.
So often what I will do, just for debugging purposes, is I might have here in the begin block, I add things like
write-verbose, (Typing) it has to be a string, so then when I run my cmdlet verbose, I can see
what the PSBoundParameters were. It helps me when I'm trying to debug to figure out okay how come this isn't
working because I want to be able to see what is going through. PSBoundParameters, are those just named parameters?
Yes. They are named parameters. That's where sometimes it can be a little tricky.
But that's why I do that, so I can see exactly
what is coming through because if I set some defaults sometimes that can work, sometimes not, so I need to,
I want to be able to see what is coming through the command, what's going to get passed to the command.
And then, hold on just a moment before I jump the train of thought here, and then I will also if I need to,
if I let's say I've added a new parameter and it's called $Test. I don't know what it's going to do, but I'm going
to add some. What I will need to do though does Get-Service know anything about the Test parameter?
No. So if I, but if I pass $Test into my new proxy command, it will fail because Get-Service says I don't
know what -Test is because remember all I'm doing is splatting. Now I can still use that parameter and you'll
see this in my, again my before and after
shots, but what I tend to do then, well actually in my tend to do, you have to do is remove that parameter.
There are things you can do to test it and if it exits and then remove it, I just get this to, I simply just do that.
If it's there, because when you remove it,
you get either true or false according to the pipeline, so I just do that.
I just say remove it. I don't really care if I get a message or not, just make sure it's gone.
I can still use $Test in my code later and what I typically will do is
modify the wrapped command. So instead of using wrap command PSBoundParameters, I'm probably going to expand
that or do whatever it is that I want to do. Most everything else will stay the same because at that point,
all I'm going to do is just pass the parameters to the underlying command.
Now there were some
questions over here. You in front. You mentioned when you debug, you sometimes put out PSBoundParameters,
but if you're actually using the debugger, PSBoundParameters still doesn't show up to that?
Well I do it with a verbose statement. So I just run the command with -verbose and I can see it.
I'm not, to be honest, I'm not a big, I rarely use -debug
because I'm doing stuff with write-verbose. I put all my verbose messaging in from the very beginning, so I can
see exactly what is going on.
And one of the reasons I do that is if I build a tool for someone and they report I'm having a problem,
it's not working, I can say start a transcript, run my command with -verbose, save the transcript, send it to me.
Then I can see exactly what's going on. And because one thing you have to remember when you're building PowerShell
scripts and tools is you always got to think about who is going to be running this.
Is it going to be you? Is it going to be someone who barely can type two letters without making a typo?
How will they use it? Will they assume to take something from one command and pipe it to your command?
So you have to take those things into account. Do I need, and I've done this in some of my commands,
well I'll have some verbose information at the very beginning that will also write out the computer name,
the operating system, the user account, other kind of meta command information, so that helps me figure out,
okay, why isn't this working for you. Oh, well you're running PowerShell v3 and for whatever reason this
isn't working on version 3 or whatever. So you include as much verbose information as you want that can help
you if you have to support or troubleshoot why your command is not working.
And there was another question there. Yeah, for the PSBoundParameters.Remove, do you have to use the string of
variable name? That is correct. PSBoundParameters is just a hash table, so you can use the dot method to test
there were some methods to test if keys exist or not, I just remove it.
And conversely, you can also, if you are splatting building another hash table, you can just add that.
But in this case, for the proxy function,
I need to remove anything that I add because the underlying command will have no concept of what that is.
I can still use $Test, that variable, that parameter anywhere else in my code.
It doesn't get rid
of the parameter, it just removes it from PSBoundParameters.
Oh and then the last thing with the proxy command, by default, and this is one of the, for me, one of the downsides,
of creating a simple proxy command with the steps I just showed you is all I
get is forwarded help. Ah, that's not going to help me a whole lot.
Now I've got to go back and copy and paste and get the help and paste it in.
That's too much work for me. I'm lazy. I don't want to have to work very hard.
But that's what the kind of the layout of a proxy function. Before we get to my solution, which simplifies
and takes us to the next level, any other questions over at least what this looks like?
We'll get some examples where you can see the before and after and we'll run them, so you can kind of follow through.
This is one of those things where I think the more you see it, the more it sinks in and you go oh now I get it,
I'm seeing where you're going with that. So we're all good?