So let's, let me see my next demo. I don't want to get too far ahead of myself here.
We're going to come back. I'm going to do another version of this so you can see again the before and after.
So that's Get-CommandMetadata, which is designed to create basically a rapid way of creating a proxy function
that you can then modify. I realize that I want to go more that.
I may want a wrapper function where I don't want the proxy, I'm probably still going to call the underlying
command, but for whatever reason, I want to build a wrapper around it, but again, I don't want to have to try
to find all the parameters and retype them and the help and all of that.
So I built
a second version of my script and I'm going to close some of these things here.
This tool actually is on GitHub. So my GitHub repo is jdhitsolutions.
There's also a link on my blog or ping me on Twitter if you can't find it.
So let's see this is this command. We'll just hide the help. I also realize in after I finished that first
function that even though it was getting rid of forwarded help, well there may be some instances where I do
want to use forwarded help because I'm still going to create a new version of Get-Service.
It's going to override and I'm still going to call it Get-Service and I want to show the forwarded help.
I want to be able to include that as an option. So I have a parameter there with switch,
so I go ahead and use it if it's there, so basically don't delete it.
The default behavior for this command is to create a wrapper function
or I can use that as proxy and it's going to do the same, a lot of the same code that I just showed you is in this command.
The big differences here, this forwarded help, is that as I go through, again I'm building a here string,
and if I'm specifying a proxy command, then it will go in and add the proxy
pieces, otherwise, it just uses the different commands that I showed you with that proxy object,
the proxy command class, to get the different pieces that I want and then manually paste them in.
The difference being, so I'm entering the parameters, the big difference is when I define here on Line 220
that process, that is what will show up in the eventual command that I'm creating.
So I can either create the proxy version of it or I can just build a wrapper
that's going to run the command and then splat PSBoundParameters, at least as a starting point.
You'll see some of my examples again before and after where I go a little bit further than that.
And even in my copied commands, you'll notice I'm inserting write-verbose commands, so you have no choice,
but to use them. Alright, so let's see how this works in action.
Alright, let's clear that. So I'm going to run Get-Command, again with Get-VM called Get-MyVM -IncludeDynamic -AsProxy.
This is basically, this will give me nope, no, no, no, no, no don't run the script.
Now I need to do. (Typing) For those of you whoever do presentations like I'm doing where you're walking
through a script, and I never do it, put a return keyword at the very beginning of your script file
that you're walking through. So if you do it like I did and accidentally hit F5, it'll hit return and then stop.
It won't run through all of my demo. I busted many a demo by not putting that in.
Alright, so we are going to create basically recreate that proxy version of Get-VM.
A few differences, I've inserted a little header metadata so it shows who created this and some copy of what
command, who created it, when they created it, I know, I just personally I find that useful.
I put in my standard disclaimer. I'm using the help. Help has all been modified.
Oh, this version I fixed my issues with the parameters, so now I've got everything in line with the way that
I want it to be. I have all
of the parameter sets and the names. And now I have the Begin, Process, and End ScriptBlocks just like we
had before with a proxy command. I can go through and modify this as necessary.
So what I did, let's just, so this is the before. So you can see I have all the parameters that I would have
running Get-VM and this is the after. So I'm going to reach in the oven, pull out the finished cake,
which in, make sure I'm on the right line here, yeah. So in this case, I went through and cleaned up the help
a little bit. It's always easier to delete stuff and then just copy and paste in my new examples.
Oh this copy command script, that function, will also detect
if the command that you are copying comes from a module, it will make that a requirement.
So it detected that this
was not from one of the standard out-of-the-box Microsoft.PowerShell modules and requires Hyper-V,
so it automatically inserts that for you.
Remember lazy.
I don't want to have to think too much. So the reason that I wrote this particular command is I use Hyper-V
all the time
and I'm running Get-VM, but I want to know what VMs are running.
I'm tired of having to type Get-VM, type it to Where-Object, where the State equals, so I just want a version
of Get-VM that has a parameter, I can't remember what I called it now and I can't see that, called state,
State= Running, so I've made that the default. You'll also notice and this once you go to add stuff,
yeah that's where you've got to earn your paycheck, so I did a little work and I discovered the class
name for that state is that, is an Enum. The advantage is, instead of making that a string or anything,
by going that route and identifying the enumeration,
I get IntelliSense. Okay. How cool is that?
So that is a new parameter that Get-VM doesn't know about, so here's how we fix that.
So I have some verbose messages. I remove that state parameter, right, because Get-VM is not going to know
that from PSBoundParameters and then I, this is a really simple version that's why I'm showing it to you,
I then modify the script command, basically say go ahead and run the initial command, but then filter it to
where object State= Running. So I don't
have to rely on having to type that all out. I can give this someone else and they want to say find me all
the VMs that are paused, they can do that without having to understand how to pipe to where and know what to type
because we've got the IntelliSense it's all braindead simple.
That command that wrapped that script command then gets thrown to the pipeline.
Everything else in Get-VM works just fine the way I expect it to be.
Now what I don't know, oh let's see if that even works. (Working)
Well let's do this here first just to show you. So get help. So all the parameters and stuff are copied over
from Get-VM and you can see my state parameter and
because I had that enum, PowerShell automatically expands all of that and shows me all the possible options.
Kind of handy.
And in my description I say that it's a copy. (Typing) Now what I don't know is if I can see on the network,
let's find out here, there's my verbose, oh good it worked. Because I'm going, because this virtual machine
I'm running is trying
to connect to the Hyper-V host, which is my laptop itself and when you present and the way I have to stuff it
up so I have a switch to make sure the networking all works and good it worked.
So I didn't have to do
anything and now I have all running VMs, -State. So
very easily, I just created a copy of Get-VM, made my little tweaks,
tweaked the help, done. It didn't take nearly as long as if I had started
with an empty ps1 file and manually had to type all that stuff out.
Questions over and this is kind of a one-way ways you would use a proxy function.
I'm still calling the underlying command,
but I have tweaked it in a way, in this case, I've added a parameter.
Yeah. (Audience Comment) So let's say like Get-ADUser, do you always want it to be -prompt department title
in edge or something, but so you're wrapping or you're doing it, now you're setting the whole value of the
parameter that already exists. How would you go about wrapping it?
He could use PS default parameter values and then you don't have to deal with…
Yeah, no he's saying if I'm building a new command and I want to set a, well yeah, it should override that or
you can just explicitly in your command because you can still splat something and specify additional parameters.
It's not an either/or situation. What about these other ones that you sort have been provided because properties
have showed they have to set other things and you're also setting that override to that.
What, are you talking about the properties on the underlying as a user object?
(Audience comment) Right. And so you said that your wrapper showed this specific value, but it's like calling
it also tries to set that. What happens? It depends on how you've written your command.
Hold on to that thought. I have some Active Directory examples we'll get to later.
Maybe you'll see something there that will answer that. (Audience comment)
They shouldn't be able to override anything unless they open up the script file and modify it.
All they're going to do is see your command. Right, I don't see how that's the way to write that to make it
work that way. Well you would just modify the help and assign, for example, here what I could do,
let's go back to my I need, even though this is default, I set a default to the computer name, let's say I
know that my, let's see if this will work. I know that my Hyper-V host is Chi-p50.
Let's reload that. Invalid class. Oh, that may be an issue. Let's put in, so we're going off the off-script
right now, but that's fine. That's how we learn things. I can't type and talk at the same time.
(Typing) I also hope that I'm running the right version of this. (Typing)
It's not passing through the computer name, which this is what someone was asking earlier.
So let's because I didn't specify, so the PSBoundParameters, so what I might have to do then is and I don't
want to totally delete, I don't want to totally ruin my command here, but maybe I will.
We're going to do this. I'm going to, let's just comment out this parameter just because I don't want to
have to modify my original command too much because this is kind of what you were talking about with the properties, right?
I want for my command computer name
to always be ChicagoP50. So I don't want to even make that an option for them, so I remove that from the parameter.
So now what I can do here
is I could add it, so let's do that. We'll just do PSBoundParameters Add Computername, right?
And I should see that because I'm adding that before I display it.
Let's clear this here. There we go. I'm not quite sure. Oh, because I have some additional code in there
That's still relying on the Computername, so that's, but so that's what you could do.
You would just remove from your version of Get-ADUser and then just hardcode in whatever other
commands you want. Would another way of doing that be to examine the collection that you could use the value
of the properties. Sure, I mean if you want you could leave properties in there and if it doesn't have,
yeah, then you could add something. So an example is make sure that those three always give up regardless
what else they have in the process. Right, a couple different ways that
you could do that. Alright, let's move on here because I'm amazed an hour has gone by already.
Or this is another version of Get-MyVM. Parameters and stuff are all the same, except this is now a wrapper function.
So it's not a proxy, so basically all I'm doing is saying take whatever parameters come through
PSBoundParameters and they're splatted in the process block and that's it.
It took like no time to create an entire working function. Can you go back into the line you were…?
Show me which line? The line that you select to amortize that.
Oh, to create this?
So I just ran my command, my copy command function, so that's when I can get VM, the NewName, include dynamic just
in case, done. (Audience comment) Yeah, the proxy, if you do it as proxy, then it creates a proxy command
version with a step-able pipeline and the wrap stuff. (Audience Comment)
Right, the first command, Get-CommandMetadata that I wrote just does proxy functions only.
This version Copy-Command because that's what it does.
It allows me to copy an existing command and I can either create a proxy version of it or a wrapper version
of it, which kind of brings me
to my next question, can talk about which is better. Why would I want to use a proxy function and maybe why
would I want to use a wrapper? Anyone? Yeah, well what you're doing if you don't use the step-able thing,
I think you actually can go through the inside command multiple times, but the behavior's not always going to
be the same. Okay. Which may or may not be, depending on what you need
accomplished, that's something. And that's why I want to have this quick little discussion here as to because
there may or may not, actually the only way you're going to know which is the right version is to probably do
both and test. It may also depend on how much you need to add or delete.
Do you need to put in stuff, I have to ensure that these certain things are met.
How much more difficult is that?
Proxy function I find a little harder to troubleshoot because everything's kind of nested in those step-able
pipelines versus a wrapper function. I mean if you look at the wrapper versions that we just created in
Untitled7, and my mouse, this is really simple. So there are a number of things that you have to, again,
and also think about who's going to use the command.
Are you going to be piping stuff to it? Will they need access to other commands or they may be part of like
the Get-VM stuff, I don't know. So you have to kind of make those decisions, but I have a tool now that you
can use to go both ways and you
can decide and it does not take very long to create something totally new.
So here is the finished version of Get-MyVM2. This is the wrapper version.
So in this case, I hardcoded in the computer name, I removed the state because Get-VM doesn't understand that,
and I'm not sure I tested this when I created this just the other day, so let's test it.
The default behavior
should be able to display all the running virtual machines on ChicagoP50.
And again, I didn't put in my, oh let's do this with verbose because I bet I'm having that same issue with
the PSBoundParameters. Oh, not clear screen verbose, that's kind of silly.
(Audience comment) Yeah. Okay, so yeah that's why you've got to test everything and I
modified it, but I never went back and tested it. So I need to go through and do the same things I did before.
I'll probably just get rid of computer, well no because I still want to give them the option, but I want it to
default, so I need to do some other magic, so I'll tweak this before I publish it or share it with all my demo stuff.
You can see how I solve that. Because in this particular case, I want them to be able to specify something else
in addition, but have it default to the current one, so I'll have to go back and look at that.
Alright.