let's run, take a look at Get-MyADUser. So I wrote this function.
This is a, let's just hide the help here, and this was created using my copy command for Get-ADUser and it
automatically got all of the default parameters because from being dynamic.
Most of these should look the same, except I made a few changes, one, I wanted to be able to search for users in
multiple OUs. The default for Get-ADUser, the search base only takes a single string.
I wanted multiple locations, so I modified
if you can see there and put in take an array. Why not? Who's in charge here, you know?
And I also wanted the ability to exclude user accounts by some pattern.
And you'll see I'll do a demo here, so you can see how that works.
Everything else is pretty much copied over from Get-ADUser. What I had to do was remove the parameters that
Get-ADUser doesn't know about like exclude. Now it knows about search base, but what I ended up doing here,
now this is not a proxy function, this is a wrapper, so here's a reason and one of the reasons I did this was
because notice I have a foreach that's basically looping through
the collection of OUs. That would be really hard to do in that step-able pipeline thing trying to piece that out.
This is much easier, at least for me. (Audience question) Actually, I think I wrote this someone posted
something in a forum and they were trying to search for users in multiple locations.
Why wouldn't they just not specify the script base? Because they didn't want to search the entire Active
Directory OU, so they've got 100,000 users, but all they care about, the user could be in one of three OUs,
which limits them to maybe only searching a 1,000 user accounts, so they wanted a way to fine tune and
restrict where they searched. Does this work meaningfully different than simply putting my script bases in
strings and then iterating in a foreach block and calling Get-ADUser?
You could do that too. Exactly. But that requires you to have more knowledge of how PowerShell were to work.
This runs faster than something like that or if its… I don't know if it necessarily runs faster,
but it's easier to type, to run the command because I just have to run Get-MyADUser and specify the parameters.
So all I'm doing is hiding all of, yes, what you could do manually.
There's not necessarily a performance gain in terms of getting the end result.
It's just a matter of
ease of use for whoever might need to use this tool.
So actually let's see if this is going to work. So let's dot source that.
Okay, so I had, now this does require the Active Directory module.
Now if I look at help for Get-ADUser, the original command, you'll notice original parameter for exclude, right.
Nothing up my fancy sleeves here. But my version, my copy version, does have and I added help for it,
which you should be doing, and you can also, I'm going to compare some parameters.
So I'm going to get the parameters for Get-ADUser and my Get-MyADUser.
It's another way if you want to prove what's different between two things.
Alright, so exclude is the only difference. Although, I know for a fact that search base is different.
So search base in the original is just a string and
in my version you can see it's a collection of strings. That's just kind of to prove things.
So I'm going to build a hash table. I want to filter on, I'm going to find all user accounts where the department
is equal to engineering. I want to search in either of the employees or the research engineering locations
and that's it. And I want to get the title and department back. So let's, this is not using the exclude piece.
If I were to do this and splat that to Get-ADUser that fails because the search base says hey you're
trying to tell me to do more than I'm designed to do.
Fine. Be that way. I'm in control. There's the result. So I searched using Get-ADUser and I wrote my own
little code
very quickly that, when I made the copy of the command, the only code I had come up with was really just that
little bit in the process block. All the other boring mundane stuff, which you have to have anyway,
I copied over.
So and that ran pretty quickly considering I have like 5,000 plus user accounts in my domain, and if you want
to see how the exclude works, so I want to find all users in the domain, except, oh so the exclude is
actually for a particular container, I want to find all users that have a name like Joseph, but skip anything
that's in a testing OU because Get-ADUser has no way to do that and that's actually probably a more typical use case.
I want to find something, but I want to ignore, there's no easy way to do that with Get-ADUser.
It would take a long complicated command, so but I put that in.
Another before and after.