I have another tool accelerator that I call my CIMScriptMaker and this is going to use
a lot of the same
ideas about creating a wrapper function, except in this case, it is specifically for Get-CimInstance.
And I'm just going to run it and show you how this works. Well you'll see the results.
You can look through the code and discover how it works. (Clicking)
And this is just, it only takes one parameter, the computer name,
because you may want to build a command that's going to query a remote computer that has CIM classes that
don't exist on your computer. What this script is going
to do and this just kind of cheats and uses up GridView as an object picker, is it going to fail.
Yeah. I think I have, yeah, yeah. First thing that the script does is enumerates all of the namespaces on
your computer or whatever computer you specify, so I'm going to pick Root\CIMV2.
It then enumerates all the classes within that namespace and I just use that GridView because that was the
easiest GUI tool to an object
picker. I could go through and do WinForms and WP app with that.
I'm lazy, right. And I can find the class that I want, so let's do Win32, no let's do service.
(Searching) I could filter, but I'm committed at this point. I have an option here if you want to test the
class, which will basically enumerate or get an instance back.
Most of the time, I'm going to assume that you know what the class is ahead of time, so
I'm not going to test it. I can filter. So let's say I want to build it a command that's going to filter on
the, oh let's see, for WMI it's the status, no is it StartName, no, the state.
Where's state? Oh, here nice thing about our GridView, there we go.
Click on the column headings. So I'm going to filter on state and by default, it's going to be equal and
then this is just going to pop up a little VB script style and running.
I can then select the properties I want to display. Let's just do description, Name, Status, StartMode,
PathName, StartName, I don't know. And then it creates a new command.
It saves to the clipboard and let's then come here and paste it in, generates a quick little help, puts in all
of the parameters. Now I still may need to test this and tweak this a little bit, but all of that grunt work is done.
I just had to go through some basically wizard to pick
what I wanted, remember lazy. Now yeah, I mean, it took me some time to build that first tool, but now you
don't have to do it, so win for you.
So this is another way. Basically I built a wrapper function. I'm still running Get-CimInstance,
but everything else that I want to do,
it's all done for me. I didn't have to create any of this code really from scratch as you saw.
Alright, questions before I get into the last part here and we look at some other before and after tools.
No, we're all good? I was just curious. Did you ever build anything to wrap thread line executables?
I have done things to take the output, yeah that's a little trickier because you're not really wrapping,
yeah, I've done some stuff for like Netstat to build a command that would run Netstat and then parse the output,
so you could do that. I don't have any cheats like these because every output would be different.
And hopefully, there are PowerShell versions or tools to do what you might have been using a command line tool for.
Not always, but.
Alright, so here is,