Okay, I'm going to quickly go through this. Because of variation
on the copy and commands would be to create commands based on CIM classes.
So instead of mucking around with CDXML, unless you just really hate yourself, create either proxy or wrapper
functions using Get-CimInstance for whatever class you need. Now the nice thing about CimInstance and the
reason I like the wrapper is because I then can very quickly either use computer name or CIM session.
I don't have to try to generate the, write the parameters for that to happen.
So I have some tools. So you could just, again, you could use the same idea of using copy command for
Get-CimInstance and create a proxy function, let's call, I have a call Get-CimOS because the goal will be to
create, so you use Get-CimInstance, Win32 operating system
and return a preset collection of parameters, of properties, sorry.
So the final version of that, that's the command, again going into the oven, is this.
We'll just minimize the help. So I didn't have to write all that code for the parameters for Computername
and CIM session. I have my verbose output, in this case, I'm adding particular parameters for the class name
and the name space and I'm then splatting that and I'm also doing something a little extra where I'm
inserting a type name for the output because at the end of my script here, I have some additional code that I
wrote to update the type data and format data, so this is all in one.
You could build this in a module. I have, just for the sake of demonstration, all in one scripts.
So if I run that, that loads function, adds all that type information, and let's see if this will work now.
Gets. So the default should be for the local computer name, you can do ComputerName.
Nope, (Typing) nope, core01, not 0 that's why. And if I were to just show you, if I pipe that to Get-Member,
you'll see that it's my custom type that added all that information.
I could create CIM sessions and pipe them to Get-CimOS, so I wrote it in basically to mimic
Get-CimInstance, but returns the variation I want, so I have a tool that I can give the help desk.
Oh, if you need to find an operating system about the computer, run this command, give the computer name, you're done.
So Get-CimInstance was kind of useful. And I also have oh this version, I also created a version that is a wrapper.
There's really, and it does the same thing, there's really
no benefit that I can tell one way or the other, at least in this particular case.
Only that one might be easier to understand or troubleshoot if you're looking at code or
kind of new to PowerShell. And I'm also going to share with you because I'm feeling like that kind of guy
and we have the time,