Alright, so let's come here and look at my accelerator tools. F8.
Oop, get the right line. So the first script I have here is a function called Get-CommandMetadata.
It kind of automates a lot of the steps that I just walked through.
I actually have two commands we're going to look at. This is the first one.
The second one takes this to a next level, but I want to show you this just so because this may be all you need
for some of your needs. So what this is going to do, and we'll just skip the help here, you have to specify
the name of a PowerShell command, you can specify the name of your new command if you want, and you can also
specify if you want to include dynamic parameters. Alright, so one thing I didn't talk about in my previous
examples,
a number of cmdlets have what are called dynamic parameters, which means you don't necessarily see them
unless some certain condition is met. It can make it tricky to try to identify those things when you're building
a proxy command or doing it in my copying command process I'm going to show you.
So I have a switch there that will say if there happened to be dynamic parameters, go ahead and include them as well.
I almost always when I run this include that because I don't know for a fact which command might have a
dynamic parameter or not. Now I do know through painful trial and error that a lot of the Active Directory
cmdlets or pretty much all of the parameters are dynamic for whatever reason that escapes me, the developers on
the AD team decided everything will be dynamic parameter.
So when I was building some proxy commands for some Active Directory tools, that's how I realized, oh I have to
include coverage for dynamic parameters and I'll show you how that works.
Alright, so I'm kind of stepping through. If I do include an alias for the command, then I just
resolve that command name because I need the actual underlying command in order to get all the command
information, not the alias. And you'll notice here for example, talking about my write-verbose, and when I
run this, I'll run it with verbose, so you can see I have a lot of verbose messages, so you can see if you
were running this what every step is doing. The other advantage, kind of a sidebar here, with the verbose
messages, documentation, right.
The message, as you're reading through the script you can see oh that's what this next section is going to do.
So if you build this all in as you're writing your script, when you're done, you've got your script documented
and you have useful feedback information for debugging and troubleshooting.
Alright, so we here on Line 65, we get that command Metadata. We saw that command before.
I then create the NewName. If you specify NewName, I'll do that, otherwise I'll just use the existing name.
Now this is kind of a tricky part. I had to add this from the Active Directory stuff.
It's very possible to have a command that when you get the command Metadata, there are no parameters.
That's what
happens with the Active Directory cmdlets. But there are parameters there, right?
But they're all dynamic. So I have some logic here that says if you do GetParamBlock and you find no parameters,
let's assume that there probably are some and let's automatically, even though you didn't specify it,
let's go ahead and get dynamic parameters. So I kind of
take advantage and so you don't have to remember to do it, I force you to do it.
Otherwise, you wouldn't see anything for it, at least the AD cmdlets.
So if you, once you do that, if you get those parameters, even though nothing shows, you can use the
Get-Enumerator and there is a property that you can eventually see of, it's a Boolean, of IsDynamic.
So if enumerate the properties, or I'm sorry, enumerate the parameters and I detect that some are dynamic,
I just add them to the hash table of my parameters property.
So it's my kind of work-a-round to look at what's dynamic and then manually, unless I kind of copy them,
up to the parent parameters hash table.
That way I can get all of the parameters. I get the command help.
Now I do this for you, no charge. Know the command help if I'm copying say Get-Service, all the examples will
all say Get-Service.
Well my command is going to be called Get-Myservice and I may want to use some of those same examples or some
of the other text in the description. So I use a the replace operator and just replace Get-Service with my NewName.
That seems pretty simple. Remember I'm lazy. I don't want to have to do a lot of hunting and replacing.
So let's do that. I also set the HelpUri to null. I then create the command metadata.
In this section here, okay hold on, it's regular expressions. Don't freak out.
I'm not going to try to teach you that pattern, just know that it works.
Huh? Yeah, I'm basically replacing the curly braces. I wrote this number years ago.
I might be able to refine that regex, but it works, so I'm just going to let it be.
So yeah, so I'm cleaning up because I also want the name to move up because I like having the string and then
the name of the variable or the name of the parameter. So that's my little magic to make that happen.
I also use a regex to find where that forwarded help, those forwarded help links are because I don't want them,
because I'm going to copy and paste the actual help. So I use regex to get rid of that and replace that.
Basically, wherever it finds the forwarded links, it just replaces it with null, basically deletes it.
And then, at this part here, building a here string, this is the new command and all I'm doing with the here
string is putting in all the information that I pulled from the proxy command and the parameters and just plugging
it in and that is saved to a variable. If you happen to run this in the PowerShell ISE, which I always do,
then I create a new tab and it inserts the text, otherwise, it just writes it to the pipeline and even create
an alias for my command. So let's not source that and I'm going to make a copy
of the, because I run Hyper-V, so I'm going to make a copy of the Get-VM cmdlet.
And I don't think it has any dynamic parameters, so I'm going to go ahead and do
dynamic, oh and let's, I said I was going to do this, let's turn on the -verbose and hopefully this will all work.
Alright, so there's all the verbose output so I can see if something had failed somewhere along the way I
would know at what point I had to go back and look. That's pretty simple.
So here is the final command. I'm going to, notice, see I called it Get-VM, notice in the help,
I changed all the help. I'm just going to hide the help for now.
Oh, I take that back. My little magic isn't
perfect. It does get rid of the curly braces, but it doesn't move it up.
So, that's not that bad. I just have to come here, hit Delete a couple times, clean this up the way I want
it to be. Those are all the parameters. And then I have the commands, the proxy command.
And so I've got the help,
it's all cleaned up, it has my names, all I have to do is again whittle away what I don't want and add what I do want.