I wrote a, I copied Get-History and came up with a new version I call Get-MyHistory
and what I have done is added parameters to specify a regex or unique because by default, Get-History will
show me everything
and I had two use cases, one I want to do Get-History, but I want to filter out all the duplicates, so just show
me the unique ones. Yes, I know. You could do that manually typing out the long command, but I'm just going
to screw that up more than likely or my other use case was I know I wrote a command and it had this pattern,
so I wrote a
parameter and added some code into the wrapper to use the regular expressions to get the history where the
pattern matches the command line. Again, I don't want to have to try
to remember how to do all of this manually at the console or rely on someone else to know what to type.
I want to build a tool that they can use using copy command, again, generating all the boring mundane stuff
then I just had to write the little fun pieces
like regex. Oh, I also wrote another version called Show-History (scrolling) that will, I'm not quite sure
what that does. Well you can play with that. Yeah. Well we can look at it.
I was just going to demo get Get-MyHistory. So I can find all of the commands that have a pattern and I
wanted to know
show me all the lines where I defined a variable. There we go. Now, yeah you have to know what the regex
pattern is, but that was
really easy to type to run the command and I built a better wheel.
I did another so I'm not going to do the copy command. I'll just go right to the final object, the final result.
F8. So I built another. This was before version 5 came out. How many of you have ever used Tee-Object?
That's a pretty hand cmdlet that I don't think a lot of people take advantage of.
With Tee-Object, you can run it and get the command at the console and you can save it to either a variable or
to a file. I'm not satisfied. I said I need it to also go to the clipboard because I do a lot of writing and
often I need to run the cmdlet and I need to copy the results to a clipboard, so I can paste it into my document
that I'm working on, and I don't want to have to go extra steps to run the command and then copy it.
I want to be able to see it, so I wrote a version of called Tee-MyObject that adds a parameter to specify the
clipboard as an option. So I just copied Tee-Object and went through and added a parameter.
I defined a new parameter set and I also ended up specifying the width through some trial and error.
If I do the clipboard, I also, in this case, again remember I wrote this before version 5, so I'm not using
any of the v5 clipboard cmdlets, so I'm using the actual Windows form, some .NET stuff to do the clipboard copy.
You could modify. What I found gives you some other regular expression stuff.
When you copy stuff to the clipboard, I was getting a lot of empty space at the end, which screwed up when I
paste it into a document, so I've got some regex to clean that up.
If I added all that, again this is just a wrapper, but now if I run this and let's just do, oh let's do this,
get-myvm Tee-MyObject -Clipboard. (Running) There we go. So it still, so I wasn't satisfied with the wheel
that Tee-Object
gave me, so it was close, it was so close. All they had to do was add one more parameter and I would be happy.
Well Microsoft is not going to make that change for me, so I did it.
A lot of the stuff that I write either is a result of something that I need for either training, or because of
writing, or something that comes across in a forum and a lot of people would probably have that issue and I
can use it then as a teachable moment. So like the Active Directory example came out of a form problem said
ah, that's kind of an interesting, let me see what I can come up with and now I have something,
you'll have something you can
actually use. Uh oh, they're having fun next door.
Questions, that was kind of the end of my official demos. Let's go back to the slides just so I
can be totally efficient here or at least cover all the bases. We can always come back to this.
So hopefully you saw a little magic there.
Questions over anything that I showed you.