So before we start that. Containers. Hands? Who's heard of containers?
Fantastic. Who uses containers? I love it. No, I mean that's the whole point, right?
We all know of this stuff, but until there's a reason or a benefit, we're not going to go and explore it,
so hopefully this is a good first introduction to this stuff for people that want to go explore.
Look, we want to kind of lessen this tension. It's a two-way thing.
Developers want to write their apps, IT needs to maintain it, the devs don't want to have the IT folks
reasonable understand and be equipped to do their jobs, and the IT folks end up thinking that the devs are just
running their stuff on their machines, but not thinking about the bigger picture of deploying it to the
actual production infrastructure. IT has all these policies you have to follow, all these procedures that
seem archaic and bureaucratic to the developer, but they're required to run a production service,
I mean that a developer often is not required to do and I have a feeling that a lot of the folks in this room
are in the middle of that arrow, so you guys kind of make the bridge between devs and IT.
So the focus here is how do make it so that developers can innovate and not be just kind of overloaded with
all of these processes and procedures and have it so that they can do what they need to do and IT can still
have some reasonable administration over the system. And the answer to that is containers.
So with containers, we have this completely new approach to building and shipping applications.
We traditionally would put out applications, deploy them into physical systems that we've built up with some
hydration script, or with a complex written manual, or a bunch of PowerShell scripts, or worse, a bunch of
batch scripts, but the whole point being here is that applications often require a lot of physical prep to
be able to be deployed. With virtual, we're a lot more destructive and we can pull stuff down if it doesn't work.
I don't know about you guys, but my dev box ends up having 100, 150, 200 VMs on it, not all of them running,
5% of them running, but it's not something I go and clean up often.
When I run out of disk space, I go delete the last 20% and the issue here is that while it's still at a fast
deployment, a lot of those same processes that apply to IT in the bare metal space is starting to apply in
the virtual space, so you're having now, we thought we had tricked them, right, we thought we had gotten around
it, but really what's happened is that now there's all sorts of policies and rules within organizations for
how you can use VMs. So with containers, you kind of get the best of both worlds and a couple of additional benefits.
You can push your app development forward, kind of get rid of a lot of the excess work in getting the
infrastructure up and mostly just consolidate a bunch of roles into a specific, into one server where you're
previously running an individual service for each.
Here, just stepping through a couple of the principles here, every application has its own dependencies.
The virtualization happens where the container engine, this really lightweight mechanism, isolates all this
stuff and packages them into these virtual containers. You have this shared Host OS that kind of lays on the bottom.
And then the flexibility that this gives you in the underlying OS is pretty great because the containers are
abstracting, the containers support within the OS is abstracting to those specific containers, what is the
host underneath it that the server was underneath it. And it's fast, right, containers can be changed
rapidly, you can scale them up, scale them down as you please. A lot of the benefits that we got going from
physical to VMs happen again with VMs to containers.
So this is what it looks like right now. Container operating system environments.
You've got Nano, highly optimized, born-in-the-cloud applications.
If it's something that has been developed, created in the past couple of years, Nano is usually the way to go.
You have Server Core, highly compatible, right, all the functionality that you expect is there.
I still see Server Core as that, what was that logical stepping stone to Nano Server and I think we're all
into Nano Server. I think you guys, if you're going to start experimenting, if you're still running full
server workloads, jump on board, come join the Nano Server train.
Nano Server is the future of Windows Server. It's a target for all internal iCloud components and new applications.
It's a new foundation for everything. It provides that Just Enough OS model to really mitigate the scope of what
could happen to a server and the possibilities, want that thing to be a role, an application, and really be
easy to maintain. If you haven't gotten this point yet, not everything will run on Nano Server.
There's going to be some work. Server Core will provide compatibility with a pretty long lead time for
existing enterprise applications to start coming aboard Server Core, sorry Nano Server.
And I mean yeah, you can see the picture there, right, let's move that way.
So next steps. I'd ask all of you to kind of embrace remote management of Server Core if you haven't already.
Understand that the GUID server is a thing of the past, my friends.
Let's move on. Server Core gives you a great way to do that today.
If you're running workloads in 2012 R2, a great place to start, so it's an easiest transition.
And make sure that things like tools and agents that only run locally, we've got to explore options that are remote friendly.
If you run into things that are big blockers for you, your partners, reach out to nanoserver@microsoft.com
and then get playing with it. So deploy it, the guide is there, feedback is on UserVoice, and that VHD link
again aka.ms/nanoeval. And lastly, RSMT feedback, you can go onto the Windows Server UserVoice.
If you go there, there's a link for it. That's it! Thank you so much!