Okay, so some functionality that's been added in the past few releases is the EMC, the Emergency Management Console.
So we showed you remoting using RSMT. You know that you can remote in PowerShell, but what happens at the
local console, right, what happens at the keyboard and mouse you're on locally, if you're on bare metal, or
when you connect on Hyper-V. So we need to provide a way… Yeah.
The one thing that it doesn't do in TP4 is allow you to start the DNS service.
Is that changing? The one thing that the EMC doesn't do in TP4 with the DNS service?
(Audience comment) Okay. I'll take a note of that after it and if you want to sync up with me, we can make
sure that your feedback gets heard. I'm not sure of the latest status on that.
So EMC, like I was saying, is the local way to get access to your configuration settings and now most recently,
network configuration and firewall settings. And with that, we can jump into a demo.
A few minutes left, so here we go. Connect to this guy. So that's what it looks like.
So I'm just going to log in here and that's what you got with EMC.
So from the top, you can see you've got your computer name, your workgroup that you're a part of,
operating system, and then basic time/date info, and then network addresses.
I'm not connected to Hyper-V switch right now, so this one isn't network accessible and you can see your two
options down there. So this has actually changed since TP3 when you guys last saw it for those of you that did.
So just tab in and then you have these two options, networking and firewall, and you'll also notice along the
bottom, the Ctrl+F6 and the Ctrl+F12 for restart and shutdown. So this will list all of the network adapters
and this shows you the info you need to make sure that you're up and connected.
Link status. Whether you're connected or not, interface, and the driver info, so driver name, date, and version.
And then notice along the bottom there, F4 to toggle the network adapter, you can disable it and enable it like that.
If you do F10, you can get the routes table to configure ARP routes, add a route with F10.
And then, IPv4 settings, so if you want to that, you can specify all that stuff there.
And then, IPv6 settings. So it's all accessible to make sure that you can get your network interface up.
And then the next piece of the puzzle, firewall. So these are all the firewall rules that ship in the box.
For my debugging purposes, I add a global WINRM 5985 rule. That's really easy to do.
From here, you can enable it and disable it. And notice that it's state toggling between enable, no, and yes.
Is there a plan to allow you to change like the local address from the EMC, for example, like you could toggle
them on and off right with the firewall rules, but you can't actually alter firewall rules.
There are discussions within a server team of how to best achieve that.
There are ways you can do it now using PowerShell, right, if you remote in, but from the EMC currently,
you can't add in TP4. Okay, and then I think that's it. Yeah, and then you can just log out with Escape.
And this works great on domain connected environments as well. Within the company, I'm able to use my domain
credentials and hop into a fresh Nano server.