Alright, good morning. My name is Neema, and I'm a program manager on the PowerShell team.
I work on PowerShell and DSC specifically and also Nano Server specifically on bringing all the cmdlets we
know and love from full PowerShell into the CoreCLR and Nano Server.
So today I'll be talking a little bit about Nano Server en masse, how we got here,
where we're at, and what the path is forward, and then a little bit about remote management,
how PowerShell integrates with Nano Server, and what we hope that you guys would do between now and the next
time we see you with Nano Server and kind of spreading the word on manageability in Nano Server.
So I'll talk a little bit about what we're hearing from customers, the journey we've gone through,
like I mentioned, we'll focus on three areas within Nano Server manageability, looking at PowerShell Core
briefly, and RSMT, the Remote Server Management Tools, take a look at some graphs and results we've seen,
benefits of Nano Server, and then focus on Nano Server in 2016 with containers, and then next steps from there.
And just a quick show of hands, how many people have had a chance to play around with Nano Server so far?
Great. And how many people actively use Nano Server day to day?
Okay. And anyone try to deploy a production workload to see if it works or not in Nano?
Alright, good. So this is the perfect audience for this talk. Hopefully I can convert some of you to at
least giving it a shot.
So three big drivers from our customers that have kind of led us to thinking this is why we need to define
Nano Server and it goes along the same tenants that brought us from Server Core to where we are now.
First of all, reboots impact business. We know that the people we work with often come back and say to us,
rebooting is a costly effort whether we're managing the systems, we're doing it for a client, or we're just
experimenting, uptime is really critical. So if you're patching a component you never use, it's kind of a
waste of a reboot cycle, and when the reboot happens, you want to get back into work and get back into work
and get back to your workload ASAP, not fiddle around with having post restart configuration.
Another big issue is server images are too big. Windows Server 2k12 R2 started to bloat up a little bit
towards the end there and we saw that with the Server Core option people had a slightly more lightweight option.
With Nano, the goal is to have the minimal, the minimal image, just the components you want so that when
you're transferring the images or deploying them, you can do it as quickly as possible.
When you're storing images, you can have per roll images customized to exactly what you want and nothing more.
And third, the infrastructure requiring too many resources. So this is where we're talking about an OS
taking up all these resources, presenting processes that are running in the background and really not giving you anything.
A good example of this when we've had feedback a lot about an early Windows Server 2016 TP Build are things
like the map service or the XBOX service. I don't want that stuff running.
And while we can address some of that stuff, Nano Server really is the solution to having just what you want running.
Also, by having a lower footprint, you can have higher VM density.
So where on a piece of metal, you can maybe run 2 or 3 server VMs, now you're talking about 10, 20 Nano Server VMs.
So this brings us to kind of our first tenant here, which is I want just the components I need and nothing more.
And to show you that, we'll kind of step through a quick journey of how we got to where we are.
So historically, Windows Server had this big footprint and you'd add on roles and features leading up to the
server 2K3 timeframe. With Server 2008 and 2008 R2, we took a little bit of a different methodology where we
provided Server Core as a GUI list option and full server that gave you all of the compatibility with
previous server infrastructure. With 2012 R2, we've kind of split up the GUI part and provided a minimal
server interface, and then on top of that, you load in the GUI Shell.
And as we move towards 2016 TP5, some of you that have experimented with TP4 may notice that we call this a
desktop experience and just server now. The default option for server is now going to be this desktop
experience where a lot more of the Windows 10 client shell that you see will be looped back into the server product.
So the Cloud journey now, these two big parts here, first of all, Azure, we want to minimize reboots here
because for Azure tenants, having these things constantly reboot is just interrupting services.
They have specific workloads that usually vesting towards some Azure resource group, which can be really
costly, even more so than on the on-prem solution that we previously talked about and also the provisioning
of a large host images has this big impact on network resources where a lot of network architects have to sit
around saying how many VMs are going to get deployed on this architecture every day, every week because I
need to allocate my network resources such that it can handle that throughput.
And a lot of times, that's the most bandwidth intensive action is deploying and spinning up VM resources.
The more recent step we've taken is with the Cloud Platform System and so Azure stack, Azure pack, the whole point
here is that we are bringing in a cloud in a box running everything you need to get off the ground,
but still there is some setup time involved, there's still some patches and reboots that cause interruptions
to the entire thing, and like you see here, I mean, the reboot times are still, they're acceptable, they're a lot
better than they have been historically, but we can get them better and that's really the primary driver
behind Nano is that we can do better. We have to let go of some of the past to be able to do that.