So the next statement, we need server configuration optimized for the cloud.
How do we do that?
So Nano headless 64-bit only and as a deployment option of Windows Server.
We've refactored it from the ground up, we're focusing on this CloudOS infrastructure, and born-in-the-cloud
applications, roles, servers that currently exist that are in use every day, we want to make those be first
priority workloads on Nano Server. And so this is what the new picture looks like.
So with roles and features, we kind of went along the zero-footprint model and even inside the company when
teams are trying to bring components to Nano, they're saying well why don't I just bring everything I got and
we tell them to take this opportunity and look at what they have and see whether or not it makes sense to
bring it to headless Nano Server world and whether it is adequately manageable using PowerShell's from the
other manageability tools we'll talk about. So all of the roles and going into TP5, this will change slightly,
will live outside of Nano Server, so we're talking standalone packages that you can pull down and install,
sound familiar to another operating system maybe. With that being said, the goal is to be able to pull these
packages similar to how you add Windows features to Windows 10 right now on demand, the way you want them,
when you want them, and to have the small amount of time between when you say install and when that role is running.
So the initial pool of roles is there, so Hyper-V, storage, clustering, DNS and IIS have rolled out recently.
In the latest builds you're going to see bigger, more improvements in the next release of Nano Server for
those two, and of course, CoreCLR, .NET Core, and we're really focusing on trying to bring driver support to Nano Server.
So all the drivers that are needed for networking storage, one by one, we're making sure that they're
compatible and that there's a reasonable story to get those injected into your Nano image.
Anti-malware, so Windows Defender is an optional package. We're working with the Windows Defender team
closely to make sure that signatures are updated via Windows Update, so you'll have a fully-maintained
anti-malware option on Nano Server still. It's not the wild west.
And then, SC and inside agents are underway and we hope to roll those out alongside the next release.
So PowerShell Core. So how many of you, I'm not going to ask how many of you have worked with PowerShell,
how many of you have worked with PowerShell Core? Okay. And for those of you that have your hands up,
keep them up, keep them up, how many are on IOT? Alright, okay.
So a few people. So the whole point of core is to refactor everything to run on CoreCLR.
That means that you'll have one common core between IOT and Nano and anything else we decide to do with .NET Core.
Full PowerShell language compatibility is there. Remoting is there.
So all those things that you expect for command invocation, PSSessions all work.
Core engine components are certain to get more green-lit, things like DSC are starting to show up and they're
fully-fledged functionality. Support for all cmdlet types. I heard some people in the room chattering about
C# and scripts and CIM, so all that stuff works. And the intent here as we work within the company to bring
cmdlets over is to make sure that people are bringing them over in the most future proof way possible.
So if there's somebody writing underlying code, we're not just picking up cmdlets from full and bringing it
over and we recommend when you do that, when you're working on your code too, don't just bring it
over blindly, take a look at what benefits Core will give you and whether or not your functionality makes sense.
And so, limited set of cmdlets initially, but we're adding cmdlets every day internally and those are
reflected in technical preview builds that you guys see. And as I'm sure some of you have seen on the client
with Windows 10 insider program, if you're on the fast string, you're getting updates to PowerShell whenever
a new build drops, so we're hoping to have that same mechanism with .NET.