Okay, so snapping back to where we were here. The point here is to support applications that are born in the cloud.
We're not trying to bring the legacy Win32 apps to Nano Server as the first tenant.
It's to support a new generation of application and tool. A subset of the Win32 APIs exist, again, CoreCLR,
PaaS, .NET and we want to have this kind of available as an OS everywhere, so you can install Nano as a host
OS onto bare metal, you can install it as a guest OS on a VM, you can install it within Windows Server
containers, Hyper-VM containers, run it in Azure, you can run it nested, you can do whatever you want.
With other hypervisors we want it to kind of be a utility more than anything else.
And future additions, as far as completion go, DSC will be feature complete in the next release of Nano server,
so all the functionality that those of you that has played with it seems to be missing or not fully cooked
kind of the similar way that we did with WMF previews, what was in previous TPs was experimental, what'll be in
the next TP should be more lock down
and every day, we're getting more and more resources that are working with Nano out-of-the-box.
So we run into one issue when I try to join the domain. Are we allowed to be calling the Nano Server first
and then try the domain join or will it be the same issue like when you need to join in like new create an image.
Yeah, the question is right now with Nano Server you have to join the domain before you bring it up and the
question is whether you will be able to online domain join. In a future release of Nano Server, you will be
able to do online domain joining. Will it be like on the final version of the 2016 or will it even (inaudible)?
I can't answer that question. It's going to be in an upcoming release.
Okay, so dev experience. I heard some people in the front row talking about writing C# code and I love hearing that.
So let's talk a little bit about what the developer experience is like.
And before I do that, so I should really ask that who's worked with PowerShell Node?
How many people have written C# code in the last 12 to 24 months?
That half of the room. Okay. Was there a sign out front? Cool, so here's the point with being able to take
what developer knowledge you have and take it to Nano Server. We don't want to redefine the developer
experience around a lightweight product. We want to take the best developer experience and bring that part
forward to Nano Server. So with that,
apps need to remove references to what's there, sorry, what is not in Nano Server and 32-bit references,
and developers can use Visual Studio 2015 Update 1 in the Windows SDK to target Nano Server today.
This functionality has been around since TP3, but it's significantly better in the past few months.
So first of all, the latest version of PowerShell WIN 10 or server 2016 TP, the latest WMF, if you're using
a VM, you make sure Hyper-V is installed, connect to that Nano Server machine,
In Visual Studio Update 1, you do a custom install, mark those 2 additional options, and then this link,
which I will have available a couple of links at the end that will get you towards all this stuff.
We'll get you the details, the files that you need to load into Visual Studio, the v6 file, and then you run that,
follow the instructions to install it, import the module, and you're good to go, and start creating a Nano project.
And I know people previously prior to the TP3 timeframe had started pulling DLLs off of their Nano Server VMs
and trying to fuddle with it, but this is really a first class dev experience now and we look to refine it
and get it to the point where it is just like developing for any other skew of Windows.
Yeah. Does this just pertain to unmanaged code or does it also pertain to anything .NET?
So the question is whether it pertains to unmanaged or managed code as well.
It pertains to a subset of .NET because not everything is there, but the intent here is that as we go through
this dev experience stuff, you would be able to explore a lot easier on your dev box what is and isn't available,
as opposed to blindly targeting and finding the APIs in there.
Okay, so it's more of like an API check versus allowing you to target .NET Core firmly right?
As we work towards a more holistic dev experience, yeah, you'll be able to say specifically target .NET Core.
The intent now is to kind of help you in exploring what it is and isn't there, and in addition to that,
there's an API port tool that the .NET team runs and that's on GitHub.
You can pull it down and say check my whatever you're working with, whatever file it is and see whether or
not this has APIs that are not CoreCLR compliant, or .NET Core, or ASP.NET compliant.
So project templates, full IntelliSense experience, your little error squiggles, full remote debugging experience.
If you download that thing that was linked and run that PowerShell script and all the info is on the Nano Server blog.
It's with the last blog post from 2015, if you're looking for it, and it kind of outlines the process.
And then also for this half of the room, there is like a Hello World example in C# that you can run,
execute on your Nano Server and I think it's like eight or nine steps should take you five minutes.
Any questions about dev experience before we move on? Great. So reverse forwarders.
Show of hands, who knows what this? Okay. Ten people. Alright.
So as we know, a missing DLL will result in an app failing to run, even if everything else that you require is present.
We need it to provide a way to run existing payloads without having to recompile for Nano Server.
So this doesn't eliminate the need to refactor code. This is merely meant as a stepping stone and having a
fully Nano Server compliant product. And so, there's a bunch of stuff that runs with reverse forwarders today.
Here's a sample of some of them and some of those versions have incremented as we've gone on and we're letting
up more and more that the intent here is to try and have these applications and these tools work directly on Nano
without the need for reverse forwards, like I said, it's a stepping stone, but they are there.
And so here's the colorful part. So let's talk about some of improvements.
I know some of you will have seen this, but let's talk about what Nano Server, what benefits there are graphically.
So servicing. These are servicing the full patch cycle from 2014. It has not been updated for 2015 yet,
but this is kind of what it looks like between Nano, Server Core, and Full Server.
Critical bulletins. You can see that the number there is significantly more for full.
And number of reboots. So the point here being that like I said at the start of this, that the intent is to
work down to a point where we take all the benefits and all the great functionality that we brought when we
went to Server Core with a little cost that people had to incur there to go to Nano Server because the
benefits far outweigh the cost as you can see just from a servicing perspective.
Security. Drivers, I mean it's every driver is one more that you wish you could run without on Nano Server
compared to Server Core, we reduce that footprint by about a quarter.
Services running. So this is always a great thing to do when you first spin up your Nano Server VM is take a
look at the list of services. It looks a lot better than Server Core.
And open ports. For those of you security conscience folks, I know that jumps out at you right away.
Going from about 27 to 12, I believe.
And deployment. So setup time. What I'm going to show you at the end of this is a great way to get off the
ground with Nano for those of you that haven't. Those of you that have spun up your own Nano image and
injected all that stuff and spent hours and written great blogs about how people can do it easier are going to
feel like I should have just waited. We now have a URL that'll get you a Nano Server VHD.
No more of this fuddling around with it, so with that setup time, under 50 seconds.
Disk footprint, half a gig! VHD size. So I mean on the way here, I realize I don't have a Nano VM with me.
My box is in my car for this afternoon's lightning demo, which I recommend you all come with all of our Nano
VMs on it. But this right here took me 45 seconds.
I had downloaded the VHD through into Hyper-V and it's what I'll use to show a demo here in a sec.
Sorry. (Audience question) Yeah, hang tight. So an installation option like Server Core here for 2016.
It's not the installation option. It is something that you pull off of media.
It's not listed in setup because there's additional steps that are required.
It wouldn't be really logical to step through the Windows setup process when what you really need is to configure
an image that you can reuse. So as you can see on the Windows Server TP4 ISO, there's a NanoServer folder.
And for drivers, for the leanest image, you just bring in what you want.
So we provide a couple of conveniences that I'll again show you in a minute, but it's as simple as just
injecting your driver as you vote to configure image. And all of the drivers that you experience, that you expect
from Server Core are available through this Nano Server OEM Drivers package.
And to run as a VM, define that Guest package.
So what I was talking about is features being available as you want them.
You'll notice that there is a subdirectory of packages. As we move forward, this will slightly change.
It will become much more logical in that they will not be static packages available on media.
I'll let you put two and two together. Right now, this is how you add packages.
Again, this experience will be greatly improved and for those of you that decide to take that VHD that I'm
going to show to you today between now and the time you start playing with that, in the next release coming out,
you may not have to fiddle with this too much because you might have everything you need, especially if you're
running in Hyper-V.
So let's talk about installation agents, tools, other software. So no MSI support in Nano right now.
Current builds require that you drop whatever you need on there or have a PowerShell script and there is new
installer technology coming. There's been some blog posts about it.
Again, upcoming release of Nano Server. So you'll be able to install, uninstall, inventory, do offline and
online installation support to kind of integrate it into your environment.
And then this is what I was talking about deploying. So up to now, you could go and do a bunch of work.
There is a tool now, the NanoServerImageGenerator, you can import that, and then you are able to just kick
off building the image, kind of just put the pieces together, run your Convert-WindowsImage and you're good
to go or there's a link, aka.ms/nanoeval will take you to a page that will describe the TP4 Nano eval process.
There's a ULA, you click the link, and it downloads a VHD, you put that VHD into Hyper-VM, and you're good to go.
I'm sure some of you could do it now and before we're done, you'd have Nano running.
So accept it,
deploys in a few. (Audience comment) Sorry. Yeah, or use your great cellular data connections.
But we have this available and if you guys want to sync with me, I actually have it available on my GUSB keys,
so I can hook those up and you can just copy it off to speed up the process.