So RSMT is one of the management options that I mentioned. So how many people have taken a look at RSMT?
Show of hands. Alright. How many people know what RSMT is, have heard of it?
Okay, so many more people. Great. So RSMT is a web-based portal to manage and it kind of includes
replacements for all of those local-only tools that you've either had to already PN or set up a remote
session to, so task manager, event viewer, device manager, control panel, even PowerShell, disk management,
File Explorer, all that stuff is there, and the team is continuing to greenlight more and more functionality.
So with that, I have a little video put together here that I'll walk us through of RSMT.
Alright. So this video is publicly available and there's a link to it at the end, but I just kind of wanted
to walk you guys through this. So RSMT as you can see in the nicely piece of portal that we've grown
accustomed to on Azure takes the server properties and then what you'll see here is a blade that shows you
all the details about that server. So you have the typical resource plan and IP info, you have blades for,
or you have all the performance information listed, and all the tools.
So here we'll step through kind of one by one to show you guys what you can see by RSMT, so OS info,
computer id info, so computer name, whether it's part of a workgroup or domain, you can change those settings
there as well without having to remote into the box or use any sort of remoting.
You can work with users by adding users there, network information is there, adapter info.
And then so if you look at each of these individual performance, you're actually getting a lot more
functionality than anywhere else we've been able to provide this stuff remotely,
so CPU information, network load info, memory use utility, usage, sorry, and disk metrics.
Disk metrics are turned off by default for performance, but you can enable those and start getting disk
metrics pulled in and there you go, so that's pulling off of the VM there.
And then for the tools, these are some of the tools I mentioned.
You can look at processes, you can search for processes, create process dumps and processes via this web UI.
You can also run new processes, so if you hit that Run Process button, type in the process you want to run,
hit OK, and it'll show back up there. You can add some more detail that isn't there by default, by using the
call and selector similar to how you would in Task Manager. And similarly with services, you have the
ability to start/stop/pause services, you can search for services, a really cool way to edit the registry,
so no more having to remote in or start a remote registry session.
You can go through here, search for whatever you need to change, whatever you need to add, gives you a nice
UI to do that stuff in. Adding roles and features is coming. For now, this just displays what's currently
enabled in remote PowerShell. So from a browser on whatever device you choose, you can remote PowerShell
into whatever box, in this case, this VM that we've got setup here and everything that you would expect about
discovery will also work. And you can see that it's following that same abuse of blade concept,
like the team has worked really hard to make this UIP as discoverable as possible.
Device Manager functionality works great. You can see devices. This is really good for debugging
environments or somewhere where you're trying to troubleshoot what's going on with the system.
Same principles that apply to maintaining systems in the cloud, kind of apply in the hybrid environment now.
And lastly, event viewer, so you can navigate through the event logs, can manipulate the query.
You mentioned File Explorer. Will that be available soon? Yeah, yeah.
So for the time being, since we're all PowerShell folks, you can do that stuff from the PowerShell prompt,
but there's two or three more tiles that are going to show up in the very near future.
Is there anything that they can't do in PowerShell that the basic UI will allow you to, like when you enable
disk metrics, can I turn that on via PowerShell? No. That has to be done through the UI because what it's
actually doing is reaching out to the agent on that
server. Firewall port that this used. Is this the standard PowerShell warning in our end?
So it's actually using an agent that you installed that configures that stuff for you and then you have the
ability to customize however you want it to connect, what port you want it to connect.
Yeah, yeah. You can definitely lock it down. (Audience question)
Sorry. Can you repeat questions? Can I repeat questions? Sure, sure, absolutely.
Are you going to interact with that agent that installed via PowerShell?
The question is are you able to interact with the agent via PowerShell.
So no. There isn't much interactivity for the agent. It's a base.
Is that planned? Yes, it is planned. Yeah. And when I say something is planned, I will caveat that it's
saying it's coming in an upcoming release of Nano Server, alright.
Is there an API exposed for this? Not currently, not currently.
Yep. Will this be available for Core as well or just Nano? Will this be available for Server Core?
It will be available for all flavors of Windows Server. Yep. The solution that you're trying in Azure,
so is this interface available for on-prem Nano or just Azure…? So you can actually connect it to whatever
you want in your hybrid environment locally, but it does run in Azure.
So you'd go into Azure, connect your computer to it, and then you can manipulate, or you could connect to it
even if it's a local machine. If it's off the internet right now, there is no way, but there is plans to try
and get this gateway service to run locally. How can you connect with a small IPM?
With IP address you can just define the same way we define that computer with the network it was in, you can just
define over the internet. (Audience question) Sorry? What ports are you using?
So I believe the RSMT team uses the default WINRM ports in addition to a couple of other.
I can get those details for you after. So is this available only if you have Azure?
It is only available with an Azure, yeah, with an Azure account right now.
Yep. Will the IOP web base in the interface follow this at some point?
Sorry, can you repeat the question? Will the IOT, the I-O-T management interface, will that follow along with this?
Or the two submerge? Yeah, the question is whether the IOT management interface will look like this.
I can't answer that question because I'm not part of the IOT team, but I can definitely get those details
for you if you want to sync up with me after this session. Okay.
Yes. Are there plans to manage any down rev operating systems? I can definitely reach out to the RSMT team
for you and get you the latest details on that if you want to sync up with me after.
Sure. Okay. Any other questions about RSMT? Yeah. I don't know if it's along the same lines, but do you
see does this support the server manager going to replace with short one larger?
The question is does this replace server manager? This is currently in addition to the management portfolio, right.
To answer your question, server manager is still there in the most recent server installs.
Yeah. Any other questions? Yeah. Are the clients just like RBAC just for the different toolsets?
Sorry, one more time? Is there an RBAC, like the role-based access control for the different rules that will be available?
You're talking about as to what you see here, like can you gray out certain functionality for a certain user?
Correct. There are plans to put segregated controls over certain functionality into the RSMT portal,
but I can't speak to when those will be in. Again, if you want to sync with me after, I can definitely give
you more details. Yes. So access control, does it have, can I, for example, have my own servers and my own
group, maybe someone outside of my organization access to manage a single server or do you do details on a single server?
Yeah. It would depend on. Sorry, the question is if you can have some sort of access where within a group
of servers you would have, give someone delegated access to one specific node, and yes, you could do that.
It'd be dependent on your infrastructure and how you're visible to the internet, but there's actually one or two
examples of that being done and if you want to sync with me after, I can share those with you as well.
Yeah. Any other questions about RSMT or anything we've covered so far?
Okay. Let's keep going.