The ports on these are interesting.
So this is a port on a remote server that your node is going to contact, and generally, you're going to be
looking at port 8080 for your HTTP or your HTTPS and port 445,
139, whatever SMB is set up to use in your environment. Now 8080 is completely configurable, but it's the
only port I've ever
seen used in any of the examples, so it's the one that I continue to use, but obviously you can pick whichever
port you'd like. Now the protocols
that the remote servers, the server-side components that DSC use, is XML or JSON over the HTTP or HTTPS protocol
and I say or JSON because in working with the report server,
you can specify in your request headers that you'd like your output back in JSON format, but the default is XML.
Now I tried using Fiddler to capture some of the packets that were being sent to the configuration repository,
but I am not good enough at configuring certificates and getting you'd have to get WMI in secured with SSL
in order to be able to run through a local, oh it was a nightmare.
Like I said, I'm a software engineer. I'm not very good at that end of things.
If somebody would like to help me with that, I'd be happy to lend my coding skills and capture some of these packets.
(Audience comment) Oh okay. (Audience comment) I own the whole domain.
I'll give it a shot later on. We'll see if we can get it to work.
So actually what I want to take a look at now, I want to take a closer look the CIM objects.
So you can use the Get-CimClass cmdlet to get the actual CIM class that is used to represent the LCM and it's
full of these methods like SendConfigurationApply, Test-Configuration, ApplyConfiguration, which sound a
heck of a lot like the things that we make the LCM do every day and it's actually very true because if you
look at the cmdlets and their verbose output, we have the Start-DscConfiguration cmdlet, it's actually just
invoking SendConfigurationApply. It's invoking the CIM method and passing it all the parameters and the
payload that it needs to apply this configuration. Now
this is actually a reason I was trying to track it in Fiddler. I was able to call some of the CIM methods
directly by using the Invoke-CimMethod cmdlet, but I wanted to try SendConfigurationApply and I could not
figure out for the life of me how to encode the payload, the actual MOF file.
I can get content on it all day long, but I was just getting errors left and right.
Maybe someday I'll be able to figure that out. I thought that would have been a nice little thing to be able
to show, but oh well. So my other example, Set-DscLocalConfigurationManager.
That's the cmdlet you use to update the LCM settings. It's just calling another CIM method on the LCM CIM class.
A couple of things that's important to remember about the communication of the LCM, obviously you have to get
all of your ports and your listeners configured correctly or nothing's going to work.
Every aspect of the communication for LCM, especially if you just came from Lee Holmes' talk where we're
talking about security, this will be on your mind. You can encrypt and use SSL on all of this stuff.
It's just really annoying to set up like most things with certificate, at least from my perspective.
And lastly, it's great to know what's going on behind the scenes, it's great to understand that CIM is what's
driving all of this, but in general, try to stick to the cmdlets, that's why they're there.
Next, I want to talk a little bit about logging. The LCM does do some logging, quite a bit of logging actually,
and if you're using the event viewer, this is kind of the folder path you can use to find where the DSC logs
are kept, but this is PowerShell summit, so we're not going to use the event viewer.
We're going to use Get-WinEvent obviously, which is very similar, although you'll notice the actual log name
is a bit different. And so what I did is
I took a snippet of log entries. So we're going to buy time and I used the timestamps to kind of like grab a
batch out of what the LCM was doing and I want to run through real quick what it did.
So we can see DSC timer is running some method. So one of the timers fired and it's calling this
PerformRequiredConfigurationChecks with the flag of 1. Cool. It's woken up the LCM.
Now we've got this job GUID, which is cool and we'll see this GUID a lot because it's on every entry
associated with this job. So we're doing a consistency check
or a pull started by computer null, which makes sense because it's fired by the timer, not an actual user.
We're running a consistency engine. We're checking our resources and you can actually see I was testing my
partial configurations here. Ran successfully. Awesome. You have a question?
Yeah. That timer is not a scheduled job, is it? I don't believe it is, but I don't know for sure.
I think it started that way, but somebody told me that it changed.
Actually, yeah, I think you're right. I remember hearing that as well.
Again, I don't know for a 100%, but I believe you're correct. (Audience comment)
Because that was one of the original problems I ran into trying to do a presentation last year where because
they were scheduled jobs, after a reboot, things would just kind of hang for a bit, so I had to alter my demo.
But so now, in V5 they are not scheduled jobs anymore. So now we've run our job and we get a nice summary
of everything, so we can see configuration mode was apply and monitor.
That's the check we just ran. We're monitoring. We can see what's set forth, that it's set for push,
a lot of information available to us. But now, as we kind of
climb back up that call stack, DscTimer successfully finished and now it's making another call.
We're calling PerformRequiredConfigurationChecks again, this time with the flag set to 5.
Down the call stack, we start something, we finish something, and then the LCM shuts down.
So what the heck was that? PerformRequiredConfigurationChecks was a method it called both times.
So I pulled it up on the MSDN documentation and I didn't get much farther.
But and I checked that this morning.
The page still looks like that and I'm not trying to call anybody out.
I'm not trying to be mean. But, (Audience comment) I looked for the Contribute button because throughout the
process of building this talk, I actually fixed a couple of typos in the DSC documentation since it's all on
GitHub, but this, unfortunately is not available on GitHub or I would suggest some updates to it.
But through all the experimentation that I've done and all of the verbose output that has scrolled passed my eyes,
I know that the parameter, the flags parameter set to one is the
configuration mode action. So that first longer set of log entries was when the configuration mode timer
fired and we performed out configuration mode action of apply and monitor.
The parameter five, which is what was used for the second one, is what is for the refresh mode action.
Now we saw in our log output that the refresh mode was set to push, which means the refresh mode action
doesn't really do anything. So actually that log is just showing us that both timers both happen to fire off
at the same time.
Now there are two other event logs related to DSC that can be useful if you need them.
There's the analytic log and the debug log. I went and I grabbed the similar snippet for this about the
same timestamps and the analytic log had two entries
and the debug log had quite a few more entries. So there is a ton of data available if you need it.
The important thing to remember about these two is that they're not enabled by default, so you can use these
commands to turn those logs on and start getting that output from then on.
To remember about logging, again, only the operation
log is enabled by default. That GUID that we saw applies to every unique job.
In Acme, I forgot to mention it, but the two separate PerformRequiredConfigurationChecks calls, they each got
their own separate GUID. So you can always use that GUID to
tie a job to itself. Moreover, that GUID is the same across all
three event logs. So if you wanted, you could have them all running, get all the WinEvents, put them all
together and sort them by time to get a really nice, full and complete overview of an individual job.
And lastly, and this was a suggestion from one of my coworkers,
don't forget to turn off the debug log when you're done because it is pretty verbose.
So let's see. I've got a little bit of time left. Do people have a lot questions?
Because if so, I can skip some of these differences and we can start doing some questions, but if you guys
are good, I'll go more into these differences. I have a question. So our session today goes on…
Well I don't want to keep everybody. I know we've got some drinking and relaxing and hanging out everybody to do.
I'll run through them. (Audience comment) Sure. So it's important to note, I'm not hitting all of these changes.
I just picked out some of the most significant ones, especially as it relates to affecting the LCM.
So some of the new or updated cmdlets, we have the Get-DscConfigurationStatus cmdlet.
This is a new cmdlet and it gives you access to the new status data that they'd made available on the LCM,
so this will tell you if it's idle, if it's in the middle of applying a configuration, if it's got a
pending configuration and what the results of previous configuration actions were.
Next, we have… Yeah. So I noticed that if I do an update configuration that I can't go and test the configuration
until that completes. Does this command run if that's the process?
No. No. No. Yeah, I believe it will come back and tell you the LCM is busy and you'll get an error.
(Audience comment) Right, because you have to wait for it to resolve.
(Audience comment) Nope. That's all you get unfortunately.
The Publish-DscConfiguration cmdlet that we saw using partial configurations, that is a brand new cmdlet,
that didn't use to exist before and I think that's a really cool way of perhaps staggering some updates.
If you've got multiple nodes and they're all in push mode, you don't have to send and immediately
ApplyConfiguration, you can publish that configuration to all the nodes and wait for the timers to fire
because they'll probably fire at different times, so you can kind of save yourself a bit of an update storm.
Next, we have the Update-DscConfiguration cmdlet. This is another brand new one and this is one that I wish
I had last year when I was preparing for a DSC talk because I had to figure out how to manually trigger some
of these updates. You can use the Update-DscConfiguration cmdlet to force an update if you, like let's say
you just push a Meta Config to your LCM to put it in pull mode. That's all well and good, but it doesn't do
anything after that. It just says okay I'm in pull mode now and then it waits for the timers to fire.
But you can use Update-DscConfiguration to tell it no, update now and it will go ahead and run the
appropriate CIM actions and get you your pull configurations. The next cmdlet is an updated cmdlet.
Test-DscConfiguration used to exist, but it used to be that all you could use it for was testing the LCM's current configuration.
Now what they've added is the ability to give it a configuration to use for testing and this is really cool
because it allows you to inspect the state of a node without going anywhere near touching its state or
updating it at all. So whatever configuration you give to Test-DscConfiguration, it'll reach out to the node
and it will basically perform a consistency check and check all the resources in your configuration for
compliance and give you a report back on it and that's it. So you could actually build multiple health check
configurations to use in your environment and just pull them up as you need and say even hey this machine
is not responding correctly. Let's say I've got a XenApp form. We do a lot of Citrix at my company.
I want to make sure all the appropriate Citrix services are running.
I could build a configuration that says this and this and this service should all be running and boom,
test configuration out to that machine and see what's going on. I don't have to do anything more.
I don't have to remote into it, I don't have to REP to it, I can get some quick data, and I know I'm not
affecting the state. How is that parameterized? How do you get it that information?
Trying to think. I think there were two ways to do it. You could give it the name of a compile configuration.
So you could, just like you were going to apply it, have a configuration run it into memory, call it with the
machine name and then pass that in, pass the MOF file in. And I think there was a second way to do it,
but I can't remember off the top of my head how that one worked.
Another new cmdlet is Invoke-DscResource. This cmdlet gives you direct access to ADSC resource in a configuration.
So let's say you don't want to look at the whole configuration. You know that there is one register resource
in there that you're concerned with. You can directly access the Get, Set, and Test methods of that resource
using this cmdlet. This is way more fine-grain access than we ever used to have to DSC.
And the last one, this is another cmdlet that already existed, but has gotten a nice update.
Like we were saying before, the Get-DscConfigurationStatus cmdlet, if it's going to tell you nope, the LCM is
busy, you've got to wait, Set-DscLocalConfigurationManager will do much the same thing.
So if I'm trying to take my node and make it a pull mode and change the configuration it's got, but it's in
the middle of applying another configuration, well I'm about to change the configuration.
I don't care what it's doing. I want to force it to stop what it's doing and change its settings now.
Guess what parameter they added? Force. So you can now use the force parameter to cancel any
action that the LCM is in the middle of and immediately apply your new settings.
There are also some new or updated properties on the LCM itself. The first is the AgentId.
This is going to come into play a lot when we're using reporting servers.
The AgentId is a GUID, it's automatically generated, and you can use it to uniquely identify your node.
In the past,
pull server configurations used to be identified by GUID and you would use that configuration id on your LCM
configuration to tell it what configuration to get. When that node reported to the report server,
it would report based on the configuration id, meaning that if you wanted to get distinct reports for every
node, you had to create a separate configuration with a separate configuration id for every node.
They've done a lot of work on updating that. Now you have the AgentId and you can uniquely identify all your
nodes and report on each of them. The LCM state properties, which were added, offer
basically a view of the most recent Get-DscConfigurationStatus, so they'll tell you what it was up to and
what the result was. The RefreshMode value of Disabled is actually new.
It didn't use to exist. It used to just be push and pull. And if you can believe it, the timers used to be
required to be multiples of each other, so you'd have to have 15 and 30, 20 and 40, and I don't know the
reasoning behind it, but they have adjusted that, so now that's no longer a requirement.
Another difference between 4 and 5 is the way you build your Meta Configurations.
I was saying before about when you use the DscLocalConfigurationManager attribute, PowerShell won't let you
use regular resources. In v4, you could, you didn't have to, but you could mix and match those resources and
have a regular configuration that when you compiled it, or when you invoked it with your machine name and all
your other parameters, it would create 2 MOF files. It would create the regular MOF file and a MetaMOF file
because you had used the LCM settings resources in there. They've really split that out.
And they also added the other resources that allow you to specify your repositories and your report servers,
which is much cleaner and more modular and allows you to specify multiples, which I think a lot of people are
going to find themselves doing, so it's great that they built it this way.
And as I was saying, it gives you a better distinction from your standard configurations, so there's a little
bit less confusion there.
I touched on this a little bit talking about the AgentId. So in the past, DSC configurations used to require
you to use a GUID for the name or pull configurations. But now, you can just use the friendly name because
the AgentId has taken that place of a GUID in a sense and the LCM will just reference the friendly name and
use that to figure out where the configuration is. Because moving from a GUID to a friendly name makes
things a little more transparent. They also introduce the concept of the RegistrationKey.
RegistrationKey is something that you set up on your pull server and it is a secure string, generally,
out of the examples I've seen people are using a GUID, that you're nodes must specify when they try to
register with a pull server. So it's basically saying hey I want to go to this configuration repository and
I want to get configuration blah. The pull server is not going to let me set up into pull mode unless I give
it the right RegistrationKey. This is just to provide a little bit of extra security so that people can't
very easily go snooping around your pull service to see what configurations you have and start to decipher
how you configure and implement your architecture on your network.
So does that only happen is when you set it up, it actually goes and connects to it right there.
Yes. Which is different, right, which is kind of cool because you get to see wow it's connected.
Now I know it's actually connected to my pull server. And you'll see it in the verbose output too.
It'll say successfully registered with pull server. Yeah, that's what I'm saying, so my question is,
is that the only time it does that because is there now like a certificate handshake between those two that
they use after that? The RegistrationKey is only used that once and if you look at the LCM configuration,
it actually gets blanked out after that, so I don't know the details, but there is some sort of an established
relationship from there. I think the node's AgentId gets registered internally on the pull server,
and so they're able to kind of bypass that pass phrase step in the future.
I didn't realize they have it blanked out. I never look at that before.
Yeah. That makes more sense because to me in my mind I was thinking well if it's still there,
then what difference does it really make? Right. It's there for every time.
Then anybody could go on and look at it and see that number. When the Jet database is used or
is that with the RegistrationKey in that Jet database. In the Jet database on the pull server-side?
Okay. Let's see. Partial configurations are also, those are brand new in version 5.
I don't have a ton to say about them. This is kind of a completely new concept.
But I think they're pretty cool, and again, they can help you with a lot of your large-scale work.
So to kind of wrap things up.