The more I thought about it, the more I realized that doing a deep dive on the LCM was almost the same as
doing a deep dive on DSC itself. The LCM does so much of the work.
Also, make sure you know the cmdlets. There's a
lot available and you can do a lot of different things with them and they're going to help you get by very well.
Also, get used to the LCMs capabilities, how you can configure it, and what you can do with it.
It's going to help you be more creative when you have to design solutions in different scenarios.
And lastly, between v4 and v5, we know that a lot of things have changed.
It's important to be aware what features are available to you based on what version you're running in your environment.
I still have environments where we're running v2, so I don't even get to use DSC a lot of the time, but it's a
very important thing to keep in mind and one other kind of, I guess it's kind of a speculation, but with all
the change that's happened just between these two versions,
I would definitely expect this evolution to continue. The report server, for example, is cool, but there's no
actual front-end for it. You have to design, you have to build the HTTP request yourself to get the reports
out of the nodes. I don't know what we're going to see come out of that, but I would bet you dollars to
donuts that something is going to change. Things are going to continue to evolve and it's only going to benefit us.
We also are celebrating 10 years of PowerShell. It's kind of hard to believe and especially as somebody who
really only, I only started working with PowerShell about three years ago, so it's been incredible,
even just these past three years and it's great to be up here in front of everyone helping celebrate these
10 years with all the people who have been involved throughout the whole ride.
I've got some links to the references that I used to gather the data.
You guys copied all that down right? Those don't matter because you can go to this link.
This is the one you would write down and this is a link to this PowerPoint and it's on OneDrive, so any updates
I make to it, such as correcting my CIM story should be available immediately.
Anybody have any questions? You want to move onto the Lightning Round?
Yeah.
I collected a couple of the strangest cases that I've seen and I put them together a little bit like a game show.
So I've got eight quick questions. If you push a Meta Configuration to a pull mode node that changes the
configuration assigned to the node, what will happen if the configuration mode timer fires immediately after
that Meta Configuration is applied? Is it A, the node pulls the new configuration from the repository and
applies it, or B, the node performs a configuration mode action against the existing configuration.
Who thinks A? No. Everybody thinks B? What's your refresh mode?
Pull. No, no, is it applying longer or? That's the configuration mode.
Set. What's that? That'll change the experience. That is true, but in this case, it wouldn't matter
because we're just saying it's going to apply the configuration mode action, but whatever that result is,
could be different, but that's what it would do. So the correct answer is B, is that if you tell a node to
say your pull node, get a new config. Until that new config is pulled by the refresh mode action,
configuration mode is going to continue to look at whatever it's got locally and whatever that action,
however you've configured it, that's how it's going to continue to work.
The question doesn't define why it changes it to pull or push. Yeah, the assumption is that it's in pull
mode the whole time and you just switch the configuration that it's pointed at.
That's my bad. I'm not going to be writing test questions for the SATs anytime soon.
But again, you could write them for Microsoft. Question three, TBD.
Let's say you have a node configured for partial configurations in mixed mode, but you haven't pushed any
of the push mode partial configurations. What's going to happen when the refresh mode timer fires?
So let's say you've got three partial configurations, two of them are pull, one of them is push.
You haven't pushed anything. Refresh mode timer fires, so what's it going to do?
Who think A? Okay. Who thinks B? The correct answer
is A. And actually, I just learned this earlier today, unless you use DependsOn in your Meta Configuration,
that might change the game a little bit, but if all of your partial configurations are just out there,
the node will pull whatever it can, whatever it's set to pull and apply it and eventually when you get around
to pushing the push ones, then it will apply that one too. Unless there's a merge error.
Unless there's a merge error, which you won't know until it tries to apply on the node.
Oh, this is a great one! If your configuration mode is applying autocorrect, will the LCM send a report to
the report server before or after it fixes any non-compliant resources it finds?
(Audience comment) Does it? Just because it's not set to autocorrect, it's…
It is set to autocorrect. Ah, sorry. Well the data's not complete until it goes through the cap so…
I had to go test this one. It actually, I messed up my configuration.
I messed up the state and let it run. It reported all resources in compliance.
So the correct answer is B. It actually sends a report after correcting the non-compliant resources,
which I guess in a way is good, but at the same time, you don't get any visibility on the drifts happening on
your nodes, so that's kind of a good thing to be aware of.
Question 4. Can you use Start-DscConfiguration -UseExisting to trigger a consistency check on a node's current configuration?
True or False? (Audience Comment) Correct answer is B false. This is kind of a trick question.
The use existing flag on Start-DscConfiguration will cause the current configuration to be applied fresh,
as though it just came to the node. If your configuration mode is apply only, that's a very different thing
than doing a consistency check and you can also see in the output in the logs, in the event log that when
it does a consistency check, it is noted as a consistency check, and when it's applied fresh, it will be
noted as apply. So again, like a lot of things in DSC, they're similar, but different.
Question 5. A node is configured for three partial configurations one, two, and three.
I'm just going to go ahead and say Start-DscConfiguration and try to push and apply a completely separate
configuration to the node. What's it going to do? Error. That is the right line of thought.
It does not let you do that. The command is going to error because you cannot use Start-DscConfiguration
at all with a node with partial configurations, unless you're using the use existing flag.
So even if I tried to push and apply immediately, one of those three partial configurations, I get the same error.
Just a couple more. These get more complicated, I swear. So we have a node using partial configurations,
so it's got one in pull, one in push, and another in pull. The LCM is set, the refresh mode pull.
What happens if you use Publish-DscConfiguration to send partial two to the node?
Now this was a question for me because normally when you set the refresh mode of the overall LCM to pull,
it won't let you do anything that's like a push or a publish. So I had to test this one out.
Now who do we, do we think A? No. Who thinks B? You're all right.
It will accept it and it won't say boo. Another node, partial configuration is complicated in that.
It threw a lot of curveballs at me. (Audience comment) It's tricky and I think we may see some evolution
of it before it really comes into standard use or we may… It should make sense though that you can combine
configurations because then you're basically testing a new configuration before you're setting it anyways.
Exactly. Yeah, it does make a lot of sense. So we have again our node with three partials, two in pull, one push.
Refresh mode property. Oh, it's still set to pull on the LCM. What happens when you use
Publish-DscConfiguration with the force parameter to send a modified version of the first partial
configuration to the node. This was a really weird one this morning.
So A, even though you use the force parameter, you still get an error because that specific partial
configuration is in pull mode, right, partial one is configured in pull when I'm trying to publish it.
B, the node takes the configuration, but then the next time refresh mode fires, it's in pull mode so it's going
to go not matching checksums and pull the other version back down from the pull server, or C, it takes my
configuration and actually updates the settings on that partial configuration to be push.
I had no idea what to expect with this one. You say A? Who else thinks A?
Anybody for B? Wow. And C? Nobody thinks C. Well that's too bad because it's C.
Why does it change into push? Because I just pushed the configuration to it I suppose.
I honestly, I just tried that this morning. I had a thought in the shower, I said what if I do that?
And when I checked the LCM settings, boom, all a sudden that configuration is now in push.
It could be to keep the older version from getting pulled back down and overriding what you just push, so I'm not sure.
Yeah. So you had an earlier question about Start-DscConfiguration?
Yep. And what it would do if with pull mode. If you use that source, it will reset the push button also.
Really? Yes, it will. Oh, you know why, I bet my example was different because I had partial configurations,
but if it's just one configuration and it's in pull mode, you can push to it with force and it will slop it to push?
Yes, it will. That would have been question nine. This is my last one.
Sorry I'm keeping you guys so long, but I hope you're enjoying it a little bit.
So if I've got a push mode node and I publish a configuration to it, so it's in a pending state,
then I change the refresh mode to disabled, what happens to that pending configuration?
Does it sit there in the pending state or does the LCM say no you disabled me, it's gone?
(Audience comment) Yeah, people say B that is removed? Anybody for A?
Okay. Who's for B just to see? About half and half. The actual answer is A.
I did a test with it this morning. It sat there in the pending state.
Now when refresh mode is set to disabled, you can't do Get-DscConfigurationStatus, you can't get a lot of
information out of the thing, but once I re-enabled it and I fired the CIM method to do a refresh timer command,
it took the pending configuration and applied it. So it sat there the whole time just waiting for DSC to be re-enabled.
Those are all the questions I have for you. If there's any additional questions for me, I'm happy to answer them.
If you think of any scenarios that I haven't covered and you'd like to see, I have my whole little domain
environment that I'm still very proud of building right here on my laptop.
Feel free to come find me, we'll test them out. I hope you guys enjoyed it.