So I've learned a ton
from all the IT professionals that I've had the opportunity to work with and talk to, especially at conferences
like this, so I'm really happy to be able to give back a little bit and take what I'm good at, writing code all
day long without breaking a sweat and kind of share some of that with you and some of the things that I've
learned exploring Desired State Configuration. Somebody else that's important for you to meet, the Local
Configuration Manager itself. This is what we're going to be focusing on.
Now I'm going to be assuming, since this is a deep dive,
that everyone's familiar with the basics of DSC and all of those introductory concepts.
However, if you do need to fill in some of the
gaps, this morning, Jason Helmick had a great talk. Unfortunately, it's passed, but you can track down the
video for that and there's a link here for the code that he released after his talk.
He's also got another one on Wednesday, have the details there. If you are
interested in filling in on some of the details, if you're a little light on those, definitely go check those out.
He's covering most of what I'm glossing over. What we're going to do today.
We are going to make a very quick run through an overview of Desired State Configuration, just touching on
some of the points that are significant from the LCM perspective, then we're going to get into the nitty gritty.
So let's jump right into it.