Another really cool thing you can do is make use of partial configurations. These you'll see applied
in the Meta Configuration that you send to the LCM. So you'll see here we're using this PartialConfiguration
resource to tell the LCM about all the pieces that we're going to be sending it.
In this mode, in this example rather, we're using Push mode. So you can use push or pull and I'll show you
pull in a second, but this is an example of configuring a Push mode PartialConfiguration, in our case,
we have three different pieces.
Some notes about using partial configurations. Once you configure the LCM to expect partial configurations,
you can no longer use Start-DscConfiguration
for that normal default operation that we do to send and immediately apply.
PowerShell will yell at you. What you have to do, what they want you to do is to use
Publish-DscConfiguration. Just as we saw before, we'll send the configuration over in a pending state.
At that point, you can use Start-DscConfiguration with the use existing flag and that will trigger the LCM to
check for those pending configurations, suck them in, and apply them.
Another really important detail is that the names of your partial configurations matter.
Basically, in the PartialConfiguration resource of your Meta Configuration, if you give it name X when you
publish a configuration to it, that configuration must be defined with configuration X.
The names have to match because that's how the LCM knows what you're giving it.
Otherwise, it would just be alright, well now I've got three configurations.
I don't know which ones what. To do partial configurations
in pull mode, we see a little bit more complexity. We've now added this ConfigurationID, which is a GUID,
which we haven't seen a GUID this whole time and I was so happy that we don't have to rely on GUIDs anymore,
but in this scenario, we still do. ConfigurationID ties all of your pieces together when you're in pull mode.
The rest, pretty similar, we're using again the PartialConfiguration resource and this time because it's pull
mode, we have to tell it where it's pulling from so you have a reference.
Just like any other reference that you would see, like if you were doing a dependsOn in any of your other resources,
you reference the ConfigurationRepository resource that holds the configuration that you're going to be pulling.
Lastly, you tell it that we're in Pull mode.
So quick question. (Audience question) The MOF file that you place on your pull server?
Yep, I'm getting to that right now actually. Here's exactly what it is.
So normally, you'd be able to deploy a pull configuration by just putting the friendly name of your
configuration.mof in that ConfigurationRepository folder on your pull server.
With partial configurations in pull mode, you have to use a friendly name .configurationid on both the MOF
and the MOF checksum file. So again, this is kind of, you're using your familiar names,
but the ConfigurationID ties everything together so the LCM knows alright, well these are all pieces of the
same one thing. Does that answer your question? It sure does. Another cool thing about partial configurations
in pull mode, you can actually put the different configurations on different servers.
This is one of the really powerful features because if you've got a large organization and you've got different
people in different departments and they all want a shot at your nodes,
you can give them their own pull servers. Have them set up their own pull servers so your security team gets
their pull server and I reference that and all the other teams get their own and you can reference all of
them separately, pull the pieces together, and apply one final configuration.
One caveat to that,
oh I guess I get to the caveat later.
It's on this slide. I'll get to that in a second. So partial configurations, we talked about push and pull,
but you can also do mixed node. So I can define a Meta Configuration to my LCM and I can tell it well I've
got a partial configuration for you. It's got four parts. This one is pull, this one is push, and these other
two are pull and it works.
I haven't been able to think of a use case for it, but I'm sure there is one, so it's very nice that it supports it.
As I said, this is great for splitting up large or overly complex configurations to make them a little more manageable.
One of the things I don't care for, although I don't
have a better solution, so I'm not complaining is that you have to custom tailor your LCM configuration up front.
Your LCM has to know all the pieces that are coming to it.
You can't just say alright well here take this configuration and then a few days later decide well I'll take
this one too, but don't get rid of the old one, apply them both.
You have to know up front all the pieces that you're going to be sending.
And here's my caveat, when you have your partial configurations, if they're coming from all over the place,
conflict protection doesn't happen until we're applying them all on the node.
And if you think about it, that's really the only way you can do it, especially if they're coming from
different pull servers, but it is important to remember because it's probably going to be a real pain to debug.
In general, when you're making configuration changes to the LCM, important things to remember are a lot of
these options are not dependent on one another, configuration mode, refresh mode, they operate independently.
So depending on the scenario
you have, you can pick and choose only the pieces that you're really going to need in that case.
That flexibility also means you can mix and match those settings to suit your need.
Configuration mode and refresh mode have three options each. That's nine different choices that you can make
just with those two options. That leave me to my
other recommendation. There are so many permutations of ways to configure the LCM.
If you come across something and you're wondering how it's going to work, build it quick in a lab, test it out.
That's actually how I got a lot of the information that I needed for this talk, which coming from a software
engineer, it was a lot of fun trying to create a domain
and install the certificate authority, yeah, that was fun. But we figured it out.
We got everything and I got all the info I needed.