Desired State Configuration lets you write code describing configurations that you then programmatically
apply to another computer and this other computer might be another Windows Server, it could be a workstation,
it could be Server Core, it could be Nano Server, it could even be a Linux Server, and maybe someday,
you can even push to your toaster. We don't know. Now Desired Toast Configuration might be a little silly,
but the point is DSC doesn't care what you're endpoint is
and the reason it's able to do that is because every DSC capable endpoint is running at LCM.
That's what allows all of this to become endpoint agnostic. Now there are two
ways of getting configurations onto a node. You can push your configurations to the node or you can
configure your node, point it at a configuration repository, and have it reach out on its own and pull the configurations down.
Now getting a configuration may not be the only reason that the node reaches out to another server.
Configuration repositories for sure are one of the main reasons, but there are also resource repositories
that node can use to locate and download PowerShell modules containing custom resources that it needs for its configurations.
There is also the reporting server, which allows the node to report updates
on its status to a central location, so you can get all kinds of good info.
And that's it. And I think I made it in five minutes or less.
Now let's get into the heart of the LCM and what can make this thing do.
The best way that I found to explore this is to look at the different configuration options.
What the LCM does is basically define on
how you configure. So you can use the Get-DscLocalConfigurationManager cmdlet to get all these options.
What are their current values? There are quite a few and I'm not going to go through all of them,
but I'm going to go through some of the biggest ones that have the most impact on the behaviors and the first
ones are the timers. There are two timers on the LCM. Each one controls the firing of a separate event and
I call them the Refresh mode event and the Configuration
mode event. These timers, these settings allow you to control how often those events fire.
Now what do those events do?
The refresh mode event controls how does the LCM on this node get new configurations.
It's got three possible values, push, which we expect you're going to push configurations to the node,
pull, which we're expecting to have a configuration repository somewhere and you're going to pull them down, and disabled.
The disabled option affects
more than just the refresh mode of your node. If you change the refresh mode to disabled, you will not be
getting any configurations updated, or applied, or monitored, or anything.
It basically turns off DSC. How often this action or inaction happens.
Again, it's controlled by the refresh frequency NIMs property on the LCM.
Configuration mode. The configuration mode setting controls what does the LCM do with the configuration it's already got.
So whenever you get a configuration on a node, the LCM keeps a copy of it cached on the machine, so it always
knows what its current configuration is. Configuration mode controls
what does it do with it? Again, there are three options. First is ApplyOnly.
This option configuration gets to the node however you're getting it there, it's always applied, but then nothing.
We don't look at it, we don't care what happens to it after the fact.
The next is ApplyAndMonitor.
In this case, again we apply, and then we will periodically check on it.
We'll say hey is that service still running that I said should always be running and the LCM will report to
a report server, if you configure it that way, what the status is and what it's been able to see about what's
in compliance and what's not in compliance. The last option is ApplyAndAutoCorrect.
I think this is the coolest one. With this option, the LCM will actually actively correct deviations that it
sees in the configuration. These are all controlled by configuration mode frequency NIMS.
That's what determines how often whichever action you pick is going to happen.
So these two timers are very similar, but they do just two distinct functions and we're going to run through
a couple of examples to kind of help clarify that. So the first example is probably the most common operation
you're going to see. So here we have our node with our LCM on it and I don't care in this example whether
it's pull mode or push mode. What happens, configuration mode timer fires off based on that setting you set
in the configuration minutes,
wakes up the LCM, and the LCM does whatever you've told it to do with its current configuration.
This action has absolutely nothing to do with any server outside of your node.
It's doing an internal consistency check. Another example and this one we're talking about push mode.
Now the most common operation that you do in DSC, in push mode especially is you say Start-DscConfiguration.
That action actually has nothing to do with the timers. It sends over and immediately applies your configuration.
So I didn't animate that one on the slide. I animated the Publish-DscConfiguration cmdlet, which allows you
to send a configuration to a node in a pending state. At that point, whichever timer fires, actually both of
them will cause this action. The LCM will wake up, it will find that there is a new configuration in the
pending state and it will apply it. Sorry, it will apply in step four.
Now it's important to note that this step four isn't connected to your configuration mode, well you could say
it is, but every configuration mode starts with apply and, so it doesn't matter how you set your
configuration mode, it's getting applied once it finds out that it's there.
The last example, we're going to look at what happens in pull mode.
So in pull mode, the configuration mode timer does the same thing that we already saw in the earlier slide.
We're just going to focus on the refresh mode timer. When that fires off, it's going to wake up the LCM,
the LCM is going to reach out to the configuration repository where its configuration lives, and it's going to
compare the checksums. So it's going to compare the checksum of its local configuration against the server's
copy of that same configuration. If they do not match, we're going to pull down
a new copy of the configuration and we're going to apply it. If they do match, we're going to skip those steps,
but it's important to note that the refresh mode action
whether it is push or pull always ends, now if it's disabled it doesn't apply because you're not doing anything,
but if it's push or pull, the refresh mode action
always ends with a consistency check, which is the same action that happens when the configuration mode timer
fires, so it's almost as though the refresh mode timer is like a superset of the configuration mode.
So that was a lot for just a couple of seconds, but now we're going to look at a couple of other
settings that are on the LCM. These three settings tell the LCM about server-side components that it's referencing.
So ConfigurationDownloadManagers references, where are my configuration repositories?
Yeah. So the configuration mode timer, does that still work when it's in a file?
The configuration mode timer will fire when you are set to ApplyOnly, but it won't do anything.
It basically wakes up and says okay I'm done and goes back to sleep.
And then last question. And when it is an ApplyOnly, does it always test true if that one time it did
actually apply properly? You mean the first time? Yeah, so in other words, it took the configuration and it applied it.
Yes. Now from them on, does it show, if you do a test on it, does it show that it's true?
Well if you explicitly issue a test, it's going to invoke an actually consistency check.
Oh, okay. But if you just are observing the activities that are happening as the timers fire, you won't see
any warning signs or any flags of anything being noncompliant. It'll basically just go under the radar at that point.
Okay, thank you. No problem. And we'll touch on that a little later.
There's a Test-DscConfiguration cmdlet you can use for that. So we have ConfigurationDownloadManagers,
ResourceModuleManagers, that is where you configure your resource repositories, again where the node can
reach out to get PowerShell modules containing custom resources and report managers controls which report
servers you're reporting to. You can configure multiples of any of these, which I think is really cool
because if you have a bunch of different custom modules that you need to use and they're built by different
business units in your organization, they could each have their own repository, you can reference them all.
The LCM will figure out where the modules are that it needs. It will search them down.
And the ReportManagers
as well. If you've got complex hierarchy and you want some nodes to report here, some nodes to report
there or some nodes to report to three places, you can do that and you really don't have to think about it anymore.
So at this point, I want to look at a little code.
I know I'm a software engineer, I get excited about looking at code, but I try to keep it down to a minimum
because sometimes I go a little code happy. So how do you build a configuration for the LCM?
Maybe take a step back, how do you configure the LCM? You use Desired State Configuration to push a special
type of configuration. This is
called a Meta Configuration and you start by using the DscLocalConfigurationManager attribute at the top of your configuration.
This tells PowerShell that you're making a Meta Configuration. What I love about this is that now PowerShell
is not going to let you use any of your regular resources. It will yell at you and this is great because
it helps you keep your regular configurations and your Meta Configurations separated.
The next thing you'll see in this configuration is the settings resource.
This is where the majority of the standard LCM settings can be applied for configuring things like your
repositories and report servers, they have their own resource, and this is how you're able to apply multiples.
You can put three instances of configuration repository web in there and reference three different
configuration repositories if you'd like. So that's how you configure your configuration repositories for
your module resource repositories. There is a resource repository web resource for your report servers.
There is a report server web resource. And I also would like to reference, although I don't recommend,
there are also
two different versions of the configuration and resource repository resources, so these are the web versions.
There's also a share version of each of those as you can use
an SMB share for your configuration or resource repositories. Report servers must use HTTP.
They don't support SMB.