So after what you can do with the LCM, I want to talk a little bit about
how it works and we're going to take a little bit of
close look at things like this. Incoming communications to the LCM.
What are the requirements? What do you need to make sure you have in place so that this whole thing works?
All that the LCM requires is the WinRM Listeners. There's a myth that goes around a
lot and it makes sense because they're very closely connected, but a lot of people think you need full
PowerShell remoting in order to do Desired State Configuration and that is not true.
All you need is the WinRM Listeners. In fact, I had a few cases, actually on the plane coming to the conference
I had to restore one of my nodes to a snapshot, and I'm on a plane, I have no internet access, the system time
is out of whack, Kerberos authentication starts failing when I try and use PowerShell remoting, but I can
still push DSC to it. So it's definitely a myth. All you need are those WinRM Listeners.
The ports that
the LCM is going to communicate on, the WinRM ports, you have 5985 to HTTP, 5986 for HTTPS.
Now the protocols and the connectivity of it all is using
this CIM protocol through HTTP or HTTPS. CIM is really cool and it's something that we were starting to hear
a lot more about and I know Richard Siddoway did a whole session on it yesterday that unfortunately I wasn't
here for, but CIM stands for the Common Information Model. So this is an object-oriented data model for
describing various components of the enterprise. It's not limited to just computer stuff, even though that's
what we're using it for. This standard was created by the desktop management task force in the late 90s and
it's actually been in use ever since. Another three-letter acronym that we're hearing a lot with Desired
State Configuration is MOF and that stands for Managed Object Format.
This, the syntax that is use to represent CIM communications in DSC.
So when you're compiling your configurations and you're getting those MOF files, it's basically a packaged up
translated version of your commands that are ready to be sent over the wire to another node.
Now as unfamiliar as many people may be with these two acronyms is another three-letter acronym that I bet
everybody's familiar with. What's really interesting is that WMI is an implementation of CIM.
Now there's more to it and I don't know
all the details on this one, but I know that WMI rides on top of CIM traditionally with some extra stuff added
and here's kind of the way
that I like to think of it. CIM and MOF are kind of like abstract concepts.
They're standards that were developed and they're maintained by a body and WMI is a concrete implementation
that makes use of those things. Richard Siddoway is giving me a face.
Have I gotten it wrong? Close. Close. (Audience comment)
So let me see if I'm understanding you correctly. WMI is Microsoft's implementation of CIM and the new CIM
cmdlets that were introduced in PowerShell 3 are also CIM, but they're a separate CIM implementation?
Yeah. Okay. Well, you heard it here. (Audience comment) More standards in here?
Yeah. Okay. (Audience comment) Okay, see and this is why I'm sad that I missed a class yesterday because
I would have been able to fix my slides. (Audience comment) That's true.
So the analogy that I kind of use for myself trying to understand this because I look at things like HTTP and HTML.
They're abstract concepts. They are a standard, a protocol, and a language defined by, maintained by a body,
and then you have a product like IIS, which is Microsoft's implementation
of a product that uses these concepts. And another way that this analogy is helpful is that
IIS isn't the only web server out there. In the same way, WMI isn't the only CIM server that's out there.
OMI is the Open Management Infrastructure. This is an implementation of CIM open source and it runs on Linux.
That is how we can send configurations to an LCM running on a Linux machine and it's probably going to be the
same technology that we used to send configurations to the toaster as soon as we get that worked out.
As far as outgoing communications go, we know that the LCM will reach out for three different purposes in general.
It's going to go to a configuration repo, the resource repo, or a report server.
I'm not going to cover setting those up. Again, Jason Helmick's talk from earlier today, he did a great job of covering that.
Unfortunately, it's already passed, but check out his GitHub code and keep an eye out for a video on that.