Hi everyone, my name is Don Jones,
and I'd like to introduce you
to PowerShell and DevOps Global Summit 2016.
Summit is a unique annual event
for the global PowerShell and DevOps community
and for 2016 we were fortunate to have Pluralsight
help us capture some of the amazing presentations.
You'll find more than 30 breakout sessions
and general presentations
representing some of the best to what summit has to offer,
you will hear from PowerShell MVP's,
product team members and community enthusiasts
and more importantly, you'll explore incredibly deep topics
that simply don't exist anywhere else.
Want to peak under the hood
of how Desired State Configuration works?
Want to learn about advanced
debugging techniques in PowerShell 5?
Want to learn what DevOps really looks like
in a real organization?
Want to see the latest about
domain-specific languages in PowerShell?
All of those and more were covered
at PowerShell and DevOps Global Summit 2016
and thanks to Pluralsight,
you can watch them at your leisure.