I'm really glad you guys came. I'm glad there's a size crowd because this is a topic that I'm particularly passionate about.
I do a lot of, I'm very curious when it comes to PowerShell and programming languages in general,
and so I do a lot of deep dives when I start thinking about crazy ideas, I wonder how this works, I wonder if
I could do that, and I go down the rabbit hole, and I disappear for a few months or sometimes a few years, and
come back later on with something neat. And so this is one of those neat things because I've gone down the
rabbit hole a few times. And I've talked about this topic at some other events in the past where afterwards I
feel like I flew a plane over their head around 50,000 feet, but those weren't PowerShell-specific events,
so it wasn't necessarily the right target audience for this kind of presentation, so I'm really glad to bring it here.
I hope you brought your thinking caps. When I'm doing content at any session, it doesn't really matter if
it's PowerShell related or not, I take questions at any time and I'll try to do my best to answer those questions
during the session, and if I can't, I'll push it until the end or maybe do a sidebar outside of the session
and figure stuff out. So feel free to bring questions up at any time as I'm going through this content and
yeah, hopefully you guys have fun and it'll make you think a little bit.
So domain-specific languages are interesting to me because they offer a lot of value above and beyond what
you get from native PowerShell. And so I want to talk about I guess a bit of a history of DSLs in PowerShell,
which is relatively short, and a bit of an ongoing experiment.
First, for those of you who don't know me, who am I. My name's Kirk Munro, and back in well pre 2006, I used to
work on MAPE and LDAP layer programming inside of a product called Message _____ Quest
and then I went to an Exchange 12 conference here in Redmond where they started talking about this thing called
Monad and kind of got bit by the bug because all of a sudden I could make guesses and be right 80-90% of the
time and that never happens in MAPE or LDAP. So that really kind of peaked my interest and ever since then
I haven't looked back. I've had my career totally focused on PowerShell for going on 10 years now.
I grabbed the nickname years ago, Poshoholic. If you want to contact me for anything, that's my Twitter
handle, poshoholic@gmail.com, poshoholic@hotmail.com, poshoholic.com, anywhere that I'm around on the web,
that's typically the nickname that I use aside from a few places.
So on GitHub, you'll just look up Kirk Munro and just be careful of the spelling of Munro because it's not
one of the more common ones, and you'll find my content upon GitHub up there, but that's kind of how you can
reach out to me.
So I mentioned we're going to talk about domain-specific languages and I'm going to do a couple of different
demos showing you the kind of things you can do and I need to bring all this with a bit of a
caveat. So this is experimental because there is no official public domain-specific language support in
PowerShell today in version 5.
They started doing stuff under the covers with some public .NET interfaces in version 4.
That's where it first started to coming to light. Some domain-specific language work was done prior to
version 4 just using functions and what you could do with PowerShell commands, I've done that,
but experimental is key on this because it's not a fully-defined process.
So I wanted to bring this here to you to get you thinking about it and to start discussions, maybe make some
relationships that continue beyond this event that you guys can talk to me about stuff or collaborate on
different things on GitHub and what not and see where we can take it because I think it's really interesting
and very compelling with what you can do with it.
So even though it's experimental, it's worthwhile bringing to the table to talk about now.
So what is a domain-specific language? Excuse me. A domain-specific language, I mean this is just from
Wikipedia, it's specialized, so it's domain specific and it maybe an entire language.
You might have a domain-specific language that is off on its own and the only thing you can do is what is
defined for that domain, but it may also be embedded within another language in the case of PowerShell
because PowerShell
you have cmdlets, functions, aliases, and all of that goodness, but then you can also embed these little mini
languages that you can intersperse with regular PowerShell and that give you some benefits above and beyond
what you get from normal PowerShell commands, so that's what I'm going to be talking about is that kind of a integrated language.
Yeah, so they're not general purposed. They're very focused on a particular task.
Why are they important? They're important because well these four reasons, so simplicity.
Domain-specific languages can take something that would be very complicated to do normally and it might require
a whole lot of code otherwise and boil it down into a very simple presentation so that you can digest it and
consume it and do things with it. Familiarity is key because you're coming from often with a domain-specific
language, you're working with a certain set of concepts and features and keywords and different things that
you have in mind from what the area of topic that's being covered by the domain-specific language is,
and so you can bring those concepts in and use them in a familiar manner just so you can make intelligent
guesses and do the right thing. Power because you can, typically, they obscure a lot, a lot of code behind
the scenes with just a very small package and structure. Structure is an interesting one and it doesn't
apply to every domain-specific language, but it applies to a lot.
When you're dealing with structure, well key domain-specific languages in PowerShell today,
Desired State Configuration, you're dealing with structure that defines your network infrastructure and how
it's laid out, and so it applies very well. The concept of domain-specific language applies very well to DSC
and so DSC is a domain-specific language. And any place where you're dealing with structured output,
so certain documents have structure, or like I mentioned infrastructure itself, domain-specific language is
worth considering for those solutions and you'll see some of the reasons why
as I go on through the talk.
How can they be implemented? They can be implemented in a whole bunch of different ways.
So I started tinkering with domain-specific languages back in PowerShell v1, I think, about just using
functions and aliases and cmdlets and defining things on the fly and doing a lot of metadata programming,
but they also could be implemented using native functionality in PowerShell 4 or later, and so the key piece
to that is System.Management.Automation.Language.DynamicKeyword.
Dynamic keyword is a class that has a bunch of static methods and that's where all the magic is intended to
happen and that was added for the purpose of DSC, but
technically, when they added it, they didn't really talk about it a whole lot because it was only half baked
and they didn't really want anybody going into it and figuring it out and I ignored all that, went into it,
and figured it out and figured out what was missing and added stuff, and so I've done a lot of tinkering
around with dynamic keyword and my stuff is still in an in-progress state, so I'm going to show some things
that are not published on PowerShell gallery, but are only GitHub right now because it's still evolving and
until I get it to the point where I think yeah, okay, I can push it there more broadly, then I'll push it on
the gallery, but for now, it's still is a work in progress and experimental, as I mentioned before.
Questions so far? No.