The first demo I'm going to go through is the first domain-specific language that I wrote in PowerShell and
that was back in my Power GUI days. So
PowerGUI is a PowerShell editor from years gone by and it was created by Quest and back when I said I started
working on PowerShell, I was fortunate enough to hear about this team that had Quest working on this product,
so I changed from mapping LDAP stuff to doing PowerShell by joining the PowerGUI team and did development and
then evangelism, and architecture, and eventually product management before they put it on the shelf because
it was free and not making money for them and they didn't like that.
And so during that time, and there were two versions of it, there was PowerGUI and there was the VESI for
Virtualization EcoShell and they were both the same thing, one was just a skin version of the other.
How many people, by the way, know PowerGUI in the room? Great! Okay.
I ask it sometimes and I see like two hands and stuff, so I'm thinking oh really it's that old, but no,
this is cool that you guys still know about it. So yeah, so back in those days when I used to work on power packs
and adding PowerGUI for those of you who don't know, one of the features it had was a management shell-like
user interface that was driven by PowerShell, and so you could add nodes and put your data in the middle and
have actions for the data on the right-hand side much like you see in MMC and modern management tools and with
that I did some tinkering with some domain-specific language work and I'll show you what that looks like.
So the first thing I'm going to do is load this ps1 file and just to show you how old this is, I haven't gone
and brought this forth into the world of modules yet. This is just a ps1 script file that I dot-sourced because
it contains a lot of functions and it doesn't use a lot of the modern even PowerShell v2 features just
because it's that old, but I still keep it kicking around. I intend to bring it forward with this DSL work
that I do, it's just not quite there yet. But it's interesting to show that you can do this using the old
PowerShell techniques of doing things. So when I load it, it adds all these huge amount of functions and
it's all about Visio, right. So it's fun when you're working with Visio to do automatic generation of
documents based on something and the most common example that I used to do back in the day was based on your
infrastructure, specifically on your virtualization infrastructure.
So I could take this and I could automatically generate infrastructure of well VMware at the time,
that's what my focus was when I started doing this work, and it would show your host and then all the virtual
machines all lined up in this diagram that's drawn on the screen for you while you run the command and so
it's kind of I guess sexy in terms of technology just in terms of seeing the UI show up on the screen while
you do it and it was fun to do.
But if you look at these, this is not domain-specific because these are just PowerShell commands, verb-noun,
so you could go through and create Visio documents using these just like you could any PowerShell set of
commands today and that was useful and I did it this way intentionally and actually this is probably how I
would create a lot of DSLs because this allows me to do one-off things by having the verb-noun structure,
but if I'm doing something entirely from scratch and I'm not just taking a Visio document that already exists
and going in and tweaking something on it, that's where the DSV comes in.
So let me show you an example of what that looks like. So, yeah, let me show you this file.
I mean you guys can look at this file and I'll share all this content.
I'll send it to Richard and he'll make it available to you. So this file contains the Visio commands.
By the way, just on the experimental line, these commands, I haven't gone through and tested this a whole lot
with PowerShell v5 and Visio 2016 just because it hasn't been a high priority for me, but I still have I've
got it working for Visio 2016 and PowerShell 5, so if you run this stuff and you find bugs in it, that's not a surprise.
Don't think well why is he releasing this stuff if it's in this state.
Technically, I'm not really releasing it. I'm sharing it as a set of examples and kind of things you guys
can do with it, and so take that caveat and feel free to experiment and take a look, but don't necessarily
build your production on it and have your manager come upset when it's not working.
So an example of how this might look in the DSL. If you notice, let me flip back for a second, the key piece,
the entry point into the DSL is right at the very bottom of this set of commands so that alias of Visio to the
Use-Visio command, that lets me jump into this kind of magic. So look at the top example here.
You can see the structure of the document being defined in the language itself, and so this is where
domain-specific comes to play, right, because I'm working with Visio, so the domain is Visio,
and anywhere where I'm dealing with Visio elements, those are the key points that I'm going to be talking
about in my structured domain-specific language. So I can create a new, I can open up Visio with a Visio
command and then I can define some defaults, the default background and the default page theme, and by the
way the default background doesn't work in 2016 right now. It'll just generate a warning.
And then I can go and I can create a new document. So then you can see I go into this document with a
ScriptBlock, and in that document, I create a page, and then inside the page, I set the background and the
diagram style, and start tinkering with the properties and all of this using something totally different from
verb-noun that lets me kind of really just look at the points using terminology that I'm already familiar with
inside of Visio.
But at the same time, I can intersperse regular PowerShell because it's just PowerShell.
So all I'm doing here is running PowerShell, even though I have this domain-specific language and even though
these commands that show up like DefaultPageBackground and page and all those things are defined on the fly
as I run this upper Visio command so that I can, all it's doing really is taking the aliases to that huge list
of cmdlets that I had, right. So I'm just, as I go inside of Visio, the first thing I do is define a bunch
of aliases to the things that are relevant at that point in the hierarchy and then as I go into document,
the same thing, and so I kind of control scope and visibility just by doing some alias turning things on and off.
And then inside of that, I can intersperse PowerShell.
So here I have some script that's just going to work with my file system.
I'm not really doing anything like large scale infrastructure, but I can.
This is a simple example where I wanted to show you how this works.
So I'm going to take that and I'll run it. And if the demo gods are nice to me, it'll work.
And by the way, the reason why I'm running this inside of the outside PowerShell session and not in ISE is
again, the whole experimental thing. I can throw this away and continue with the rest of my content without
worrying about it being mucked up. So I'll just copy and paste that in and why did that paste like that.
Hang on. Right-click-based. Better. So now it's running and you see Visio opened up in the background and
let me see if I can quick go to it. Where'd it go? There. So that was kind of jumping in and progress,
but that's the kind of magic that happens because it's doing a lot of auto layout on the fly, right, so you can
picture this being larger, going across a whole lot of infrastructure, maybe going to a huge set of Hyper-V
hosts that are discovered through SEVMM or going into Azure and bring in virtual machines or anything related to
just figuring out what you have for your infrastructure and doing things that you have to do to create
documents that kind of manage that and show that to management who doesn't get PowerShell and doesn't know
how to go and ask those kind of questions and giving it to you in a way that's automatic.
And so you run this kind of a command and it just goes and does the PowerShell work to interrogate the system
and then generates the document on the fly and that's the magic of a DSL.
And this is again just using the old school PowerShell functions and commands.
And if you look at another DSL that's out there, Pester. Pester doesn't use, as far as I'm aware,
the internet keyword stuff. They're just using functions and commands inside and aliases and what not to
make the magic happen. So this allows you to do that without getting into what I think will become the go-to
way of doing domain-specific languages going forward. Cool? Could a provider be considered of the main system language?
A provider could be, but it's generalized. So go back to the definition, I mean domain-specific,
because, it's kind of both, right, because a provider is specific to the way that you access the different
data silos, but yet generalized because it covers so many different silos and anybody can create a provider
for any source. So yeah, it was a great question and I was thinking about talking about providers,
but I kind of hesitated because it's a bit of both, I guess, because you have Get-Command, Get-Child, sorry,
Get-Item, Get-ChildItem, all those common sets of core commands, there's like 30 of them, and they work against
providers, and so that's specific to the provider model, but there's no domain-specificity to the---
specificity, thank you---to the internal silo that you're working with.
So if you're working with SQL Server, the only parts related to a domain they might see are the labels like
tables for the tables container. You might see some of that show up in the structure, but it's not quite the same thing.
Oh, and also, going back to the same Visio example, so here's another example and this is just showing backing
off a little bit from the domain-specific language itself how I could call directly into the commands to do
the same thing and I could technically write this using the cmdlets, but I like the declarative nature of the
structure for things so that when I'm drawing out in my head the diagram of the content, I can sort of draw
it on the page just using this terminology. Useful? Yeah, very.
Okay, good. So back. Now I've just got a whole series of demos, so I'm going to jump back and forth between
slides and demos. So that was my first language that I did domains for, and so as I mentioned, that was back
in the PowerGUI days and this is fun. My son, this long, long time ago back when he was a kid because he knew
I was really into PowerGUI and so he made that for me one day when I was away on a trip, which is kind of fun.
Kids are great, right, because you just learn so much from how they do things differently than how we do things.
So my son is into automation, but not at all using PowerShell. His kind of automation is in Minecraft where
he creates these huge farms to generate these blocks that he uses throughout the rest of his world's Minecraft
and he's on YouTube, and he's got his channel, and he's got like a 100 videos posted, and so his automation,
I don't
understand at all because I look at those blocks and the red stone and how that all connects and I wonder how
is he wrap his head around that because I don't want to read text, but anyway, it's just fun to see how automation
applies in different ways. Oh, and I guess it's not fair if I don't mention my daughter.
So my daughter, she's more managerial, so her automation is more making sure I'm up at 6:00 in the morning
because she wants me to automate making her lunch for her for that day for school.