Now that I've gone through that class itself, I want to talk about how that class and how work I've done with
that class allows me to redefine how DSLs are created. So I work on a whole bunch of modules and these days
all the modules I work on I put the suffix of Px at the end, which Px kind of looks at a glance, maybe if I squint,
like Rx, kind of like remedies or prescriptive solutions and that what these are, so a lot of the modules I create,
actually all the modules I create, so you'll find if you do a search for StartPx on the PowerShell gallery,
you'll find a lot of content from me and on GitHub some things are not on the gallery yet like LanguagePx,
that's my solution. So I create this module, LanguagePx and I want to show you what that allows me to do.
Who here knows about Doug Fink's ImportExcel module? Have you guys seen that?
A good number of people. So ImportExcel is cool because ImportExcel is also about doc creation.
You've got content and you want to push that into an Excel spreadsheet and maybe have some pivot tables and
some charts associated with that and do an automated way, and so Doug's been investing time and effort in
there and that's been quite popular and people really like it. And so, when he first started showing that
content and showing the commands that are available, I immediately thought of the DSL work because of the work
I've done in that space. So let me just load that module up and I'll show you what the command set looks like.
So it's got a whole bunch of commands in there, stuff dealing with ranges and stuff dealing with conditional
tests and Excel charts and plots and pie charts and all these different things.
And that's the functionality that's available in module, but when he first released this, the key thing that
he was showing was one particular command. He was showing the command Export-Excel and some demos that he
threw up quick videos on Twitter. So Export-Excel allows you to take content and export it from PowerShell
into an Excel document much like Export-CSV, you can export to a CSV file.
And if you look at it, right now it's got a lot of parameters and more being added over time as he adds more
and more features to this. And so that's interesting because it allows me to do what I want to do, but I really
don't personally I don't love the dash this, dash that, so on, having to use a splatting to get the work done.
With all these different parameters, I prefer thinking about Excel documents in structure, in the structure
that I'm creating them in. So yeah, so here's an example showing you the pipeline approach to creating an
Excel document, so I'm just going to call Get-Process and then I'm going to export that into an Excel document
with pivot data showing the pivoting on the working set size, pivoting on rows, I'll have the name for the
rows in my pivot table, it's going to include a chart, and so and I run this.
It's going to take a second. While that's running, I'll close down my Visio because I don't need that anymore.
So this is going out and just getting the process on my system and then using a .NET library that's inside
of this module and oh hang on a second. There we go. That's interesting.
I just updated this module like yesterday and I wonder if that's why.
I should not have updated it before the demo. I didn't really update this one.
I did update -module and it got all of them. So okay, so plan B.
So I don't want to troubleshoot this right now. I mean I did a debugging session yesterday and that might
have been appropriate for doing some of this content, going through these errors.
So I'm not going to troubleshoot that just this second. I'm going to keep to talking about the structure
and the language and how I think that I've been able to improve on it.
Oh, you know what? I wonder if it's because I've got the document on my system.
Where's my path? Mydocuments test.xls. (Typing) Okay. Let's try it one more time.
That may have very well been why. Whoops. Try again. By the way, I don't know if you noticed when I just
made that shift to there back to this. So PowerShell drives are crazy powerful and if you are finding yourself
jumping back and forth in locations inside of PowerShell a lot, I recommend that you go into your profile and
create PS drives because they allow things to be done much more easily than usual.
So I have, there we go, so I have inside of PowerShell this documents drive for my documents, I have modules
for my modules folder, all modules goes to ProgramFiles\WindowsPowershell\Modules and so on.
And so I use these to jump around my file system a whole lot and feel free to email me or ask questions about
that if you want to know how to set that up because it's a big timesaver.
So there, that was why because I had the file already on disk. So it creates this document right,
which is kind of interesting, so it's got a big table here showing a bunch of processes on my system.
I mean the data is not really interesting because it's an ugly pie chart and it's not really that meaningful,
but I wanted a simple example. So that works today and I'm not going to save it.
And I want to make sure that doesn't exist anymore. So that kind of shows you the process working just inside
of a regular PowerShell-like syntax and then you can switch, right?
And so you can switch to splatting and so splatting is interesting because all of a sudden what you're dealing
with large command sets, you can boil that up into this nice little hash table, so you see params and then I've
got a bunch of values and if you don't know the way splatting works, when you see on the Line 26 right there,
Get-Process | Export-Excel @params, @params tells PowerShell take that hash table and anything that are
keys are parameters names and anything that are values are the values that I'm going to use for those parameters.
And so it makes it nice to be able to take something long like what you see on Line 14 that runs off my screen
and shorten it up in a format that you can see in a document, so I use splatting all the time for that reason.
And so, anyway, this is the exact same command just moving to a splatting format, which I'm not going to run
because you saw the output, but this is better because here I can see path and I can see some properties like
show and auto size and so it's a bit more structural, but it's still not quite where I want it to go yet.
And so, I've got this LanguagePx module, so let me load that and I'll show you want it contains.
It doesn't contain a whole lot. It contains invoke keyword and so the invoke keyword piece is the command
that gets invoked by aliases. So trying to explain this. When I create a DSL, all the commands in the DSL
technically, they show up in PowerShell as aliases. Those aliases are all mapped to invoke keyword,
which in turn looks and checks what was the alias name used to call me?
Oh, that's the keyword you want to invoke, and so that's how that maps between the alias and the actual
internal dynamic keyword that is going to be found and run. New-DomainSpecificLanguage allows me to define
a domain-specific language because I didn't want to just create domain-specific languages, I wanted to create
a domain-specific language that allows me to create domain-specific languages, so up one more level,
which is really cool and powerful. And so, I've got this New-DomainSpecificLanguage command and then there's
Register-DslKeywordEvent. So as a keyword is being run, there are two different types of events that can
happen and those events are associated with script blocks through Register-DslKeywordEvent and I'll show you
that, and then Remove if I want to take a domain-specific language back out again.
Now here's an example of when I saw what Doug had done what it might look like to do the same thing using a
domain-specific language, well technically using this domain-specific language to create a domain-specific language.
So I can define with New-DomainSpecificLanguage, which is part of LanguagePx, a language called ExcelPx,
and inside of that, I've got ExcelDocMagic and these are just arbitrary values I pick, right.
So ExcelDocMagic is what it's going to be, it's the name that I gave for this language.
It takes a name, that name filed is actually the name of the document that it's going to create,
and then it's got some properties that are general document-specific properties like do I want to show it or not,
do I want it to auto size or not, and then it's got the data, so PivotData.
And inside of PivotData, I've got row properties and the aggregate value for the PivotData and whether or not
I want to include a chart and which is kind of fun because when you look at this versus the other syntax,
the command syntax, including a chart only applies if you're also including a pivot table and you learn that
by looking at the documentation for Doug's commands for ExportExcel and you can figure okay well I can't
do -IncludeChart unless I'm doing -IncludePivotTable, but a syntax like this makes that implicit because you
have the structure because you can't define IncludeChart unless you're inside of the PivotData and if you're
inside of PivotData, that's because you have a pivot table. So this allows you to make sure that the pieces
are lined up the right way, especially when you're dealing with commands that have very large sets of parameters.
This allows you to kind of wrap it up in a bundle and make it look better.
And then so here's the event handler. So Register-DslKeywordEvent and so I'll show you this.
It's actually really straightforward. So Line 51 down to the end of the curly brace on 62.
So DSL name is ExcelPx and the keyword path is ExcelDocMagic. So this is me telling PowerShell that whenever
ExcelDocMagic is invoked, I want it to fire this event and there's two different types of events that I have
support for right now, OnInvoking and OnInvoked. So you might have some stuff that you want to have happen
as the command's being invoked and you might have some stuff that you want to have happen after the entire
thing's been invoked, which is important because if I scroll back up a little, I told you I was going to
hoping you guys were going to bring your thinking caps. I get a feeling I'm making some heads hurt, but that's okay.
So you see ExcelDocMagic at the top and then inside there's properties and pivot data and what not and
there's no events down here below associated with those guys because that's just structure.
I could create a language where individual keywords have things that happen, have code that executes behind
the scenes each step along the way, but I might also create one where really all I'm defining a structure and
then at the end, I want to take that structure, which is just a hash table of hash tables, I could just step
through it and get information from it and then do things with it, so that's what this scenario is, OnInvoked.
After the entire thing is done, this ExcelDocMagic command runs, I'm going to invoke this action and the action
all I'm doing again is the splat table I showed you earlier? This is just building a new hash table to splat
in to import Excel. Question. Within your structure, which level are the keywords?
Is ExcelDocMagic the keyword? That's the first one, yes. Okay, but then properties and PivotData are also keywords?
Correct. And so that's because of this nested structure, that's where, that's why I was happy to see that
they push and pull or push and pop to the dynamic keyword object
because you have to deal with the fact that you're dealing, the different scopes as you go down deeper and
then come back up again, and so that's exactly how that is defined.
I create internally a large table that has paths and then based on where you are in the path, I take keywords
like properties and I say okay well properties is available now.
So this comes with, sorry one more question, so PowerShell doesn't store that as ExcelDocMagic.properties.
No. It just stores properties. Correct.
Yep. And then ExcelDocMagic is actually a type. No, it's actually a keyword.
It's not a type. It is a keyword. Yeah, so all the ExcelDocMagic and Properties and then Show and AutoSize,
so the difference here, some of these are properties, so where you see I have, I'm following a syntax
that looks like C#, right? So Boolean and then some values or strings and some values and so I support some
very common, yet primitive data types for associating values in property bags, so property is defining a
property bag, it will have .Show and .AutoSize on it, and if you look below where I have my hash table,
Show = $_.Properties.Show. Right. I'm all good with that. Name follows ExcelDocMagic?
Yes. So what I'm wondering is so all of that is the value of name?
What is name? Oh, so if looked, go down a little further. So, let me.
I'm stuck on name here. That's okay. So ExcelDocMagic, here's the execution of that syntax up top.
So name is just my path to my xls file, so I'm just giving it an identifier and then internally I can refer to
that and actually do stuff, so in my code. But when you go, can you keep up scrolling to that function and
I'll tell you why I was, I might not be the only person. I might, but I might not be the only person.
In all other cases when you have something like RowPropertyName, it's type is string, and string proceeds it
on the line, right, so the pattern here is the name and then the value.
Correct. So it's, sorry, type, the type or the type of the property and then the value.
Yes. And ExcelDocMagic receives name, so I'm thinking that that's a type.
Right. I get what you're saying. It is actually a definition of the keyword.
Well it's actually a property of the keyword. So when you have a keyword, so this is again all new
experimental stuff and so these are great points. So ExcelDocMagic is a keyword.
It has a property called name, which is just arbitrarily a string because that's the way that I've figured
out how to do things internally, and then inside of ExcelDocMagic, it creates two other keywords,
properties and pivot data, and each of those keywords are just property bags that have values that are type
associated with them, but the actually properties or parameters, they're almost like parameters,
for keywords like ExcelDocMagic, those are just a string, they're just arbitrary, so don't think about having
to type those. The way this works right now, I only use types in property bag.
I could probably update this to have more of a bracket structure with types and values if that would work.
I have to think about that. That's good feedback, but does that answer your question?
Make sense? It does. Okay. I think some of the confusion might be that maybe we didn't realize that new
domain-specific languages use LanguagePx, not part of the system automation language .NET.
I mean, it's not built into these. No, it's part of LanguagePx and internally it implements and uses the
dynamic language keyword, right? So that's how I'm doing all of my magic to make this happen, and so yeah
down here I register the event handler to do work, which is just calling the same code I had up top and then
the bottom you can see the syntax to actually go through and run that, so it could just call ExcelDocMagic.
In name, I give it the name of the file that I want it to actually work with and then I just set my properties,
and go, and it's done. Which I like the syntax. I mean, how many people see the value in a domain-specific
language syntax versus just having verb-noun commands? Yeah? Okay.
I mean, it's a preference thing. A lot of people think well yeah but you really get verb-noun, that makes more
sense to me and they can use that, which is great and it still works especially if you wrap those in your DSL
so that you can use either/or, which you can here, but I like the DSL syntax.
I think it makes a lot more sense when you're dealing with structured information.
It allows me to separate getting my values and getting my content for my structured document from the details
describing the document itself. Sorry, one more question. Are these your, is where PowerShell is concerned,
the things inside of the curly braces are ScriptBlocks, right? Yes.
I mean, it's the same deal like Pester or… Yep. And you had a question.
Yeah. I notice when you registered the DSL, you actually have Get-Process.
Do you ever abstract that or would you create specific keywords for particular actions?
Oh, yeah so I could. This is right now, you're right, this was a simple example, kind of a proof of concept
that I threw this together when I saw Doug's work just kind of showing what you can do, but you're right,
ideally, Get-Process should happen external to this because you don't want to bake your data into the DSL itself,
so it's lockdown. You're right. So can you put parameters into the action ScriptBlock?
Well yes, so you could have more than just name or I could have,
I could modify the DSL itself so that inside of my, inside of PivotData that I define a data set and that the
data set goes there, right, so inside of there I could have some PivotData and then define my data value and
have that equal to Get-Property, so it's pulled outside of the DSL itself.
Yeah, yeah, so there's different ways. It depends on how you structure it.
I think the fundamental question there might have been can you have parameters in an event handler?
So, no. Right now you can't. Yeah, your event handler is taking the data that you get from the structure
of the DSL itself, so the way you would parameterize that is by having the DSL have some argument or some
value that it can work with and then internally, your event handler is going to know to take any data source,
any data type and do the job.