So one of the things I do, I work for Provance Technologies.
Provance Technologies does IT asset management and now we do full IT system management, and so within that work,
we've done a lot of work with System Center and we've plugged into Service Manager and we have this whole
solution of asset management inside of Service Manager and one of the things that we wanted to do was to add
auto close functionality, which is a really straightforward feature that's just missing in a service manager,
but I didn't want to just create a management pack the normal way because creating management packs involves
XAML and XAML and compiling workflows and building DLLs and a whole lot of steps that are just really complicated.
I wanted to make it so that somebody could create a management pack more easily,
so I built this DSL using my DSL, my LanguagePx module called ManagementPackConfiguration and so it defines
a management pack and then it sets some attributes on that management pack and then build options,
admin settings, which creates a UI, and so this is quite extensive and you can look at it as an example.
I'm not going to run it on my system because I have nothing related to Server Manager on this system right now,
but I wanted to include it as an example showing how big you can get, right, I mean I showed you a small
example and this is a much larger example of a DSL and the kind of things you can do with it, but it's pretty
powerful and pretty cool and it's great fun to watch this happen because I see DLLs being compiled
and built, and placed in the right structure, and then putting it into a management pack, and then into a
management pack bundle, and code siding, and so many steps, again, but done in a simpler way, right.
So it's about peeling back the onion and getting down to
just defining the content. So on the resources slide, that last piece that I mentioned is from ScsmMpcPx,
so if you go into GitHub, that's where you can take a look at that larger example.
LanguagePx is on GitHub, that's the main module I was talking about, and of course, ImportExcel you can grab
from the PowerShell gallery.
And if you want to contact me for anything, there's my contact information, which I already mentioned at the beginning.
So thanks and if you do see these people while you're here at this event, tip your hat to them because these
guys have been on PowerShell for a heck of a long time. It's a great product, a great foundation, so give them
credit for their work because it's fantastic.
And that's it. Thank you.