So another demo. So let's talk about the---hum? (Audience comment)
Yeah, so the class, dynamic keyword.
So let me jump over to the second one. So the dynamic keyword class is a public class and it's controlled by
a bunch of static members, so I'm just going to run these one at a time.
So it's available in PowerShell v4 and later. In PowerShell's version 4, you're not going to see all of these
because there's a couple new ones that are added. I'll get to that in a second.
But you can get the members, you can use Get-Member-Static to see what's available on it and then let me just jump back.
So by default, in PowerShell there are no keywords. If you want to see what keywords are available in the
system, you just run Get-Keyword, but by default there are none. If you ran that from inside of DSC,
you would see stuff because it uses keywords, but otherwise, you don't see any and the configuration keyword
is technology not a dynamic one so that the entry point doesn't show up.
Now so all the management of keywords is done using these static methods and these are the ones that are available
in version 4, so AddKeyword to define a new keyword, and by the way, dynamic keyword has a constructor that
takes no parameters and then you just set a bunch of properties on it.
(Audience comment) Yeah, yeah, so you can just do hash table creation, yeah, so that's really easy.
So there's AddKeyword, there's ContainsKeyword to see what keywords are currently on the system, Get to either
look up all of them with no parameters or a string to get, excuse me, a specific keyword, and then of course,
removing them by name. Now I didn't add this to my slides or to my script, but I should add it.
I'm just going to create a new one, so k. I'll do it without the hash table just so you can see the properties.
So there's a keyword, and so on keywords, it's got a whole bunch of different properties that are dealing with
how do you or Get-Metadata and how do you define that and make languages and what not, so I mean there's a
meta statement, there's parameters for the keyword, there's some parsing stuff in there, and to be honest,
because this stuff is not documented, I certainly haven't figured it all out.
All of my work has been through spelunking and trial and error and this is kind of like a hidden goodie in
PowerShell that it's public, but it's really a work in progress. I'm talking to some team members on the
PowerShell team about ideas I have around how this could be done and I know that the way I am doing it right
now is probably not the way that they recommend doing it, but it's based on what I figured out and got working,
so you can kind of look in through this and figure out how it works.
I'm not going to go through and explain these things because I probably would explain them wrong because of
the fact that it's not documented and is based on when I figured them out.
I can have conversations about that outside of this session pertaining to the code that I've written,
which is public and on GitHub and I can show you and you can take a look at it, but I don't want to go into
the specifics of those today because I think that's a bit of a black hole.
So those are the ones that are used for management, and then of course, you could also clear the keyword list
at any time just by calling reset and the new ones that were added in version 5 that I just kind of discovered
the other day, are Push and Pop. And so one of the things I discovered when I was tinkering around with this
in PowerShell v4 that was an interesting challenge is that internally there is a single dynamic keyword table
that uses just a set of strings to identify the keywords. And so if you have multiple languages that have the
same keyword in different context, that's not going to work because you have one internal table.
So that was one of the challenges that I had to work around, so I created my own table and I'm constantly
shifting keywords in and out of the table that is currently being used by the language in the work that I'm doing.
So if you look through my code and you see some of that stuff, that's what that's there for.
Since then, version 5, and I'll makeshift my work to version 5 because I've just tried to move forward with
where this stuff is going. Typically, I'm the kind of guy who likes to do down level support as much as I can,
but this is so half-baked that I'm eager to move it forward leverage what they do with it going forward.
But push and pop, which I haven't tinkered around with yet, I can only guess and actually I looked at the code
using Reflector, that what they do is one takes the current set of keywords and pushes it down a level so that
you can start with a brand new set, which is important when you're going through different layers of script blocks
inside of a language and
then pop as you come back up those layers. For those who aren't developers, can you talk about like .NET
Reflector and IoSpy. Sure. They're really easy to use and you don't need to be a developer to understand
either to use them or to understand the output. Yeah, so it's a great point.
So I mean, everything these days or so many things these days are going open source.
You see all the news about different parts of different modules in PowerShell going source and different
parts in .NET going open source and Xamarin announcements, and all this goodness, they're publishing the
source codes, so you can just go and read it. But what about when you don't have that source code?
So PowerShell itself is not open source. You can use tools like IoSpy or Reflector, Reflector is a
commercial tool, IoSpy is not, and you can load DLLs inside of those tools and it's going, then that tool will
internally inspect the contents of those DLLs, show you the classes, give it to you in a searchable UI,
and you can browse through and just really dig through and figure stuff out and that's a huge learning tool or
it's great for troubleshooting bugs, great for just figuring out maybe some undocumented features because
documentation certainly is not always up-to-date with what commands can actually do, and so those are good tools.
Thanks June for that comment. Those are good tools to use and I use Reflector every other day, if not every
day just going in and digging around and figuring stuff out. And power comes from understanding those things.
Now so that's a high level look at what dynamic keyword has to offer in terms of interface and there's a lot of
functionality that I'm still working on, like I mentioned, but I'm happy to work on with people if people
want to work on that with me.