Let's search the transaction logs for,
I'm sure at your company that something came up missing in a database and you say who deleted that and all you
hear is crickets. Well somebody deleted something or some process deleted something and that's one of the
reasons you want to make sure you're using service accounts for everything because guess what, if you use
your account and you set up some process and something comes up missing and you're actually innocent,
you're going to be guilty based on the auditing.
So this is actually the command I wrote. It's got all the same things I write in every command I ever use.
It actually iterates through all the transaction log backups and the active transaction log.
And I'm going to show you here real quick, this is some dynamic SQL that I'm writing and I'm writing it based on PowerShell.
So what happens is when
you query the transactions logs, you can break the transaction log up across 64 files.
Well guess what, when you want to query it, there's a position for all 64 files and if there's only 1 file,
you have to have the 1 file listed, you have to have default listed 63 times and if you have 5 files,
then you've got to have default listed the number of times that it's necessary, but you can dynamically generate
that SQL based on information on another table in SQL Server. So you'll generate your Transact SQL code that
somebody would normally have to write manually.
I want to show you a simple example and then we're going to see what code this generates in addition to the
delete operation that occurred. So let's find out what happened to our database.
So you can see there that a delete operation occurred on 3/28 at 3:19 PM and it also gives us the log
sequence number we need to do the restore with to restore it just before the delete operation occurred.
The reason we knew this, we had a report from somebody that a specific record in the database was missing.
And you'll notice sure enough when we try to query that record, it's not in the database.
So writing dynamic SQL code. So I have a function here, a static function.
It's code that I showed earlier. It's very simple. So I'll get all the users with the last name of Browning.
If I wanted to make, and this will show you in a very simple way what I'm doing.
So all I've done is, we do this in PowerShell all the time, all I've done is parameterized the function,
but I'm using the variable inside my SQL query because it's going to get translated before it's sent to the SQL Server.
So if I want the last name of Browning, I can get that, but if I want the last name of Smith, I can get that as well.
So that's the idea. And the other example is very complicated and kind of convoluted, so I wanted to make sure
you knew what I was doing. So what we're going to do, I actually tweaked this code and this tweak doesn't
exist on GitHub. There's a tweak in here that's it's actually going to do Write-Verbose and it's going to
output the query itself in the verbose output. Make sure I get a clean Output window.
So what we can do we can actually take this query here, yeah write that manually.
Guess what, I could take this, it's not formatted very well, but it's not formatted that bad when it works.
I just want to get it to a point where you can see all these defaults because it'll run like this.
So that's the code we generated. So when I execute that, guess what, same information.
And then, I'll show you an example. There's no deletes in this one, but it'll still generate the code.
This one's a little bit messier because I've actually got four or five, I think five backup log files.
Thank you. That tells me somebody's paying attention. (Working)
See normally when I go to SQL Saturdays I have stuff to give away and I had stuff to give away, you would get something.
I just don't want this to be formatted so bad. I want to be able to see any problems that I have.
So that looks good. So you'll notice I've got more transaction log files and we actually have one more problem here.
So when I execute that, it should execute without error, without return records and it does.
So it dynamically creates this information.