So that means it's time for the demo. We'll come back for a few more slides toward the end of the session.
Okay, I want to show you the environment we're working with here.
So this machine is running Windows 10 Enterprise edition. We've got Hyper-V.
We've got a domain controller running and if all these are running Windows Server 2012 R2 Server Core,
so we a domain controller. We have a SQL 2014 box, a SQL 2008 R2, and by the way, they say you can't run
2008 R2 on Server Core, it's not supported, so don't try this at home, but it is running on Server Core.
And then this SQL03 box is a Windows 2008 non-R2 with no PowerShell and it has SQL 2005 with no PowerShell.
When I go to SQL Saturday events, I hear from a lot of DBAs that hey I can't write one PowerShell command to
query all these different versions of SQL and Windows and so on. Yeah, you can.
You just have to write it for the lowest common denominator. It's kind of like if you still have PowerShell
2, 3, and 4 in your environment, you can write one command and use it on all those machines, but unfortunately,
you've got to write it using v2 syntax.
So just to prove to you SQL03, I've tried to run PowerShell, hey it doesn't exist.
If I look at the Windows features, no PowerShell. And the reason I chose this version, it's going to be out
of, SQL 2005 I think is going out of support here in a week or so, but I wanted to get the newest version of
Windows Server and SQL that didn't require PowerShell. And actually, what I'm going to show you will work on
even older versions. So we'll switch back and forth between a couple of virtual machines.
I've downloaded a prep for this demo of made the text size 130, changed into the demo folder, I've set my
error messages to yellow because the red ones are kind of hard to read on the projector.
So we're going to query the servers and actually the machine I'm on just to make sure we've got connectivity
and also to show you the PowerShellVersion. So we've got version 4 on one of the servers, version 5 on the others,
and the one that doesn't have PowerShell is going to fail. And I've got detailed notes in here as well.
So we'll get into the entry part of this. I'm just going to enter a 1 to 1 remoting sessions on SQL02 since
it's SQL Server 2008 R2.
I want to show you the few cmdlets. I want to show you where we were and where we are as far as how many
cmdlets the SQL team has added.
(Working) And actually only two of these, three of these are part of the, so we've got two here.
We've got two that are part of the SQL cmdlets and the other ones are part of the SQL Server provider.
So in SQL 2008 R2, you've got 5 cmdlets total. That's it. That's all you get.
And I don't know about you, I've still got SQL 2008 boxes running in production today and I would imagine
that a lot of people do.