Okay, so today we're going to be talking about Building Unconventional SQL Server Tools in PowerShell.
And I speak at a lot of SQL Saturday events so and I've actually been working with SQL Server longer than PowerShell
and I've been using PowerShell since version 1.0, but I started with SQL Server in the 6.5 days.
Also, notice at the bottom of this slide you can download my demo code if you want to follow along in the presentation.
There's just a couple of minor tweaks I made to my code. I had somebody, an attendee in my last session
recommend that because the code is not always so easy to see on the projector.
Anyway, so I've been working with SQL Server 6.5 in the mid-90s and
I guess they originally designed that product from Sybase and it was back in the crazy days when you could
actually stick moldable databases in the same device, which meant you could take databases that had nothing
to do with one another and stick them in the same physical file, which yeah, was insanity, not a good idea.
So the product has gotten a lot better since then. I've done certification since 6.5.
I did like the MCDBA on 7.0 2000 and MCITP on 2005. I can't remember if I did the 2008.
I do more PowerShell nowadays, so I kind of figured that I'm not worried about SQL Server certifications.
But I am the DBA for the company that I work for. I'm also the Exchange guy, the AD guy, the SAN guy,
the firewall guy, you name it. I'm the only engineer. But today we're going to building some unconventional
SQL Server tools in PowerShell and you'll see what I mean by that.
We'll go through this slide, but I do have one question for the audience first.
Who was in my session on Monday? Okay, I'll try not to repeat myself too much.
If it's really important for the attendees that weren't there, I'll repeat myself.
But if you didn't see that session, I would definitely recommend taking a look at it even if you're not
working with DSC. It was DSC related, but there's some good tips in there if you're just building any kind
of PowerShell tools.
So my name is Mike F Robbins. I'm a Microsoft MVP on Windows PowerShell, SAPIEN Technologies MVP,
leader and co-founder of the Mississippi PowerShell user group, co-author of Windows PowerShell TRM 4th edition.
I wrote a chapter in the PowerShell Deep Dives book. I was winner of the advanced category in the 2013 Scripting Games.
And if you want to learn more about me, just see my blog site.
Okay, I've got some questions for the audience. How many IT pros do we have in the room?
Okay, good. How many developers? And you may be both. Okay, what about DBAs?
You may be like me. You're the reluctant DBA. Okay, and who's working with SQL Server today?
Okay, good. I'm glad. The session is going to start out where it's not too advanced, but by the end of the
session, it's going to be deep because I didn't want to start out by talking over anybody's head.
Okay, so who's writing Transact SQL today? Okay. And who's working with the .NET Framework?
Okay, and who's using some type of source control system for their PowerShell code?
Okay. And who's using some sort of unit testing system such as Pester?
Okay, and the source control and unit testing, that's something that you definitely want to learn more about.
And who's using the PS Script Analyzer? Okay, that's something that you can use to test your code with for
best practices and if you find that your code is just horrible based on the PS Script Analyzer,
there's actually some reading material I've got for you on the resources slide because what you want to try
to do is write your code so that you don't have a lot of problems with it and it's really a thought process
and that's what my sessions this week have been about is I'm not going to give you a fish or a toolkit,
but you're welcome to my toolkit because they're on GitHub. If you want to start with it, just support the
repository and I do take pull request, but I want to teach you to fish.
I want to teach you how to write your own toolkit. I want to teach you the mindset.
So the information we're going to be covering is we'll talk about the SQL PowerShell module and snap-in.
We'll talk about the SQL PowerShell provider, talk about SQL Management Objects, the .NET Framework,
Transact SQL versus using cmdlets, functions, modules, toolmaking, automation, and we're going to use
PowerShell to write some dynamic T-SQL code because why not use the tool instead of doing things manually,
even writing your code manually, write PowerShell code. I've actually used PowerShell code to write
PowerShell code for me.
And I've got a good blog article on doing that with DSC configurations.
And I presented for the Omaha PowerShell user group. That session is recorded and I demonstrated that as well.
So how do I get the SQL PowerShell module?
So this is from SQL 2014. It's installed as part of the management tools.
Now in some previous versions, I was actually able to install just the SDK and get it that way, but I found
in 2014, I actually do need the basic management tools to get the PowerShell functionality.
Now that's going to change. On Friday, they actually
released a preview version of SQL Management Studios, so it looks like what they're starting to do is break
out the SQL Management Studio from the like install disk and the good thing about this, this is a preview
build for March, the good thing about this, there's several things in the PowerShell SQL module that are fixed.
It no longer changes your current location. It no longer uses unapproved verbs.
It also loads much faster and I'm going to show you the code they're using today why it loads so slow.
And the more modules you have on your machine with SQL 2014 or prior, the slower it loads because of the way
they wrote their PowerShell commands.