Now what I want you to think about is I'm sure everybody here is it's a beginner concept filtering left.
I mean everybody should know that you want to filter as early as possible in the pipeline.
So but when you're working with SQL Server, it may not be a 100% clear what you're doing.
So what I can do is actually query a SQL Server database and I'm actually going to do a select * from the person table.
I'm going to bring it back to PowerShell and filter it down to the people with the last name of Browning.
So I have a list of the users with the last name of Browning. Well I can actually do that same thing inside
my SQL code, which is a lot more efficient.
It's kind of like some of the Active Directory cmdlets. I mean I think we all know they leave a lot to be
desired sometimes depending on what you're doing and depending on the size of your organization and what
you're doing, a lot of times you're better off using ADSI. But if you don't know ADSI, then you've got to
use the PowerShell cmdlets.
So anyway now I execute this other command and you'll notice it was instant.
So what I'm going to do I'm just going to run the first one again and then I'll run the second one as well.
Well the first one took 1167 ms. So the second option took 8.1 ms and this is all running on this machine,
so we're not having to take into account network latency and all that sort of stuff.
So what's the difference? The second command was 21 times faster than the first 1.
So what I actually try to do, I try to write all my code in Transact SQL because I want to filter as early as possible.
I don't want to bring anything I don't need back to PowerShell and a lot of my knowledge with SQL Server is
actually, when I started working with PowerShell, it just made sense because you don't want to query all these
table and pull every column and every row back only to filter it later and it's the same concept as filtering
left with PowerShell.
So what I can also do, I can also run store procedures from PowerShell.
So that runs fine. Well there's kind of a caveat here. Not all store procedures will run in PowerShell and
not all T-SQL code will run in PowerShell. There's a store procedure called sp_who2 and it's basically the processes.
And you'll notice I got an error message. It says that duplicate columns are not permitted because it's trying
to pull back two columns with the same name and we can't have two objects with the same name.
So what I'll do, let's just copy this. So if I put that on my SQL Server and this is SQL Server on query1.
If I execute that, it executes fine. Well the problem is you've got a SPD here and you've got a SPD there,
and the reason you've got two SPD columns is they're doing a join, so they're joining on that column because
you have to have the same, it may not necessarily be the same name in SQL Server always,
but the problem with this, we can't just go modify system store procedures.
It's probably not a good idea to start with and even if it works well for a while, guess what, when you apply
a service pack, your changes are probably going to go bye-bye.
Okay, so what's the solution to that if I really want to run sp_who2?
I'll just write my own.