So if you spread your transaction log backups across 64 files for some insane reason, it'll work.
Okay, now for something really cool. We've only got a few more minutes.
Okay, so what this is doing, it's getting me the chain of backups
and what I would do is never trust the information that SQL Server gives you.
You'll say sure, your boss will say do you have backups of the database, sure.
It says so right there. Guess what, that's pulling it out of the database.
Something else could have cleaned up those files and deleted them.
Just because it says you have a backup, doesn't mean you have a backup.
So that's what we have test path for.
So now we're going to restore the database. We're going to restore it in an alternate database because you know
March 28, that's been a while, so we would lose all our records since then if we restored over the top of it.
So I actually have a command here called a MrSqlDbRestoreFileList.
It gets the logical and physical filenames so that you can do a move on those to a different database name
when you're performing a restore. That's the other thing you want to do when you're writing your commands is
have it so you can pipe your commands together so that the output of one can be used for the input of another.
So we're going to generate an error here. I read a blog article about this last week.
Guess what, the log sequence number that we get from the transaction logs, can't use it in a restore because
it gives you a three-part hex decimal number that's separated by colons.
You have to split that, you have to convert that to numeric and the first part you just put the 2 numbers
in there, the second part has to be 10 digits, so you pad it with 0s, and the third part has to be 5 digits,
so you have to pad it with 0s, and then when you're done, you have to join it all back together and then you
have the number you can do a restore with. So guess what, I wrote a tool to do that, I wrote a blog article
about it and now I can delete that from my memory.
So that's this Convert-MrSqlLogSequenceNumber, so that's the converted number.
You can also pipe the, when you're searching for a delete, you can pipe it directly to the command.
So now we're going to do a restore and we're going to stop at that LSN, the Log Sequence Number.
Now if we do a Find-MrSqlDatabaseChange,
it doesn't find anything, but this is no longer a valid command because this command searches the transaction log backups.
I just created a new database. The new database doesn't have any transaction log backups.
So the real way to find out if it worked is to query for the information that was deleted and there it is.
So as I told you the other day, every time I write a command or write another command to undo everything,
so that's cleaning up my demo. We'll jump back to the slide deck.
So I'd like to thank everybody from the PowerShell team that's been around for the last 10 years.
We wouldn't be where we are today if it wasn't for those guys. We'd still be the click, next, admin.