Okay, so we'll just exit out of that remoting session.
Something else I want to show you is I've installed a SQL 2014 client tools on this PC.
And I want to show you that what it does it actually modifies the PS module path.
So there's some DLLs and other things that have to be installed to make SQL management objects work.
With SQL 2014 when you import the SQLPS module, all that happens magically.
It imports the DLLs and everything. Now if you have SQL 2008 R2 and you want to use SQL management objects,
you have to actually manually import the DLLs and there's plenty of documentation on the web for that.
So if you want to know the details of that, just do a Google or a Bing search on it.
Okay. I'm going to import the SQLPS module. It's going to take a couple minutes.
Do we have any questions at this point? I'm actually going to mess up our cameraman.
I'm going to walk off the stage here. But this is what I like about PowerShell is that SQL gives me that
little four square box to operate in and a lot of other products too.
And if I did something like called Microsoft and said hey I edited the registry on my server, they'd sorry that's
not supported, but with PowerShell I could probably call them and say yeah I modified the registry at PowerShell,
oh, that's okay. So I don't have to operate inside the box that people give me to operate in.
So you'll notice, we do have two cmdlets in here. I could use the verbose parameter to see the details of this,
but I have an encode and decode SQL name and I know why this occurred
because back in the snap-in days, they had those cmdlets and the snap-ins actually don't do the checking for
the approved verbs, so when they moved it to a module, they just moved their cmdlets, well then they started
getting this warning. So what they've done in the new version I said this was fixed in is they've been doing
what I've been telling them all along. They renamed the cmdlets and aliased the old names to the new ones,
so that way it's not a breaking change.
Okay and if you noticed, it actually changed my current location.
I was in the Demo folder and it changed me to the SQL Server PS drive.
I want to show you some of their code. So this is one of the things that it runs when you load the SQLPS module.
So they do a Get-Module -ListAvailable which is going to get every module on your machine and pipe it to where object.
So that's where my comment comes in that the more modules that you have on your machine, the slower it's
going to be to import the SQL module, but that is also fixed in the new SQL management installation.
And of course, you see that it's signed, so it's not like I can just go hack this file and fix it you know.
Okay, so let's change back to the Demo folder. Let's take a look at all the cmdlets we get with SQL 2014.
We get lots of cmdlets. We actually get some analysis services cmdlets and there are lots in the SQLPS module,
but when you import the SQLPS module, it imports both of those. So I stored it in a variable just because it's
not so easy to see how many. So we actually have 57 cmdlets. So between 2008 R2 and 2014, we went from 5
cmdlets to 57. I think that's a huge improvement. Okay, so what we can do, we can actually run Transact SQL
code directly from PowerShell using the invoke SQL command cmdlet that exists in SQL 2008 R2.
So I actually just queried the list of databases on SQL01. Pretty simple.