Okay, so there's something else called SQL management objects.
So I can use SQL management objects and I want you to remember that SQL03 that I'm about to query does not
have any PowerShell installed on it. So I can create a new object and then I can use that object.
Guess what? I just got the same output as space_who2 store procedure with PowerShell from a machine that doesn't
have any PowerShell installed. Pretty cool, huh.
How do you connect to that machine?
I just created a new object and this actually uses DLLs behind the scene that are on the client, on the machine
you're querying from. So
using SQL management objects has the dependency of having the SQL management tools installed on the client
you're accessing the server from, but it does not have the dependency of having anything like PowerShell
installed on the server end. It does require SQL Server, of course, and this is one of the ways you'll see
developers actually access SQL Server. And SQL management objects, I'm going to show you something here in a
few minutes that it's what the PowerShell provider uses, it's also what the cmdlets that they, all they're doing
is wrapping their 57 cmdlets around SMO.
So when do you find yourself using let's say a connection string, instead of loading all of the objects in (Inaudible)?
I recommend using the .NET Framework like you're talking about instead of SMO if you can because it eliminates
the dependency of having the SQL management studio or at least the PowerShell module installed or the DLL specifically.
Can you give examples of use cases for instance?
Well the use cases would be if I want to deploy something on a 1000 machines, I don't want to put the SQL
management studio on all those machines, I just want to run the command, and I've got some examples of that as well.
I've actually got a data reader that I've created and if you don't write .NET, then there's actually some
really good stuff because I don't know that Warren Frame is in here, but I stole a command from his GitHub
repository and you can find it in my repository now and I don't feel bad about stealing it because he stole
it as well, but everybody who's changed that code is actually noted in the comments.
Justin Dearing, he's another PowerShell and SQL guy, if you know him, he's noted in there.
And I don't mind getting commands off the internet if it's all text based, but if it's a DLL and it's a black box,
then hey that's another story. But even if you're not allowed to download commands from the internet and run
it, you're allowed to create your own, so you can just go get Invoke-SqlCmd2 and take a look at what
they're doing and then write your own version of it. Or if you're allowed to copy and paste, then you can
just copy and paste and create your own command. Let's just do the same.
Did that answer your question?
Yeah.
And there's really different use cases. I know a lot of DBAs and they actually prefer SQL management objects,
they prefer to work with those because they're not developers and they really don't feel comfortable working
the .NET Framework, so that would be one reason is sometimes like me, I'm not a developer either, but I was
able to figure out how to write a data reader and then I found the SQL command, Invoke-SqlCmd2 and I was like
hey I'm kind of wasting my time. I'll use this one because it's much more efficient and well-written than
what I had written.
We'll run the same command just to show you that the same command would work on a 2014 server.
And we're kind of covering these rapidly. I just want to show you some of the options that we have and then
we'll get into a few more advanced things. Okay, so one thing I want you to notice here is we now have a SQLPS provider.
It's right here at the very bottom. So that's part of the SQL management or the SQL PowerShell module and it
also shows up as a PS drive. So you can use that PS drive and you can actually, I've got a list of my
databases and what recovery model they're in and so on and that was fairly easy.
But I don't know about you guys, but I actually hate using the providers because they're not very well
documented and if you're trying to use tab completion, especially in a SQL provider, a lot of times it'll hang.
So it's not one of my favorite ways to query SQL Server and I'll show you that it really doesn't matter.
So we still have our SQL object that we created, so we can use it.
And you'll notice that both of these commands, the output is basically the same from the SQL provider or from SMO
and there's a good reason for that. So if you see what type of object we created here, we created an SMO
database object and that was with the SQL management object option.
Well I'm going to show you what type of object the PS provider creates.
So it creates the same type of object, so all they're doing with the SQL PowerShell provider is wrapping it
around SMO so that you don't have to be a developer if you don't want to and you may ask why don't these
commands look the same, the output of these commands. One's got more databases than the other.
They're doing some filtering with the SQL PS provider. So if I use the Force parameter and run the
same command, I'll actually get all the databases. So with the SQL PS provider they had the system databases,
unless you use the Force parameter. Okay, I just have a quick example of, I can also run Get-Database,
which is one of the newer cmdlets. Guess what, same information.
You know what type of, I bet you could guess what type of objects it's going to create.
Guess what, SQL management object. So all those commands, the PS provider and the cmdlets, all they're doing
is wrapping around SQL SMO. (Working) Okay, I think I've already imported these modules, but yeah I've
imported those already. This is actually what you used to have to do to import the SQLPS module and keep it
from complaining about the names as you would do DisableNameChecking.
One question I hear from DBAs is why do this in PowerShell? Why just not do it in SQL?
What's the big deal?