Well the big deal is I can't use the output in some other system, so since I'm the AD
guy and the SQL guy and the Exchange guy and so on, if I did this in SQL, then I couldn't use the output directly
anyway in another system.
So what I can do, I can actually run a command. I've done a bunch of joins here and I've even done a little
bit of text parsing with PowerShell. Don't be afraid
to do text parsing with PowerShell. If you can write a command more efficiently using text parsing than using
objects, don't be afraid to use it. I've seen people, they'll want the manager in AD and they'll actually
query the user and then do another query on AD to get the manager.
Well you have the manager, you have the DN for it and you can actually parse the manager out of that DN,
Distinguished Name, without having to do a second query to AD.
So anyway, I'll query these and guess what, all those joins and all, just imagine this is the HR database.
I've got the person's name, I've got their SAM account name, their UPN, all this is in SQL, not in AD.
Well guess what I can do with that? Create AD users.
So let's query this OU in Active Directory and I'll show it to you as well while that's waiting, it's the AdventureWorks OU.
I'll do a refresh, there's nothing in there. And we'll give this a second.
It shouldn't take that long, but do we have any questions at this point?
Well we got an error message. So let's do this. Let's just do a get-aduser, we'll do a get-adcomputer.
We'll make sure I can talk to AD and we'll say sql01. Okay, so we're talking to AD.
Let's run that command one more time. I don't see anything wrong with it.
You know that's the definition of insanity is to do the same thing and expect the different results,
but my definition of insanity is to do the same thing more than one time and get different results, which I just got.
If you're not insane, it will drive you insane. Okay, so what we're going to do, we're actually going to
encapsulate this inside Measure-Command. We're going to run the same query again, we're going to pipe it to
New-ADUser, and we're going to see how long this takes.
And I've shown this at some SQL Saturdays and I always challenge everybody who can type faster accurately
than I can run this command. And nobody has taken me up on the challenge yet.
So I run that command. It shouldn't take too long, unless we have a timeout.
So it took, I can see there at the bottom it took 3.1 seconds. Well guess what, 290 Active Directory accounts.
We put their name in there, we put their telephone number, we put their address, we put their job title.
Now who's got temps at your company that can do that and do that accurately in 3.1 seconds?
So just go ahead and fire your temps.
That's the benefit of doing this in PowerShell is you're not tied to one system or one technology.
So now if I query the OU, I can see there's 290 Active Directory user accounts.
Okay, let's talk about the .NET Framework. I actually wrote a SQL data reader using the .NET Framework.
It's a function. It's got all of the stuff you should have. It's got comment-based help to tell you how to
use it, it's got parameter validation, it's got a Begin block that sets up the connection one time, it's got a
Process block that'll iterate through all the commands on the same connection, and then it's actually got an
End block that'll close the command when it's done, instead of building a command for every query that you're
going to run. So it's a little more efficient to do it that way.
So I can actually use that command to query a database. So what I did I actually got backup information from
my MSDB database with that command. At this point, I want to jump over to another VM.
I've got a Windows 8.1 VM here and I want to show you the SQL tools are not installed on this machine.
The only SQL tools on this machine are my SQL tools.
And I don't mean my SQL, I mean MrSQL.
So I can take and run this data reader using the .NET Framework and receive the same results without needing,
without having any dependencies whatsoever, so that's the benefit of using the .NET Framework.
What I can do is and this here I actually have a command that we ran earlier, so I'm actually going to create
a very simple function to get a list of the databases and remember SQL03 doesn't have PowerShell.
So from a machine that doesn't have the SMO DLLs on it, I can use the .NET Framework and query a machine that
doesn't have PowerShell on it.
So I haven't found a reason, if you're able to write your own SQL cmdlets in the .NET Framework or use somebody
else's, I haven't found a reason not to use the .NET Framework. Generally, it's because it's much simpler
just to use SMO because it's there. You don't have to reinvent the wheel.
That would be the downfall of the .NET Framework, but when you can steal somebody else's code on the internet,
then you don't really have that downfall.
Okay, so this is the code we ran and I put it in this file as well because this is the only file that's on GitHub.
So now we're back to, notice now I'm going to use Invoke-Sqlcmd2, which is the file I was telling you about.
I'll get the same results. But it's not a data reader. You can use it in place of where you've used Invoke-Sqlcmd,
you can actually update and delete and everything. Okay, so let's do something that's a little more exciting.