This is a resource slide. There's some free stuff. PowerShell.org, the PowerShell Virtual Chapter of SQL PASS.
They do like lunch time meetings. They had one today, matter of fact.
SQL Saturday Technology Events. I'm speaking at SQL Saturday Atlanta on May 21 on toolmaking and I'm speaking
at SQL Saturday Pensacola the first weekend in June on Desired State Configuration.
And I've spoke at tons of SQL Saturdays. I speak in Baton Rouge every year.
I've spoke at Birmingham, Alabama, Mobile, Alabama. I've spoke at Atlanta before and so on.
I speak at some SharePoint Saturdays as well. I spoke last year at SharePoint Saturday in Nashville.
The Microsoft Virtual Academy. Now SAPIEN Technologies, the reason I have them under the free section is they
have some really good blog articles that June Blender is writing and also their forums.
They actually have some decent forums and it's not just related to their products.
They have some on just writing PowerShell code because as a SAPIEN Technologies MVP, I've been answering some
of those questions. PowerShell Magazine. I've written numerous articles there.
User groups. I run the Mississippi PowerShell user group as I mentioned earlier.
That's a virtual user group. If you don't have a local user group and we record our meetings as well on our YouTube channel.
You can, an alias for that user group website is mspowershell.com.
Twitter is another resource. GitHub, blogs. If you want to find a list of good blogs, go to my blog site
and see my blog role.
If the people that I have in my blog role are not writing good code or not consistently blogging, then they get
deleted off the list and somebody else gets added.
There's a PowerShell Best Practices and Style Guide and this slide deck is also on GitHub under my presentations repository.
All these are links to these sites, but that's the reading material I referenced at the beginning if your code
is not passing script analyzer. Okay, there's a couple of paid product.
I was actually the technical author for this Pro PowerShell for Database Developers.
It's a good book. And then also Pluralsight. We've got one more slide.
So that's my contact info. There's the book I co-authored and also the one I wrote a chapter in.
I'm a big believer in personal branding, so you'll find me at mikefrobbins pretty much anywhere.
Sign up for services, even if I don't use them. If you want my email address, I have a challenge for you.
Go out to my blog site, see the about page, my email address, my real email address is encoded, so decode it
and send me an email. And then there's the user group. Thank you guys for attending.