Alright, so I didn't ask this earlier on. How many of you have been working with Desired State Configuration?
Raise your hands. Alright, about half the room maybe. Did you have a question?
Yeah. I was curious. So is there a place that we could go for documentation on how to do that sort of if
we got away with any of that. There was a link in the slide deck.
Are we giving out the slide deck? Yeah, if you can let me help them at the end, I'll make sure to get those to you.
Okay. Alright, so I'm going to, we're going to be really short on time here, so I'm going to breeze through
some of this stuff. I'm going to go over the configuration reuse.
There are basically
two use cases, I think, primary use cases for reuse. There is reuse-like functions, so I have a configuration.
I'm going to do some stuff multiple times in that configuration, so I want to have a chunk of something that
I don't have to write out a bunch of times with for loops in it and all this complicated logic.
So there's that use case and then there's the other use case where I have a distributed environment.
I have someone that knows SQL. They're creating a configuration that I want to use for my web app or IIS or
whatever where I'm not authoring that thing, but I want to reuse it so that I don't have to write the same
code again, so there are a couple of different ways that you can reuse configurations and I'm sure there are
way more than that, but these are two kind of bigger ones and I'll go through some examples of both of those.
And the options that we have
for configuration reuse or composite configurations, I don't know if we've done any documentation on this,
but composite configurations are basically
just using a configuration like a function. So in your script, you say I have this configuration, now I want
to reuse that configuration in the configuration below that I use.
It's not packaging it up in any special way. There's no versioning or anything like that.
It's just I have this code, so a good example of that is before we add the new service set and those new
resources that we put out there, if I want to make sure that 20 of my services are turned off in DSC,
I don't want to, well for optimization purposes, I probably don't want to have a big configuration that has
service, service, service, service, service, so I can create a function or a configuration that is above my
other configuration that says I have a for loop, I'm going to pass in all of the resources that I want to or
all of the services I want to shut off, it's going to loop through those, create all of the individual resources,
and then dump that out in a MOF, so you can create that above your configuration and then call that within
your configuration just like another resource. So it allows you to do stuff like that very easily.
There are partial configurations, which I think a lot of people jump onto right away when they have a
distributed environment that says this guy's going to configure my system this way, this guy's going to
configure my system that way.
I want to take those things and jam them together on a target node.
There are a lot of good things about partial configurations, but there are lot of or there are other things
that aren't so good about partial configurations like partial configurations you need to set the
MetaConfiguration and say this is how my system is going to look with these chunks of partial configuration.
There's no versioning for partial configuration. It's just whatever if my configuration changed, I'm going to
apply that and there's what else with partial configs. (Audience comment)
Thank you. That was my other point. Yes, the other thing is, so it's going to take all those configurations
and doing DSC it's going to say are there any conflicts with these configurations?
But it's not going to do it when you compile the scripts. It's going to do it on a target node after it has
all the configuration parts. It's going to jam them together and then go something failed, fix it, and you have
to figure out what that is. That's one of the negatives to that.
Then one of the positives to it is I can be a security guy and I don't care who's out there, I want this
configuration on that target node and I want it to apply. So it takes, puts the power in someone's hands who
need to make sure that this configuration applies on that system. And the last
option is composite resources. It's very much like composite configurations,
except you bundle the thing up into a module and say I want to be able to share this with a bunch of
different people, so it looks just like a PowerShell module, it just has resources in it that are able to be reused.
You can have parameters that you can pass in and do the configuration and stuff like that.
One of the key things to know about composite resources is it looks and behaves very much like a resource,
but it's different in that if you're using pull, those resources only need to live on the build server.
They do not need to live anywhere else. You don't need to put them on the pull server.
They do not need to be on the target node because they get exploded before the MOF is generated and turned
into those underlying resources and those underlying resources are what need to be on the pull server and on
the target nodes. So if you have logic in there that's trying to get information from the target node,
it's not going to work because that's never going to be run on the target node.
Alright, I have a quick demo here of the different examples.
So right here, I have a composite configuration. Can everyone see that okay?
Alright on a composite configuration, this is very much like the example that I mentioned.
I have an Iis configuration up here and then I three other configurations for configuring WebApps.
I'm going to do the exact same thing when I configure each of those WebApps and I'm going to stand up Iis and
I'm going to open up a firewall port, so I create a configuration up above here that has a single parameter
that's a port parameter, and I'm going to install, make sure the web server role is enabled, and I'm going
to open up a firewall port on that system. And then I can call this thing in each of these things just like another resource.
So this configuration is Iis. That becomes the type like any other resource in here.
So I'd say this type of resource is Iis. You know what it is because I had to find it up above in this script
and I'm going to give the unique name of basic to this thing and the one parameter that I have in that
configuration is what I pass into the property here and then do that configuration.
So I can get each of these WebApps configured very easily, cleanly, someone looks at this, they can know
I'm standing up Iis on this system. I can name this thing whatever I want and I'm going to open up Port 80
on this one, I'm going to open up Port 880 on this one and another port on the other one.
And so, it gives you that reusability and when the MOF is created for each of these things and I can show you
that here real quickly, in the composite config. That App1 MOF, one of the things, so a couple things here,
the name of the ResourceID here gets jammed together so when you create
composite resources or composite configurations, in the MOF, it generates the unique name for that resource
by saying this is the type that I have :: and then this is it. So basically it takes the name of the
configuration and then the name of the configuration you're in and puts them together with ::, so if you have
multiple layers there, you'll know where that thing came from. So it gives you the ability like in Azure
automation DSC, they're going to be able to combine those things together on their porting, so you can say
where'd my failure happen and dig down into the individual resources from there, so it gives you that unique
name for that. And when you do a get status, it'll have those names in there as well, so you don't have to
dig into the MOF to see that. But you get your configuration right there.
So the next one, real quickly, and again, if anyone has questions at any point, just yell.
How many levels deep do you go in? We don't limit how many levels deep you can go.
(Audience comment) It'll keep going. Do word wrap and then you'll be able to see it.
Alright, so the next example here real quickly is the composite
resource and now you'll start to see kind of these are used in very much a same way as a composite configuration,
but I said you'd bundle that thing up into a module and this example right here is a module that I created,
so this is a Fabricam_Infra, so I have common stuff that I want to use here.
I have a module directory. I have the module psd1 here that defines the thing.
I have DSCResources inside of that and with the new versioning and stuff like that, you have a version folder
in here as well. So inside of the DSCResources, I have for each of my individual composite resources,
I have a folder for that and then I have a psd1 for that, which doesn't do a whole lot, but that needs to be
there to define that, and then I have a file, which is just my logic that is IIS, so it's a name of the resource,
.schema.psm1 and then you have the same code in there that you would have in your configuration above that.
So I have that for IIS, I have one for Security, and then I have one for SQL.
I don't actually use the one for SQL on my example. But then I have my psd1s here.
So the difference that you'll see here is that importing that new module and then I can use that just like I
could the composite configurations, but I have my Iis Basic, pass in my port, and I'm good to go.
So when I compile these things, you'll actually see that they look practically identical when you come down
to the resources themselves. They have the same naming, so it squishes the two together.
It says here's my composite resource. I'm going to squish that name together with how it was used in my
configuration, so you can uniquely identify that, and otherwise, it looks exactly the same.
(Audience question) Yes, I can. So I go to SQL. Go ahead. So one of the things that happens in here that
is nice about composite resources or composite configurations is you can do logic in here.
Like this one I have a validation set and a version, so if you have different things that you want to do
depending on the version of SQL you want to install, you can do that logic in here.
And did I delete that? Oh no. So I have a switch statement says this is where I'm going to get the install
for each of these different things and then I just use that in here somewhere in the source thing.
So it's a source and I use a source in here, so it's going to install in a different place, so you can do
that kind of logic in… (Audience question) Excuse me? (Audience question)
It really depends. I will show you an example after this demo real quick on some of the pluses and minuses
to each one of them. But it depends on your use case and how you want it to work.
So the question was in a distributed environment, which should be used, composite resources or partial configurations?
I have a quick question. Sorry. So I find that using the PS Desired State Configuration and an
XPS Desired State Configuration kind of confusing. Yes. They're not the same thing, right?
Yes, well they're not. So it's like I think I'm putting on the new versions, but I find that I have to call
the old one because that's where the cmdlets are, I guess, and I get the warning sometimes I don't, and so what's
the difference, I guess. How do I… So the idea with the XPS Desired State Configuration was essentially the
things that we thought that we might pull back into the box, we would put in that module, but that has not happened
and I don't know if it will happen. So should we call it something else?
I mean we can, I don't know. It's a module. You can rename it and call it whatever you want, not to be
flippant, but it's potentially. There are a few different things that we're looking into and one of the
things is should we open source all of the PSDSC and the stuff that's on the box, shouldn't we just put that
up on the gallery and let that be there. So it's, and if we did that, we would definitely squish the two
together and make that one. But we are, in general, investigating naming of the modules that are from the
community in XDSC. Desired State Configuration is one from the community.
Alright. Sorry, (Audience question). Will what work with class base?
(Audience question) You composite, yes they will. Composite resources are actually much simpler in class based.
I probably should have had an example in here, but I don't. With the class-based resources, you just use a
class syntax and then you can have multiple in one module. It actually simplifies it quite a bit.
But then you can't do versions of the pull server right? For, that's correct yeah.
Alright, so partial configs here real quickly. So I have the same set up with partial configs.
When I run each of these, it's going to generate a MOF for each of them and then basically on the target nodes,
you have to come in and say I have partial configs for each of these things and in a case where you're pulling,
in this case I'm pushing, so I've defined a MetaConfiguration that says I'm going to push each of these
configurations to the target node. You define the partial configs that are going to be on that box,
give it a description and then when you push the target or the partial config there, it'll get it,
jam them together, and then apply it at that point. So each of these will generate a single MOF like you see
here in my Partial directory. So it'll just generate a MOF for each of these and then you send those to
whatever machines should apply them. Go ahead. Will it wait until it
has a configuration for every partial defined before it compiles and does the final jamming or if you only
have two submit right now and two are coming later, will it submit the two it has and then allow you to wait
for another one. That is a very good question. The question was about how it applies partial configurations.
We allow you to define that in the MetaConfiguration. So in the MetaConfiguration, if you have this partial
config depends on another partial config, and that's not tab completing, but if you have it dependsOn with
another partial config, it'll wait until that other partial config gets there to apply it, and if not,
it should just apply it. Well it's not just going to go because you have to, well with pulling it will,
with pushing, you push it, and then you have to apply it. So alright, so now I will, I went through those.
I'll jump back
to my presentation here.