Encrypted MOFs. So
we got a lot of feedback on previous versions that it was difficult to use certificates to encrypt the MOFs
that you were sending
to the target node. So one of our goals here was to make it easier to make sure that your MOFs on the target
node were encrypted and secure. But the total purpose here is to make sure they're encrypted in transit and
at rest on the target node.
So we have a couple of use cases securing the MOF in-transit. We have a documentation on that.
There's a link in the notes in some of our documentation on our documentation site.
So what's new here is there's a new requirement for document encryption EKU and the provider for the certificate
must be Microsoft RSA SChannel Cryptographic Provider. That's a very important note
because if how many people were using WMF4? How many people moved to WMF5?
How many people got broken? There you go, so yeah. So it's a good thing to know if you're moving from WMF4
because we did make a breaking change and that's how you fix it by creating the right kind of certificate.
So the big feature here is that we automatically encrypt the entire MOF while it rests on the node once it
gets there in WMF5. So is there a big advantage in that type of certificate?
Let me answer that. Previously it was possible to generate types of certificates that had tack vectors on them,
but if you had a certificate without the proper type of EKU, you could use them in ways that would reveal
their private, not their private, their public key. This type of certificate, if you generate it correctly
and via the best practice, the public key shouldn't be given away and you shouldn't have the problem of the
potential attack against such certain cert. So this was done to increase the security of the encryption.
Yeah, I see that. (Audience comment) So
how does it work? LCM automatically encrypts the entire MOF using the Data Protection API on the target node.
This means non-administrators cannot decrypt the MOF. That's no matter
how you generated the MOF. The MOF
generated by PowerShell is not encrypted by default. So it's still recommended that if you're using
credentials to encrypt the MOF to protect it in transit so that your password
is not lying around in the MOF that you sent, that you have lying around before you sent it to the node.
So before we go to the demo, do we have any questions?
Not where we have the demo. (Typing) So first I'll show you the code if it will come up underneath.
So one of the things to point out here as well. We did this work so that we'll encrypt the MOF in place.
It doesn't prevent you from the using the old
methodology of encrypting the password, so when you use a certificate to encrypt the passwords,
that still works, so you can do that and then we'll encrypt the MOF on top of it, so if you really need that
extra security of I want my passwords hidden throughout the whole pipeline, you can still do that and that
works with this. So. I guess that was my question. Is it necessary then if you're encrypting the MOF?
I mean I guess it really just… So we've gotten feedback from customers that there is other things other than
the credentials that they want to secure like the location of some of the files they're copying from,
so they may want to encrypt the entire thing. Instead of may, we just encrypt the entire thing for you all the time.
I know it was the other way, right? If I'm encrypting my MOF, then do I say what you do for my password?
You'll see in the demo, but the encryption only happens when the LCM receives it and then writes it to disk,
but there is other parts of the process where it's not encrypted.
So the MOF created on a pull server itself you're using would remain in under _____?
Is that correct? That's correct. And even you encrypt the password, it only encrypts the passwords.
Anything else in your MOF generated by PowerShell is not encrypted so like Path SMB shares are not encrypted.
And in Azure automation DSC if you're using that, it is encrypted on the service by itself, so when you
generate the MOF, they encrypt it, and then save it to disk. And when it's on disk, it's encrypted and then they
decrypt it, send it to the target node, and then it gets re-encrypted over there.
That's exactly what I was going to ask. Does that mean you no longer need to set the plaintext
password true variable under 5 or is that still needed in order to…
That is still needed. We are doing some work with Azure automation to make it so you don't have to do it there
because they do encrypt it at rest. So I have a very simple configuration.
I have a
MetaConfiguration here that sets the thumbprint. I have the thumbprint already in a global variable.
Then I have my configuration and I use XPSDesiredState and DesiredState, so I'm importing them.
Then I create a user and I create a script where I'm not running as that user and I'm going to verbose output
the name of that user and then I'm going to run as the user that was just created and output the name of the
user and I have a function here to generate the configuration data, pass in the thumbprints that we're encrypted
with the same thumbprint. I have a comment here that there's an alternative way to encrypt using a certificate file.
I'm not going to use that or demo it, but that's true, and I'm also telling DSC that I AllowDomainUsers.
This is the local user, but it's still, we'll deal with that later.
So I'll go ahead and import that module. I'm going to run the MetaConfig, apply the MetaConfig,
This tells DSC
to use the certificate to decrypt any MOFs edit users.
Now let's go look at the MetaConfig, and if you see here, I'm going to have to find it.
Give me a second here. Where is the… Here CertificateID. We have the CertificateID.
We have everything else should be defaults. So we'll move on, unless there's any questions.
The now I'm going to prompt for that password for that user we're creating.
I don't know why I'm being so strict. The password doesn't matter.
So if you notice here, we're using a new type of encryption called CMS.
There are cmdlets for it and I'm using the password twice, so it's in here twice.
But as I said, everything else is unencrypted. All the code to get the user is unencrypted.
So we've already had questions about that, so just showing you that.
And then I'll run the configuration. And so we created the user, we ran not as the user, so DSC runs as
local system by default, and then we ran as a test user. I'm going to go and get the user,
get the configuration. I also, so this basically just shows the same thing.
When we do get, we're running as the same users. I'm going to delete the user just so that the user's not
on the system. Now we can go look at the MOF. We don't see anything because it's all encrypted and that's that demo.
Any questions? Are you saying you could have just made the file by hitting your hand and on the keyboard?
Now where's the fun in that? Then the challenge to you would be to decrypt it after.