For the PowerShell DSC, A Look under the Hood. My name is Mark Gray.
I'm a program manager on the PowerShell team. I've been working on DSC since the beginning essentially,
before you guys saw it, so I've been around for a while. I have with me here Travis Plunk.
I'm Travis. I'm a senior software engineer on DSC. I've been working from the beginning.
I've worked on the engine and the Azure DSC extension for DSC.
Alright, so what we're going to talk about today, the format of this first of all is going to be open,
you guys ask questions, it's going to be very interactive hopefully.
Push the button. Thank you.
Jason even came up beforehand and said make sure you push the button.
So it should be very interactive, ask questions, interrupt us, let us know.
We have four things that we are going to dig
into here and then we'll leave it open for questions, so anything you guys want to ask questions about from
a DSC
perspective, let us know and we'll dig in. If we can do demos with the questions, if not, we'll just answer
the questions or what have you. So we're going to talk about a lot of the new features in WMF5, so the encrypted MOF.
We're going to dig into what the purpose of those is, what the good things are, what the bad things are,
all that kind of stuff. We're going to dig into configuration reuse.
Nobody wants to write scripts of the same stuff over and over and over and over again.
So in DSC, there are a number of different ways to actually reuse configurations, so we'll kind of dig into
those, what the good parts of it is, what the bad parts, some are good for some things and others are good
for other things. And then configuration status. I, as Kevin pointed out earlier on, I came from the GP world,
so one of my big caveats or one of my big things that I have been pushing for since being on the DSC team was
we're not going to build a black box from the PowerShell or from the GP perspective.
You had policy and what happened with the policy? I don't know, let's build a tool to figure out what happened
with the policy. It's policy so it should have applied, right? You don't know that.
So configuration status gives you a good look into what DSC did, what the status of it is, and all that kind of stuff.
It's actually a rich set of information in MWF5. So in MWF4, we had some basic information there.
We've made that really robust, so it gives you a lot of information, and we'll show you how to dig into that
and see all that information. And the last bit is the pull server 2.
There have been a lot of sessions already. All day yesterday was on DSC and pull server and all that kind of stuff.
We'll touch on some stuff with that, especially as it kind of relates to Devops and things like that.
So we'll dig into that a little bit and some things there and then open it up for questions.
With that I will hand it over to Travis to talk to you about the Encrypted MOFs.