So like I mentioned before, there's some
plus and minuses to both composite resources and partial configurations and this is taking a look at what it
looks like in kind of a DevOps environment where you're deploying to a pull server and you're going through
dev, test, prod, and what have you. In this example, I have the security, SQL, and IIS, partial configurations
in a web app that actually depends on those things to actually work.
And in a continuous integration deployment kind of environment, you go through and I the security guy create
my partial configuration, I deploy it, it's out on a pull server.
If there are any nodes that need it, aside from that DependsOn, they're going to pull it down and start
applying those things. Assuming you have DependsOn correctly done between all of these, it's going to wait
until it has all of them to apply them. So each of those partial configs go out to release.
They're out there sitting on the pull server. I deploy my web application.
It goes out there. A target node pulls it down, applies it, everything's happy, everything's good.
And then my security guy comes along and says I'm going to create version two of this thing and this is a little misleading.
There are version numbers on this slide, version numbers don't exist on partial configs like I mentioned before,
so when you have dependencies and stuff like that, if you push a new version of this thing, the security to
your pull server, the client's going to say, is there a configuration that has changed with this?
Yep. Alright I'm going to pull that thing down and apply it. So in this case, I go through my process of,
or I the security owner say I'm going to go through my process of build, test, and release, and then push
that thing out
to the pull server. In the meantime, Mr. WebApp 1 has never done any testing on that.
So unless the security guy knows WebApp 1, all of these
things are above me, but depend on me, they're going to get affected by this thing when I push that thing out
to the pull server. So in this case, you're going to have this
WebApp that has a new setting that's being applied that could affect it and you have no idea that happened.
So that's one of the things, and in some cases, if I'm the security guy, I don't care if I break WebApp 1.
If I have a security issue, I want that thing out there. So there are some situations where you may want to
do that kind of thing, but other situations where you're going to be like whoa, I don't want to know about
everybody in the world that's going to use my particular configuration here.
So that's where you get into the world where you have composite resources.
So I have a composite resource,
same kind of situation, these three composite resources, I'm using them as the WebApp guy, so they are all in my WebApp.
I'm using them. All things are good. That WebApp that I own that I'm using those things go through the dev,
test, prod out there, everything's working good and the security guy comes along and goes I'm going to make
this change to the security configuration, that doesn't affect my app at all.
Nothing happened because this happens,
these get pulled together at compile time. So when I'm ready to release my new version of my app, I
do my new version of my app. It's reusing the new versions of those composite resources, I go through my test
production and deploy that thing and everything's happening. So if you don't know about all of the up services
that are making use of your resources, then composite resources would kind of play into that a bit better,
so there are different situations where you want to do the different things.
Does that make sense? Alright, I see some heads nodding, other one's yawning
and sleeping, but head _____. Is it the plan to take one path moving forward or are you going to continue to---
No. Like I said, I think there are good circumstances
for using either one. Like the security example is a good example.
If you're the security guy, you want to make sure the settings are set a particular way and if it breaks
somebody, then they're going to come back to you and yell and you're going to tell them what they're doing wrong.
But if you determine that you need to support both of these methods in order to support those different
scenarios, whereas you could recode and support all those scenarios in one feature.
Okay. That's sort of a question. Yep. Okay, it's a feature request.
Yes, it is. Put it on UserVoice. Okay, Get-ConfigurationStatus, Get-DscConfigurationStatus.
We had some feedback from the previous release that it wasn't easy to determine the status of previous configuration runs.
So the purpose of this is to get the status of previous configuration operations.
A couple of use cases. If you call it with no parameters, it'll just get the status of the last operation.
You can add the all flag and get the status of all logged operations and you can add the CimSession and get
remote operations with the previous two combinations. I've also updated our public module of xDscDiagnostics
and provided access to historical verbose output. This is not a feature DSC provides, but the information is
there and it works a significant percentage of the time.
I'm not going to make
for promises that I can't live up to. It doesn't work all the time, but it's useful.
So let me start my demo. So first, I'll just show you the all. You can get that it'll just show one, but not all.
So I've had several runs and the first one I'll get is I'll go get the first initial attempt and get it in the
status object and I'll show you what that looks like. So my first initial attempt was success with three
resources, but there's more details in the status object, several rich objects.
I also, like you see here, there's many different types, Consistency, Initial, Reboot, LocalConfiguration.
I'm not going to go through all of them. I'll go through a couple during the demo.
But let's look at all the settings. We have MetaConfiguration here, so each time it runs, we record what
the MetaConfiguration is, so you can go back and see maybe it didn't run because the MetaConfiguration was wrong
and we have the resource if this is a success, so we only have resources in Desired State.
So let's look at the
rich object MetaConfiguration and we have, I was pushing to the machine, everything's pretty much the default state here.
Let's go look at those resources in the Desired State. So I had three things here, the testUser, DontRunAs,
and the RunAs. This is the demo I did earlier for you. So let's look, we have a JobId.
This is how we track, when you send us an operation, we track it by a JobId.
So now I'm going to run that cmdlet that I added and we'll get the details.
So we have all the verbose output. This gets it from a JSON file.
I ran it with--- Question, Travis. Yeah?
I had a quick question on how is that historical information attached?
Like is there any information on how far back, even a limitation on how far back in time you can go?
Yeah, I believe it's set in the MetaConfig
StatusRetentionTimeInDays. It's cache. I'll get to it later in the demo on where it's cache.
I believe I will, unless I removed it. So I'll go through a reboot.
We store this for reboot operations as well. So I didn't show you the status object, but the status object
is pretty much the same, so we have the verbose or an operation that counted as a reboot.
So this was something you couldn't get before. And yeah, here like this all of this information is stored in
this directory in here under System32\Configuration\ConfigurationStatus.
We have MOFs that store what the end box cmdlet is giving you and JSON files, which store that verbose output.
And if you notice, not all the MOFs here have the verbose, so if they don't have the JSON file, we don't have
the verbose output for those operations. So here's a failure just to get something interesting.
We have resources not in Desired State, so these objects are pretty rich.
We have the exception details with StackTraces, the full serialization of the exception object.
So you can go back and figure out why this failed, what line it failed on, etc.
Here I just did a throw, so it's not that interesting and it was in a ScriptBlock, so it doesn't actually
have a line number. But that's ConfigurationStatus. Alright,
so next I'll give