you guys a choice here. So next I have a few things with the V2 pull server.
There are a bunch of sessions on the pull server including all day yesterday and thing like that that's going on,
so I can talk about this. There is one thing that I want to show, but if there are questions that you guys
have, that you guys want to ask and see how we can answer them, I'll do that.
Otherwise, I'll go into this and kind of talk about that one thing that I want to talk about.
Is there a question over here somewhere? Just one question. Yep.
You mentioned a DSC is going to encrypt on a target. Are there any plans to move that into pull server if we
don't want to use any DSC? Potentially, but no commitment right now.
(Audience comment) What's that? What about the data source, so we can do that?
There is a UserVoice for that already, so go plus one that if you want to.
Yeah. Will the DscConfigurationStatus do have something that's actually imported to a compliance server…
So in the version that comes with WMF5 and is with 2016, all of that data that Travis just showed you gets
sent up to the pull server, so that's one of the things that I'll show you here real quickly, but we don't do
a good or we don't do a great job of giving you access to that data.
It's all stored there. It's in the database. But we're not going to tell you how to get to it, but we kind
of tell you how to get to it. So I will actually jump down. There are a bunch of questions here that we've
heard from a bunch of different people, but I'm going to kind of because of time jump to my demo here real quickly.
So I'll touch on a couple things with a pull server real quickly just because they're here in my face.
So with the pull server, the best way to configure the pull server as JSON and others have said who's used
the resource, we have x resource out there. Use that to do the configuration and don't try to do it on your
own because it'll take forever. This resource makes it much easier and JSON's script actually makes it even
better and work better. So use the configurations that are out there to do the configurations of a pull server,
your life will be a lot better. The TargetNodes itself. That's on GitHub you're saying?
What's that? The ones that are on GitHub? Yeah, and the ones that are on gallery, so as part of the
xPsDesiredStateConfiguration, there's a x webservice, I think it's called, use that to do the configuration
of the pull server. So one of the other things to keep in mind if you're using the new functionality in the
pull server where you can say I don't want to use a configuration Id, I want you to say this is the name of the
configuration I want the TargetNode to get. The name is only used in this, yes, there's a MetaConfig.
So you can, in the MetaConfig, say this is the name that I want.
That is only used at registration time.
It's never used after that again. Whatever that node is registered with the server with, will be used to say
this is the configuration that the TargetNodes get. The idea there is that you should be able to go to the
pull server and say I want to change that and not have to touch the client.
The client should just get the new configuration and apply that.
So the RegistrationKey, there may be a bug with that, according to Travis, but the RegistrationKey,
once registration is done, gets deleted, and if you put it back, that's the trigger to the LCM to say hey I need to register again.
So with the current implementation that we have, the
way to actually change what's in the database on the pull server is to go to the node, put the RegistrationKey
back in and change what the configuration name is, and then that node will register to get a different configuration.
In Azure Automation, you don't need to do any of that. You don't need to have this configuration name at all.
You can just have the
RegistrationKey in here. It registers with Azure Automation DSC
and then in Azure Automation DSC you can say I want this system now to get this configuration or what have you
and it'll just get that configuration, so it makes that a bit easier.
And if I have my way, we'll make that easier with the on-prem pull server as well.
So
the next thing is these resources here define where to go get the configuration, so this one is where to get
the actual configuration. This one is where to get the resources.
This one is where we report the status, all that rich status data.
You don't need this one. If you don't define this, wherever it gets the configurations, it's going to go try
and get resources if it needs those. You do need, although you shouldn't, you do need this one to tell it
where to report. The idea with these is to give you the
flexibility to say I want to get configs from here, resources from here, and report over there, but right now
as it stands, the minimum that you need to configure pull is the configuration repository and the
web repository or report web repository. Can you expand on the required resource real quick?
Yep. They look identical. So each of the places where you go to get resources and configurations and pull,
you need to register if you're using the new registration or the new configuration name method.
And the thing that tells the LCM whether to use the configuration name or the configuration Id is the configuration Id.
If you have the configuration Id set in the settings, it's going to use the old way of doing it.
If you don't have it there, it's going to use the new way of doing it.
Clear as mud? Yes. Is that part of the reason that the configuration Id isn't wired when you're doing the
partial config in pull? No. That's a bug. That's a different thing?
Yes. And I'm angry about that bug. Alright, so the next thing that I want to show you is I told you that the
reporting is not exactly easy to get to, but we do provide a way of getting to the reporting data.
So I will cruise through here real quickly, but I basically what I have here is just the script that's going
to go through how to access the APIs that we provide that give you access to the reporting data.
It is not something that you're going to necessarily build tooling on top of, but it does give you the access
to the reporting data, and the reason I say that it's not going to be something you're going to build tooling
on top of is we have key in the APIs that we call that is the AgentId, which is essentially the Id that is
generated either the ConfigurationId if you're using that method or
the AgentId that's generated by the LCM itself. You have to pass that in to get the reporting data for that node.
So yeah, basically if you have a bunch of nodes, you have to iterate through each of those things with the known AgentId.
And the reason. Excuse me? Is this documented? It is documented, yes, and I will put these scripts and
stuff like that up on GitHub and we'll share them soon. So basically, what I'm doing here is I created a
couple of functions and those functions just basically allow me to parse the JSON that is returned.
So this pulls the generic JSON data out and this pulls the status data out of that included JSON.
So I will make sure that these things are in memory here and they're opening doors now.
Alright, so I will run that. Oops, I need to do that over here. So I will do that here.
I will F8 that, that'll run, and I will skip over these two. These two basically just pull up and show the
schema for the pull
server, so you can actually, if you know anything about code data, you can dig into that and figure out how to
actually do the queries and stuff.
I'll just do a couple of the queries. You can get the node information about the node that is configured on that system.
So it's just an Invoke-WebRequest and we have the pull server, we have a nodes location, you give it the AgentId,
and then you get Agent information and that'll pull the information about the agent.
We have the configuration names and then the primary one is the reports, so you can pull the reports down for that node.
So I'll actually jump to that, so you can at least see that.
So a couple things here. I'll run that guy, then you can see the reports that get generated from that,
so this basically just took the last one and people are lining up already.
So this will take the last one. Basically, by default, we return all
of the reporting data for a node when you use this query, so if you have a month's worth of data, we're going to
return it all when you call that. We give you a way through OData to filter that out, so you can say I only
want to get, in this particular
case, I only want to get this high level data without all of the bloat of all the reporting data, so I can dig
through that and say I care about this one job. So in this particular case, I have, I get the data and I'm
just getting these particular columns, so I'm not getting all of the big status data that
Travis was showing you. I can figure out, I care about this
particular job. You can get this JobId and then you can call back into the API with that and get the
original data from that. So we do give you the tools to do it.
It's a bit manual right now, but we do allow you to do that right now.
(Audience question) I don't know. That's a good question and I will look into it whether you can use the
OData tools to actually generated cmdlets for this. Is there any other questions?
We'll be up here for a few minutes, but thank you very much.