So yeah, so we learn a lot and hopefully that resonates with you the way we are addressing some of the main areas.
So specifically about engineering, one of the things that we are changing in the culture within the team is
that we are becoming more and more of a DevOps culture about how we are developing innovation within the team.
And what I mean by DevOps culture and model is that we really are focusing more of how we deliver innovation
based on solutions that they are really addressing the customer problem.
This kind of goes to the point that Kenneth was referring earlier, that direct communication with customers
and with the community is surfacing scenarios and controlling the spaces that we need to start thinking about
not only just delivering features, but it's about delivering the solutions.
You deliver that that in way that it's a platform that enables others, you to absolutely take that technology
and results in progress within your companies. Now here that is a really important shift culturally how we
are doing that. The other thing too is the concept about functional and test code.
Remember when I said only about the roles and responsibilities how they are evolving in Microsoft, so one of
the things that we are doing today is start thinking about the software engineering.
They need to start thinking about when you write functional code, you've got to have test code associated with it.
So part of the code reviews prior to checking new code is to be sure that you have robust test coverage as
part of your functional code. The other pieces have all the scenario validation and demos.
For all of you who maybe has been adopting a DevOps model, this is really important.
It's about really holding accountable the engineers to be able to demo the features and the scenarios that
they are working on. You see something really cool. Today, actually later today, you're going to see a
little bit of that. But I think it also will enable us is that PMP to partner with us, then when we finish
the work, yeah, were also addressing that problem.
And we go reach out to you guys and others and make sure it really is.
So there's an ongoing process here that we're evolving through. How do we do our engineering in a way that's
a little more test and demo-driven, if you will, almost to make sure we're completing the scenarios.
A few places where we've not quite closed those gaps, we're trying to close and I think it'll really help us
over the next year or so as we try to land the complete result if you will.
Yeah, I think that through that journey, I'll ask the obvious question.
How many of you think that we should do more about debugging and troubleshooting in PowerShell and DSC?
It's a rhetorical. It's a rhetorical question because we know that.
So yeah, where I think it's going to help is that the engineering team has started developing the scenarios
to these solutions. We've got to start having the mindset to say
how easy for me is to also troubleshoot the scenario. What kind of instrumentation I need to put in place?
What kind of eventing I need to put in place? It will really help you have that telemetry to help us to troubleshoot.
You'd be able as well to debug problems within the environment. So this is a scenario that we're going to do
little more, include like a script on alias has been a greatest start.
We learn a lot of that. That is a great approach and how we can start helping you and helping others to
really focus about how debugging and troubleshooting can be done within PowerShell and DSC both in the
private cloud, as well as in the public. Another thing that we do, either this is going to start becoming
absolutely more important is about implementing this process of tracking things, right.
I want to start providing a _____ engineer monitor, visibility, and transparency to you about our tests,
about the results of those tests, so you can have a tool as well to apply the same test.
It could be Pester, it could be a set of other type of a technology.
But it will help you to say when I deliver a module or I'm delivering a solution, that you have some tests
associated with them. It gives you visibility about what the results are expected, so when you are doing your
own development and deployment, actually that will have as a tool for you to actually do the same things that
we do in Microsoft.
And it's really an interesting approach because I will say that it's a little more, not just a DevOps approach,
but also taking kind of the open source model to some extent. Even if the code is not open source,
maybe we should pretend that it is and how we would actually do our development in those scenarios and that
would actually help us out a little bit. So we're certainly, I think, kind of learning as we go from both
models and trying to adopt it inside as well as out. So we'll see an increase in that.
Absolutely.
I think we talked a bit about the overall of what we're going to start doing here.
Let me just, I'll bring these all up and then we'll talk about it.
So we are, excuse me, we will be delivering more blogs, more, and I would say right now the PowerShell blog,
and you can give me feedback on this after, I'm happy with this, right now the PowerShell blog occasionally
is a little more formal. It's more casual. We're probably tone that down a bit, move the formality a
little bit more to the home page announcements and hopefully just have a little chattier blog where people
are more comfortable sort of having a discussion, if you will. We'll increase the overall,
the community artifacts, and our engagement and this is worth noting. We do rely on you overall to handle
the community in a broad sense, but I would say that we need to lean in a little more in a few areas and
actually, A, make sure we're monitoring to check if there's okay, some fire blows up, how do we solve this
really quickly, make sure we're really addressing the issues the community is beginning to have,
make sure we're backstopping it and engage directly just as frequently.
We had a great time when we had that new Twitter account that actually Angel created for us and it's been a
lot of fun to watch people jump on it, it's been fun to use, obviously, you're not going to have an in-depth
of design discussion on Twitter. Some people occasionally try to, in which case, we'll try to kindly redirect
you, but we do have a process for that. Yeah, in fact, over time we want more and more our thinking, in fact,
we should address this just a little bit. UserVoice is actually not up here and it probably should be.
It's really not a social media, but part of what we do want you to do over time is to drive requests and
issues into UserVoice, so we track them. They're being looked at across many levels of the organization it
turns out and the team is looking at them regularly every week actually just to make sure that we actually got them.
Now we move
hundreds and hundreds from Connect, alright, and so those we're sort of going back through more slowly,
but anything recent, we should be on fairly quick. And for some reason you haven't gotten a response within
some reasonable period of time, feel free to reach out direct and say hey I just thought I'd note that I put
this out there. You can do that just directly via email. But nonetheless, over time, now just because it's
up there and we've looked at it, doesn't mean we're going to do it the next week, right.
So we'll try to also get a little more transparent as we can within our reasonable business constraints about
when we're actually doing things. We're working through ongoing planning on a regular basis, so it's a little,
it will come and go our ability to share that. Sometimes it will be high, sometimes it will be low.
Over time, we think that we will end up with the issues being kind of raised on UserVoice and then probably
more in-depth discussions as we begin to flow this process more in the RFC GitHub kind of a discussion,
so we can have those discussions. We just started. If you'll notice with some
RFC stuff even today and we'll probably grow that, so sort of look in that space, if you will.
Theoretically, if we were to look into the community holistically, you see Twitter and otherwise is broad
discussion, broad quick tweets. The blog is a more casual interaction.
The home page the more official announcement. UserVoice is the way for you guys to tell us hey we have a bug
or a feature request to weigh in on that and then in-depth discussion will probably take more of the GitHub RFC.
Now I think one of the things that I want to highlight also so well are involvement, how we are going to be
working with you in the future. I think that this is an important thing and it's a change for us culturally
is that we need to go also to where you are. I mean the reason why we've done the Twitter account or there
is actually a really popular Facebook PowerShell page, yeah, it's got an alias, we start learning that the
community is everywhere, which is awesome. We are like super happy about it and this then does create a
challenge for us because the challenge that we've got to go and learn, the discussions that are occurring in
all these different social medias, and then try to bring those learnings back into our team to figure out how
to address a particular problem or how to prioritize work. Another thing too that I want to highlight about
increasing the community's sharing artifacts. So we are going to go and invest a little more as we
developing these solutions to give you with those solutions the artifacts to enable those scenarios.
I think that that's really important, so it's pretty open source.
I want to be able to make it completely available for you, not only just to use, but contribute as well.
So help us. Help us with the contributions. There are tons of innovation happening in all your companies that
you do every day, so if you see a vehicle for you to share that with the rest of you, this is the time to do it
because I think if we evolve, I think that we want to become more and more open with all of us basically to
share these artifacts across the companies.
Absolutely. And one thing worth
noting here, I know I got the direct customer engagement. We already talked about that.
I won't land it again, but I will note that we are imminently aware that many of you are kind of forward leaning.
You're kind of in the early adopter crazy innovator early majority phases and there are many companies that
still exist and Microsoft leveraging our technology, which are more in the late majority lag are those who are
more cautious in their approach. That's okay. We want to hear from them too and try to support them as well.
So while we're pushing more and more aggressively in this open source and new world, we know that there are
some people, in fact, there was an interesting survey read the other day where as soon as we said the word
modern, like the entire room just died. It's like I don't want anything modern.
I want what's working today. It's like, you know, and so there is this interesting a blend of culture that
we work with on a regular base that Microsoft just because of the breadth of our offering.
That doesn't go away. We're happy. We want to work with both aspects.
We will be very forward leaning moving forward, but we're simultaneously, one of the reasons we go so far
down with WMF 5 is we recognize that people are not necessarily moving forward on the core technologies,
but they want to, but we feel that PowerShell actually enables them to run their operations across all
technologies better, more efficiently, and actually allows them to adopt a new technologies underlying
platform technologies sooner. That's actually part of the argument we have to make in order to go down level.
So we're well aware of that.
One thing I want touch while we're waiting for Erin is that we talk a little bit about this whole community artifact sharing.
The one thing that we learn, there were a couple of questions earlier in the previous talk that we had,
is this concept about versioning. You know how problematic versioning is becoming, right.
As we start releasing more modules, scripts, previews, we realize that the current versioning scheme that we
created literally 10 years ago,
it really ties into Windows, it's not going to scale moving forward.
So when you're still thinking about versioning of DSC resources for like for a class base resources,
well when you start thinking about, it's a great example, when you start thinking about all these different
cmdlets that we're going to be delivering in the galleries, I feel one of the obvious questions like how are
we going to be managing versioning, right. So one of the things the team is doing right now, we are going
through a journey to figure out how to redesign a versioning scheme, so as we start releasing more previews
and more artifacts to the galleries, we'll start addressing these versioning scheme.
I think we're going to have some discussions in the near future with many of you to give us feedback, right.
We'll start some MVA discussions, we'll go over and eventually get to RFC sometime in the next while as we
start talking to the versioning. And it's not just the modules. Even as you know, we've put PowerShell on
CoreCLR in order to put it to Nano. Well CoreCLR does side by side, so how are we going to handle that?
How are we going to handle that versioning story? So we're doing kind of an all-up think about.
We'll just give you mine.
Here you can take it.
We're just giving an all-up discussion around versioning. We have to step back.
And versioning is one of those tricky things. There is no easy right answer.
If there was, we would just steal it. We're not proud here alright.
And if you have it, I'm okay stealing it just to be clear. I'm not proud about this.
We don't have to reinvent the version.
I don't feel the need to reinvent any wheels here.
We don't want to do that.
But it just turns out none of these wheels really are great that we've found yet, so but we'll work with you
to see if we get one that really works across all of the artifacts that work with PowerShell.