So thanks for letting me swing by. I've been in PowerShell 14, 15 days.
Wahoo! Not bad. Thank you very much. So I've been at the company for about 17, I'm with Microsoft for about
17 years in a lot of different roles, everything from evangelism, to developer support to ultimately landing
in SQL Server and the data platform. Up until a couple weeks ago, I was the director of content publishing
for that whole shebang bang, so if it's analytics, if it's SQL Server, if it's machine learning, real time,
that was me and my group and we produced something like 18 billion topics on a yearly basis.
You were looking at 60,000 page views a month. On average, I get 18 million page views over on SQL Server.
So why would I leave there to come to this room? And if any of you have not seen Ed Wilson's blog.
Why would you ask that question? I don't understand that.
It's a lead.
I was confused.
It's a lead in.
Okay, just thought I'd make sure.
I mean, besides
the extra pay I mean always gets to work in PowerShell. So why would I leave that to come over here.
And here's the thing that is really motivating for me.
What am I more passionate about than a job title or a particular technology?
It's when I see a very active community that gives a crap about helping the person to their left,
that's willing to contribute their knowledge back to the betterment of the community as a whole.
Love that. I love it when we have a dev team that actually cares about the scenarios you're trying to do
and whether we can get them all done and do them cleanly. That's one thing.
It'll mature over time. But you put those two things together and you put all that goodness in an open framework
where you have the ability not just to help the person next to you,
but help the person across the country, help the person that's just getting started, help fix a problem up in open source.
That's where things get really, really interesting, and to be honest, you can't move something like the data
platform over to a system like that, but you can take a language and you can take that platform, and you can
take this community and enable it to support each other. So I would encourage everyone to take a look at Ed Wilson's
blog from yesterday. I was a guest blogger there and we're talking about what's
the future of PowerShell documentation. The future of PowerShell documentation is actually sitting in this
room and listening to this video ultimately long term. We're going to go completely open source with our
documentation, which means you have access. If you see something that's bugging you, you can go fix it.
If there's a better way of explaining some a hard concept, you can help us help the person to your left.
All of our documentation is going to be up on GitHub, very simple contribution requirements, but everything that
you do, you get credit for. Your names on that article, your picture's on that article.
If you're
promoting your personal portfolio and your persona, we're going to link out to your stuff all in an effort
to get us to a point where we take a look at some of the other open source languages like Python.
Now Python documentation is ugo. It is the way, it's like going back to 1985.
It looks horrible, but the content itself is exceptional. It's easy to discover.
They break the hard concepts down and there's not a bunch of paid writers sitting in a dark room somewhere
just cranking out words. It's the community going up there
hey there's a better way. Or don't forget you've got to remember these three things.
So we're kicking it off with DSC right now. There's a pilot going on.
JP who's one of my writers here. We've got another swath of content that's moving up into the open portfolio.
We're actually going to be bringing core PowerShell as a reference, so as we talk about the shifts that are
going on in engineering,
documentation
has been doing the same thing. If you look at how many product teams that we work with that are producing
PowerShell, it went from 2 or 3 to I think our last count was 380 development teams at Microsoft are
contributing to PowerShell in some way, whether through modules or extensions.
To be able to operate at that speed, it can't just be the PowerShell team.
And it can't be just the four or five writers that I have on my team.
It's going to take a community to make this actually work and we're going to start that by investing and
opening it up, getting it out of the way of you guys helping and supporting each other and sharing that guidance.
So my name is Don Gill, my email address is the easiest one ever, dongill@microsoft.com or Twitter, you can always
hit me up if there's something wrong, there's something we should be doing better, I'm the guy that's going
to help make it happen, whether it's on the online, whether it's in the shell itself, we can do this better.
Hit me up. Thank you.
Thank you.
Yah, thank you much.