Good afternoon. You know, normally, what you have seen in the past is that Jeffrey Snover tends to be here
to talk a little bit about the future, but this time Jeffrey's on a trip.
He's in Hawaii somewhere taking a vacation. Can you believe it? But anyway, so Kenneth and I, we're going to
spend a little time today talk about the past, the present, and the future of PowerShell.
For all of you guys who don't know me, my name is Angel Calvo. I'm the partner group software engineering
manager for Enterprise Cloud Management. My team is the team responsible for the management technologies for
Windows, as well as PowerShell, Desired State Configuration.
Ken Hansen and I guess I've been on the PowerShell team for 13 years, a very long time.
Turn the mic on. Who didn't turn that on? Is that working? Yes.
I'm Ken Hansen and I don't know how to work these mics, but I do PowerShell for about 13 years,
so that's---I need a command. Where's the command turn on mic? Alright, good deal.
That's it.
So let's talk a little bit about PowerShell.
This is great. So it's 10 years, 2006-2016 and I couldn't resist putting up the actual original book that
came out with Monad. Anybody remember MSH and Monad? How many Monads do we have here?
Thank you very much. You guys have been with us a long time. It's been a fun journey.
I just couldn't resist.
Lee Holmes actually had it on his desk just so you know where that photo shot came from.
It's kind of a fun little thing. We thank you for your great support.
Our mission we actually started with a while ago and this is a great one almost worth reading.
Deliver an extensible scripting environment that is secure, interactive, programmable, production-ready,
that's a lot, to enable consistent, now you're getting really out there, consistent and reliable automation
of administration tasks. What's fascinating is, we're not there yet, but we're going to do our job eventually.
Yeah, we are.
Alright. The good news is we've had 10 years of progress. With your help, we made great strides,
but there's a lot to do.
In 10 years, I mean this year, November?
November 14th.
November 14th, 10 years of PowerShell. I mean it is quite an amazing journey for all of us,
especially for all of you who been since day 1.
A few gray hairs to prove it.
And actually, the community, I mean what an amazing community. By the way, how many of you started using
PowerShell 10 years ago?
Isn't that amazing? Give these guys a hand. This has absolutely been a phenomenal journey.
It's these people who together with the rest of the community made PowerShell what it is today.
I mean this was known not only at Microsoft a journey, it was a journey that we took with all of you,
so we really appreciate it. You help to get us to what we are today.
Oh, and to make a point to that, these are about 80 names, I think it's 81.
These are actually people, the community, not members of Microsoft, these are all community members who filed
bugs in the year 2004 on PowerShell at the time. Isn't that an incredible list?
Eighty people. From the very beginning, it's been a community effort and one thing I couldn't resist because
we did miss this, we're going back in slides, a complete no, no, but I can't resist.
Right there at the bottom right-hand side, if you want to, for those of you who are archeologists and you
want to go see the original BNF, go see Jim Truher. He's actually got it.
It's kind of fun. And Lee Holmes actually had at one point a VM running the old PowerShell.
Just wanted to point that out. It's kind of a fun thing to have.