Yeah, yes.
We can't resist. Now we're into the more fun predictions. We always have, we've always believed in
PowerShell and in audit, it's PowerShell or no UI, it's UI or no PowerShell.
We've always believed the worlds that peanut butter and chocolate work better together, unless you're allergic
to peanuts, but that's not the problem. So what we're trying to say here is that over time we want to make
sure we have great UI over PowerShell. And so, we've actually plumbed a few things, but we will get
seriously considering, notice the word consider, it's might caveat.
Seriously.
But seriously, find some way to actually auto-generate UI out of PowerShell modules.
Yeah, awesome.
It might not be the prettiest, but it should be sufficient and then hopefully we're even looking at ways for
you then to be able to do curate a UI on top of that. It's an interesting project.
A few people told us we were crazy and that we would fail, but we're having a lot of fun and we are somewhat confident.
Community. I think, we've been talking a lot about community and definitely the future of PowerShell is the community.
It's all of us. It's the people here, the people who is basically around the planet using PowerShell every day
and I think as we start thinking about communication, like how we're going to work together, we want you to
be a significant part of the future of PowerShell. We are introducing an RFC process.
I believe in the MVP summit for all of you who are MVPs, you got a preview of that.
But this is something that we want more and more. PowerShell file.
We've done amazing stuff together. We're going to continue investing in PowerShell when it comes to
integrating into Windows, integrating with some of the Microsoft technologies, but there's this other aspect
about you are the expert in PowerShell. We need your help. So if you have ideas, if you want to request
changes, design, we want to provide you a vehicle to do that.
UserVoice, that kind of stuff.
Absolutely. And the RFC process, as well, right.
Absolutely.
And the other thing too about the GitHub, I think that this is another thing, GitHub will begin our official
place where we want our communities to work together and you're going to start seeing a lot more and more of
GitHub open source projects. A lot more.
We just started.
This is just the starting of what is coming next and we want that to be absolutely the repository for all of us,
for you to start sharing and we're going to start providing, how many of you know Joey?
Joey's somewhere in the back. He's what I call our community problem manager, it's the best description,
and he's working right now in our government about how we're going to be doing these, how it's going to help
the community to work together about sharing artifacts and technology moving forward.
Yeah, and I don't want to hit, I know we've hit the community a lot and open stuff, so I won't belabor it anymore.
The one thing worth noting is over time PowerShell gallery will continue to become a more and more trusted
distribution surface for many things, possibly and besides just PowerShell artifacts, but certainly for
PowerShell artifacts both from inside of those which we produce as Microsoft, but also we're trying to find
ways where if another company produced an artifact that you know it's supported and validated,
it's actually from them, that kind of stuff. So we're trying to make sure that it is a trusted place or at
the least you know which modules are highly trusted you can go download and use and we'll continue to grow
that over time. It is something that Microsoft all up is sort of beginning to learn and get their head around.
We are in many ways the PowerShell team has been a great place to work at, I kind of stepped back a little bit,
and a horrible place. It's been great because we always get to do something new and crazy.
It's been horrible because everybody looks around and says what are you doing and then we have to sort of
fight our way free of the entanglements that come with the past.
But that's another case where we kind of stood out there and we started stood it up and you've guys have been really
supportive, that's really helped us get the message out and more teams are looking at it going hey we could
use something like this, and so we're working with them. Some of that is artifacts might show up here,
some might show up somewhere else, but thank you again for your help.
But this should become a trusted place to go.
Yep. And I think in the open source, so just to point out a couple of things.
One of the things there we highlighted earlier was the concept of how we started using our platform to
integrate into open source technologies like Chef. And I think that you're going to start seeing this trend
should become more and more broad. I mean, the goal, I mean, the dream for some of us is imagine the day
that no matter what language that you use to actually build your application.
You can use PowerShell and DSC as the automation language, the utility language, if you will,
and the configuration method for actually deploy your application in the cloud and manage it in the cloud.
I mean that is the dream. That's what we want to get to. I mean, how we're going to do that is by doing this
level of integration with a number of technologies that are available today in the open source community.
And just a couple of more predictions here moving forward, one, now this is kind of a different one than the others.
This is where we're actually just beginning. We're going to use a lot more telemetry and metrics of success
across our team. How do I know we've had a good community engagement?
I'm going to have some statistic that I try to get some sense on it.
Now that's not the only way we'll do things and the only way we'll measure success, but we would love to
engage with those of you who are crazy statisticians and have some ideas as to how we can measure your guy's
success because one of the things I do struggle with is I don't just care about our success, okay I've got
tons of downloads, but I'd also love to reach pass that a little bit and say, okay, how do I know that my
community has been successful in deployment? How do I know that people are not stuck on something?
How do I know that the corporation received great value from the PowerShell, their use of PowerShell or DSC?
How do I measure the fact that DSC actually, in some cases, it's easy.
Well DSC reduced my deployment and reconfiguration time from a week to three hours.
Okay, that's a great measurement. Anything like that you can give us or any other ideas you have around that,
please feed them in because it's really more of a request for information this one is as a prediction
because we're going to do something here, it be great to have it actually be great.
Micro-services. I think that this is a, you probably got a taste of that with OMS Azure automation with our DSC integration.
In reality, that's a pull server that we have basically deployed into the cloud using Azure.
Yeah I think one of the things that which they're seeing is more and more of an investment in our platform
than this one should just deliver in the platform. We're going to start delivering services that you can
actually use for doing things like, David communicated yesterday in a presentation, editor services.
How can I plug in my favorite editor in order to do PowerShell? How can I basically do validation of my
scripting into the cloud, so I can have it hosted validation services, maybe Pester is a service,
think about it that way. Configuration. DSC is a platform, well what is configuration as a service?
Things like pull server.
Pull server's been a big one. We just had a whole discussion around pull server and it's a great little
product, in fact, we put it out there first originally, more as a sample.
We sort of backed into it a little bit. It's like hey we got this platform, we got this LCM, how do we make
sure you can actually use it in pull mode. Oh, we'll write a little piece of code to make sure it works.
Okay, well that's a good, we need to make it a bigger piece of code. Let's make sure
we actually have a good sample out there. Oh, okay let's take the next step.
Let's actually oh people might want to use that sample as a test case, and over time, we've grown this thing
to actually be something that Azure put out there with the intent that people would actually write larger
tools and more complete tools on top of the basic underlying protocol.
What we discovered is everybody says oh I want a pull server and starts using it automatically.
They exceeded our expectations.
Our adoption and the speed of adoption certainly exceeded our original expectation, which is great and
certainly we're stepping back and saying okay how do we fill that need in a way that will meet the overall business
objectives, but also just meet the community's. And so we're thinking through how to do that in a way again
that would be open and thoughtful and bring everybody in and let us create a great experience instead of
one right now, which needs some improvement. We're going to keep working on it.
If you're hitting roadblocks in the pull server, file those, tell us, and work with us in the future.
I think it's really important too that the role of micro-services in the hybrid scenarios, it just kind of
goes to the point that Erin made earlier, is we start thinking about heterogeneous, we start thinking gross cloud
type of integration. It's really important having the sort of services that allows you to do both.
You can be on-prem, but if you want to go to the cloud, it allows you to easily integrate with other types
of cloud services. So I think this is a scenario, especially like deployment it would be a good example of
that as well.
Absolutely. And another place is where this does pivot us a little bit towards, as Angel was talking about
the scenarios and solutions, we will pivot. We're a platform as you mentioned in that other meeting,
we're a platform first and foremost and we want to make sure people succeed and we'll probably start picking
a couple of vertical
places of like deployment or something like that. Make sure okay you can really get the bits out there,
they're really going to be successful and have an all up solution with the package manager, DSC,
PowerShell all combined together.
And I think another thing that's about a good reason why I think the name of the summit has changed.
I mean, I think it was a year ago, Don and I, and a few others, Jeff and we were having this idea about how
we evolve it, how the summit will evolve and I think Don came up it's like well you guys got to think about
these DevOps then, right. We were like looking at each other like yeah I guess this is for real.
It's really a culture shift in IT. And we realized that wow there is this amazing opportunity for PowerShell
to become the language that basically ties things together and the concept of both the tool, if you will,
chain of DevOps, as well as, as people start evolving and moving the solutions that you want agile deployment
and operations of those solutions, PowerShell and DSC can play a significant role of that.
So I think that moving into the future, this is a scenario that we're going to be investing more and more,
and we're going to be working with our community of tying that to a chain all of us together.
And this is kind of the area which PowerShell is sort of born to do, right.
The reason we have PowerShell in the first place is not everything was a file, document-based management in
Windows it was goo, right. You had stuff in registry, stuff in API, stuff in XML, stuff who knows where,
and so PowerShell kind of originated as a glue language within Windows and has continued to grow into a bit
of a glue language as Erin pointed out, even a little bit of the we do spread our arms a little bit across
the shell and the developer scripting scenario and that's actually on purpose, right.
And there's that intent to have always be able to make you be able to do things in PowerShell.
It's not a single-purpose language on purpose, in this case, unlike other languages that I've participated in.
So we think in fact it as before in the DevOps world become more and more of a glue logic, our intention is
that it will in fact become known there and be able to do that.
As a part of making sure that happens, in version 2, we have no major announcements.
And in version 2, actually in version 1 of PowerShell when it first went out, we had no PowerShell on Windows.
You had to just download it. You guys might not remember. I remember this, right.
You remember. Okay, it was just a pain. You had to download it all.
In version 2, we wrote on the board our mantra was before everything else, PowerShell everywhere so that people
didn't have to do that, right. So our goal, in that case, drive was getting all skews of Windows.
And you'll see as we move forward and try to become more of both the glue language and technologies,
that we're going to try to make sure we're able to push PowerShell technology everywhere whether it be DSC
or gallery or different components, we want to make sure that in fact that we're able to push things.
And we said before the open source will go or go on as fast as we can with as much as we can within the realms
of reasonable business and within the realms of our resources. And so, we're continuing to evolve that story,
but our goal is to make sure that our tools are available for you.
Yeah, I think as Kenneth say, well we want PowerShell everywhere, I mean, I think is the---
Technology everywhere.
Yeah, we want technology everywhere, but we want it to be a tool for everybody and I think that this is
something that as you start, you saw some of the predictions in the past and some of the predictions in the future,
you're going to start seeing more and more of that. Stay tuned.
Velocity. We haven't, we did start moving things a little quicker as you noticed.
That will continue. We're going to try to move them quicker and with higher quality moving forward and with
a little bit of communication all simultaneously. We'll try to get that stutter step working a little better.
There is a drive towards simplicity. Now this might not be obvious.
This is our last line. This might not be obvious, but we do actually try to make this so, that was the whole
intent of DSC. If you take a look at it from the user perspective, if there's a good match and take a look
at the PowerShell code, you get about a 10x factor of simplicity out of just a DSC configuration when it matches.
Now what we've got to do with DSC is make it easier to get there and make that more complete coverage.
Does that make sense? But the whole intent was reduce the challenge of complexity, so that we can achieve the
scale we need to in this industry and the rapidity of release we have to.
That's why we do DSC. And so we will take a look at both DSC and other technologies to try to make it
simpler and simpler for the end user or in certain cases. We recognize we don't always land in the first
place when you start looking at things like the pull server. And then last, but not least, there's _____ of completeness.
We talked a little about the scenario issues. How do we actually make sure we are complete and well-rounded?
That's where we're counting on you guys to do some UserVoice and feedback and to tell us what those issues are.
So with that said.
Yeah, I think, thank you. I think that the best way to finish is to thank all of you.
I mean, we come to work every day at Microsoft because of you. I mean, really.
PowerShell has been an amazing experiment. I've been with the team now; I think it's my fifth year now coming
in as a different role. Kenneth has been here for 10 years, 13, 13 years.
Thirteen years, something like that, maybe 14.
And it's amazing to see where we are. I mean, for me from five years ago to today, I mean I'm looking in this
room and I'm looking at the other people and I'm looking at the momentum and it could not happen without you, your help.
So we need more help. We need more of you to basically contribute.
You know to help is basically take PowerShell for another amazing 10 years, so thank you from my point of view.
I don't know.
Thank you very much.