Well that was a good view of the future of Windows Server, but I think we want to talk a little bit about
looking forward at our predictions for PowerShell in the future.
We can't have a looking forward discussion without some random predictions, so we have to.
Disclaimer, we are not architects like Jeffrey. These are predictions that I feel pretty good that I think
that we can achieve.
Well kind of in an order of like achievable to aspirational.
Exactly. So I feel pretty good about kind of our predictions, so I've got to bet, I would bet in our predictions---
I'm confident of that one.
I'm pretty confident about this one. So as Erin mentioned earlier, Windows Server 2016 is coming up
and it will be available sometime this year. And with that, we will release a WMF 5.1 update that will
contain all the changes from WMF 5.0 all the way through that what we call RTM release, so it will accumulate
those changes, yeah, whatever
we end up calling it, whatever marketing is used. GA I think is was we call it nowadays.
I think so, yes.
So GA will accumulate all the fixes and we'll re-release to help you take the latest changes.
One thing that's really important, it goes back to the feedback.
Please give us the feedback because this is the opportunity if there are some bugs, issues,
suggestions that you want us to consider that is this interesting time between now and then, they can help
you to get those changes and bug fixes into the WMF 5.1.
And the goal of this release of 5.1 is a little more of a service pack type of thing, if you will,
because in fact it will be the way that we support 5.0 moving forward, so we already put WMF 5.0 out there.
We'll be making the usually Microsoft support issues whatever it is with it all that we normally don't have
that many QFEs out of PowerShell, still we would do those kind of things, but we roll up any and all changes
into 5.1 and that's how we would actually support the 5.0 after that and then we'll be making changes on the
5.1 base and you'll get the usual Microsoft contract on 5.1, which would be required then like 3 or 4 months
after we put out 5.1. We'll do whatever sort of makes sense in that space.
Will those updates be released as KBs? We're still in discussion to figure out exactly how those will also be released.
That's a great, yeah. So we'll keep looking into that.
That's a good question by the way. That's actually we are going through that, internalizing that right now.
But this is a, anyway I just want to make sure people have got their head out, they know we've got a lot of
done with 5.0. We didn't want people to be surprised. We said oh by the way, now you need to roll to the 5.1
in order to continue forward as it will align with the Windows Server release and all the support alignment
with a Windows Server product, if that makes sense. And we'll blog about that later.
Oh, this one!
Yeah, OpenSSH. So OpenSSH is an open source project by the way.
It's already available for many of you. Please feel free to contribute.
We'll keep updating it. We will release an OpenSSH in Windows 2016.
It will be available. It will be just to give you visibility will be first of all.
It's not going to be perfect.
Oh no, nothing is perfect in software, but I'm sure we can make it awesome.
It's going to be great.
But I think the point here is that initial, just to set expectation, it will be kind of like WMF.
It would be what we call an autobahn, so it will be a package that we'll make available for you in the gallery
that you can install it. It will be supported. And then over time where one of the things that we are
considering is actually bring as part of Windows and install, but we need because we want to get some of the
feedback from you and from the community from using it and then we'll continue improving it.
We are working very closely with the OpenDSD community, as well.
They are helping us, especially about together the crypto security of
Windows with OpenSSH, which is really what we are spending most of time.
And we're really excited about this project because I think it's going to help us a lot in the enterprise.
This is a pick by many of you and by many other people who are not here today.
That's right. A lot of fun. Oh and this one. We are continuing to invest in security and breach.
I think Erin highlighted that a little bit. That hasn't gone away.
It's only become more important to us and to our customers. Even as a part of that, from our perspective in
security, it also goes back to some of the quality issues. We continually are asked hey we want the gallery
to be the place to go for high quality stuff. Security also is kind of related to that.
We're going to continue to focus on security and quality on a regular basis.
One thing just to point out, I mean, this is a really important area for investing.
How many of you know Lee Holmes? Okay, so Lee Holmes' role is changing.
Recently, we made an announcement internally in the company. He's going to be our lead architect for
security for Enterprise Cloud because we start realizing we need to start thinking about security,
not necessarily just within PowerShell, but when you take PowerShell and you put it in the cloud, how are we
going to be thinking about protecting, doing things like assume breach, and that sort of scenario.
So that tells you that we are really behind the security efforts.
It definitely is the top of mind for the company for us.
And it's kind of cool you came out of PowerShell.
Yeah.
For all the security, you might remember our very first PowerShell don't turn on remoting because of
the supposed exploit. And
documentation. How many people would like documentation? And here to make sure that in fact you get that,
where's Don? Right here. Don, please give us, stand up and give us just a few minutes if you will.
So I didn't realize that the tail end of that was bet Don's job.
That's right. I didn't warn him I was going to put that on the slide.
So not only was it this Don, but it was the Don that just came up.