Alright, I think we can move on.
We're going to shift a little bit. Absolutely.
We have a guest speaker today
who's going to join us. How many of you know Erin? Yeah.
Erin is my boss, that's one thing and she also runs Windows Server completely and a few other things
as well, so she's going to tell us a little more about the future.
Awesome. It's great to be here. It's amazing to see from kind of coming
into this room, was it two years ago Don that I think we were here.
Three, two years ago.
Two years ago here.
Two years ago and just seeing the increase in folks that are seeing and interested in PowerShell,
interested in what we're doing in a DevOp space and here both learning from what we're putting out,
but also sharing the collective wisdom that's in this room. It's amazing to see.
As Kenneth said, I'm Erin Chaplin, the director of program management for the Windows Server team and I
thought I would just share a few top of mind things around what we're doing in Windows Server in particularly
how PowerShell and the whole DevOps experience fits into that. We're working, we're hard at work right now
on Windows Server 2016. Our technical preview for it came out late last year.
We're kind of on the eve of having a technical preview 5 that should be out later this month and that's kind of
our last big release before we'll hit like the final version of Windows Server that's due out later this year.
Windows Server is an interesting point, right, it's an interesting product and it's an interesting point in
the industry and just in general, right. We're at a transition period and when we think about Windows Server,
we really think about two roles that Windows Server plays. Traditionally, it's been very much part of the
infrastructure and that whole space and as we see the infrastructure and where that's moving,
that's undergoing a lot of changes, particularly as we think about the whole transition to the cloud, right,
and I think one of the things for you to think about or have in context is when we think about the cloud,
we really, we don't think about kind of public cloud or private cloud or something, we think about cloud as a model, right.
And that's a big transition that we're going through just in terms of how do you deliver applications
and services in a more agile way and we haven't got it perfect yet, right, but we're working through that
transition as we think about where we go and how we help customers embrace that cloud model on whatever term
that they have. And Windows Server plays a key role of that because it fulfills the on-premises sort of
promise to customers of being able to stand up a cloud model and stand up their infrastructure on their terms.
And so, Windows Server is kind of part of the whole cloud ecosystem we would say either running it on-premises
in a data center running it, in some service provider, or Windows Server is actually the underpinnings of
what the Azure cloud runs on top of, and so a lot of the work that you'll see with us in Windows Server 2016
that's coming out is focused very much on that cloud model and how are we the cloud-ready operating system.
What are we doing in terms of taking the learnings that we have from Azure and running kind of this public
cloud at very large hyper scale and then bringing that down and delivering it to customers to provide the
Fabric of the infrastructure within their environment. So huge investments we've made in the whole software
define space, so software define networking, really kind of providing that infrastructure
that allows you to have the portability of your applications and be able to move them right between different
clouds, between on-prem, between the public cloud, work that we're doing in the software define storage
space to really let you kind of get the power of software and the high resiliency that you've had and historically
through hardware, but delivered through software to lay as the foundation and then all the investments that
we're making kind of in the Hyper-V layer and the compute layer that go along with that.
One of the big things that I'll just kind of put because I think it's important in the context of this community
is a lot of the work that we're doing around assurance, right, and we know the world has changed from a
security point of view in just in terms of how people think about their operating environment and wanting
that assurance that what they're running in the Fabric and the infrastructure is secure.
We've done a lot of work in 2016 introducing a new set of functionality around shielded VMs and this ability
to really kind of encrypt using BitLocker your virtual machines that are running on top of the Fabric and
then have that, the Fabric tested in a way so that you can guarantee that the Fabric is the Fabric you want
it to be and that the VM won't boot. And a lot of these things where
we're thinking about, okay these things you maybe don't need to worry about when you're in a public cloud
environment, right, because you trust the provider or what not, but when you are wanting to stand up your own
infrastructure, they become super important for you to have. So we play a huge role in Windows Server just
around that infrastructure and how we're taking that forward and how we're helping organizations in a
modernized the underlying infrastructure that they have. The other part that's kind of super relevant to
this audience is the role that we play as an application platform, right.
Really you have an infrastructure. Why do you have an infrastructure?
It's to run virtual machines and the new world containers. Why do you have those?
It's to run applications.
And we really see that whole space is changing pretty dramatically, right.
If you went back and thought about how applications go from conception through to the deployment in an
environment 10 years ago, we're in a very, very different world right now.
That's why you're seeing kind of a lot of work that we're doing, particularly around PowerShell,
Desired State Configuration, but also then the ecosystem around that of Nano and the new installer work that
we're doing and contributing to the testing environment through things like Pester and all of those things as
being super important to our strategy and we're trying to figure out how we modernize that as well and how do
we take a lot of the agile concepts and things that we're seeing more
in the OSS world and kind of Linux world and community of how people put together applications and how they
go and kind of get the packages they need, put them together, integrate them, have configuration as code,
do that in a kind of heterogeneous world and put that plumbing and that basis into what we provide from a
platform point of view for Windows Server. So 2016, there's a ton of stuff in it.
It is I would say the start of this pivot towards this more cloud model and how we're thinking about
taking it into and landing that transformation in organizations all the way from the infrastructure up to the
development space and we see PowerShell as being kind of in some sense a bit of the glue between those two worlds, right.
It has a lot of and when we initially developed PowerShell,
there was a lot of emphasis around it being a language and it having a lot of these properties that were really
important from a development space and if you have a development background, those things being things that
you come to expect and come to need in a scripting environment, etc.
But it also, we've done it and put a lot of our IT hat on it as we implemented it to make sure it was kind of
user friendly and it mapped into what you need to do from an IT infrastructure point of view.
And so we really do think it's positioned as being the glue between these two worlds and a lot of the
investments that you've probably had Kenneth and Angel talk about today are part of us thinking about how do
we evolve it and take it forward and have it be a showcase in our arsenal of tools in this new model, in this new
world as we think about really helping people embrace the cloud.
Again, whether or not that be public, whether or not that be on-premise or through a
partner or trusted service provider. So hopefully that gives you a little bit of
context to kind of where we are in server, where we're going. It's a release that we're incredibly proud of
just in terms of the amount of innovation that I think that we're bringing to bear.
And so if you haven't checked it out, I would encourage you not only to check out the PowerShell and the kind
of WMF aspects of it, but also a bunch of the core investments that are going in the platform underneath both
from an IT infra-sight point of view, but also then as the next generation application platform when that's
really starting to be designed or optimized for more of that cloud first world.
So with that, I think I'll stop and yeah.
Awesome. We're looking forward to it. Nano's going to be a great one in Windows Server.
Nano, well I just want to say Nano and containers, right,
are pretty big in terms of the transformation that we're making.
I mean just seem odd where we talk about Nano and the impact it's going to have just for the size, for an automation,
for a performance, so definitely the role that PowerShell is going to play there like Erin says it's going to be significant.
We're going to need the help of our community to actually start taking some of the assisting cmdlets and
investments that we manuscript and you bring those down through Nano because we start thinking about
heterogeneous type of environments, but in management and
automation, if we want PowerShell to assist in investments that you have to be reused when managing Nano as well.
And simultaneously when the server, as we just talked about before, spans this broad spectrum of customers,
and so we're actually able to land you for those who are going a little slower than necessarily the Nano adoption,
so we really think 2016 is sort of began to both show the future and handle the past and kind of bring them a
little more together in a more cohesive way.
And so the last thing I can say is probably in a little bit of a request and an invitation, I would say,
and that is we're going through a transition. I think if you, it's an exciting time to be at Microsoft right now.
I've been there for almost 18 years and it's just the climate internally and just the
willingness for people to take a look at how we've done things in the past and really to go oh does that
really work, is that really what the world needs, is that really how we should interface externally, is just amazing.
And so, we are going through this transition. I think we don't have it all figured out, but I think we have
a pretty good idea based upon input from folks like yourself about what's needed and what the problem space is
and what could help and we're trying to do our best to kind of match, I would say, that input that we have with
what we put out. And so, it would be first kind of a request to have a little patience, right.
We're going through this journey and this transformation together and we're going to get hopefully more right
than wrong, but the good news is that we are increasing our frequency of getting things out there, and so we
can adjust as we go along. But we won't get it right unless we have the partnership with folks like you that
are in this room, and so please take advantage of the various different community organizations,
the UserVoice site that we have, all of those pieces, in order to really channel your feedback in because I
will tell you if anything this is one of the teams that I think it takes that input more to heart than other
parts of the organization that have been less, more isolated in the past and like
it's a little bit more of a heavy lift for me to get the folks that are working on kind of core protocol level
stuff that they don't really have a community to interface with to go accept some piece of user input.
I think the PowerShell team has a reputation of listening to those things and have the kind of request that
we're not going to get it all right, but keep it coming because I think that only benefits both of us in the long run.
So thank you.
Thank you very much.