Alright. Enough of the distant past. Moving to the past year.
So what an amazing year. I mean we made a lot of changes in PowerShell.
And really the PowerShell ecosystem and the technologies, I mean we, one of the things that probably you are
obviously very familiar as the work that we do in Windows and Windows Server and you know it started only
last year, there was a number of technical previews that we have released.
It's through those technical previews we have released as well multiple WMF previews and it was an extraordinary
journey for us because we learned tons and we're going to talk a little bit more about that.
But actually we want to highlight that while we're still releasing WMF to each of you in a frequently basis,
we've also been releasing management technologies in Windows and Windows Server.
And in a couple of weeks, we're going to be launching the technical preview 5 Windows Server 2016.
You're going to see some additional innovation that we are planning to release for both PowerShell and DSC.
And talking about WMF 5,
I can't resist, how's that for a download list. That's probably the fastest adoption I've ever seen of
Windows Management Framework, and in fact, it's going, we don't actually have the next week there.
We actually just finished week six and it keeps accelerating. So certainly, we've got people interested.
They're landing it and just to point to the final PS resistance,
that's what's in it. That's a carefully curated list and we expect there will be a test on it somewhere at
the end of the summit to make sure we've covered all possible capabilities.
You know, there's a lot there. There's a lot to tell people about.
There's a lot to speak to.
And you know the area that I think that, well recently, about a month ago we released the PowerShell gallery.
How many of you are using the PowerShell
gallery today? I mean, wow. This is pretty awesome. We had this vision back about a year ago about creating
a repository, public repository for all of our community to come to basically share and make available resources
to help us just adopting some of the new features of PowerShell and one of things that we learned when we did
the launch, I mean look at the downloads per month. It's quite remarkable.
I mean, right now is one of the faster galleries that we have in Microsoft.
I think of the number right now. How many downloads we have so far?
About 1.3 million.
One point three million downloads of PowerShell artifacts I have already have occurred in the gallery.
Now as we talk through that a little bit, there is something worth noting, so the caveat, and that's that
although there's, I think this month we had almost 450,000 downloads, so it continues to accelerate rapidly.
Some of those do come from the Azure RM profile, and so there's kind of, right, about 150,000 over the last 6 weeks.
On the other hand, 150, the 450, probably 500,000, 600,000 in the past 6 weeks minus 150,000 is still a hell
of a lot of downloads. So absolutely amazing ramp up, in spite of the actual sort of thing.
We'll work with Azure to make sure the numbers get a little crisper, but it's been a phenomenal adoption.
One thing that you heard probably earlier today from Neema, the product manager who presented the Nano coverage,
is that the effort that we have made in PowerShell to also read faster PowerShell for the full CLR dependency
to a core CLR dependency. This was something that was really important and in order to bring together a lighter,
a smaller version of the OS. You make a high performance. When you're looking at the numbers, they aren't showing
in that graph. They intend to actually show you kind of the impact that we have.
In delivering the PowerShell, there's going to lean, it's going to be faster, and it's going to actually start
moving towards to a more CoreCLR dependency in the future. I think this is really important as we start
building the new server in Nano, so here that's something to highlight.
Open source. We have been moving about as fast as we can within the resource constraints we have and the
business constraints we have to go to open source. That journey just started and already we've actually got
a ton of opportunity, certainly the gallery is certainly one thing.
At that gallery, it's where we sometimes forget that we just launched this gallery in like April, May.
It was just like almost a year ago, 2015. It's not very old. We're certainly out of the preview mode and
people are using it in production all the time, so it's a great thing.
We've also got the Script Analyzer, a bunch of editor services, the Visual Studio Code, and of course,
the OpenSSH, which we're looking forward to.
To making available. We'll talk a little bit more in the future about that.
We want to thank each of you because I know that many of you in this room, the other people who are going to
be watching this, they really have helped the team, engineering team, in particular, about just start
evolving ourselves into this open source culture.
So an interesting story is even before, we had just finished putting the gallery up and we hadn't yet made it public.
We hadn't told anybody. We had just put it up there, no it wasn't in preview, it was just they didn't tell
anybody it was up there and we were going to announce it the next day, and within hours, we got 600 lines of
submission of poll request that actually go would you please take these in.
How the hell did they find it and now they decide they're going to just?
This guy must have been waiting for this. Oh my gosh. Oh, they did it and just landed on it.
Within a few minutes after that, we got back to him and said oh could you make this tweak to your code and
then we'll take it and he did minutes later. So just a great, it's been a great experience.
Thank you very much for your overall support of that effort and of all of our efforts.
We cannot do it without you.
And especially we want to thank some people for their contributions because we've got some names here of
people who really had an impact in our community on and delivering value into our open source projects.
We have Iain Brighton and our thanks for the Hyper-VM, the DNS, ActiveDirectory, and DHCPServer,
some great effort and work there. We really appreciate him. Aleksandar Nikolic for all the documentation.
Boy, open documentation. Thank you. Very useful and helpful. Everybody cares about that.
Keith Hill. I know I've got a Keith Hill here. Don't I have a Keith Hill?
He's been around? No. Did I see him? I didn't see him. Alright, I know what I don't know.
Apparently, he's not here. Clint Branham. We have a Clint. And Daniel Scott-Raynsford.
These guys have really done a great job and we just want to say thank you publicly here, and of course,
we'll say thank you to them also in person for their great effort.
And this will continue. Every while we'll say thanks to a few key contributors across our community who have
really helped us move forward.
And I think, are we giving something away for the contributors? We are, yeah.
Well these people in this particular case, Michael Green, if they are here, they can just see him.
Michael Green has for them $15,000 worth of Azure money useful for one month.
So one free month, that's a subscription to Azure.
So basically, one month unlimited almost.
Almost, depend on the usage. A lot.
Depending on what you use.
That's a lot.
So it's a substantial amount. We really do want to say thanks. Our appreciation, not just to them, but to every
single one of you who have contributed over time. If we could do it, we'd give it to everybody who
contributed any code.
Absolutely.
Well we thank you. We really appreciate it. One more hand for these guys who contributed,
even though they're not there.
Thank you.
Our thanks. Oh, the home page.
The home page.
We released the home page last year.
Yeah, last year again. Last year a side project out of Joey, Neema, and a few others.
They've done a great job. Okay, how many people have actually been to the PowerShell home page?
Wahoo! Not that many. It's worth going to. It's not that hard to find.
It's microsoft.com/powershell, so you can find it pretty easily.
It is where we'll probably start driving a little more traffic. Even right now, of course, we have I
know 60,000 I guess home page visits here in this past month or so, which is not huge for our traffic,
but it's a substantial. The key is we'll start probably putting more announcements actually on the home page
and then blogging almost directly referring to that. So as we'll start doing stuff, it'll start coming up,
we'll start doing the advertisements, we'll start talking about maybe PowerShell around the world as we
started doing any celebration stuff for the 10-year exact date anniversary, we probably will put it up there
first and then we'll blog about it and that will enable us to actually to shift our blog a little bit,
and I'll talk about it a little later, to a little more chatty, a little less formal tone, a little more the
formal stuff up on the home page, but it's well worth your perusal and occasional look at.
And if there's things that you think ought to be there that are not, feel free to tell us and I think it's
even worth a UserVoice. Feel free to actually put it on UserVoice if you want to.
It's just a way to actually communicate with us.
And then we're just going to I'm just going to go very quick about other things that we delivered last year,
well, actually even within the last few months. Right, you know one of the things that we've been doing,
it started with Lee Holmes with JEA. How many of you are using JEA today in your enterprises?
The few, the brave.
I highly encourage to really look in JEA as a vehicle to really think about security and protection in your environment.
Definitely one thing too that we are doing is the editing piece and as well as some encrypting MOFs.
I think that this is something that is becoming more and more important.
One of the things that we are learning with security is that PowerShell is becoming quite popular and you'll
probably start seeing in the news, actually today there was a new article about DSC,
in Hacker News,
yeah in Hacker News and we're going to start seeing more and more of this.
It's fantastic that we see the popularity and the send time, this creates obviously a challenge for all of us
about how we start protecting PowerShell in investments and implementation in the enterprise.
So this is just in a starting point of what we're going to be doing in the future and you're going to start
seeing a lot more and more security focus, but here's to highlight some of the things that we have released so far.
Now there's a thing coming in the next 5.1 update.
Yeah. There's this concept about assume breach that we are focusing as well, so we'll talk a little bit more about later.
And the PowerShell support and DSC integration for the OMS automation.
I think that was, I don't know, how many of you know about Azure automation?
Okay. So one of the things that, thank you, one of the things that we learned with Azure automation is that
when we introduced the integration of native PowerShell and DSC, we saw an incredible adoption and I think it
like about 25% of people in Azure automation today they are using some shape or form of DSC and I think that
this is an important thing to highlight because one of the things that we are learning now with PowerShell is
that we want to start integrating more and more into the cloud. It's starting to provide more of an extra
service for our customers and the community. DSC Linux.
It's been great because they finally put it out on the, I think, the open source code actually got it in
December 2015, so we're sort of starting down there. This is another good path for us.
We are going to slowly, but surely as we know try to give PowerShell technologies so you can use them where
you need to. Overall, and I think DSC on Linux is the first kind of effort, sort of get our feet wet,
and sort of understand what that process looks like, so we're really excited about that effort and hope it moves forward.
I think over time trying to consolidate. Right now, they're two separate code bases.
I think we're going to bring the code bases together and that is the plan.
And over time want to bring them together so the Windows and the Linux code base would perhaps be the same.
That'll take us a little bit of time to do that though and some shifts, just work with us.
One of the advantages of doing stuff open is everybody sort of gets to see it and use it early.
One of the disadvantages is everybody gets to see it and use it early and stuff changes a little bit,
and so we're going to try to be a little more directional, I think, in our communication, in our guide and
say look here's how we're, we'll be a little more open about here's where we're going with this,
here's what we're doing on this source project, and work through both the RFC process. and we'll cover that a
little more later, but just get your heads up. This is one of the great things.
One of the other things we sort of skipped by is the Azure Extension Handler.
We've had some pretty good traction with that right now with here right now where, of course,
you can automatically do DSC, get stuff uploaded, downloaded, create your Azure VMs a lot more easily than
you could before.
Yeah, I think we are planning to continue updating the Azure Extension Handler with additional modules as
well with this configuration and yeah. And so that's something that is going to be a continued this point moving forward.
And then finally, the DSC integration with Chef, in particular, but as well as with Ansible.
You know actually we should really thank Steve because Steve has done a lot of work to really take the power
of DSC as a platform and really start to integrate it with Chef and I figured that was an amazing collaboration,
so thank you for doing that.
That's great.
I'm expecting a t-shirt by the way. Looking forward for the t-shirt.
And we also worked with others, so we can't only love him.
No. When you build a platform, we have an awful lot of people.
You can have preference, but at the end of the day, we are building a platform and I think that this is
something that I think you're going to start seeing a lot more continuity is how we start basically
integrating the platform with other open source projects. This is something that we're going to be doing
more and more.
And we appreciate anybody who layers tools over the platform that we have, we'll have to do some,
but God bless the ISEs and tooling.
Yes.