So with the great things in the past, I'm really happy about what the team has accomplished, what all of you help
to accomplish and it's that we learn a number of things and we want to share some of those learnings because
I know that some of the things that we're going to talk about today are things that you are aware and we are
aware as well and I want to address it, we want to address it from both angles for an engineer and as well as
for product management because when you're thinking about, for example, agility, I've got to say something
that we learn in Microsoft, when you try to ship in Windows and be agile, we learned that there are some
interesting challenges because engineering processes, cadence tooling, we are evolving in the company.
Yeah, sorry about that. So I'm going to give you a good example what happened in WMF 5.0 RTM and I know this
was painful for some of you. What happened is that frankly we had a bug, we recalled the bug back in December.
The amount of time it took us from taking that bug fix, we release a WMF 5.0, it was roughly like about two
and a half months, almost three months.
It was too long.
It was frankly a---you can ask tons of questions like you see if I was in your place, I would be asking like
wow what kind of bug is this. This is like so dramatic that it's taking the team so long or they didn't know the
uses of it, are there more quality problems, right? In the instance, frankly is that yeah, we had a bug,
part of our agility, we missed this bug, but it was that reaction.
The amount of time that it took us to react, it was primarily driven that when you got a bill, a Windows package,
it just takes a lot of time. We've got to go through a number of days and processes that really doesn't tie
well with the Windows shipping vehicle. So moving forward, we're going to change that.
We'll talk a little bit more about that.
We're working on that and we're working with the Windows team as well.
People have this in focus. It's just a whole corporate effort.
Yeah, absolutely.
And our efforts as well. We're addressing it at each layer as we can, I think is the right answer.
So thank you for support
and apologize because I know this some of you took a dependency in the December release and definitely I know
that counts and it needs to and is something we're addressing, and we'll talk a little bit more on cloud.
It was a year ago Kenneth and I we were here talking about this transformation in the company culture, right.
The transformation is that when Satya took over the company as the CEO, it was very clear that we needed
to adjust, not adjust the way how we worked, but actually in the way how our engineering roles they were evolving.
So if you recall, the engineering role evolved in Microsoft where the developer and the tester became one
single role called software engineer. So we still, we've been evolving this.
They have a significant impact on all of us because when you think about Microsoft, we've been operating
under that moral for 35 years. In one day, we decide well we're just going to change all that.
Well a key example goes back into the open source stuff because like a few years ago, if I considered any of
those projects, I would have been escorted not so graciously out of the building, right.
SQL and Linux?
And so now it's a very different culture. It's a very different top/down mindset and there's
still a lot of how do I do my day job, exactly what am I responsible for that we still have to work through
and make sure we land the process, and occasionally, we're going to make just a few errors on our way,
so bear with us, we're on a, I think, great path, but we're not quite done yet.
I think we are definitely closer than ever before.
Amen. That's exactly right. Okay, we're sustained there.
As a part of that, we're actually going to continue to evolve how we're handling communications, right.
So let's talk about a few things going through there. One is even just during the re-release, we felt we
were pretty aggressive on the communication for the WMF recall. As we started the re-release over that period,
we kind of went a little quiet. It was like okay, we think we're going to have it the end of January and
then it was like oh, okay new problem, okay, into February, and I was a little frustrated from our standpoint.
I'm sure it was from your standpoint. And we're sort of working through exactly how when we have nothing to
say, we say something, so the people know we haven't forgotten you, but I've got nothing more I can tell you
and how do we do that? There's some pros and cons to doing that every minute versus every week versus every
month and sometimes as you go through that as we work this journey, there's times where as we communicate
more frequently, we will have a tendency to get it a little wrong because we even have been a place in that
case where I would have said four days before an event, hey it's going to be this date and then like three
days later, oh no, it's not. And so, we're struggling with ourselves and we'll work through that with the
community, sort of get a sense as to how we communicate these events.
So just to be clear, A, we definitely want you to know everything you need to know to get your jobs done and
to make you comfortable, and B, we're working pretty accurately through that process and how we can address
our needs and your needs simultaneously. We do ask for your continued support and a little patience as we
sort of fight through that. In general, we'll probably opt to communicate a little more than what we have in
the past, but just be aware that there's always trade-offs here.
Just as an observation, we continue to move still fairly quickly through the preview and the various models
and I would say finally we're beginning
to get it, and on the other hand, we just started the home page based on people's lack of how to where do I go
to get a canonical sense of what PowerShell's really doing. I get all these different blogs and so forth.
We started the home page for that. We started the gallery. We started all these projects up and I would say
that over the next five to six months we're going to be sort of more operationalizing some of the
communication efforts that we have around them. How do we do this?
One thing we've thought about doing we'll see how it flies, but it's certainly on the fun idea list is maybe
we'll end up doing it every other month little top of mind where I'll sit down and maybe Angel will join me
and we'll do a looking back last month, looking forward the next month, and here's some key technology things
that we're thinking about and then maybe once in a while, we'll also do maybe sort of more of a Q and A,
a broader Q and A with the whole community. We just finished a couple hours this morning with a group on DSC.
That was a useful, it turned out not to be DSC, a bunch of things, but that kind of thing is on our mind.
I don't know why or where we'll land on them, but we certainly want to make sure that we involve and integrate
more and more. Let me, I'm going to spend just a little more time, I know I should probably talk about all the
stuff we're going to do, but since I'm here, I guess I'll end it here and then we'll come back to it.
Innately, the community is immensely hugely larger than the PowerShell team.
Right. There are just more people out there, which is good because that's how we make money, right.
If we didn't, then Windows might be bad. With that many downloads, you know people are using, 1.3 million,
even if some are Azure, people are using the technology they've got in production.
There's going to be a ton of questions. I have always been astonished that for the past 10 years when we do
a new PowerShell session and even the getting started sessions that Don or Jeffrey occasionally do are packed
with 1,000 people. After 10 to 15 years, alright 13 years of talking about PowerShell at the various
Microsoft events, we still have hundreds and hundreds of people who have never touched it yet.
That's going to continue. What that means is we got a lot of people not only in the community now, but a ton
coming in and then we have the audacity to create new technologies like DSC, which for people who are already
here create a whole new set of questions and issues and things, so we rely on the community.
We rely on the community to help the community. I know we can't scale to do that.
What we can scale to do is to engage and understand when there are firestorms and engage in the firestorm,
try to prevent it with some documentation and we can educate the educators.
We can talk to you guys. Does that make sense? There is this layer between us where we just have to actually
use you and other people like you. When we started the first PowerShell summit, I spent a little while on this,
but when we started the first PowerShell summit it was because in fact we were at a Microsoft conference,
TechEd Europe, I think it was Berlin, and Jeffrey and I had just finished a, we'd had again a massive intro
session and then we'd had an ask the experts kind of a thing and we filled it and we filled it again the
second day we actually had to turn people away and we just said okay where can we go to give people really
in-depth knowledge of PowerShell. And we said, we've got to have our own little conference, don't we?
And then we said, that was one breath, the second breath is and we can't do it.
Because if we do it, Microsoft has an attention span of a nat. It's like oh, a new thing.
And so, we said the community has got to be able to come together and do that and that's when we worked with
Don and others to try to pull together the very first PowerShell summit in Red Rock Las Vegas four or five
years ago
and the intent there was we'll talk to you guys and we'll get you guys to help us improve our product because
you have higher access and they have a high bandwidth conference for you guys to make sure you connect with us later.
So I'm sorry for that long soliloquy. I just want you to get a sense of that's how I think of it, that's why we
spend so much time on these things. We really want to get educated by you and to make sure that you guys
have the right message. So if there's problems you're having in the community, if you're answering questions,
unable to do them, answer them, answer them, answer them, when you hit a brick wall, reach out to us directly.
Go ahead and reach out to the Powershell PM team at microsoft.com, go ahead and reach out directly on UserVoice.
Do that kind of thing which will inform us that you need help communicating with other people because we
don't always know. We can't always know.
I think I just want to highlight one point. I think that, look, we are moving a lot faster than ever before
and I know that we caused some pain last year with the WMF previews, right.
We were releasing these previews and it sounds really good, but in reality, we are not keeping track and
communicating how those previews they were affecting each of you with the changes that we were making in the technology.
So we need some times the help of the community because as we start having these communication channels,
if we start basically train the trainer I think at this point, which who is you, we need to be able to depend
on our community as well to help us through Twitter, through Facebook, through all the different channels
where we start seeing a lot of momentum about communicating about PowerShell issues or PowerShell feedback,
so it's really, really important.
Absolutely.
And just to be clear, along with the general community engagement, which we'll up a bit, we'll go through
that in the next slide. We do have actually in the past year, we've had hundreds, hundreds and hundreds of
in fact, direct customer engagement with some specific cases. If there are people you think that have a
particularly interesting set of use cases for PowerShell or PowerShell DSC, reach out to me,
my team KenHansen@powershell.com or my team and actually just talk to one of my guys or Ron Hill and we'll
put them on the list of people that we will potentially go and just chat with and drill a little bit into their scenario.
We can only spend, obviously, we only have so much effort, but it's an important list to us.
We're always happy to add to it and it's been I would say increasing by probably a fact of 20 over the past
year from what it was before, so it's not just a casual invitation.
It is intended to be used just use it wisely, pick good people, and we'll make sure we engage them a bit more deeply.