Good morning.
We're going to do a second session on DSC in a vSphere environment.
I'm not sure if some of you saw the session on Monday where I gave the high level view on what we're doing
with converting,
configuring your vSphere environment to a DSC-based configuration-based environment.
First of all, this slide we can't show it enough. These guys did tremendous work in the last couple of 10 years
and more even. Without them, this thing wouldn't be happening and what I'm going to talk about wouldn't be
happening, so thank you to all of those on the list. Much appreciated.
What are we going to talk about, while the one on Monday was kind of high-level overview where we looked at
the concepts that I'm trying to following to convert your vSphere configuration to a DSC-based one, I'm now going
to dive into some code. So for those of you who don't want to see a lot of lines of codes, you still have
time to leave if you want or get an extra coffee. I don't know what you prefer, but there will be some code
involved this time.
I will show you one of the things I'm looking at and developing. It's in a far, it's in a stage that it's
usable, but it's open for a lot of expansions as we will show later on.
We'll handle some points more in detail like we mentioned on Monday.
In your vSphere hierarchy, there is a tree structure with all kinds of different nodes in there.
You have folders, data centers, clusters, and so on, so determining where your new resource will be created
or defined is quite important that's why the location, location, location thing is in there.
So we need to make sure that we position ourselves on the right note and that inventory tree the moment we
try to create a new resource. There's a small example of reusing code like we always do.
I do at least.
I think it was during the last VM World that we made this famous claim, don't write the code, just steal it
if it's already out there. There's a lot of valuable blogs out there, tons of code, so don't reinvent the wheel.
But one thing you should keep in mind, if you copy something from the internet or even your best friend, test it.
Don't run it like that in production. We never do that, of course, but just as a warning on the side make
sure that you test what you copy from others.
And automation, as it should be case with everything we do in PowerShell is
our ultimate goal. Who am I? Okay, I'll keep this short since I already had in a previous one.
I'm Luc Dekens. I do a bit of talking at VM World in the last years.
We have a book. Second edition just came out. I will plug my book only once in contrast to some other people, right.
And if you want to reach me, there's a Twitter handle that you can use to contact me and there's a mail link
on my blog if you need more detailed questions than 140 characters in a question.
Okay, a quick overview for those who didn't attend a session or already forgot.
It has been two days of brain melt, at least it has been for me.
DSC is a very valuable resource array of configuring your environment.
Now unfortunately at the moment, VMware themselves, they don't provide any resources for that, but since we
have the option, we had the option in the past and we still have it to script DSC resources.
Now with WMF5, we have the option to do those class-based resources with even better, more optimal.
I'm trying to start something going where we have resources defined for your complete vSphere environment.
So like I showed last Monday, we already have quite a few, but it's still a lot need to be done,
especially in the finer details of the configurations. Another thing, an important thing, that we want to
obtain with the converting to DSC is that we want this famous separation of where and what.
I just made a small two screenshots at the bottom there. So if you look at that one, the right one, is the one
where we will actually do something. That is your actual folder name that you're going to create and the location
where you want to create that folder name. This is the part that you want to put under source control.
This is where the changes will be visible where you can make the drift with the previous situation.
On the left, that's the what you will be doing. That's only a small extract.
That is the one that creates a folder and it uses the data that we specified in the right side text that you
see there, which is part of your configuration file. So this is the important concepts in what we are trying
to do with DSC for a vSphere.