Now this script is producing the files that I showed previously. There are some extensions that I want to
create on this script. I'm not there yet. I'm working on it, but they will be coming.
There's first of all the integration that get, there is a very good module or announced at least that allows you
to automatically once you have that configuration file, you will start it automatically, so automate will be
our primary goal. You will automatically start it in your get environment.
And then were some of you in the previous session with Steve Marowski and Michael Green I think on this release pipeline.
In fact, this plugs it into what these guys were saying. This is the integration that we ultimately
want in our automation of our environment. We want not only the creator's configuration files,
that's only part of the story. We want to recreate, for example,
you create a new distributed switch, okay, we can generate the configuration file, but I would also like with
this script since we're handling the object, recreate or create the Pester code to test that switch if it's
function is as it should. We have all the information available.
We know the name of the thing, we know the configuration settings, we know where it's located, so with this
ultimate goal of automate everything, this would be a nice integration that I'm looking at.
Same goes for PSake, I want what they announced these composite resources.
It's typical in a vSphere environment we could use this very well.
I think I used the example of a cluster. You have a default cluster in just one click, but then again if you
look at the components in a cluster, for example, there's high availability, you have the source scheduling,
you have DPM. Those require additional parameters, so you could use those as SUP resources under your cluster
and your complete cluster could become one composite DSC resource in that case.
So instead of generating all these individual DSC resources configuration files, the ideal world, we should be
able to create a composite resource and just plug in the values that we need for that specific instance that
we are trying to move under DSC control. There's one shortcoming in the script at the moment and I mentioned
the blue and the yellow folders, but you notice as well in the beginning already that there are other types
of folders, the hidden ones, remember, there's network and data storage.
Those need special taking care of because their paths are a bit different.
In fact, they need to make sure that they are created under those hidden folders.
If you create a folder where you want to store, for example, all your datastore clusters, that folder should
be created under the hidden datastore folder, not under the VM or host folder, so I need a bit more expansion
on that one in the script.
Another thing that is quite useful and this is one of the beauties of PowerShell, you can have access to
everything in your environment. In this case, I created, I'm working with this class-based resource VMW folder.
You could look at that resource folder, resource class, list the properties and check for completeness.
So somebody in your team adds a property to the class, you could use this to check if the configuration files
that you are recreating are complete, are containing all the properties that should be there.
I know not all of them are required, but still it would be useful to have all of them in there.
So this is another part I'm looking at, use what is available or what is returned by the Get-DSC resource to
make it more complete what you generate in your configuration file.
And then of course, you noticed my text that I generated was all left-aligned.
We need a bit more alignment. It makes it more readable, but that I consider one of the minor issues that I
need to solve in the ultimate script.
Are there any questions on this? I know it's a lot of code. It's 10:00 in the morning.
You have more sessions to come. You have a question?
(Audience comment)
Yeah, this is something in fact that I discussed in the first session, but I can pull up the slide so you can
have a look. If you give me a minute, I'll switch to that one. I think I still have it here.
(Audience comment)
No, no problem. That's just a minute.
What we discussed in that, this is just a view on the lab I'm using to test this environment, but it gives
you a good idea of the set up that I'm propagating here. Bottom right, this blue box is your vSphere environment,
classical thing, VSCA vCenter hypervisors. Top left is your standard Windows domain, domain control and pull server.
I need a work station to edit some stuff, so I have two of them because I want to test them on 8 and 10 at
the same time, but that's just a practical thing. And the key thing in there is this vEngine that you see on the left.
So on that vEngine, that is if because we can't install LCM agents, VCSA is an appliance.
VMware doesn't like you to put stuff in there. ESXi is a closed hypervisor.
They don't want you to put stuff in there, so what we're doing is we are installing the LCM agent on that vEngine
and it's on the vEngine that we run the configuration files. On that machine, you need PowerShell and
PowerCLI on top of it. That's the one that will actually do the changes in your vSphere environment on the right.
So yes, you need PowerCLI on that vEngine. But in the end, you don't need to touch your vSphere environment at all.
You just need this helper server. Does that answer your---?
Yeah.
Okay, thank you.