Now I mentioned it earlier, the vSphere Inventory tree is quite complex and this is partially because
historically it grew like that and they added new types of resources that they had to fit somewhere in their inventory tree.
What I did here and most of you ever use the vSphere classical client, they will know this view.
There are four types at the moment that you can look at. Top left, you have the one where you have the view,
what VMware calls the host cluster view. So there you see what they also call their yellow folders.
You see the data center's clusters and your hypervisors in there.
Top right you see the VM template view. That's the one where you will actually be able to set your VMs in
specific folders and on these folders you can then apply permissions which will allow you to delegate certain
parts of your environment to specific groups of users. What is newer and that appears later on, at the bottom
left, you have the one for data storage. They have introduced the concept of data store cluster some time ago.
That is the hierarchy that you find under there. And then the last one, the fourth one, is where your
network configuration is stored in the hierarchy. Again, we have two types of network objects.
Basically, you have the standard classical switch is the VSS as they call them and you have to distribute the
switches, which is VDS. In these screenshots, what you see the yellow and the blue folders are the ones that
you actually define. If you create for example, in the bottom right, if you create or distribute a switch VDS1,
it will create a number of port groups by default. Uplinks, for example, will always be there.
And then, as you add additional port groups through that specific switch, they will start appearing under this
node in the hierarchy tree, so just to make it clear that there are different ways of viewing objects in your vSphere environment.
So the path is quite important. Now if you want to make an inventory.
So the ultimate goal that we want to achieve is we want to have an inventory of our existing vSphere environment.
We're not going to start from scratch. Once these DSC resources are available, we all or most of us have a
running vSphere environment, which we want to be able to convert to DSC configuration.
So what is important is that we get a complete inventory of the environment to start creating your configuration files.
So the obvious one, if you look at the cmdlets that are available in PowerCLI, for those of you who don't
know what PowerCLI, PowerCLI is an at all. It used to be PS snap-in.
Now it's converting to a module. There are a few PS Snap-ins left.
What allows you to configure and manage your vSphere environment, so it's on top of your PowerShell tool.
Now the obvious one would be there is a cmdlet Get-Inventory. When you run this, we see a lot.
This comes from a test environment, which I kept obviously very small to make it manageable in one
screenshot, in fact. What we see here, we see most of our elements, components of our vSphere environment
coming back, but we are missing some. Remember we had screenshots of distributed switches, of datastore
clusters, these are not in there unfortunately. So I did a count so we can compare it with something that I
will do later. We have 22 objects returned from your vSphere environment, but it's not complete obviously.
So
what do we do? And this is a guideline that I give all of the people.
If the cmdlets don't do what you want to do, you have to go through the API.
Now luckily,
PowerCLI from day one first of all the cmdlet Get-Few in this case to easily tap into all the API
methods and properties. So if you're missing something or you want the very specific configuration that is
not provided by your standard cmdlet, go through the API.
The API is not the most obvious environment to code in. There's the API reference, there's an extract screenshot
at the top right here and setting up or making goals through those APIs or obtaining those properties in there
is not always too obvious. Now in this case, we're lucky. There is a basic concept, a managed object,
which they use internally to retrieve inventories from a vSphere environment and that's what we are doing here.
First of all, everything in vSphere and vSphere API starts from your service instance.
This is so to say your base object from where everything else is starting.
You even find, and that's what we will be using later on, you even find your root folder of your complete vSphere environment.
One thing that is quite interesting with the service instance, you can use this against the vCenter.
VCenter is the management layer on top of all your hypervisors, or you can use this exactly same API directly
against your hypervisor, the ESXi node, in this case. So you use the same scripts to inventorize all of vCenter
or an individual hypervisor if you want to configure an individual one.
Now what we did here, there is like I said one method.
We just called CreateContainerView. We used that one to get us a more complete listing of what is in your vSphere environment.
Very straightforward. I'm not going to go in too much details. It requires a number of parameters where
you start, in this case, we use, like I said, the root folder, which is also available in that service instance.
You can specify what kind of types you want to return and types that will be things like data center, cluster,
and virtual machines. And this also explains why with our cmdlet Get-Inventory, we don't get everything
because they only retrieve, because it was written in the early days, they only retrieve the things that we saw,
folders, virtual machines, clusters, host, and so on, but they skipped datastore clusters and network objects
like virtual distributed switches.
So what I'm doing in this goal, I'm just passing it null. I'm not passing any types.
And then by default, it will give you all of the types that are available.
And the last, the recursive on this is an obvious parameter. In this case, you just want to run through the complete tree.
It's as simple as that. If we run this,
we get this kind of inventory. So most of the stuff that we saw in the Get-Inventory cmdlet, we will see back,
but we now have a complete view. Remember it was 22 in the previous 1 with the cmdlet, now we have what is
it 28 of those, and we also see stuff appearing in there like dvs, dvportgroups, datastore clusters, and so on.
So we have now a complete view of our vSphere environment, but there's too much in there.
There are things in there that are normally hidden and that you don't see in the GUI or the WebClient interfaces.