Okay. What we want to do and I explained that in the beginning, location, location is very important.
If we create a new object or want to create or configure a new object with DSC, we have to be able to exactly
tell them in which node we want to create that object.
So this is a funny location picture, but it stresses the fact that location can be quite important in some cases.
What I'm doing here, we're coding or trying to code in this case the part into which a specific object is located.
The code again is quite simple. There are a few basic concepts in this script.
We are again passing through a vSphere API method using the same CreateContainerView.
We limit what we want to see. This is an advice that you should always use when you start using this Get-View cmdlet.
These internal objects are quite big. There are tons of properties on there, so only retrieve what you actually need.
It will make your script a lot faster, especially if you're running in bigger environments.
You can imagine that creating something that has 100 properties and returning it takes a lot more time then,
in this case, we only need two properties and the property that is returned by default, the pointer to the object
is always in there. You don't have to explicitly specify it. Now if we use this code and we
run this, now we're getting somewhere. Now we are returning the name of our objects, the type in the second
column, and what you see on the right is the parent, so that is the node just above the one that you are
listing here in this inventory. It is represented as a pointer, so don't look at that exactly, but it's something
that we will use in the next step in our script.
What we're doing here and I'm showing something that I always try to use in my scripts and my functions that I write.
First of all, make it modular. If you have a specific functionality that you want to achieve, make it a separate function.
That's what I'm doing here with Get-ParentName. Secondly, what is also quite interesting, instead of writing
tons of lines of code, make your functions recursive. So traversing an object tree is ideal for a recursive function.
So we had the same code as we had before. We are now just creating or going to try to obtain the part to the
object that we're looking at and we do this recursively by calling that Get-ParentName function that you see over there.
And then,
we go a bit deeper in the function itself. We, in the end when we have the part, we just return that as a
property on an object that we create for each inventory object. So this is the ultimate goal we want to see
the object, the type of object, and the parent, the complete path, in fact.
And this is what we're having now. What you should be noticing that some of these things in the path,
some of the nodes in the path are not appearing. There is, for example, I'm not sure if it's on this one,
yeah it is, there are the ones in the first red box there. These are what they are called hidden folders.
In their inventory system, they made some hidden nodes in the which they can attach those four types of
object we mentioned in the beginning of this talk. We have the VM view, the host view, network view, storage view.
Those are the hidden folders. Those we don't want, in fact. We're never going to configure them ourselves,
so the next step in our script would be to just eliminate those from our script
and that is done quite easily with the WHERE clause where we can just say if you encounter an inventory node
with that specific name, don't show it to me. I don't want to know it.
And on top of that, in the function where we define or create a path to the object, we also skip those.
You don't want to have to specify those in the path of the object that you are inventorizing.
So this is all very straightforward PowerShell code, PowerCLI code, I guess there's nothing.
If there are questions, don't hesitate to ask. Don't start writing this down.
I will publish this when I get back home and you will find the complete function because it is a bit bigger
in the end. You will find it on my GitHub repository.
Okay, we are there. So this is now our inventory, the function that we started with originally.
We have all the information we need. We skipped the ones that we don't need, so this is quite complete.
It's better than the Get-Inventory cmdlet because we also see stuff like distributed switches, we see the datastore clusters.
Datastore clusters are called internally StoragePod, that's why you see it shown this way, but it's the same thing.
It's the internal name, which apparently is different from what cells in the end decided it should be named.
Now, what are we trying to go to. We want to create, that's our ultimate goal, we want to create these
configuration files automatically from an existing environment. So what you see in the red box there,
that's the stuff that I want to generate with the script in the end.
All the rest in my configuration file is rather static. I could use that in an inline string, code it once,
and just create the file, but this part is the part that really depends on what it discovers in your environment.
So what I'm doing here, I'm using an inline string and I just make a placeholder there.
That's the one that is marked and highlighted in yellow. That is the one that I will replace with text that
I generate based on the inventory we created with the function earlier.
So it's a very straightforward thing. All the stuff that is fixed or semi constant, you can do that in the
inline string and the stuff that is different or will change in your environment, that's the one that we will
insert in the text. How we do that is very straightforward. Everything is there, it's a string, you just do
a replace and place of that marker with the text you generated in the end.
Now there are a few properties on these resources that are quite important.
There is, for example, the one where you will tell it your specific node.
Imagine a folder, which is a subfolder of another folder, so we have Folder1, Folder2.
We want to define that dependency. So if we create Folder2, we have to find a way to say Folder1 should be there before.
So DSC allows you to do that with the DependsOn. Now we have to create depending on the path.
We have to construct that dependency dynamically from the inventory we are pulling.
Again, this is quite, can become quite complex because a folder can be located under a datacenter or it can
be located under another folder, so there's a bit of logic involved to find the correct dependency that we want
to use in our DSC configuration file. In the last lines at the bottom there I'm actually generating the specific
text for that specific invent. This is an example from the folder, but we have similar things for datacenter
clusters VM hosts. This is just to show you how I do it in the end.
There's a bit of logic, for example, for the folders where we decide if it's a blue or a yellow folder.
Remember yellow is the VM host cluster view. Blue is the VM template view.
And in the end, we will arrive with something that is actually usable in our DSC configuration file.
There are a few issues that you might encounter when you do this kind of inventory.
Suppose and vSphere allows you to do that, you have a folder with the same name, but in different locations
in your hierarchy. So you have to find a way to actually find the one that you want to look at.
Now I could have written quite some code, but luckily, and now I'm coming back to the point that I made at
the beginning, don't reinvent the wheel, just
steal the code. There is a guy who already wrote a function to do that, which happens to be someone I know.
He allows you to give the path to a folder, so he will follow that function, will follow the complete path
and give you the correct object. So no more issues if you have likewise names or folders with the same name.
You just give the complete path and he will return to you the correct object that you need in this case.
So we plug that in our script as well and then
if we run it ultimately, remember it was especially the where part that we were interested in the configuration variable.
This is the end result for folders in this case. I just re-include the two screenshots of those two views on
the inventory here to show you what we are actually doing there.
If you look, for example, at Folder4, that's the one at the bottom, the blue folder, you will see that there
is a dependency Folder3 should be there before Folder4 is created, which is obvious.
It's a subfolder on that one. But in a similar way, we have for Folder2, for example, which is a yellow
folder top view. That's a folder that is hosted, the parent of that folder is a datacenter so you then have a
dependency as we showed there in the DependsOn on that datacenter Homelab that we created earlier or in another line.
Now once you have these dependencies, the LCM will take care of it and he will do the right or do the right thing
to regenerate your complete environment.
Once you have this stuff, it's quite easy to put this in the source control.
You can use this to find drift in your environment. Somebody changes, somebody deletes a folder, this will discover.
Once you have this defined, in DSC it will find it and correct it, but you could also use this kind of stuff
to migrate your environment. Suppose you have a new vCenter, new version, an update, a new hardware, I don't know
what, you just want to transplant your complete environment. You could create that configuration file and then
just use the configuration file to recreate exactly the same structure on that other vCenter.
So the use case is for this kind of configuration files are quite interesting, so source control,
but also migration and recreation. You can use it in a DR environment where part of your environment would
by disaster disappear, you can recreate it quite easily that way.