Anymore questions? Yes, Josh.
Those folders are inherently designed to obtain things.
Yes.
Do you also have resources for maintaining that alignment so that virtual machines that could be in a
specific folder do not get moved to other locations because from an operation standpoint, that's what I see
happening is someone inadvertently when they're selecting it and then drag it to another folder and lose it.
Yeah. That's a good. Josh wants to know if the location in your vSphere inventory, if that is or can be controlled
by DSC and yes it can, of course. If we look at one of the earlier slides, let me pull it up again.
Okay, if you remember that slide from earlier on in the presentation, this part at the right, that is in fact
the location that you want to look at and what you are asking, if I understand the question correctly,
if somebody would move your VM from Folder2 to Folder3, for example, now with the VM in the configuration
definition, in the configuration file for the VM, we will have this path.
Path will always be there. That's why I'm stressing that obtaining this path is quite important in this
complete DSC setup. If DSC LCM agent sees that your path is not correct anymore, you will automatically get
the set call and that should correct it. So what we will have in that case, if it fails on the test of the
path, you will generate a move to that folder. Same goes not only for folders, but also for datastores,
for example, or even clusters for your VM.
So ultimately, your DSC LCM could be even, in fact, vMotioning, SVMotioning machines to comply with the
configuration that you defined in your configuration files. So it can go very far in the end.
There are some tricks, there are some things that I need to resolve because you have to take into account
high availability, for example. You're not going to specify that a VM should run on a specific ESXi node.
There are some cases where you perhaps would be inclined to do that.
I'm thinking of those VMs and I, at least, have them in my environment.
Some of you probably where people have applications that still require a dongle or something like that.
(Audience comment)
Or yeah, something like that. You need to fix it on a specific VM ESXi node.
There you would need to override what HHA is trying to do with your environment, so it's a bit complex on that level.
Yeah.
Would it make more sense to just create DSC resources to manage the DRS rules and make sure those DR rules
are in place, so if someone changes a DR rule, it adds a rule back.
Yeah, so DRS, the cluster configuration in vSphere has an option DRS and in DRS you can specify rules where
you can create affinities those VMs should be running on those ESXi nodes.
Yes, I fully agree, but that is more on the level of vSphere management.
You should be managing that in any case, but rules. Now those rules in itself, you can configure with your DSC configuration.
That is something that I will add on the cluster resource. We shouldn't rely on only the DSC configuration
to define the configuration. I fully agree that it should be in the rules.
Correct. Thanks. Good question.
Honestly, I think that is an extremely valuable use case because we still see a lot of people who are running
applications like Oracle or even SQL Server where you're paying like per socket or things like that.
Being able to not only say that, I've set up affinity, but I'm also ensuring that then be can't be broken provides
a lot of confidence if anyone were to try and come and audit you on that.
So how will you know that it's not going to be implied? Well I have affinity.
My score is just configured in a certain way so that it doesn't crossover and I'm using DSC to ensure that
if anyone accidently makes a change to that affinity, it autocorrects so that we don't get into a situation
where we're no longer compliant.
I agree, but on the other hand, I would be more inclined like we heard that to do this with rules and DRS
will also discover that its numbers were sitting on the right machine.
Perhaps the DRS cycle is not as frequent as the LCM agent cycle, but I consider this more on management of
your vSphere environment. LCM is another layer, another level. Getting those rules in the cluster, that I would
leave to DSC LCM. But applying the rule, I would leave that to vSphere in this case.
But you're right, you could envision doing it that way as well, but then you would be recreating the same
functionality that is already there in vSphere.
I'm simply implying that those affinity rules be set and managed so that they can't be staying with DSC.
Yep.
So vSphere is still doing its thing, it's still responsible for ensuring and guaranteeing that the workload
doesn't move, it's just that you're simply saying that DSC is keeping an eye on DRS affinity to make sure
that those rules don't change because someone could change one of those rules in DRS and virtual center server,
which could cause a problem that would make you noncompliant, but if DSC is just keeping an eye on that,
then that's less likely to happen. But yet you still let DRS do its thing, not have LCM do it.
Yeah. Fully agree with that one. Yeah, good idea. Anymore questions?
Yeah.
Do you need a vEngine for…?
No. No, that's the reason why, okay, I'm not going to pull it up again, you remember.
With the vEngine, you can use multiple sessions in there. So each session could be connecting to another
vSphere server be it multiple vCenters, be it multiple ESXi nodes or a mix of those two, no.
Because in the resource, I'm going to pull it up in any case because this is quite important.
That was on session one, but I can pull it up if I, okay, let me check if I know.
I can't find it immediately, but I can show you after the session that I am doing is in fact in each resource
entry in your configuration file, I had two properties, which is a vServer, which is the indication to which
vCenter or ESXi you are connecting and vCredential, which is a credential you should use for that connection.
So per resource you can define where it is located, so in the case of multiple ones, you go to the correct
one in that case. Does that answer your?
Yes.
Thank you. Any more questions? Just what I also mentioned in the first session on Monday, these DSC resources
are a work in progress. I have a number of them. When I'm back home, I will start publishing them.
They are now in a private repository that I'm using to develop them.
I will put them on public GitHub because this thing, its environment is so complex no one person will be able
to do all that stuff, so I'm counting a bit on community contribution there in the coming months.
I don't know what. Also, on the priorities because like I said this stuff is quite complex, I could imagine
that I would now if I put priorities on my to-do list so that I would first be looking at distributed switches part.
Perhaps the majority of the users say I would rather first see a fully working cluster resource, so it's in
fact up to you guys to tell me or do the work yourself or tell me which one should be the next on my list.
Yeah, we already reached that one of course since we are discussing your questions.
No. Anymore? Okay, then I thank you for attending this code heavy session.
I hope I didn't bother you. Thanks!