Now where I want to spend more time is on ACL changes.
Somebody has granted themselves access to something else in Active Directory that you weren't aware of.
Probably ought to check on that too, shouldn't we? So by default, in the schema somewhere, there are default
permissions defined for all the objects. That'd be kind of painful to go actually delta all those to see what's
because over the life of the directory it's going to be really messy to figure that out, but I want to show
you a way to look at this. So using that same thing Get-ADReplicationAttributeMetadata, how many have used Get-ACL?
Alright, yeah, you're working with, looking at the permissions of an object, did you know that Get-ACL
actually works against Active Directory objects? When you get that AD drive letter, you can do a Get-ACL to
see what are the permissions on an AD object. So what we can do then, the ACL on an AD object is stored in a
property called nTSecurityDescriptor. So think about what we just looked at with the group changes,
now we can filter the metadata of every object in the Active Directory to see which ones have had an ACL
change in the last 24 hours or the last week. Sound interesting?
Yeah. So now we can actually go look and see who has been delegating access in the environment recently
and get a report of that.
So what we're going to do then is we're going to get a list. Now you need to be careful here.
Grabbing a list of every object in the directory, that's going to be, yeah, you'll be there a while, so instead,
what I'm just going to do is I'm just going to filter on OUs. We'll start there.
So I'm just going to get a list of OUs, and for each OU, I'm going to grab the replication metadata of that OU
to see if there have been any changes to the nTSecurityDescriptor and then I'm going to sort that in descending order.
And so when I look into this data, I see that the HR OU, let's zoom in there, so the HR OU on April 1st of
all days had a permission change. Now the rest of these OUs, this is my lab, so it's been a long time since
anybody's touched these. That was April 1st of 2014. Wow. Yeah, that's been a while.
Alright, so let's make a change then. Oh, I'm sorry. That's whenCreated.
I apologize. Let's look at the proper attribute here. Let's scroll across to the LastOriginatingChange.
That's actually the date we want. There we go, that's the one. That's 4/6/2016.
So right there I can see the LastOriginatingChange on that ACL was the 6th.
That was this week. Somebody changed access to the HR OU. So what do you think we ought to do?
Let's go look at the access for the HR OU, but there's a problem with that.
Let's see what the problem is. What I can do then is say, alright, here's all of the ACEs that have been
updated in the last amount of time, let's say within the last 90 days here.
So then what we will do is we'll look at here's the HR OU in CohoVineyard.
Alright, so let's get on down to see the actual permissions now.
So what we can do is I'm going to do a quick little dosey-doe to query the property names for the permissions
out of the schema so that we're not looking at GUIDs, that makes it easier to see the permissions, and we're going
to look at objects with change permissions. And so here's our list and actually let me skip down one more
section, here we go. So permissions that were changed. So what I'm going to do now is going to say okay,
here's a list of all the objects, and why did that give me nothing?
Oh, okay, I just grabbed the data, now list Out-GridView. There we go.
So, here we go. Here's the HR OU in the top of the list and I see the change originated on the CVDCR2 and
if I scroll across, let me zoom in here, I want you to see what we're looking at.
I know this is a lot of data, but everything we want is right here.
So let's take a look. I'm going to zoom in and I see these are the named permissions that are applied to that
OU and it will tell me what's inherited, what's not inherited, GenericRead, Write, for User, Computers,
and groups, things like that in the OU and as I scroll across, I will see here are the account names that are granted
access to that and there's GoodGuy. But here's the problem, every one of these are currently on that ACL.
We don't know which one was changed. We just know that this is the current ACL.
We don't know which piece of the ACL was changed, which ACE individually was added or removed.
So I'm going to cheat and show you another way we can look at that.
This is the piece that I woke up about 6 am after a full night of conference sleep and I thought I need to do
something else to really take this to the next level. So two years ago here I did
a presentation on Active Directory snapshots. Some of you are nodding your head, most of you probably never
heard of Active Directory Snapshots. It was a feature we introduced in server 2008 and you think, wait a minute,
snapshots, Active Directory, I thought we're never supposed to snapshot Active Directory right.
Well that's VM snapshots. This is the actual database. There's a feature in Ntdsutil where you can do a
volume shadow copy of just the Active Directory database and logs, and keep that, and then mount it into memory
on a different port, and query historical AD values. Pretty cool, huh?
So now we've got this prior state of Active Directory in the current state of Active Directory.
Well somebody I know happened to write a module to do all that for you, so you don't have to type all those
long crazy commands, alright. So out on the blog,
it's called Oh Snap! Active Directory attribute recovery, yes, Oh Snap!
So what I've got is a function library here with my snapshots, and in this functional library, I have some
functions here like let's see we've got a---
So an answer. Yes. These guys never bothered to audit something, but they did do an AP snapshot?
Okay, alright. I'm glad you asked the question. I just want to make sure it's (inaudible).
No, they never did a snapshot. That's oh snap. Exactly. Right.
They didn't do the snapshot. That would have been amazing. It would have been amazing.
It would have made this very easy. There would have been five people who were in AP snapshots.
Right, right. So my part of my role here is to tell you to go start using snapshots in your environment
because you can do, you don't have to buy some third-party popular product to do attribute level recovery.
You can do it for free with this functional library on my blog. Alright.
So you can do free attribute level restores copying the data back out of a good copy of AD when somebody
blew all the email addresses out. I know some of you have been there.
Alright. So I've got a snapshot here that I took
in my environment. Here's the last snapshot I just did today. And so what I'm going to do is I'm going to
mount this snapshot. So yes, they didn't have a snapshot there, but the moral of the story is go make snapshots
and schedule them. It's all documented on my blog. So what's happening here is we're actually mounting a
utility dsamain.exe, I'm giving it a port 33389 that nobody's using right now, and now when I look at my
snapshots, I'll see that it's mounted this exposed name here into this $SNAP folder, so it's actually
temporarily restored a copy of an older Active Directory database and logs.
So I've got
that mounted on a separate port and now I can query the live AD and the history AD and compare the results.
And I have created some functions here for you that you can query an object and give it a list of attributes
and it'll rewrite those attributes back into production copy. Alright, so free recovery.
Yeah. This might be kind of hard to answer, but I'm just curious like what's the general size of something like that?
I mean, is it huge or is it relatively easy to keep that kind of stuff?
I mean, small? Yeah, it's pretty small. But you do want, in my article I give you some guidance around
keeping that cleaned up. You don't want it to get out of hand. Just determine how many you want to keep.
So
today I wrote a new function in this module called Compare-ADObjectACL and I pass it in a OU path because HR
was the OU where the attribute or the permission change happened, and so I want to compare that OU ACL
between what's historical and what's right now. So when I run this, it dumps out a list of permissions.
Here's a permission that was removed. Oh, look at this, somebody removed HRAdmins from the HR OU and they,
I guess that's it. It looks like they just removed the HRAdmins was the change that they made.
I could probably update my snapshot to see the other changes as well.
But anyway the only challenge here
is that I have to manage, I haven't built the logic in yet, but you have to manage the date that the snapshot
was taken against the date that the change happened. Make sure you get those date windows set correctly,
so you can go view the actual changes that were there. So that will allow you then to take a snapshot and
view what was in place before somebody made the change. So I can go, it's like a time machine to look at my
directory and see what was there before Joe Jr. Admin came in and fixed everything.
You've had Joe Jr. Admin come in and fix things in your directory, right?
So you've got to go refix them.
So now that I've done, I've looked in there, I've found that I'm just going to dismount that database,
mount it in memory, and this little LDP icon down at the bottom will go away, and then that is now unmounted,
that snapshot is gone. So that's the way that you can do it, but it does require you to be prepared and take
snapshots on a scheduled basis in your environment. What about deleted users?
Let's go ahead and delete these two guys if they're, yeah. And let's go take a look then, let me skip through
here ACL_Changes, Recycle_Bin, here we go.