Now this script I've actually---it was PowerShell Saturday in Charlotte several years ago, Mike Robbins,
I think, came up to me after the event and I'd done some talk about Active Directory and he says man I've got this
problem where this guy has been in the company for 20 years and he's been in every department, he's been added
to every group and I don't know which groups he needs to, he's basically a domain admin at this point.
He's got access to everybody's data because we never took him out of all those old groups.
Everybody can identify with that situation? So how can I find that group history mystery?
How can I figure that out? So I wrote this little thing with this AttributeMetadata cmdlet and what it does
is it's going to show me for this user, let's go look at every group they're a member of and find the date
that they were added to that group. So here we see for this user he was added to manufacturing in 2013,
accounting in 2013, HR in 2013, 2011 he was added to legal and some other test group in there.
Obviously this is just a tiny little lab environment, but in your real world you'll have 40 groups in there
and you'll be able to see using this data,
then going back forensically to see when they were added to every one of these groups they're a member of.
Is that handy? Alright, so that's called the group history mystery.
Yeah. I've run into something with this before where, I can't remember why it was limited to last 1,000
changes that had been made on a group. Have you run into something like that?
First I've heard of it. Okay, I need to research it further. Okay.
Deleted metadata will disappear after a while if the license was…
Right, right. So the deleted metadata will disappear. These are the ones that are still active members of the groups.
Yeah.
Yeah, what I also ran into was a group that I have that has almost everybody in the company in it and when I
looked up the metadata for it, I can only find the last 1,000 changes or less.
Oh. That was an issue too. That's probably going to be a limitation on the metadata attribute field,
how much it can hold I'm going to guess for a group of that size.
Yeah. So its binary data. Actually Brandon Shell, BS on POSH, he wrote before this cmdlet existed,
he wrote something that would actually, it was a very manly function that would go parse all the binary data
in that attribute and give you the data, but now we have a cmdlet to do it.
So yeah, it's a lot easier now. Does this require having admin rights for some of these to reset these?
Probably so because if you're looking at delegated administration in some of these places, you're going to
have to have domain admins because I'm thinking that every user has read to just about anything in the directory,
but there are going to be places where they don't have it, so yeah, you probably should use an elevated
account to do this. Yeah. So a smart malicious act is going to do as little as possible, as little destruction
to the structure as possible. Right. So the holy grail is like finding these, the holy grail would be like
finding a service account, Kerberos it could hash, or even the Kerberos to generate the account.
In other words, you could generate a KRBG, whatever KRBT, that hash.
Can we use these cmdlets to dig in and try to see those tickets or who's generating them?
Is there an account that's generating more tickets than they should?
You could look at the KRBTGT and look at the attributes on it and see if those, if the version stamp has been
incremented for that like the hash and things like that on the password attributes.
Now which version is it. When you do the prep on the environment, in one of the recent versions of AD,
it actually changes that password, so don't be surprised if you see a change in there from the original value
it's supposed to happen. Do you have to change it twice to change the password?
I don't remember. But yeah, I haven't looked at it in detail, but it's in there.
So we've got just a couple minutes. Let me finish up here and then we will take some more questions.
So last up is a GP link metadata. I'm not going to take the time to display it, but basically part of the
clues that we got from one of the other security vendors that were on site with this customer was that they
thought there was some suspicious Group Policy activity during the event window and I wanted to see what group
policy changes had happened in the environment.
So now imagine I've got an OU object, that OU object has a GP link attribute.
The GP link attribute is a string that holds the GUID of every policy that's linked to it.
So now I can just go through all the OUs, look at the metadata, and see which GP links historically have
been versioned recently telling me that one of the policies linked to it has recently changed.
Again, I can't see specifically which one. So I found some policy activity on an OU and I could see though
that it looked like normal behavior because there was a test OU where they had developed the policy and I
could see that it had been unlinked from that OU and linked to a production OU and they went back and
correlated it with their change logs and it was a scheduled change, it was normal, so I could not corroborate
the story of the vendor saying hey there's some suspicious GPO activity because I looked at it all and it looked fine.
So it can even take that, and there's a whole blog post on just that piece as well, if you want that.