I want to tell you a story. So I go help customers. That's what I do.
Some people call premier field engineers, they're like ninjas jumping out of helicopters.
So it was a Friday evening and I should speak to the microphone over here.
So it was a Friday evening and I had just logged off for the day, getting ready to have dinner with the family
and I'd worked it out where I had two weeks at home to do some remote project work so I didn't have to be on the road.
I was really looking forward to the next two weeks. Friday evening, I sit back in my recliner, I've got my
comfy clothes on and my phone rings. We have somebody called the on-duty critsit manager, and a critsit is
kind of like you guys are on call for your company, right, but we're on call for every company in the world.
Alright, and I don't get those calls very often, but I got the call and the manager says we need you.
Have you seen the news? I said no I haven't looked at the news.
He said turn on your TV or look at the internet, whatever. And so I look at the news and I oh no.
So I, he says we need you, this was Friday evening, he said we need you on site Monday morning with the customer.
Now this customer will be unnamed. I'm not going to tell you what industry, what geography, anything about this
customer, alright, because we do this on a regular basis. So I get to the customer site, I show up to the
standard security check-in where they give you your badge and all that with the security people, right.
They don't have any computer. Their computers are turned off. They're handwriting nametags and writing them
on a clipboard. This is the security check-in at the front desk at the company.
I get off the elevator and there's a sign posted for all the employees that says do not turn on your computer
until further notice. And that week, the FBI was at the company briefing employees on identity theft
protection and how to guard themselves online. It was post-apocalyptic.
This IT environment was pretty much cratered by hackers and they call me to come in and say we need you to
look at the Active Directory and tell us if it's okay to bring back online.
When we realized that we were breached, we started shutting down domain controllers and we had two that were
offshore in other countries where we've got the VM captured and we've taken the time of a couple days to
transmit that VM over our high speed lines to get it in an isolated lab.
We want you to look at this DC and tell us if you can find any fingerprints of the hackers in the Active Directory
data so we know whether it's okay to reuse this domain environment because otherwise, we're building completely
from green field the entire company. That's kind of a big deal.
I wasn't ready for that.
So Active Directory Forensics. Here's our problem.
How do you track malicious activity in your domain environment when you didn't have the auditing turned on?
How many of you have auditing properly enabled in your Active Directory environment?
Right, properly, right. Alright, about two-thirds of you, so that's about, yeah, that's actually better than average.
So what our problem to solve is how do you find the footprints of what we call an actor in your environment
if they're tampering with your Active Directory data and you did not properly have auditing turned on.
It's a big deal.
What we're going to do is we're going to dive into just the single DC lab here and look at some things
and teach you some concepts, some ways that you can work with your Active Directory data and try to find some
of these things. So what we're going to imagine is that you create an account, you create a group,
you put the user in the group, you nest that group in domain admin somewhere to try to hide that it's not
an immediate member of domain admins, you grant that account control of an OU, then you delete the account,
delete the group, kind of what we would assume to be hacker activity is now.
The truth is, with targeted malware aimed at companies sponsored by nation states, they usually don't even
need to create accounts because they're going to find somebody on the network that's stored their password in
clear text and they'll just use their accounts. So sometimes we may not, and that was part of the case at
this one particular customer. The hackers didn't really need to create any extra accounts because they had
already found all the passwords in a spreadsheet in the network.
I know you guys don't do that though, that's okay. Alright. Don't be that company.
Don't be that company, alright.