So let's dive into the lab here and take a look.
So first off, I've staged some changes in the environment I want us to look at and what I want to do is look
at the Active Directory RIDs, Relative IDs, essentially. I want to look at in descending order what are the
most recent new accounts that were created in the environment?
Now the scary statistic that I've heard is that the hackers have been in your network 11 months before you're
even aware that they're there. So this is all best effort really here, but what we're going to do is we're
going to look at a list of accounts, newest accounts, from the moment we discover the breech, we're going to
look at the newest accounts and determine do any of these look suspicious in any way.
Alright. So I'm going to take a look here, Get-ADObject. Now the SearchBase is going to be here, the Path,
the root of the domain, and I'm going to do a Subtree search Get-ADObject standard kind of deal here.
And so I'm looking for all the accounts that have an object SID.
Any object in Active Directory that has a SID, that's going to be a security identifier, which would be users,
computers, and groups. We're going to pull back those types of objects and then I'm going to put some funny
business calculation in here for the date of when it was created to get something that's recent.
And let's see. I'm going to do ResultPageSize. We were just talking about paging here a second ago.
One of the things I discovered working in this particular lab environment that they gave me was I'm working
with a large data set, thousands of accounts, and the Active Directory cmdlets were choking and timing out in
places, so I had to put a page size, and I had to kind of play with how big the page size was, and I found that
100 was about right for the chunks of data to process. And so I'm going to pull back from those objects the
whenCreated, the objectSID, and some other things, isDeleted. And what we'll do then is we're going to
actually take the objectSID, which is the domain SID- the RID, that last little bit on the SID and just parse out
the RID just for information and it doesn't have to be sequential necessarily, but we're just going to take a
look at these most recent accounts in the environment. And if I zoom in here with mark's tool, so here we've
got the objects SID, the RID, when it was created, is it deleted, and this is just looking at accounts in the
last few days or the last week. So is it deleted, what type of object is it, user or group, and you can see
GoodGuy and GoodGuys. Those are the demo accounts that I've created for us to play with here because we're the
good guys, right. So that's just a quick way to look and see what's the newest accounts.
Not a big deal there, just a quick query to say alright looking at around the point that this event happened,
we're there any new accounts that were created that look suspicious.
Now, how many have heard of something called Admin SD holder?
Alright, so if you're not aware,
there's a process that runs on a domain controller, your PDC, every hour, and anybody that's a member of those
specially protected groups like account operators, backup operators, domain admins, it's going to run a
process to make sure that people in those groups haven't found some nefarious way to elevate their access and it
resets their access on their accounts, so this is called the Admin SD holder.
Anytime you're put into a group that's nested into one of those groups, there's a flag that gets set on your
account that's called Admin account. So let's take a look here.
So I've got a little script that's going to query for this property AdminCount.
If it's set to 1, then I know that's a protected group member. So an account that's somehow nested into
another group that's nested into a privileged group that's going to be reset automatically on that hour interval.
So what I'm looking for then is I'm going to process through these protected groups, and then for each one of
those groups, I'm going to get a member list, but I'm going to do this a really special way here with
something called Get-ADReplicationAttributeMetadata. Boy, that cmdlet is a mouthful.
This cmdlet never gets old. I've been demoing this cmdlet for years and it is your best friend when it comes
to forensics in Active Directory. So before I get into the function here that I've created, let's just kind of
step through this a little bit. So I'm just going to pick a domain controller and give me an hour's interval
of 24/7 and I'm going to query Get-ADGroup where AdminCount is equal to 1, and then I'm going to look at my protected groups.
So here's my protected group list, print operators, replicator, backup operators, and then notice this
GroupLevel1, GroupLevel2, GroupLevel3. I put this in here on purpose to show you that no matter how deep you
nest the groups, these are all just nested. Group 1 has group 2, has group 3 and then group 1 itself is
actually nested in 1 of these privileged groups like domain admins, I believe, over here, so we can look at
those protected groups. So now, let's take a look at something called Get-ADReplicationAttributeMetadata
on the Domain Admins group. Now somebody was telling me earlier today that they had used this cmdlet,
but they didn't use the ShowAllLinkedValues. This cmdlet is going to show you, Active Directory keeps track
of what you do,
and if you update any single attribute on any single object, there's a version stamp for every attribute on every object.
So I can see how many times that one lady in the company that's been married five times and her last name
attribute has changed every other month, okay. I can see there's been version that many times every time we
had to go update the last name attribute, okay.
So ShowAllLinkedValues though is especially for groups with that linked value replication I mentioned just a
second ago, so it'll show me all the users that are members of those groups and when they were added to that group.
So let's take a look at this particular example here. Piping everything to Out-GridView, my favorite cmdlet,
right after Import-Csv. So here we go. It's showing me that the object category is a group, gives me each
one of these things, there's the Sid, there's the adminCount, it's a special adminCount is 1,
it's a special group, here's the description and so forth, it's the cn.
But if I slide over here to the right, what I want you to notice, let me scroll across here, I have to scroll
across my view and this is all tiny. That's the one thing I don't like about demoing Out-GridView, I have to
scroll a lot. So last originating change time up here says this is the last time that attribute was ever
changed on that object and if I scroll all the way to the right, I'll see a version stamp.
And that version stamp says how many times 1 is the time when it was originally created as an object, when it was
born in AD, and then any increment above 1 indicates that attribute has been changed, how many times,
just subtract one from it. So if I come down through here I can see look there's some attributes that have
been versioned significantly. So let's slide back over here and what I want you to see is that in this domain
admins group, you can actually take a look at the members in the group.
Now you can see here's a deleted user GoodGuy that I've been playing with a couple times setting up for the demo.
Here's a migration account from the AD migration that you had to set up.
Here's Bob. Somehow Bob made it into admins. And there's GroupLevel1 that has a GroupLevel2 and 3 nested
inside of it, so those are members. And over here, we can see the date that they were added to domain admins.
That's interesting. Then if I keep going across here, it'll show me which domain controller the update originated from.
So the ADReplicationAttributeMetadata will show me the last change to every attribute on an object and which
domain controller initiated it and the date and time. Does that sound handy?
Yeah. Sounds pretty handy. As long as it was the last change that we're looking for there.
There's also another property over here that will tell us if it was deleted.
So if the user was ever a member, here's a last originating delete timestamp.
If we look at the column title here, LastOriginatingDeleteTime and there's the value of 2/23 whoever that
user was there was deleted out of domain admins on that date. So we can see additions and deletions using
this cmdlet to view group memberships here. Now the one thing to mention is that this is linked value replication.
If you've got the old school 2002, 2003 early era, the group memberships are in a blob in a member's property
and it's replicated as a blob, then this doesn't apply necessarily.
But with the linked value replication that we enabled in 2003 and above, you should see this, so all your new
groups should be seeing this.
And to comment on that, if you upgraded, do you delete the members and add them back to the…
Right. Right. You've got to reset the group membership to make them LVR.
So if I add a group member, actually, he's already a member of that group.
Let's say we remove Bob from the group there and we can go look at it again and then we can see that Bob here,
I bet this is the one I've already demoed earlier. Let's see, is he still in there.
Yeah, he's already been deleted, so it would update his delete date.
So what are we getting at here. What we can do then is we can say for each one of those members, we can go
through here and take a look. So what this report then shows me is these are all of my privileged groups,
Backup Operators, Domain Admins, Administrators, Enterprise Admins, all those special groups, and here's a
list if I scroll to the right who are the members that have been added or removed from those groups within a date range.
So I can filter on that property over here FirstOriginatingCreateTime is not what we're looking for.
We're looking for LastOriginatingChangeTime, which tells me that this attribute, this user was added or
removed on this date, so this is just PowerShell objects filtering, right.
So I can just filter that now and run that once a day, once every six hours, put it in my monitoring tools,
and filter on all my privileged groups, filter on that date, and I can get an email now around the clock anytime
somebody's been added or removed from a privileged group. Does that sound like a good idea?
How many of you get notifications on privileged group changes? Alright, for the rest of you that don't have
your hand in the air, this is a free no-frills way to do that with just a couple lines of PowerShell.
And this is all documented out on my blog, so the code is out there for you to get publicly.
I'll give you that URL here in a minute. So what I did was I just took all that code and put it into a
function and the function just has a domain controller parameter and how many hours in the history you want
to look and it'll go grab all your protected members, ProtectedGroups, enumerate through all their members,
and see which ones have been added or changed in the last X hours, so that's a handy way to go drill into that.