So back in the day before the recycle bin, you delete an object,
it gets tombstoned, and then there
was Mark Savage's tool that you could put the object back and it looks really beat up when it comes back,
but it's just got the SID enough to really preserve the identity, so you don't have to go reset all the permissions,
but it loses everything else essentially. Now we've got the recycle bin.
We don't have that concern because now we have the recycle bin. Depending on what interval of your tombstone
lifetime was set when you implemented it determines how many, usually it's modern system it's 180 days,
you've got the recycle bin, then after that, you've got a tombstone for another 180 days, so potentially a year
theoretically to get an object back.
So the problem is when you query in Active Directory in the deleted objects container, so if I look at the
Get-ADDomain, there's a property on Get-ADDomain that tells me where the deleted objects container is.
I find that exact property here. Deleted objects here and CohoVineyard is my sample domain today.
So I'm going to pick that deleted objects container. So the other thing I was thinking was hey what if the
hackers deleted some accounts or deleted some data in Active Directory that I want to go inspect.
So let's take a look. I'm going to look at that deleted objects container here and I'm going to set that as
the search base for my query. That's where I'm going to start my query, but when you're querying deleted objects,
you have to include this parameter IncludeDeletedObjects because normally those are hidden by default.
So I'm going to view those deleted objects and grab those under a variable called DeletedObjects and then I'm
going to sort them by modified, but the problem I had here and let's see, there we go, and so you get the Dell
thing in the name and all that. There's a last known parent attribute as well in here that gets populated
when they're deleted. The problem is that basically there are some date fields in here, but there's no good
date field to tell me when it was deleted, when or where that delete originated.
So what I want to do then is look at the metadata just like we've looked at everything else, now I can see
which domain controller initiated that delete putting it in the recycle bin and then go look at the logs on
that DC for that time period to see who was making the change.
Alright, so that's the way we track it back. We use the replication metadata to find which DC originated
change, then we go look at the security log on that DC to see where it was.
Now most likely these security logs are rolling pretty frequently, so you would have to have some type of event
log collection forwarding something going on in your environment to be able to search those historically.
So what I could do here would be to run through and let's take a look at with the metadata here, put that in the GridView.
And so now I've got deleted objects, whenCreated, and whenDeleted right here.
Alright, so that shows me when the object was deleted and what that's pulling back is it's a calculated value
based on that metadata for the change date on the object. It says this is the last change was putting it in
the recycle bin, so I know that's the date it was deleted. And so I can now see a dated list of what things
were deleted in descending order from today and then go look at the event window, those date ranges that are
suspect and see were there things that were wholesale deleted by the hackers in that window.
Anecdotally, while I was surfing through this company's directory data, I found an actual account with the name Hacker.
It turns out there's a user in Europe with the last name of Hacker.  So they were legit.