So let me wrap here. So where can I find these scripts? Go out to aka.ms/ADForensics and that is a link to
the blog feed that has all of my posts that are tagged with forensics-related topics.
So you can go check all of those aka.ms/ADForensics. Also, in my Microsoft Virtual Academy Video series,
I have eight video segments on MVA about doing Active Directory with PowerShell.
The fourth segment in that is all about forensics where I talk about some of these same topics, but I don't,
I didn't go into the same level of detail that I did today, but it's all there for you,
the ReplicationAttributeMetadata and things like that. Also, Microsoft is doing a lot in the area of cyber security.
I've been on a few of these covert dispatches myself where
they don't even tell me the name of the customer. I showed up, they said here's the address, I'll meet you there.
It was like I was volunteering to be abducted or something and I'm going to go in this secret door and it's a
need---it's like cloak and dagger stuff. They don't even---in our systems we don't even track the name of the customer.
We use a fake name all this because it's very confidential when we're dealing with cyber security investigations.
So we have a full team of PFEs and MCS consultants that specialize in cyber engagements.
If you're company has been hacked, if you get that call, if you become aware of it, please call us because
some of the kneejerk reactions that you take as soon as you find out you've been hacked, the things that you
think are the best thing to do, are not. And we have trained experts that will help you investigate and
remediate your situation, so please contact us. We also, there are a lot of vendors in this space and I'm
not trying to just say that we're the best, right, but we are because we have special tools in the world that
nobody else has because we're Microsoft. We have lots of special data that they simply don't have.
Please call us
if you have a cyber incident. Satya Nadella at the end of last year did a special press conference with some
people in DC about cyber security. The things that are really hard to track is when you're looking at millions
of event log entries across domain controllers for the last year, how do I know what's normal activity and
what's malicious activity. We're using machine learning to study event logs and identify abnormal activity
in your environment. So we're doing a lot of research in this space.
We have a lot of experts to help you with your cyber security needs.
And so I mentioned at the beginning that you really need to make sure that you have your auditing set up correctly.
Here are some blog links particularly to the Ask PFE Platforms blog that have some expert advice from some of
my peers on how to properly audit your Active Directory environment so that you don't have to worry about
these other methods to try to find the data when it's too late.
So, closing then. Don't be that company. Don't put clear text passwords in a spreadsheet.
It happens. These companies end up in the news. Audit your Active Directory environment the right way.
Set up alerts. Take the sample code, even if, most people are always complaining about IT budgets,
this is PowerShell. Do it for free, use these scripts, and set up alerts in your environment.
Learn this ReplicationAttributeMetadata cmdlet. It's going to be your best friend.
Cyber security is a huge topic. This is just a very small part. There's so much more we can do with cyber
forensics in Active Directory. This is just to get you started there.
So check out the new machine learning stuff I mentioned from Microsoft.
And if your company gets hacked, please call us. And I don't say that to put other vendors in a bad light.
It's just that we have experts that this is all they do and they live on site with customers for months
helping them recover from these terrible scenarios. And finally, if this has helped you, please send me a tweet
just so my boss knows that I'm actually not golfing, but I'm helping people in the real world.
Thank you. Alright.