So why do we need an application, the development lifecycle, or module of the development lifecycle?
This is kind of like a classic software development cartoon that you always see around the place and it's
like kind of a hit on communication. The customer describes their swing as this like weird three-tiered
swing that doesn't really make too much sense, but it kind of gets the point across.
And my favorite one is how the programmer wrote it because it's this crappy little string swing hanging on
the ground, pretty much like all the code I write. And then business consultant obviously is this grand
chair hanging in the tree. I love how it's documented, it's just missing.
The customer was built like it was a rollercoaster. But in the end, what they really needed was a tire swing.
So because of that, we kind of have this iterative development process and it's been kind of a term that's
been around for a while in the application world and it applies directly to module development because
if you think about it, a module really just is a different type of application and it's circular in nature.
So you hear things like agile development processes and iterative development and everything.
This is a case for iterative development of an application. So you kind of start with requirements gathering
and this is where you go and talk to your key stakeholders,
and depending on what kind of module you're making, it might be yourself.
You might be the key stakeholder for that module, but it might be people in your company or people out on the
internet might find interest in this, so you want to go out and kind of pull those people, gather requirements,
and then get those requirements kind of documented, prioritized, and figure out what you need to get done first,
that kind of thing.
From there, you're going to kind of move on to a design step. A lot of people may think that you don't
actually do too much design. I don't do too many Visios or anything like that, but
there's a lot of design conversations that at least take place. You might be whiteboarding something or just
having a conversation on GitHub issues where you're dropping pictures or seeing why did you do it this way,
that kind of thing, so there's at least a conversation around design.
From there, we get to the fun part, which is development. So everybody loves writing code, turning it out in
your favorite editor,
but there's a lot of nuances that come with that. You want to be able to track your changes, you want to
integrate with other people developing on your module. You want to be able to roll back in case something
happens, that kind of thing.
And kind of integrated with development is testing. So there's a whole concept that you should be testing
while you're developing, so test-driven development or behavior-driven development.
Well there's kind of testing that takes place after the development has completed like user-acceptance testing.
So there's this tooling out there to help us manage that.
From there, we have to think about release. So it's great and all that we have all this code up in GitHub,
but historically, it's been kind of hard to get access to PowerShell modules.
You had to download a zip, you had to make sure the files were unblocked before it would load it and that
kind of thing,
but nowadays, we have the PowerShell Gallery, so we can manage our releases a little bit easier.
We can get it out to the general populace a lot quicker. But we have to think about things like breaking
changes, we have to think about version numbers and that kind of thing, so that's where the release
management comes into play.
And as you can see, then we move back into requirements gathering because you know after you release it,
the first thing that someone's going to respond to you is like this doesn't work, or why did you do it this
way, or I need this feature, so you just continue to work through this application lifecycle.
So when you see terms like ALM, that's Application Lifecycle Management and that's kind of what we're
thinking about in terms of module design.
So there's a bunch of tooling available out there for this kind of stuff, so you can use a lot of the same
tools that other software developers are using, so C# and .NET developers are using GitHub.
We can use GitHub for PowerShell modules, like I said, it's still just software development.
So you can use tools for requirements, design and gathering like GitHub issues, JIRA for tracking work items
or even like Visual Studio team services.
So a lot of these things are free for open source developers or small projects and stuff like that.
And then when you move into like the development phase, you can use things like your favorite editor,
you can check things into GitHub or Bitbucket or GitLab or whatever you want to use for that.
Testing in the PowerShell world, we have Pester, which is great for both kind of unit and integration testing.
It's really straightforward and it actually integrates really well with AppVeyor, which I'll show you later.
Finally, when we get to release management, you're can use things like GitHub where you can put your releases
up there, they have a release concept. But pretty much for PowerShell modules, you're going to want to start
using PowerShell Gallery, so people can easily install your module.
And then kind of managing the orchestration of all of this is our build system.
So what we're going to look at today is using AppVeyor. So AppVeyor, free for open source projects.
You can also get a paid tier. It gives you a few more bells and whistles.
And then there's things like Jenkins. If you go up to
powershell.org, they actually have free continuous integration systems running on Jenkins I think for open
source PowerShell projects.
I think it's TeamCity.
Is it TeamCity? Okay, alright. But yeah, that'll be another build system that can be in this list.