Yeah, so that is the module and now it's available, you can go download it, you could go comment on my GitHub.
One thing I wanted to note is I took a very kind of simple approach to this and there's a couple things that
you might want to consider before actually doing it exactly this way.
Like this is a great way to kind of get up and running, but for one example is anytime I commit anything,
it's now publishing to the gallery, so it's updating my module and really it's just running automated tests,
no one is really smoke testing it by hand or anything like that, not the best idea.
What you could do is create two different branches, one a development branch where you do all your
development in testing, and then once you're satisfied that something is complete, then you merge it into master.
So the development branch still runs your AppVeyor tests, it just skips the publishing step.
And then when you pull request into master, that's when you can decide to publish.
The other you could do is have a manual build on AppVeyor to actually say I want to publish this module now,
so over on AppVeyor, publish, and complete that, and publish it to the gallery, so it's a little more manual steps,
so you can decide when to release rather than doing it automatically.
Yeah, so that is kind of what I wanted to cover. If you guys have any questions, I'd be happy to take them now.
Otherwise, feel free to get a hold of me. Cool. Alright, well thank you very much.