Alright, so I'm going to do the most dangerous demo of all time right now and I'm going to rely on the
conference internet to communicate with three different web services, so nothing is scripted here.
Alright and what's funny is I was actually working on this presentation yesterday and GitHub had an outage
for about 20 minutes in the middle of my practice. I'm like oh no, what did I do?
But it looks like it's actually back up and running today, so hopefully it works.
But so sign up for a GitHub account. It's super easy just like anything else.
When you sign in, yours is going to look a little different, like I follow a bunch of stuff, so that's why
I'm seeing all these notifications and I have all these reposts on the right-hand side.
What you're going to want to look at is a New Repository button, so you click that and you can create a new repository.
Let's say I want to create my module and my module is going to be a LoremIpsum generator, so it's just kind
of a random text generator. So just name your repository and then you can put a description in there.
It's telling me that this repository is available. Public repositories are free, so you can just sign up and
get that for free. Private repositories are not, but they're relatively cheap, but for the purpose of this
demo, we want to make a public repository for people to communicate on this particular module.
So the first thing you want to do is initialize with a readme. A readme is just that page that you see when
you first load up a GitHub page where it'll have like a description, it might have some images, a how to,
that kind of thing, like what is this thing. So you can initialize it with a readme and then you always want
to select a license. So I've actually had modules that I've published that didn't have a license specified
and I've had people comment and say like I can't even use your code because you don't have a license and my
company won't allow it, so you have to be careful which license you select and you want to make sure that you
have one because it kind of covers your butt, as well as whoever is using your code.
If you're ever curious about what a license means, you can head over to tldrlegal.com and you can just
search the different licenses and it has like a super easy-to-understand breakdown of what that license
actually means and what's covered there. So there's all kinds of cool stuff like what's a GPL license why
shouldn't I use it, that kind of thing. Alright, so now we're ready to create our repository and luckily
that was pretty quick. So now we have a repository where I can check in code, I can create issues, I can set
up my wiki, all that kind of stuff. But if we're going to follow the kind of development lifecycle,
the first thing we want to do is start tracking what requirements we have for our particular module.
Well a LoremIpsum module really needs to be able to, I've already typed in here, really needs to be able to
generate text, so generate random text. So the markdown language that you can put in these GitHub issues is
really rich, so you can do all kinds of things like put quoted text, you can have code, you can do links,
you can have images, you can actually reference commits and other users so they get notifications,
all that kind of stuff, but we're going to just leave that blank for now and look at some of the other
options on the right-hand side here. So labels allow you to kind of categorize your different issues.
You can have multiple labels on an item, in this case, as an enhancement, so we don't have any code here yet.
You can create your own labels and all that kind of stuff. There is also the concept of milestones.
So milestone is kind of like a container for a bunch of different issues.
So for example, we'll create this issue and we'll go back to the Issues tab and you can actually create a milestone here.
So you can actually group issues and pull requests into a particular milestone and milestones can be time boxed,
so you can say, I want this milestone done by the 7th, and then it's great for things like releases like 2.0
should be released on the 23rd, or it's good for features where you might want to say all these issues relate
to this particular feature, but we're going to say I want all this completed by the end of this session.
Alright, so now I have my issues set up and you can see it maintains like a history of things that are either
referencing it or have been added to it. So now if I set like the milestone, you can say, oh it's been added
to this milestone. I can add a comment like this is a great idea because all my ideas are great ideas.
And then, my favorite new feature is that you can upvote things, so that's pretty awesome, which is actually
kind of helpful when you go and look at an issue and you see how many people have actually said like yeah,
you should probably implement this even though the Issue pane is kind of organized by when it was submitted
sort of thing. So I mean you can reorganize it if you need to, but yeah.
So now that we have an issue, let's actually go out and try to get some code up here.
So you're going to go back to the code tab and there's a couple of buttons here that are helpful.
So right here, this is the actual URL that you can use for any git client, so there is a million git clients out there.
My favorite one is called GitKraken because it's a really cool name.
Then there's this handy button here though that you can click that actually will trigger one of these built-in
tools directly from the website. GitHub desktop is kind of GitHub's official client and then you can use Visual Studio.
I actually have GitHub desktop on here already, so I'll just click that.
It'll ask me launch this application, I'll click that, and GitHub Desktop will pop-up and ask me where I want
to clone this repository. So I'll click OK. So now it's actually cloning the repository out to my local box.
When it does that, I get the entire repository local. So if you haven't used Git before, Git is like a
distributed source control system, so when you clone a repository, you're actually getting an entire copy of
that entire source control system. And it has some links back to where it came from and that's how you sync
back up to your upstream repository. So now I have
my license and readme file available. You can actually go look in my GitHub folder, I have those files locally here.
So I can go ahead and edit that stuff, but let's actually implement our module.
But luckily enough, I already have done that. So I have a module sitting here that all it does is generate
some LoremIpsum text. It has one function in it, it accepts min/max words, min/max sentences,
it has some LoremIpsum text, then outputs that to the command-line when it's done or the output string when it's done.
And as any good developer, I also have some Pester tests I wrote.
So the Pester tests test to make sure that certain things are happening when I am generating this LoremIpsum text.
So what we're going to do is we're actually going to copy these to that folder and if we go look in that
folder now, you'll see that I have these two files, and if we go back to the GitHub client, you'll see here
that now I have these two files as changes in the Changes tab here.
So anything that's marked in green on this right-hand side is an addition.
Anything that would be marked in red is a subtraction, so you can see the changes in the code.
Since I'm just adding two files, the entire thing is green. So first, well what you can actually do is this
is kind of neat is from here you can say Fixes #1. So it's actually going out to GitHub and when you use the
the pound sign, it's looking for that issue number and if you say Fixes #1 because I have now generated this code,
it's going to reference that issue in this commit. So now I've committed it and what you'll notice is you'll
go back out to GitHub and refresh and it's not here. That's because since it's a distributed repository,
you actually need to sync it back up to the upstream repository and there's a handy Sync button right here that
you need to make sure to click after you've done commits.
So you can do a bunch of commits and then sync at a later date. So sync does two things.
It pushes up to the repository and it pulls down from the repository.
So in this case, we don't have any changes that were different from what I had locally.
I am only pushing changes up, so hopefully that happens pretty quickly.
And then up on GitHub, what we should see is now we've updated or added these two files up here.
So once these files are up, you can check on the different commits, you can see all the history of those
files, you can see what was included in each one of these commits, you can actually make comments on each one
of the lines and say like why did you do this or like this was dumb and then write a comment on the entire
conversation or on the entire commit if you wanted to.