So I'm Adam Driscoll. You can talk to me on Twitter if you have ever questions after this or whenever.
Email me. I'm a Senior Application Developer at Concurrency. We're a small little consulting shop out of
the Milwaukee area. I do a lot of like azure and System Center stuff.
I was also the developer for the PowerShell tools for Visual Studio, so that's kind of my open source baby.
And today we're going to be talking about PowerShell Module Development Lifecycle.
So what does that actually mean?
So what we're going to do during this talk is cover these kind of main points.
First of all, I'm just going to kind of talk about what a development lifecycle is and why you want to use
something like this for your PowerShell modules. Then we're going to look at some tooling that you can use
for your development lifecycle. So we're going to start with GitHub issues and milestones.
So I'm going to kind of go over the basics of what that means, how to track requirements, how to do some sort
of design using GitHub. Then we're going to talk about GitHub for source control.
So there's a lot of different source control systems out there. I just picked GitHub for the purpose of this
demo because it's free and available on the internet. So we're going to look at the basics of that, how to get
your code up in there. I'm not going to get into super detailed description of all the things you can do
with GitHub source control because it gets pretty complex. That can be a talk in itself.
From there, we're actually going to talk about AppVeyor. AppVeyor is a continuous integration system that
you can actually hook up to your GitHub repository and it integrates really, really nicely and we're going to
use that for running automated Pester tests and actually yesterday, I added here for deploying to the PowerShell Gallery.
So we're going to use AppVeyor to deploy to the Gallery, so then our module is then available for download
from the gallery. So you can kind of think of this as the entire lifecycle of your module.