Alright, so now we have our module, it's fixed, it's tested, it's running.
I guess I could have showed what a green test looks like. So if it's successful, same thing, Pester output looks
green rather than red so, but now we have this test module that we want to have people use.
So what you're going to want to do is go to the PowerShell Gallery.
So if you haven't gone to the PowerShell Gallery yet, it's powershellgallery.com and what it is it's based
on a technology called NuGet, same thing that Chocolatey is based on and same thing that NuGet's based on
and it's a package management system, so you can upload packages, in this case modules and scripts, and then use
the built-in WMF5 cmdlets and I think they're WMF4 now as well, install module, install script, find module,
and it will actually go out to these repositories and find the modules that are available.
So it'd be great if our module was up here and available for people to easily use when they are just on the
command-line, so they could easily install our LoremIpsum module.
So what you're going to look at is this Publishing tab. So you'll notice that if you want to publish a module,
the thing you want to specify is and you're going to use the Publish-Module cmdlet and you can specify the
name of the module and then a NuGet API key. So a NuGet API key is more or less your identifier for your account.
So if I were to click on my account, you would actually see my NuGet API key, which I'm not going to do because
you've got to treat it like a password because if anyone gets that API key, technically, they could publish
modules as you. So I'm not going to click that, but that's where you'd put that.
So now let's actually go and update our appveyor.yml file to do this.
So if we go back here, run that, and go back here, you can see there's a lot more stuff going on.
The first thing that I'm doing is I'm changing the clone folder. So
I might just not be, I haven't used Publish-Module all that much, so I'm going to be doing something wrong,
but I actually had to mess with it a little bit to get it to work correctly with a path rather than a name.
So if you look at what I'm actually doing with Publish-Module down here, I'm specifying a path and that's
the clone folder that I'm specifying up here. So it'll automatically look in there.
That's what will have my psm1 and my psd1, so that'll all be in there.
The other thing that I added obviously was this deploy script. So the deploy script, the first thing that it
does is it installs a package provider for NuGet, which will also update it to the most recent version,
so it's a step that's required because we are using an image that does not have that in there automatically.
I guess I glossed over the fact that I did change the image, so by default the image is called Visual Studio 2015.
That does not have WMF5 on it. So we'd only actually have the Publish-Module cmdlet in that case.
So what I can do is switch over to the AppVeyor image called WMF5 and it has that available to us.
So then I'm calling Publish-Module. I'm specifying my NuGetApiKey, which is this ApiKey environment variable,
and then the path to my module. So
it's going to go out, it's going to discover that module manifest, it's going to look in there, upload all that
metadata to the gallery, and then make it available for people to install.
And what you're seeing down here is the actual definition of this environment variable.
So what you can do is you can specify an environment tag, the ApiKey, and in this case, I'm using a secure variable.
So this is not my ApiKey. This is an encrypted version of my ApiKey
because if you remember, when I was running my AppVeyor key or AppVeyor builds, you can see all the command-line
output, so we don't want to just dump our key on there for anyone to get access to.
What we want to do is actually use a
secure variable from AppVeyor. So the way that this works is this environment variable when it's actually
running inside AppVeyor, is decrypted. So technically, if I were to just dump that to the command-line and
it printed it out, it would be an unencrypted value.
But it only unencrypts it for builds that are not pull requests.
So if someone forked your repo, changed this script to dump out your API key, submitted a pull request,
which caused an AppVeyor build to run, it won't actually decrypt that key, so you can't have anyone
maliciously trying to get your key out sort of thing. So the only time that it would run would be when you
triggered a build either through a commit directly to master or pulling in that pull request because you've
validated the fact that someone didn't do something malicious with that key.
So to create secure variables, I'll just show you how to do that real quick.
Oh, our build failed. See there our tests failed. I wonder if it fixed them.
Oh yeah, fixing the test did not fix the test, so there's still something wrong there.
And to create an encrypted variable, you can just click on your name, click encrypted data, and just put it
wherever you want in here, click Encrypt, and it'll actually give you the value and what you need to put in
your AppVeyor YAML. So that's really important. I've actually, especially for deployment purposes,
there's lots of reasons that you'd want to do that. For PoshTools, I actually need to do that for the code
signing cert password and stuff like that, so you've got to be really careful because you can shoot yourself
in the foot. I had to rekey my code signing cert like four times because I kept messing this up and dumping
my public key to the AppVeyor log. I'm like ah. Alright, so now that we have that, we can actually check in
our publish, which isn't going to work because our tests are broken, but that's okay.
Publish module. Alright, so submit that. So now that's going to kick off a new build and it's going to take
that extra step of actually publishing it. So I don't know if I actually took a screenshot of that,
but that's okay because I don't want to wait for it to happen anyways.
But once you actually publish something to a gallery, what you'll see is something like this.
So here's our LoremIpsum module that gets published. You can see it got all that metadata from that module
that I generated automatically, so it generates the LoremIpsum text and you can see that now they have functions,
you can click on those, find out more information about that kind of stuff, and it actually has the ability
to copy and paste this and run it, install it, that kind of thing.
One thing you'll note about the PowerShell Gallery is that this module is unlisted.
So when I was making this demo,
I came to the realization that once I published this module, I couldn't delete it.
I was like why is that case. Do you guys remember that MPM thing that happened, or yeah, MPM thing that
happened where that guy unlisted his module from MPM. Did you hear about that?
Yeah, so that's why they do this. So that's why they do this. So you can't actually delete your module.
You can only unlist it, so people can't find it and install it manually.
So I can relist it, so now that makes it publicly available for people to download again.
So yeah, if you didn't hear about that MPM thing, some guy had like a 10-line MPM package that like thousands
of packages---what's that?
(Audience comment)
Seven, yeah. So he got like some guy he had some naming right, he had the naming rights to it pretty much
and some of other company wanted naming rights and what he pretty much said well yeah, if you give me $10,000,
I will let you have the name, and they're like no, and they took away the name from him or whatever, and so he
decided to unlist all his packages, which just broke the world of Linux for a while there.
So that's what we're trying to prevent, I guess, with this. So you can't actually unlist your module once it's
or delete it once it's published.