Remember that we have a broken project right now, we have no tests that are running during the build.
So this would be a great opportunity to actually run some tests as part of our build to make sure that
whenever a developer checks something in, it's not broken.
So what we can do is update our yml file, so let me do that. We come back over here, you can see that I have
added a few more steps to our yml file. The first step is that we need to install Pester.
The AppVeyor image that's running, I think it was like 2012 R2 without Pester installed, but what's really
nice is it comes prepackaged with a bunch of other software including Chocolatey.
So since it has Chocolatey installed, we can actually just say send this to Pester, it'll go up to the Chocolatey
package repository, download Pester, install it, and it's available for us to run tests against.
And then the other section that I added was this test script section.
So test scripts run after the build steps, so if you go look at the AppVeyor documentation, there's all these
different steps that the build process actually takes and the last one that it'll take before deployment is a
test, I guess test up. So in this case,
we're specifying that we want to run a test script because by default what it's trying to do is it's trying
to find .NET assemblies that contain either NUnit or MS Tests in them and then it'll run those automatically.
Well in this case, we kind of have to do some special scripting to get this to work.
So the first line here is, actually stole this from Warren Cookie Monster to do this because it works really well.
And the first step here is to invoke Pester, so we just call Invoke-Pester on the current path and then we
want to output it as an NUnitXml file. So
NUnit, like I said, is a .NET-based unit testing project, but it has kind of like a standard format that lots
of systems integrate with including AppVeyor. So it's really nice that Pester has that because it can
integrate with things like AppVeyor and TFS and all that kind of stuff because they know how to consume that particular format.
I also want to pass it through into a variable so that I can check the actual status later in this script.
The next thing that I want to do is create a new WebClient and upload this file to AppVeyor
and they have a really nice like API, like a REST API that you can deal with for doing all kinds of stuff
like setting different things that appear in the build and uploading tests like this.
So this actually, you go out to the URL, it's /testresult/nunit and then use another one of those built-in
variables, environment variables for the job id. So then AppVeyor, yep go ahead.
I have a stupid question. Where is this stuff running from?
This is running, I think AppVeyor is hosted in Azure.
Alright, yeah so now we're going to find this test result file, upload it up to AppVeyor.
We use the JOB_ID to associate this file back to our job. So
once it's uploaded, then it actually will parse that XML file, discover all the tests listed in there,
and then you can kind of see a nice little GUI in AppVeyor for the tests.
The last line is we want to actually fail the build if the tests fail.
So in this case, we're checking to see what the fail count is and if it's greater than 0, we throw an exception
and that'll actually cause the AppVeyor build to fail and you'll get like a red build up in AppVeyor.
So if we save this, check this in, adding tests, commit that, sync that, and then okay you can see that this
was a previous build that I showed that doesn't do any tests and it succeeded, so we're green right now,
but like we said, it is a broken build. So now we added the tests to the yml file, and it's actually going
to run this build and run the tests. What's going to happen there is you're actually going to see something like
this where you get the output from Pester, and it's kind of cool because it actually formats it like exactly
like you'd see in the PowerShell console and you can see all the tests failed.
In this case, I must have taken this screenshot when I had three tests instead of two, but you can see that
up in the top left where it says broken that it's red. So you'll actually be able to look at the build,
see that it's red, if you had one of those little badges out on the front of your GitHub repository,
it would be red, so it's really obvious when it's broken sort of thing.
So these tests are going to run, they're going to fail, and then what we can do is we can actually go out and
figure out how it broke. So that's where you go back into source control, you can look at the commits,
you can say oh, this guy was fixing the module, what does that mean?
It's like oh. Adam! You're dumb! And then comment on it. And from there, what we can do is we can go and
fix out build again. So I'll go back to our module, bring that guy up, change it back to less than to fix
the tests and hopefully that would fixing the tests. And sync. Alright, so now that commits back up to master
and we go. So that's kind of how you can automate things during the build.
So there's lots of cool stuff that you could do here, not just running tests.
You could run things like script analyzer to have it validate particular things.
You could have it sign your script so that you don't have to worry about doing that locally.
Anything that you could think that you'd have to do to like publish your module before you publish your module,
so that's a great opportunity for the continuous integration system.
What's also really nice is, it's nice for you as a single developer, once you start working with a project
with a lot of developers, that's where it really, really starts to pay off because you have merges happening,
people don't always know exactly what everybody is working on. So when you merge it all together in a continuous
integration system, it's super nice.
The other thing you can do is set up different builds for different branches, have it run on schedules,
that kind of thing, so you can do more complex things maybe once a day or something like that where you run
integration tests and that kind of thing.