Alright, so now let's say I go in here and I am
actually editing my module and for whatever reason, I'm just looking at this and I'm like oh dude, why did you
put less than there, that should be greater than. And I don't have anyone code review this.
I don't run any of the tests. I just change this and I'm like I'm super smart, I'm just going to fixing the module.
So I fix the module, commit it, sync it, everything's happy. I'm a good developer, I'm using source control,
I am done, but the problem is now that I've checked this in, obviously the test is going to fail because all
my tests are going to fail because I've changed this logic that is incorrect, but without any kind of auditing
in place, there's no way for me to know that happened. So what we can do is we can actually integrate with a
continuous integration system. So one available continuous integration system is AppVeyor.
AppVeyor is like it says a continuous delivery service for Windows and it's used by a lot of projects.
It's actually, I'm starting to see a lots and lots of projects using this and it's really cool because it's
free for open source projects. You can pay for plans. I think the big thing with unpaid subscriptions is
you get in a queue and sometimes it takes longer for your build to actually happen.
So once you sign in, you can actually sign in with your GitHub credentials and it's automatically linked to
your GitHub account. And you can see here, I have a couple different builds that I've set up, but what you're
going to want to click is the New Project button. So the New Project button, since it's linked to my GitHub
account, it just lists all the repositories that I have. So now I have my LoremIpsum account and I can just
click this handy dandy Add button here. Alright, so now I have my build set up.
So what you can see here is there's no latest build. It automatically tracks changes in the GitHub repo,
so anytime
I commit a new change to my repo, it will automatically start a build,
but you can modify a lot of those settings here on the right-hand side.
There's a bunch of settings for AppVeyor. I'm not going to go through all these, but there's certain things
like only building certain branches, building only with certain tags, that kind of thing, building on a schedule.
You can also set things like environment, so they have different images that you can work with.
You can set environment variables. You can have it run tests, you can have it run build scripts, you can have
it deploy certain places, so we could automatically have it deployed to GitHub releases or something like that.
And then there's all kinds of other stuff. What's really important is you've got to make sure you get your
cool badge on GitHub repo that the build is passing. And then one recommendation that I always have with
AppVeyor is that you don't actually set all these settings in here and use this because it's really hard to
audit changes inside this GUI. What you want to do is actually make the changes in there, save it, and then grab
the appveyor.yml file.
So YAML is Yet Another Markup Language is what it stands for and it's actually a really simple syntax and it
just the appveyor.yml file can contain all your settings that you would put in this UI.
So then you can check it into your repo and when you put it in the base folder of your repo, what it'll actually
do is read that instead of the settings here and then it'll set up your AppVeyor build based on that, rather than this.
So if we went and actually went and built this, so what you're going to notice is it's going to start a build
and because I'm cheap, I don't actually have a paid subscription for this, so you're going to notice it
queues it, so that's what this status is marked here. It's queued and it's going to flash this little blue thing
until it starts. And then eventually it will finish the build. Luckily, I took some screen shots of this,
so we don't have to wait the entire time for this to happen, but
I'll go back and show you guys as it finishes sort of thing. So what you're going to notice the first time
you build a PowerShell module with AppVeyor without setting any settings is you're going to get an error.
So the error here is that, oh man, error here is that you need to specify a project or solution file.
The directory does not contain a project or solution file. That's because AppVeyor is kind of set up for .NET code.
It's looking for a Visual Studio solution or project in the root directory that it can build, and since we're
building a PowerShell module, we don't have that. So what we need to do is actually change the way that AppVeyor builds.
So there's a couple ways that you can do that. If you look in the settings, you can actually just turn off builds
and then you won't get that error anymore, but it won't do anything.
You could also just run a script and what's nice with AppVeyor is you can select PowerShell script and then
and use whatever cmdlets you want to actually build your PowerShell module.
In this case, you might have noticed that when I was checking, I was creating my module, I don't have a
module manifest here.
So one nice thing that we can do then is during our build, actually generate that module manifest on the fly,
And since the module manifest has a version and AppVeyor has a version, what we can do is we can get that
version dynamically and set it into our module manifest. So
what I did is I actually created a appveyor.yml file and let's take a look at that.
Actually what I'm going to do is copy that into output directory and then open it from there.
Alright, so here's a YML file. It looks very similar to the one that I showed that was up on there.
It sets the version syntax or the form that you want for your version, in this case, it's 1.0, and then this
will increment every build. Then I'm using the build_script keyword and specifying that it's PowerShell
script to call New-ModuleManifest, and in there, I can actually set the module version using the
ModuleVersion parameter and use an environment variable that AppVeyor provides.
So AppVeyor has a bunch of different module or environment variables that you can specify, one of them being
the current build version, so it'll set those before it actually executes anything for your build.
And then I set just a bunch of other properties for my module and what I can do is I can actually go and
check that in, so Adding my appveyor.yml. One thing I noticed that you need to be careful of is make sure
that appveyor.yml is all lowercase. For whatever reason if it's camelcase, it will not work.
Alright, so now go back, okay, so yeah we finally got that error actually in AppVeyor.
What we'll notice here is once this syncs, it actually picked up on the fact that I committed a new change up
to AppVeyor, so now it's actually running a new build up there. So as that goes, what you'll see is it's
going to generate the module manifest and it's going to succeed and it's going to look a lot like this.
So I created a new module manifest, here I'll zoom in on that a little, go, or I won't zoom in on it a little.
Okay. And you can see the whole command-line, which is kind of cool.
So it cloned it, it checked it out, it called New-ModuleManifest, and then the build is success.
It didn't find any tests or anything like that and we're good to go. But---