Alright, so let's switch over to a demo. So if June was here, she'd yell at me because she told me never to
actually type in a demo, so I'm going to do this entire demo typing.
Alright, so the first thing that we're going to do is we're going to use a new class keyword.
New class keyword is really straightforward.
It looks just like you're defining a function, or a workflow, or whatever, a configuration.
And then the name of your type is
what follows, so class Bike. I have a bike. So now what you can see is as simple as that, I have a type defined.
No reason to call Add type, write C# code, specify all kinds of weird string escape characters and stuff like that.
We have a type defined just like a DateTime object. It looks very similar.
Except it won't let me cast that. Right, so it's the same concept.
It's a type available and it's actually a .NET type, so it actually compiles down to actual .NET code.
So now, we want to add some properties to this bike. So what does a bike have?
A bike has maybe a manufacturer, a bike has a model, and a bike has a year.
So we can see here is I've defined different particular properties of this bike.
On the left hand side here you'll see that this is actually a type qualifier.
It specifies what type this variable or property of this object is and if you omit that, which this is optional,
it becomes of type object
and everything in .NET inherits from object because everything is an object.
So then you could assign any particular value to that particular property.
So now if I wanted to create a new instance of my bike, what I could use is New-Object just like any other
.NET type, once my IntelliSense stops, you can see I can create a new instance of that bike and it actually
lists out the properties. I have a manufacturer, a model, and a year.
Not very interesting because none of them are set, but what we could do is you could actually specify default values.
So if I want to say my default value for a year is 2016. So now every time I create a bike, it defaults to
2016, but it doesn't make much sense to have a bike without a manufacturer or a model.
So let's actually create a constructor. A constructor is the method that is called when you actually create
an instance of a class, so Manufacturer. So by default, there's always a default constructor created where
it is just an
empty method with no parameters that does nothing. In this case, this is a non-default constructor and it
requires that you pass in two parameters.
So now what we're going to do is we're actually going to want to set the manufacturer and model on this
instance of the object and that's where you use this keyword. This keyword is referring to the current instance
of this class, so in this case, I would say this.Manufacturer and then I'd take the value that was passed in
for the constructor. So now if I go to actually create my bike, what you'll see is you'll see an error
because it says that the constructor was not found.
Since we overrode the default constructor, we can no longer create this object without specifying those two parameters.
So if we ever use a New-Object to actually create objects, what you can do is you can say -ArgumentList and
then pass in two arguments. So now I when I create my bike, it has a manufacturer, it has a model,
and it has a year, so that's really cool. While we're on the topic of creating new objects,
let's actually check out one of the new operators that's available in PowerShell.
So if you haven't seen this syntax before, it's actually a new syntax that was added in PowerShell v5 to
actually create objects, so instead of having to use the New-Object cmdlet, you can use this shortened
syntax where you say the type name followed by two colons and then new
and pass in the arguments that you're going to call the constructor.
So I'll just kind of shortens the syntax is another way to create, but does
the exact same thing that a New-Object does.
Alright, so let's make this bike do something. So one thing that bikes is that they pedal.
So let's create a Pedal method. So pedal or methods look a lot like functions.
They have the function name Pedal and then two parentheses or you could put arguments and then a method body.
You can see I put void in front of there.
Void is the return type of this particular method, so with methods, you always need to specify a return type,
otherwise it doesn't know what it is. So in this case,
we say method void. We're not going to return anything from Pedal, but we want it to do something.
So okay. We want it to increase the speed. Every time you pedal it, let's increase the speed.
So I create a Speed property and then let's set the speed, whoops, not ComSpec, whoops, I have to say this.
I always have to say this. Alright, so now, I increase the speed every time I call pedal.
So let's create a new bike, start a new variable, and we can call pedal on it now, and we can dump.
Alright, so now you can see that when I pedal my bike,
the speed goes up. There's one problem with our speed variable though.
I can just set speed to whatever I want. Now my speed is 100, I don't have to pedal anything.
I wish my bike at home worked that way, right? But to alleviate that problem, what we want to do is this is where
the concept encapsulation comes into play. We want to hide this speed and variable.
So now when I try to run this, you can see that speed is no longer available because it's hidden.
And it no longer lets me set the speed because it's hidden and only that particular instance of that object can
modify the speed
and that allows us to control the internal state of this object and not allow people to mess with our speed
without calling pedal.
But let's say I wanted to get the speed. I do still want to know how fast I'm going, so let's put a little
speedometer on there. So we can say int GetSpeed return this.Speed.
Alright, so this is a definition of a method that has a return value.
You can see instead of void, I'm doing int because I'm going to be returning an integer
and I'm using the return statement to actually return that internal variable.
So although we can't set speed from outside the object, we can actually
return the actual value of speed via this function here now. So with this pedal there, you can see now it
returned that my speed is 1 because I pedaled once with that bike.
So a couple interesting notes about methods and partial classes, you need the return statement.
If I get rid of this return statement, you can see it's going to give me an error that it says not all code
paths return a value within this method. It's required to return a value if you are specifying a return type like this.
And when it says not all code paths, you have to make sure that if you have if L statements
and maybe return something in the if statement, but not in the L statement, it will still give you that error
because you are required to return something from this method.
The other thing to note is that the return statement itself is required.
If you were actually writing a function in PowerShell, you wouldn't have to use a return statement to get
something to return from that method, which is another really interesting difference between PowerShell
methods and PowerShell functions. So if I had a function that was called GetSpeed and I did the same thing
where I just said speed, which would be like 1, and I called GetSpeed, it doesn't give me any errors,
I can run this and it outputs 1. But the other thing that's interesting is that I do 1 here an then 1 here
and call GetSpeed, what do you expect? It's going to return 2 right because you're jumping 2 objects to the
pipeline in this case. So you got 2, 2 1s. If I do the same thing up here where I put 1 in there and call
GetSpeed, I only get 1.
That's because the PowerShell methods don't actually have access to dump things to the PowerShell stream or the pipeline.
So it doesn't---that 1 is just thrown away when that's executed.
And what's interesting about
PowerShell methods as well is that they're actually ScriptBlocks.
They are not compiled completely to .NET code, so you can use things like other cmdlets.
So in this case, I called GetSpeed and I actually wrote to the host and said Hey and it returned 1.
So there's a couple of gotchas with using methods. So it is PowerShell, but it needs to be formatted in a
specific way to kind of play in the .NET world, so
that's how that works. Alright, so let's look at one more concept, kind of basic concept that I want to talk about
and is that the fact that we can actually create enumerations.
I think he has a question. Oh, sorry. Go ahead. Is there any other way to create more of like a read-only
type property where you still want to see it as a property, but not have it modifiable?
That is a really good question. I did not find a good way to do that.
(Audience comment) No, there isn't. Okay. So this kind of reminds me of Java.
You can do static, yep. Can you do static properties? Yep. (Audience comment)
Yeah, so this would be a static property. No, that's in C#. Sorry, go ahead.
Can you do more than one overload, but where you say New bike and you do it with the one variable, rather than two?
Yep. So overloaded or nothing exactly. So if you were to just get rid of maybe you didn't want manufacturer
in there and just wanted the model. Yep. Yep, you could do that or you could nothing.
You could put back in the original with nothing. You could do bike.
Oh, yeah right. Like this. Yeah, then you put your default back again.
Yep, exactly.
One other question. After you've defined the class of what variable, can you still look at the Speed property
by just a $bypass speed? No. So if I went Bike.Speed, oh wait, maybe you can.
It doesn't make sense though. Do you know why that is Jeff?
That seems like a bug? Well normally what I do is I would write this separate function which would just take
the parameter and then brings up a class and then call repetitive. Right.
If you create a function and it takes a parameter to the bike and then I can just call the internal method of the class.
Ultimately, you don't want to have to be mucking around writing code like that.
You want to build _____ and you want to build functions that someone can use and then call all this that
you're typing now. This is a demonstration. Right. I'm really surprised you could access this because it
should be hidden. Can you do status also? I think if you do like bike Select *, it would do the same thing
Bike Getspeed down. Oh, I got you. That's interesting. Do a GetMember to that line -Force.
Ha ha. Interesting. So it is hidden. It's hidden. It's there, it's available.
But then you can Stop, right. I would say yeah, you probably can just hide it too.
Did you read class? Uh, huh. The class is being created every time.
So it really is hidden. It's not actually private. Right, okay.
(Audience comment) Oops. Yeah, not really it. (Audience comment)
Right, unless do -force and then it will be there. You could probably do it with Bike.Speed = 100.
Yep. Interesting. We're all learning today. You could always make it a static pin.
Should be able to. Yep. So then you could go Bike Speed = 100.
Yeah because it's no longer part of the actual object. It's part of the class itself and you can mark it static.
Alright. Huh? (Audience comment) It returned 0, which is kind of surprising because well it didn't find that,
so it probably returned the default value because it didn't know what speed it was.
But if I did something like, yep, so I did Bike Speed here and then…
(Audience Comment) We found this object. (Audience Comment) Oh, you're right.
(Audience discussion) Right. Yeah, pedals broke this. Right. Or we can assign it.
Yeah, sorry. Alright, okay.