So if we jump back to here, let's actually go into WindowsPowerShell Modules, this is a DSC resource for Hyper-V.
You can see that it has a DSCResources folder, under there it has more folders for the different types of resources.
Each one of the resources is made up of a MOF file, so now all of a sudden you're going to be in this MOF syntax
where you need to specify all these particular attributes, you have to extend from OMI_BaseResource,
it's just really hard syntax to kind of try to remember. And then when you want to implement the script,
the actual details of that particular DSC resource, what you need to do is actually create three particular
functions, you need to create Get-TargetResource, Set-TargetResource, and Test-TargetResource to be able to
actually work with that particular resource and our DSC configuration.
But with partial classes, they make it a lot easier. So I actually have a DSC resource I made with the new
PowerShell class syntax. So you can see here that the way that you do this is you actually, is that big enough,
okay, you use the same class keyword, and in this case, I have a light.
So I have some like special lights at my house that I can control from the internet, which is a horrible idea,
but you just put a DSC resource attribute on the top of it to signify that this is a DSC resource.
One thing that's required is a DSC property that is marked as a key, in this case, it's the name of the item
or the name of the light in the house and it can be a string or an integer.
From there you can add all the properties that you want. You can specify different types.
You can actually specify enum values and then you're required to implement three different methods.
The first method is set, so obviously that updates it through the state that you set it to,
test tests to see if it's in the state that you require it, and then Get just returns that particular
resource in light. So these signatures are required to be in this state for this to work and that is kind of
how that works. So like in this case, it's just going out to the internet and actually setting these things.
And then the other side of things is just the manifest file that you need to make sure that you actually
don't do that. When you create a new module manifest, there's a new property called DSCResources to explore,
which apparently is not in here. I've actually installed this DSC resource already.
I'll show you an example of how I use it. You know, let's actually open this one, something like that.
Alright, so just like you would create any other configuration, you create a configuration, in this case,
I'm just naming it Lights, and then you want to call Import-DscResource.
So Import-DscResource looks
in two places for your DscResource. It is going to look on a system-wide modules folder in system32 and MOF64
and it's going to look in program files for that particular resource.
It's not going to look in any of your user level resources because LCM runs as the system user.
And then you can see that I'm just using that resource as is. So in this case, I'm using my light resource
and I want to turn on the Basement Light, that's the key. This is the URL; it's going to turn Bill's
basement light on. And then I want to set it to ON sort of thing.
From there, we run lights and then we start the DscConfiguration, so I can run that, and you can see that it
is now running that DscResource that we just created. So we actually went out and okay, I want the lights,
you can see it created the mof file and we look in here you can see it looks like just any other DscResource.
It's actually using that Light resource to send a Url to state and that kind of thing.
Yeah, and I ran it on this computer. So that is how you kind of define DSC resources in PowerShell.
So it's a lot more straightforward than the actual MOF format that you saw previously.
Alright, I feel like I totally missed something.