Yeah, now that we've experimented with hidden, I'm going to get into another example.
Let's create a VideoGameConsole. So a VideoGameConsole has what, a company that makes it, another string,
and a string that makes it and a name to it how about. So now we can actually go off and we can create
VideoGameConsole. Simple enough right? Let's create a constructor that does that, so Company and Name,
and then this.Company = Company and this.Name = Name. Alright, so now I can't create it without those two things.
But let's say we wanted to actually create a I guess more specific version of a VideoGameConsole, so just like
you can create a video game, let's extend from VideoGameConsole, which is our base class now.
So in this case, if I wanted to create an Xbox, what I can actually do is I can say VideoGameConsole and this
is the syntax that you use to actually extend from another class, so in this case, Xbox is a more specific
version of a VideoGameConsole. It's still a VideoGameConsole, but it has its own properties to it.
And you can see what's happening here is the base class VideoGameConsole does not contain the parameter of this constructor.
Just like we had an issue when we were calling new before, in this case, it can actually even define this new
class because it needs to call the correct constructor and since video or Xbox has a parameter
list constructor, it causes this error. So what we need to do is actually call the correct constructor for
the base class. So this is the syntax for that. So I say Microsoft Xbox and what this actually does,
Xbox, I think that's here. (Audience Comment) Parentheses after Xbox.
(Audience Comment) Oh, yeah duh. Thank you. Yeah. Alright, so you can't create a VideoGameConsole.
It still gives an error, but now I can create an Xbox because the Xbox because the Xbox actually passes in
the values to the
base classes constructor. It sets the values and then when it's written out to the screen, we can actually,
we have an Xbox.
And the thing about this is you can say, well is this a VideoGameConsole?
Of course it is. It comes from VideoGameConsole. But is this an Xbox?
Of course it is an Xbox because it's a more specific version of a VideoGameConsole.
So on the same vein, what we can do is you can actually create a new VideoGameConsole.
So if I wanted to create a Playstation, what I could do is replace all the important pieces and now I have Playstation.
So is a Playstation Xbox? No. But is a Playstation a VideoGameConsole?
Yes because they both inherit from the same base class. So one thing that VideoGameConsoles can do is they
can actually let's say draw their logo. So to draw a logo, what do we do?
We need to maybe find some ASCII drawing program on the internet that can convert logos into ASCII in PowerShell
and then maybe I have that snippet here. (Audience Comment) Alright, so the contents of a draw logo look like this.
They take in that ascii.ps1 file, they grab some Xbox.gif that I had sitting around, and then they call
that to actually draw this. So let's actually switch out here. Save this because one thing you'll notice is
I am using PSScriptRoot in this particular method and that's actually global scope variable for this
particular script, so that's why I had to save it. So now if I do, if I want to call that what I can use
down here is change this back to Xbox since that's where it's defined and DrawLogo, which is neat.
So save that and, oops don't, save that powershell MyDemo and that didn't work the same way that it worked last time.
(Audience comment) I would if it would draw in the ISE. Aw, that looks horrible.
But you can see it took the actual Xbox logo and it drew it in ASCII inside PowerShell.
Okay, kind of neat trick, but now let's say we want to go out and do the same thing in the Playstation class.
So like any good developer, what do we do? Copy and paste the code, put it in the Playstation class.
All we need to do, right, is change the Playstation logo. So let's say we have Playstation.png, change that,
let's change this to a Playstation, save it. We're on our little gimmick again and you can see it drew the
Playstation logo rather than the Xbox logo because it's a different class implements that.
Could you put that like in the base class and move that down so you can…
And for my next trick. So what we're going to do so that we don't need to do that is do exactly what you
just said is take that, put it the base class because we don't want to reimplement all that logic again, alright,
so that's why we do that. What we can do is actually make that hidden and then let's just have a file path here,
rather than having to pass in or have to reimplement all this logic over and over again.
What we can do is we can actually just call this. So get rid of all this and we can say this.DrawLogo,
pass in Xbox.gif, grab that, put that in Playstation as well, and now we don't have to worry about
reimplementing all that logic because twice as much code, twice as many bugs and you change that for whatever
reason you have to redo it over again. So you can see now it still works the exact same way, but all the
implementation details are up in the actual DrawLogo implementation inside VideoGameConsole.