So this is all really cool and you can do all kinds of cool stuff with PowerShell classes, but the other thing
that you can do is you can actually extend from .NET classes.
So what we could do is you could say class DoubleList and there's a nifty little thing that you can do now,
using namespace System.Collections.Generic. So using namespace, have you ever had to type out a really long
type name like that before? So what using namespace allows you to do is to not have to do that, so like if I
did New-object -type name, I could just do List int right? If IntelliSense ever worked.
And it didn't actually, he'll actually go back to that. So that works because I'm using a namespace now,
so it shortens all those namespaces, so this is kind of a concept that's always been in C# and vb.net where
you can kind of shorten namespaces without having to type it out throughout your entire script.
But if we wanted to actually extend from a list like that what we could say is DoubleList.
I think there's a bug here I was going to email people about. I'm going to actually take this again and
we're going to extend from that class. So now we have this DoubleList class.
We say new-Object DoubleList. That works because it is just a more specific version of a generic list that
has integer types. But let's say we wanted to double all the input as we add it to that particular list.
So what we're going to do with our new method and we're going to say add, we want to take an integers of some
value and we want to add it to the list. So there's this really cool syntax that you have to use to actually
get to the base class where you actually say List int this .Add value.
So what this actually does is it actually casts this variable into the base class' type and then calls
that version of Add. Otherwise, you're going to end up calling yourself and it's going to be recursive.
So in this case, what we want to actually do is multiply by 2. So every time I call add, call the base class'
version, but before we do that actually multiply it by 2. So we create a DoubleList, something like that,
like DL.Add 2, DL and I can see it outputs 4. So this is an example of how we can actually extend from .NET types.
So we can do all kinds of things like
I've seen examples of people extending from Windows forms controls to do new user controls, to do new Windows,
that kind of thing, without having to do any kind of add type stuff, so that is an example of that.
Alright, so now I kind of want to talk about DSC resources and why we have PowerShell classes at all.