Alright. Today, we're going to be talking about getting started with classes in PowerShell v5.
So my name's Adam Driscoll. I was a PowerShell VPM, a cloud and data center MVP.
I work for a consulting firm out of the Milwaukee, Wisconsin area.
I do a lot of system center and Azure kind of stuff. I also worked on the PowerShell tools for Visual Studio,
so you might have seen that around, so started that project. Thank you very much.
So you'll be seeing that in the next couple versions of Visual Studio, I hope.
And yeah, so I'm a senior application developer at Concurrency.
So getting started with PowerShell classes. I kind of want to talk a little bit about object-oriented design
just because to understand exactly what classes are, you kind of need to understand a little bit about object orientation.
So the idea with object orientation is that it's a programming paradigm based on the fact that everything is
an object, so you don't just have functions and scripts and variables, you have these objects that have
particular properties or fields related to them, so that kind of maintains the state of those objects.
You also have functions or procedures often called methods in the .NET world and that is actually processes
that take place on that object. That object might be able to interact with other objects, it may change the
state of that particular object, but everything is composed of an object.
So when you start thinking about classes, you can kind of think of a class as a blueprint.
So this is a blueprint for a G.I. Joe Crossfire. So you can look at the blueprint.
It's like calling different things out in different states of this object.
It has four wheels. It can be on and off. It can be turning left or right.
It has a particular speed. Those would be the different properties of this particular G.I. Joe car.
The other thing that it does is it has different functions that you can apply to it, so you can turn it left,
you can turn it right, you can go forward and back, probably can shoot the gun or something like that.
Those are the different methods for this G.I. Joe car.
When your actually create an instance of that G.I. Joe car,
that is an object. So it's based on that particular blueprint, but you can create many objects based on that blueprint.
So when we define classes, that's what we're defining. We're defining that blueprint for the G.I. Joe car
and then when we actually create them with cmdlets like New-Object, we're actually creating instances of that
G.I. Joe car.
So there's a couple benefits of OOP that are kind of important to note when kind of getting into object-oriented programming.
The first is encapsulation, and inheritance, and then polymorphism.
So they're kind of some of the basic terms that you'll hear when researching OOP.
So the first is encapsulation. So this looks like a mess and you probably have no idea what it's doing,
it's hard to figure out. You'd have to know exactly what all those wires were doing to be able to do anything
with this particular circuit here. The same goes for scripts, so
you know, I've written scripts where everything's a global variable and you're just hacking out functions
and it gets really messy, really quickly and you hand it off to your coworker, they can't figure it out
because they have to know exactly about everything about that script to be able to work with it the same and
that's why we have this concept of encapsulation in classes. So the idea being is you have something like this
where on the left hand side is the inside of that Wii remote. There are all kinds of circuits,
there's different resistors and capacitors, there's the gyro for like moving your hand around and stuff,
but you don't really need to know how that works to be able to use a Wii remote.
You just flick your wrist, press a button, and that's because all that logic is encapsulated inside of
that remote and then we have a simple interface on the outside of it.
The same goes for classes. You have simple methods, simple states, but all the logic is kind of hidden within
that particular object. The other benefit that we get is inheritance.
So not quite as the same as inheriting money, but the idea with inheritance is that you have base classes and
base classes have particular
properties that you can inherit from other classes. So on the top here we have a wagon.
The wagon has wheels, you can steer it, that kind of thing, but what you can do is you can think of other
four-wheel vehicles. There are more specific versions of a wagon.
They introduce new functionality. They behave a little bit differently.
They might look different. So on the left of a car, it's got an engine, it still has four wheels, it can still
steer, but it's a more specific version of a wagon. On the right-hand side, you have a four-wheel bike.
You pedal it, you can still steer, and from there, you can actually base class it down to even more specific
versions, flying cars or Teslas, a bike with a little roof on top of it, so you don't get wet in the rain.
But it's the same core concept and the same properties that are available in the base class are also available
in all the classes below it.
So I want to show you some examples of how we can create base classes and how we can inherit that
functionality, so we don't have to reimplement the concept of a wheel in all our classes.
Finally, there's polymorphism. So polymorphism is kind of the idea that you can extract away some of the
implementation details based on those base classes. So a
good example is an example of remotes. So all these remotes do different things.
All these, I think the one on the left is maybe a TV remote, middle is a receiver, and the right one is a
Direct TV remote. They all have different buttons, they look really complicated,
but they all do a similar thing. They all come from a base class remote that can turn on a device,
they all have a power switch. So the idea being is you can hand it
to someone like grandma and say, I just want you to know about the power script or the power switch.
You are a remote that can turn things on and off and that's all you need to know.
So we can do something similar with classes where we'll be able to pass base class implementations to other
classes and they only need to know about the very basics of the class and not all the other details that come
along with it. And I'll get into some examples. And I'm going to run this mostly as a demo, so I encourage
you guys to ask questions and I'm just going to kind of go with the flow.
But why do we want classes in PowerShell? For a long time, .NET developers, in general, who have gone from
like a C# background and come into PowerShell and been like we want classes.
And we want classes because we want to integrate with .NET better.
We want classes because we want to write something that's familiar to us rather than just scripts and modules
and that kind of thing. But the real reason that classes eventually got implemented was for the implementation
of DSC resources.
So if you've ever implemented a DSC resource, script-based DSC resource, it takes quite a few steps and you
have to actually use the MOF file format to author your class and it makes you get out of PowerShell,
you have to do two different things to import it and everything, so it takes a couple steps and it's not
really PowerShell friendly. So that's how we got classes in PowerShell was to implement DSC resources and
I'll show you guys some examples of that.
And then finally, we can take advantage of some of those object-oriented techniques I just talked about
actually extend from classes in the .NET framework, implement interfaces so that we can call particular we're
not be able to call previously in PowerShell.
So we are kind of entering a different realm in terms of PowerShell authoring.