Let's slip back to the presentation. So that was kind of my demo and everything.
I want to kind of leave it open for questions. I know there were some in between.
Yep.
I was wondering about deriving like constructors. Can you do that as well?
So like say you had like your base class has got whatever kind of copy or something and a constructor for that,
that sets off my properties or whatever, then you want to basically like extend that and add another class
with a few more properties. Do you inherit that constructor? In terms of inherit, you would call it from
the other constructor. You wouldn't really inherit from it. So you had, just kind of like how I showed
before where you call it with that base keyword, so if you had Class2 and Class1, you would actually have
to call it with that base keyword where you'd say Class1 base and then call anything in there sort of thing,
if that makes sense. Yeah. But yeah. Any other questions?
Yep. Probably a great person to ask, do you know if there's ever going to be a merge in Visual Studio code
and the ISE? If you were in David Wilson's session earlier today, that's kind of his goal.
So I would definitely watch that session when it gets up on YouTube because that's what he talked about.
The PowerShell editor services are kind of where everything is heading, so hopefully we're going to have one
editor service to rule them all sort of thing. If you actually get the latest preview that's going to be
coming out soon, you'll actually be able to say File, instead of New PowerShell Tab, there's a new PowerShell
Experimental Tab and
that is actually using the new editor services, so that's a good way that the community can start to test
those editor services. Let me ask you answer your question more directly.
We're not merging the two editors, we're just going to share a lot of the…
Yeah, okay. Sorry. I didn't realize you were sitting right there.
Mission accomplished. Yeah, right. Cool.
Cool, well thanks for coming and I
hope you have a great rest of your conference.