Now downsides. One, I'm not actually sure if you can do this in
version 5 right now because v5 introduced this new encryption, so the MOF files actually sit on the drive
encrypted, and I'm not sure if it would be feasible for your local crazy resource to get that same certificate
and encrypt them. It should be. I just haven't really dug into that.
It should be possible because they're not encrypted on the pull server, right.
They come across the pull server in clear text. Now they do that across an HTTPS channel because none of us
are dumb enough to run an HTTP pull server, right? Right. Right.
So they come across clear text through an SSL channel. The LCM is what's encrypting them to begin with.
Therefore, that certificate has to be somewhere on the machine we can get to it; therefore, crazy resource should
be able to A, decrypt it because the LCM has to be able to decrypt it, but crazy resource should definitely be
able to create a dynamic MOF, encrypt it, and then stick it in pending MOF, and then the LCM will copy it to
current, and then read it. Make sense? Seem plausible? Are there tools?
Are there any tools. Wow. Wow. Are there any tools for making MOFs?
Yeah, configuration scripts. That's not a flip answer. Right, because if crazy resource is a configuration
script, then PowerShell knows how to run configuration scripts and make MOFs.
Or if crazy resource has the ability to .source a configuration script to run it, it will produce a MOF.
Right, .source this file, run it, blah, MOF occurs. Right now, that's the only reliable tool we have for
making a MOF. Another downside is troubleshooting. It's going suck.
It's complicated. It's going to suck. It's going to be complicated.
There's a lot of moving pieces and here's the downside. Anytime you've got logic running at the furthest
point from you, it's harder. So if you were to do this, you'd really, really have to be disciplined about
logging, really disciplined about logging, ideally, into the event log because you can get to that remotely
fairly easily. Worst case, dumping stuff into a file that's in a well-known location so you can get to it,
you're going to have to log the snot out of stuff. How many of you are used to producing like nuts verbose
logs in your scripts. Yeah, the rest of you need to get to a point where you can raise your hands on that question
because it's going to need a lot of logging to do this. Now if you modularize that, if crazy resource is
doing five different things, mapping a printer, doing whatever crazy stuff it's doing, if you modularize that
really well, it should be easy to test those functions in standalone in a variety of situations,
run them through Pester tests, make sure they work before you deploy them.
Test your code. Okay. A couple folks looked surprised when I said that, so I just want to make sure.
Logging is going to be really, really important. The application of that MOF, right, so we created the
dynamic MOF, now the LCMs going to run. Ideally you want your resources, whatever resources are being called
by that dynamic MOF whether it's a Microsoft resource or one you've written your own, you want it to be
spewing a lot of log data too, like to the debug log or something like that, to the point where if you're using
one of the Microsoft ones and you don't feel it logs enough, you're need to walk your butt up to GitHub,
fork the project, add a ton of logging, and then do a request for them to pull it back in.
Wow. You have two lines of logging for every line of code. Yep, that's okay.
That's just what I feel we need. So I mean a lot of logging is going to have to be necessary here.
You guys don't look scared enough.