Hello. My name is Don Jones. Welcome to Stupid DSC Tricks. So this is not kind of a standard session that
you might have already gotten used to in your short time here at summit.
We're not going to look at a lot of code, and we're not going to do a lot of demo, and we're also not going to
do a lot of slides. We're hopefully, going to do a lot of talking and discussing.
As a, I've been working with DSC for a couple years it's been out now, right, v4, you spend a lot of time
talking to different people who kind of have the base idea of what DSC is supposed to do like from a business perspective.
Alright, for example, one of the things you can tell people is look DSC is at the end of the day very similar
to Group Policy, right? You're going to have this policy-based thing that tells your computers how to,
what to be, and you're going to ship it out through some magically method and the computer will just do that stuff.
So I mean super, super high-level, very similar. And so they start digging into it, well can I do this,
can I do this, well no, I mean not really how it's designed. You've got to rethink your philosophy.
So over the past month or so, Murawski, Dave Wyatt, and I have kind of been having this informal bounce back
and forth Exchange about some of the ways we could get DSC to do stuff that maybe it wasn't specifically
designed to do. Not that it's bad, but kind of hacking it. Like where could we really just like jam your
fist in its mouth and make it do what you wanted it to whether it wanted to or not and that kind of spilled out.
We have a private Slack channel for the folks that come to my DSC DevOps camp.
It's about 20 folks who were there last year, and so these are folks who have their brains connected to
PowerShell 24/7 and they're doing DSC and they're doing DevOps and they're running into the problems and
they're trying to get creative about solving the problems and everything else, and so we start going back and
we start kind of coming up with ideas of ways we can do different stuff that when you look at the DSC PowerPoint
slide, you're like no, it could never do that, but maybe it could.
So I thought this would kind of be a nice place because I know a lot of you---how many of you are using PowerShell?
Oh, that's reassuring. Good, that did not happen the last time I did this.
And how many of you are using DSC? Even just fussing with it in a pilot?
Okay, good. So I thought this would be a good crowd to bounce some ideas off of and maybe have folks say
well what about how could you do this and see if we can come up with some approaches, right.
So that's kind of what we're doing.
Oh, by the way, you guys have seen this slide before, right. Quick round of applause for all the folks who've…
I'm really proud of the fact that---I don't know if you know, it's a little bit rare on a lot of product
teams at Microsoft for people to stick around for a decade. Alright, it's an easy company to move around and
you want to move onto something exciting and new, so it's pretty cool that there are so many people who've been
around that long.
So this is really meant to be kind of a brainstorming session, a think-outside-the-box session.
Let's talk about some things that we'd love for DSC to be able to do for us as a business,
right, forget the technology. Anything should be possible if we have enough money.
So let's just think about what we want it to do and then get a little bit outside the envelope and think
about how we could force it to do it. So I'll kind of kick things off with an example, which is
this one, dynamic printer mapping. Now talk yourself through how DSC works, right.
You sit on your computer, you, the author, you sit on your computer, and you type out a PowerShell script,
a configuration script, right, and it can have lots of logic in it.
You can have if blocks and loops and all kinds of crazy stuff in there, yeah, and you push run, and what's it produce?
MOF. MOF. One or more MOFs, right, Management Object Format, MOF file.
A MOF file is just text file. It's not code. Now you can have little snippets in there if you do a certain
type of resource called the script resource, but generally speaking, a MOF is static.
This MOF is what I want that computer to look like and I created that description completely out of context.
I didn't run it on that computer. I'm running it at a totally different place in time.
I'm just giving it to that computer and that computer then runs that, but the computer doesn't think about it.
Right, the MOF says you need to be a domain controller. You need this IP address, you need to be running
these services, you need these files copied over, don't ask questions, don't make decisions, don't think about
it, I'm not interested in your opinion, just do it. Now what we tell people is in a server workload,
that's kind of okay, right, because servers we tend to set them up, we want them one way, and then we try
really hard to make them never change, right, that's why we have ITIL, right, stop all change.
That's what that means. And but it doesn't apply so well to client scenarios because clients are,
client computers, well who uses a client computer? Users, right, and they're squishy.
They're people. They move around, they get up, they change jobs, they install Elf bowling,
they uninstall this, there are changes. Well one of the neat things about Group Policy is you don't actually
set up all the policy decisions up front. Some of the decisions get made by the client as it downloads it,
right, what organizational unit are you in, what domain are you in, what site are you in, what user groups
are you in, what WMI filter type things are going on? So it can be very, very kind of dynamic and customized
and the Group Policy you get today might be slightly different from the one you get tomorrow.
Well that's not what DSC really does. DSC just says be this always.
Now obviously there's certain client's computer scenarios, you think kiosks or if you work at a bank and
you've got those floors full of phone slaves, you want all those computers to be exactly the same all the
time, sure, but most users are squishier than that. And so, one example is dynamic printer mapping.
Now if I'm writing a DSC configuration script, I can certainly have a printer resource that says install such
and such printer. Right, no problem. But if I tell you to install the printer for Building A and you run
over to Building B for a week, how do I get you a printer over there?
Right, it's not---there's no evaluation. The LCM, the Local Configuration Manager, as it's reading that MOF
doesn't have the ability to say alright we're going to do printer mapping now, so it says map into Printer A,
but gosh, I just know he's not over in that building right now, so I'm going to pick a different printer.
It doesn't do that. There's no logic in the LCM, it's just following a set of instructions and calling a
bunch of resources. So this is one of the first problems we started down because it's one of the first
things that comes up in a discussion when you're trying to explain to someone why DSC and Group Policy are
different, and we thought we could totally do this with DSC, completely.
How? All we have to do is write a resource that dynamically maps printers based on some criteria.
So in your configuration script, you say whatever the resource name is, map a printer, yes, map nearest printer,
yes, and that's all that goes into your MOF. Your MOF just knows that it's supposed to map a printer.
That's it. The MOF doesn't know where the printer is, doesn't know where it should map it to, it doesn't care
about any of that, so when you compile that MOF, you create that text file, you slam it out to all your nodes,
it runs a DSC resource, which is just PowerShell code, or can be, right, and that PowerShell code goes oh,
okay, I'm supposed to map a printer, great. What's my IP address right now?
Let me go see what Active Directory site I'm in. I can figure that out locally.
I can actually go see a list of published printers in Active Directory and find one that's near me and I'm
going to go ahead and map that. So the dynamism, in that case, lives on the client computer.
It's not in the LCM. The LCM is still relatively dumb, but the LCM is calling on a smarter friend who can
make that runtime decision. And we started thinking it was some of the ramifications of that, right,
because you have that idea and then you put your third drink down and you start to think is this a good idea,
and after three drinks, obviously it's a great idea. So the next morning we thought, alright, so what are
some of the ramifications of this. Well how often does the LCM run a consistency check, by default?
Fifteen minutes. Is it going to be bad for that thing to be constantly trying to remap a printer?
Well, if you have it go look at what printer it should map and then just check to see if that one's already
mapped, and if it is, well don't do anything, which is how resources are supposed to be written, right.
Don't do anything until you test first, right, run test. Only run set if you have to.
Well, maybe that wouldn't be too bad. And we actually---how many of you work for healthcare?
Yep, there's always a couple. We actually thought, you know what, this would actually solve a couple of really
cool scenarios because you get into a hospital situation and the doctor runs from room to room to room and he's
logging on different profiles, but he wants his profile to be mapped to the printer that's in that room right
then, so he's not printing out someone's personal information six rooms down, right, so we thought actually
this whole really frequent dynamic remapping thing in certain scenarios could be kind of cool.
But we stopped thinking about that because healthcare freaks us all out because blood, gross.
So what do you think? Comments? Have anybody ever thought of going after it that way?
One thing you're going to have to think about is unmapping a map for…
Oh, and when do I unmap it? Yeah. We thought about that too. Partially, we weren't sure if we cared or not
because I guess what it was is in that we figured if the test runs and you're mapped to the one you should be,
don't do anything, but if you're not, then just go unmap whatever was there and then map whatever you should
be right then. It kind of depends on the business situation, right.
If you've got some HR person who's got a local printer you don't want to unmap, you'd have to have some way
of accounting for that, yeah. Yeah, we kind of walked through that a little bit.
What else? What if you're not on the network? What if you're not on the network?
Well then you're not going to be printing, so it's not a problem.
(Audience comment) Well yeah, it might. That, again, all gets down to your test, right, or your set.
We had a little bit of argument about where we'd put those. I think we eventually decided maybe both.
But your set should certainly say look are we even on a network here?
I mean maybe we don't have the right printer, but is it even possible, and if not, forget it.
That's more doing exactly the right thing is what you're doing, is you're now, what are the failure scenarios
I might run into and let's account for those, so we're not just spewing errors into the log, but yeah,
you do have to walk through that. What else? You might be able to develop some tests, I mean, I'm not on
the network, I have no printer, I mean that's what the test would look at.
Yeah and that was actually my argument is in the test, first check to see if I can even possibly get to a
valid state, and if I'm not, just say true, so we don't even run the set.
(Audience question) Yeah, so how do you determine the locality to a printer?
That's your problem, right. And I say that with all love, but the fact is, we're all going to have a
different set of business rules for how we do that and what we're talking about here is you're going to have
to build a certain amount of infrastructure potentially to let you do that.
Some people might have databases. Some people might have something they put into Active Directory.
I've got plenty of customers who don't have all their client computers in Active Directory, and so they're
going to have to have some other place to look it up. Maybe there's a SQL Server.
Maybe you've got some back-end tool or something. So yeah, you're going to have to do all that, right,
those are things. I don't call them challenges, they're just part of what you would have to solve as part of it.
What if say your nearest printer is down. Now see but let me pause you real quick.
Before we go down the rabbit hole of making this a printer mapping session, I want to point out that what you
guys are thinking about are the right questions. We're not trying to solve the printer mapping module here today.
What we're trying to do is make DSC do stuff that it is initially not designed to do.
All of those questions are answerable. We could code an answer to all of those.
It might mean having to have a directory of printers and who's allowed to use one or whatever, which actually gives
you more control and flexibility than you probably have today. We can do those things, but the point is
getting DSC to a point where it can let us do those things. So yeah, we do have to have all those things.
What else we can get to is there like an alternative configuration or a second configuration?
There is no alternative configuration. In fact, let's talk about that.
ESPN, you and me, we had it yesterday too.