Here's how the LCM works at a really high level. When it gets a MOF, right, so we're pushing them off to
the LCM, right, either we're pushing it or the LCM has been programmed to pull it from a pull server, right.
Those are the only two ways you can get them off there, right? No.
No. That's a trick question. Trick question, there's three ways to get them off to the LCM.
What's the first way? Give me one. Push. What's the other one, second?
Pull. The third is injection. The third is called file copy. It's very advanced, haven't really had that
technique for more than five or six decades. And if you're going to inject, here's what you need to know.
In the folder where the configurations live, you've got pending.mof.
It's a text file. Pending.mof is the one that you just got most recently and haven't done anything with potentially.
Current.mof means you are currently running a consistency check and that's the MOF you're using.
This is a really cool thing. Look, they're two separate files. Why are they two separate files?
Because if the LCM has one of them open, you can't write a new one to it, right, you guys have run into this
before with every file type ever on a file server. Right, so it's not like this is word collaboration.
So when it starts to run a consistency check, it makes a file copy of pending.mof, names it current.mof,
so it can have one exclusive to itself without having an exclusive lock on pending.mof.
So while a consistency check is running, you can overwrite pending.mof.
You can also do it when there isn't a consistency check running.
You can anytime you can do it.
We've also got previous.mof and that's the one I ran last time.
That's kind of a last known good type of recovery situation. This is
why if you're in DSC 5 and you're really, really messing around with like how many of you like to just kick
the LCM and make it run right now and not wait 15 minutes? Right.
You know what, you're going to live for at least 20-30 more years, let it take its time.
Right, you're not going to die that soon. But that's why if you screw up a config and you get the LCM into
kind of a ah state, you can use Remove-DscConfiguration. There's a command to remove the previous config
and you have switches, which one do you want to remove? Previous, current, pending, right, so you can remove
all of them if you want to. And that's why it's important to do that if you need to kind of get it out of
its own head. But so we've got these ones we can mess with. And so this takes us to a really, really kind
of important capability. We could, for example, tell me if you think this is crazy.
Let's say I write a custom resource and we're going to call it crazy resource.
I ship that out to all my machines, yes. I write a configuration script and all it does, the only thing in
my configuration script is run crazy resource, crazy resource parameter yes.
That's it. Okay, I run that configuration script. What gets produced?
The MOF. What's in the MOF? Just one thing, right. It's a text file and it says run crazy resource.
I push that out to my computer. It goes into pending.mof, right.
LCM sometime later, ah, time to run a consistency check. Fifteen minutes has expired.
I'm going to copy pending.mof to current.mof. I'm going to open it up.
At this point, is there anything stopping me from doing something to pending.mof.
Nope. So it runs crazy resource. Crazy resource dynamically generates a whole brand new MOF and sticks it
in pending.mof. Who said, ugh? I didn't say these were smart DSC tricks.
Look at the title of the session. And at the very end of that dynamically-produced pending.mof, it recalls itself.
So the last thing in there depending on everything else is call crazy resource again.
And so it runs that. That'll take a minute, two, whatever it takes.
LCM waits 13, 14, 15 minutes, okay, pending.mof copying it over to current.mof and wow, look at all this stuff
that's in here and all those decisions were just made 15 minutes ago and they were made locally on that machine.
You could obviously do a hybrid approach, right. That's kind of an extreme example to lay it out.
You could certainly ship out a MOF that had a lot of your base configuration stuff and then called crazy resource
to just dynamically add-in printer mappings or whatever dynamic more local intelligence things.
You could evaluate the WMI repository, you can make decisions, you've got the full PowerShell scripting
language at your disposal to create a new MOF that will run the next time.
Crazy resource could say, okay, look here's the base MOF. I'm going to copy that off here to make my own
little copy and I'll use that as my starting point and I'll add dynamic stuff to it as I go.
That's crazy. It's called crazy resource.