What else? Who else is moving toward a servers are cattle, not pets, kind of environment and are using DSC to
help with that in some ways? Yeah? (Audience comment) Good. DSC and Chef, yeah.
And it works? You're standing, so I'm assuming that there hasn't been a blood bath.
Not yet. Not yet. It's possible. You just have to decide that you're going to change your processes.
And you know what, if there's a theme to this whole discussion, it's forget what you know and think about fresh, right.
That's what this whole thing is. Forget what DSCs architecture is as you've been told.
What could you do with it if you just stepped outside of the lines a little bit?
Forget about well you've got to have a machine name. Do you really?
Right. So just step outside those lines a bit. What are some other architectural things that you wish DSC did
that you just don't think it can do? Oh, that's right. Everyone's completely happy with the product and
doesn't want any changes to it. I forgot. (Audience comment) Ah, that is actually really good.
Dave Wyatt and I have an argument about this and I'm afraid he's right, the bastard, because I wanted to make,
so the question was what about one DSC resource calling another DSC resource and you might think why would
you do that? Well here's a really good example. Let's say I wanted to write a dynamic evaluation resource.
Okay, so in my configuration script, it would say pick a basic resource that you like.
Oh, that's good. File. So let's say we only want a copy of this file if this thing in WMI is set to this value,
right, something like that. So my idea was we'll write a resource and let's query this WMI class, compare it to
this value, and if it's true, run the file resource with tab to indent these settings.
If it's not true, tab to indent, run the file resource with these settings instead, right.
And so we kind of went down this and I said so look and there are two answers.
Answer one, if you are using function-based resources, you can totally do this because they're just modules.
So you're if then resource, if we can call it that, can we call it that if then, your if then resource can
just go load the module into its scope and call the test in a set and it can just manually pretend that it's
the LCM and run those things. It's a little harder with class-based resources because if a class-based
resource attempts to instantiate another one, you actually get an error saying that there's a configuration,
a consistency check already in progress, like the LCM gets involved and stomps on you.
So we haven't figured out a work-a-round for that yet. But for function-based ones, you can have one
resource call another. Class ones, I still think there has to be a way to step out of the scope and get into it,
but we haven't gotten it to do what we want quite yet. (Audience question)
Sure. Change the INI file, restart the server. We still have INI files?
That's awesome. I love INI files. What else? Anybody tried to do anything crazy with DSC or are you just
doing like file, package, network, firewall. Yeah, just the basics.
Nah, go home and get crazy with it. Go nuts with it. Try weird stuff.
Set yourself up a little lab. What do you need like three machines, client, server, pull server.
Do crazy stuff because crazy stuff is how we break it and crazy stuff is how we break push the edges.
And until we try to break it, nobody can fix it, so we have to try and break it first and let's find out
where it's not doing what we think it needs to do so that we can tell the team because that's really what
they want to hear, right, they know they're just guessing as to what we need based on conversations they've
had, but they need more conversations and we've got to try and break stuff, we've got to try and push the
edges of it and find out you know what this model would work really well except for this one thing it won't
let me do. Can you take that off? Make a case for it. Reporting's tooling.
Yeah, go ahead. One thing I'd like to see is something to deploy the DSC in an existing machine so you
generate configuration like based out of this because… Sure, point DSC at a machine and have it just
generate a config for how that machine is set up. Two responses, response number one, that's tooling, right,
that's not so we got to make sure we're differentiating between platform and tooling.
DSC is not tooling. DSC is platform. So what you're after is a tool because that's not something you're
going to do every five minutes. You're going do it as a provisioning thing.
We'd also like tools to do reporting for God's sake, that'd be nice.
We'd like tools to be able to keep track of what config was supposed to go to what machine.
That'd be great. All that will be called system center expensive something, something, something, something
I'm sure, one day. So we'll diverge to tooling for just a second.
I don't think you do want that. I think people think they want that and I hear that a lot, but let's go down
that rabbit hole a little bit because when you point that thing at that machine, is it just going to enumerate
every single registry key, file, service, process ever? Or is it supposed to compare like a base OS with?
It gets really tough and Windows has got 632 quad zillion management points and it doesn't know which one you care about.
Now what I would say is that it's probably legit to ask for a tool like the packaging tools used to do where
it can watch. Yes. Right. Okay, I've got everything up. Here's my base image.
Begin watching. Yeah, but except people make that. Right, that's what, oh heck, they used to be a sponsor
of us, dev power people with stuff, ScriptRock. UpGuard now. Oh, they did change their name.
No one knows why. Yeah, so there are people who do that. You're going to have to pay for it, but you know
if you want nice things, you have to pay for them. I'm not sure I would ever expect Microsoft to produce
that tool just because they've declined to do so in so many different iterations, the exception being App-V.
Right, which is part of how App-V, that's how you App-Vify an app as they watch it while you install it.
But they bought that from someone else, so it's hard to tell. But yeah, those tools exist.
Now what they don't currently do, what UpGuard does not do is make a MOF out of that, but I think that's just
a matter of enough customers saying you know what we'd really like.
How about installing MSU files? Installing? MSU files. Installing MSU, you mean patches?
I don't know. I go back and forth on that one. I don't view DSC as a patch deployment mechanism.
But what if you need a specific patch? Oh, you just need one like on a short term thing?
Short of just because that system for your business case needs this patch in place.
Yeah. And you want to make sure that it's on there, but not maybe necessarily run the entire Windows update.
I'm not sure. I go back and forth. I'm not saying you're wrong.
I'm just going to imply it. (Audience comment) And part of me says that DSC can't be the one tool you use
to maintain your entire infrastructure and that the best use of DSC for a software deployment situation would
be to use DSC to make sure that you're software deployment solution is installed and active and running and
then use your software deployment solution to push files and crap.
And the reason I say that is because software deployment is such a thing.
You have to track status because you want to be able to query it.
You have to have distribution points. You have to worry about WAN links when you're pulling software and I
just think that starts to get outside of basic config. I think your basic config is make sure that this
other solution is configured so that it will do its job. That's kind of where I sit.
We're in this weird space with software deployment right now. My suspicion is that as Microsoft moves more
and more toward a cloud command and control in tune style stuff with maybe on-prem distribution points,
you'll start to see that becoming easier. I think right now it's great to say just use DSC to configure your
patch management and software deployment solution, except we really don't have a great one.
We've got Windows update and SCCM and that's it. Can't we call it sick 'em anymore?
So yeah, that's kind of one of the reasons I'm not really looking for the package resource to be all that awesome.
To a point, like to the Yum RPM level sure, but I don't really want to see DSC become a whole software
deployment solution because we already have so many of them and they all suck.
So I'd rather get one of the ones we have working, but that's something fun to talk about.
Let's drink and talk about that because it's more interesting. Yeah.
So the squishy metaphor like where users and DevOps… That's not a metaphor.
People are squishy. Try it, poke him. Squishy. So after the point there, I can see that argument there,
but for the service where it's maybe there's just the one application they want and really the particular
latest version of… No, no, I think you and I are on the same page there.
I think as you get into a server and your goal is to provision a server and you need this management agent
and you need this and this and this, you need to get it to the point where it can participate in the rest of the infrastructure.
I think that's a legitimate use for DSC being able to deploy packages contingent on A, us getting something
that really works well like PowerShell Package Manager hopefully will for us, right.
We need a Yum RPM Package Manager, not just giant file full of Windows Installer files and it'd be really
nice if we could just burn Windows Installer to the ground and never look at it again.
That'd be great because it's the source of most problems because people build crappy packages.
Not that Windows Installer is bad, it's what people do with it, right, guns don't kill people, developers kill people.
So it's basically that. So I think there is definitely---this almost gets into the DevOps-ish world, right,
do we have, no we don't have time. Well sometime when we're drinking, get me to tell you my whole DevOps story
and that kind of fits in it well. One more question all the way in the back.
He was first. (Audience question) In doing who? Networking. Networking.
Love it. Switch. Oh, you mean like using DSC to manage switches and stuff?
Yeah, so that's pretty much your job to pressure your network vendor because Microsoft has already done all
the work they need to do in that space. They've created a reference OMI stack, right.
OMI is basically a super lightweight WS-MAN stack and a super lightweight CIM repository that doesn't require a repository.
It's all in memory, so it's designed to run small footprint, small processor, it's designed to run in embedded
devices like switches and there's at least one company, Dell, that's already jumping on this bandwagon and you
can shove them off into one of their switches and it'll do it. So that's happening.
You've just got to make your vendor jump on board. Who's your vendor?
Cisco? It will be Cisco and Azure. Yep, have fun. Good luck with that.
(Audience comment) Cisco and some of their stuff is, yeah, and they'll roll it across generations.
The fact is that Microsoft with DSC did the most intelligent thing I've seen the company do in a long time
and they didn't invent a lot of new crap. They just adopted standards that we're already out there, and so for
other companies to jump on doesn't mean they have to bow down to Redmond, they're just doing what the rest of
the industry had already decided, but not actually implement it. Microsoft was the first to put a big
implementation out there and got the ball rolling, so that's already happening.
So look, cool. Guys, we're at the end. Thanks very much and enjoy the dinner on tonight.
Thank you. And let's keep talking and having ideas. Yeah.