What are some use cases, some things that you wish you could do with DSC?
Before, because I have another tangent I want to go down, but before we do that, what are some things that
you think you want to do with DSC that on the surface doesn't appear you could do because of where the logic lives.
Well I want to get from having pets to having cattle. Pets, that's actually my next tangent.
But right now, I've got pets, so how do I get the DSC to make my pet into cattle?
Hold that thought. Yeah. I want to get the output of one resource as input to another resource.
You want to get the output of one resource as input to another resource.
Yeah, I want my pool to not have algae, but that I think is a more fundamental design issue.
Hang on. I don't want you to wear your arm out. We'll get there.
We've talked about that because that's a really serious need. It would be best for the product to address
that, but since it doesn't, we decided to hack around with it. How comfortable are you modifying every
resource you use? Fine. Sure, good, brave man. I like you. We're going to drink tonight.
It won't go well. Our idea was to take the same basic hash table that is in the configuration script that
essentially goes into the MOF that becomes the input to both your test, and your site, and your app, right,
and persist that in just a known location that every resource can then choose to read in.
We've even, talk to me and you might be able to talk me into getting access to our private Slack channel
because we've even started hacking around with some tools to kind of abstract that, right, so you can just
include this module and then have a persist function and whatever the opposite verb is function to add to
your resources so you can do that. One of the reasons we felt that would be better than a memory-based solution
is because it almost acts a little bit more like workflow in that if something happens midway through and
there's a reboot or whatever, right, the whole idea behind DSC is it should be able to just pick right back up again.
Well, that would give you some state information about where you were because the LCM will know, but you won't.
Yeah. Yeah, we've been hacking that around. You. So the package resource and binaries like the canyon virus,
where it's a gig in size. Every time a consistency check runs whether I need the version installed or not,
it's going to download that thing again long enough to look at it and say oh no I've got this looking, forget it.
Yeah, so short version of question, package manager sucks because it has to go get the file in order for it
to determine if that's open and when the file is huge, it just takes a long time and hold things up and I
think it really we can boil that down to the current package resource sucks.
And that is really not the fault of the people who wrote the package resource.
It's the fault of the people who wrote Windows Installer and InstallShield and all this other garbage.
So Windows itself just does not have a great way of doing that.
I think the go forward solution there and we're just like on the precipice of this starting to become a thing
is PowerShell Package Manager, which if you're using the right repository that supports checksums and
everything else would let us author a new package resource that could check things that way.
It would be nice if package manager would look at the product Id and say it's installed.
Well lots of things would be nice, but it doesn't. We can write our own.
I don't think writing a better package manager is at all outside the scope of what DSC does and let's take
that as a philosophical point. I'm not actually picking on you, well a little bit, but not really.
If you're looking at one of the Microsoft provided resources for DSC, other than the file one, which is binary,
right, so if you're looking at those and you're like yeah this kind of sucks.
It'd be nice if it did this instead. You need to get your butt on GitHub, fork the project, and fix it instead
of complaining, right, because there's certain bits of the product that only Microsoft can do, right,
like we can't fix the LCM. We can't fix the pull server code. We don't have access to that.
The things we can't fix are the things they need to focus on and the rest of the stuff, we need to do for ourselves.
And that's just how it is. It'd be nice if they gave us everything, but then they could do our jobs and we
wouldn't need our jobs. So that's where we are right now. So the package, there's actually a lot of people
who are hacking away to make better versions of that. Get involved in one of those projects.
Okay. The current one relies too much on the Windows Installer database and anything not hooked up to
Windows Installer sucks and then the Windows Installer validation process sucks.
Anybody ever query 132 product on a Server 2003 machine and then lose your job?
Why is the server slow for six hours a day? Virus, I don't know.
I'll run a scan. That's my log in script story. So anymore? Any things that I'd love it if DSC could do
this, but it just doesn't seem possible the way it's architected.
Because that's why we're here. We're here to hack the architecture.
Okay, so you're completely satisfied with everything DSC does and you feel the architecture is completely
approachable and finished. That's fantastic. We'll pass that onto the team.
They'll appreciate that. Ordering like composites can't be dependsOn, right?
Ordering and composites. Right, you can't do a dependsOn. I would argue that you probably don't want it to
because the amount of logic that would go into tearing those apart and going down that rabbit hole would make
the thing impossible. I'll make a design argument, which is---so do you guys know the whole reason that---
you guys know what dependsOn is, right? You need to jiggle your heads.
Okay. The whole argument in favor of doing dependsOn is in case the LCM ever becomes multithreaded.
If the LCM is doing 10 things at once, it needs to know which ones not to do yet and that's what dependsOn
is designed to document. My argument because that becomes a problem for composites, I have an argument
against dependsOn, which is that it makes your configuration document harder to read.
Unless you actually list everything voluntarily in dependsOn order, it becomes hard for a human being to parse that.
Alright, so that's going to happen and that's going to happen, and that's going to happen, and oh, oh no,
that's going to happen, then that's going to happen because this has to.
It gets harder just to mentally grasp it. Make file. Kind of like a make file.
My argument and this is a design thing and this is something Microsoft would have to address.
My argument is that a not doing dependsOn and instead doing a sequential, which is like what Chef and Puppet
and those guys do and occasionally giving us a keyword called coalesce meaning here's 10 things, do them first
in whatever order you want to and then stop until all of those things are done and then continue with phase 2.
That would have been semantically I think a lot easier to read, a lot easier to implement, and avoided that
whole problem because then sequence becomes important. So we can talk about that with them tomorrow because
they'll be here. Yes, we can suggest that. Jump up and down and scream.
Anything else architectural? I want to do dynamically generated configurations.
I want to do dynamically generate config, yeah. That, right. Locally.
Yeah. Yeah, I'll give you two places I think we could do and I think we can do this almost nearly today-ish
in terms of dynamically-generated configurations. I think we can do locally dynamically-generated
configurations on the node today. You're going to have to write your own resource to do that,
but that's what we're talking about here. I think we are nearly to the point where we could also dynamically
generate them on the pull server. Now that pull server protocol is documented, we just don't have any code
to look at so that we can make our own smarter pull server. I think we will get that.
I mean, they've been pretty clear that their goal is to open source at least sample code where you can build
your own and at that point, we could have our own pull server taking state data from right then and
dynamically generating a MOF to hand to the node. I think we're close to that.
We can do everything now except the actual pull server because we don't know what the code looks like and
none of us wants to just reverse engineer the protocol. I think we're nearly there.
Let's talk about cattles and pets. The cattle versus pet thing is something that's going to require 10%
operating system design change and I don't think these are major.
I think it's just a very evolutionary step and 90% us changing our processes.
How many of you, for example, assign static IP addresses to your servers?
Why? Do you not have DHCP? Did you not know about DHCP? Are you afraid of DHCP?
Are you superstitious about DHCP? How many of you just think DHCP is freaking voodoo?
Who thinks it's science? Yeah, so let's take that for a second.
Vendor requirement is bull. That is the 90% us changing our processes.
Right. You can't say I wish I could do X, but there are stupid people in the world.
I know that. We're all surrounded by them on the highway every single day, but that's not a reason to,
you can't say I need to re-engineer the entire universe because of stupid people.
No, that's an HR problem. You need to bury the stupid people in the desert.
That's why I live in Vegas. If you've got stupid people, you can't have nice things, period.
So we're not talking about the situation where you just politically can't have nice things because you've got
the option to go find a different job. So let's talk about the technology things, right.
There is no reason to not have your servers getting their IP addresses from a DHCP server or a DHCP-like entity.
Right, you get on SCVMM, for example, and you've got like IP address pools and things like that aren't DHCP,
but they're vaguely similar, right. There's no reason that a configuration, a DSC configuration MOF needs
to be pushing a static IP address. They should be set for DHCP. And if you want to as you're kind of
MetaConfiguration be configuring reservations and stuff like that, God be with you, that's fine,
but cattle don't have names and an IP address is a name, and so you should not be assigning names.
You should be doing that at a metalevel. That's problem number one.
Problem number two, machine name. Right, that's the other unique piece of information we have to set, well ish.
Windows anymore makes up a name for itself when you first install it.
Let it keep it. Who cares what the cattle thinks its name is. I don't care.
As part of the configuration, rather than assigning a name because your configuration is often going to be
role-based, right. You're configuration's telling a machine to be a certain way.
Part of who it should be is registering the necessary CNAME records in DNS.
That's what you talk to it by. Right, if you're in this application, well then register that name and that's
what we're all going to call you. The only couple of, and this is where we get to the 10% that has to be an
OS design change, the only couple of weirdnesses you get there is let's say PowerShell remoting becomes involved.
Can I easily remote to a machine via a CNAME? Yeah, not as easily as knowing its name because I need to
know its canonical Active Directory name if it's in Active Directory, so I can get a Kerberos ticket for it.
It won't work with a CNAME. But you can certainly work around that, right.
If, for example, you were doing the right thing and that machine was requesting a certificate for itself with
its CNAME, then that certificate could be used on an HTTPS listener, which is what you should be doing
anyway because none of us are dumb enough to be doing remoting over HTTP, right?
Right. Home Depot, guys, Target. It's going to happen. So if the machine knows its role, then it knows
what CNAME to set up for itself. And yeah, are you going to have to then come up with a back-end process
to periodically scour or scavenge those? Possibly. You could certainly have things like expirations on them
because the LCM is going to run periodically and make sure that it's re-registered.
So you just look to see the last time it was just every hour, right, the LCM doesn't have to run every 15 minutes.
You know that, right. It can do it less frequently. Every hour, go update the update record on your CNAME
so that I know it's recent and if anything becomes too old, I'll have another process that scavenges those.
Pretty much exactly like DHCP works. So you've got your CNAME record there.
That means you can go to our PKI. How many of you have PKI? The rest of you need to catch up.
We all need PKI. Go to the PKI and get a certificate in that name and now you can hook that up to an HTTPS
remoting listener, and so now I can remote easily into the machine using its CNAME.
I never need to know its natural machine name. You think Microsoft knows the machine names of all the crap
they have running in Azure? I doubt it. They sure as heck don't have an Excel spreadsheet somewhere
tracking all that garbage, which is what you use, I know. How many of you use Excel to track your static IP
addresses or servers. Yeah, of course you do. He's the only brave one who admits it.
The rest of you are lying. I know. So when you start thinking about the things that are unique, most of them
are only unique because of the way we're accustomed to doing things, not because there's a tremendous technological hurdle.
Is it inconvenient to change? Well no. It's only inconvenient if you're holding onto your old processes.
If you just let go, then it's actually not hard at all. Static IP addresses for servers, I mean, move on.
Let it go. Let it go. I'm not singing, don't worry. We only do that in the closing session and it's a song about beer.