So here's the thing,
when you make a MOF out, so you wrote your config, you run your config, your config makes a MOF.
We need to change the name of this and there's two ways we can deal with this.
First of all, I'm going to show you the old fashioned way, which Morawski and I actually still really like this way.
Yeah, what?
I like it too.
Oh, you like it too. Okay, good, good. We're on the same page because this way works.
Oh, this is not a good thing. So we need to change the name of this and here's what we're going to change it to.
We're going to change it to a GUID, a GUID, that really long ugly number and we're going to then tell the nodes
that we, the ones that we want to use that config, we're going to tell the nodes in their LCM what GUID
number they're supposed to look for. So what this means is on your pull server, you're going to have 6,000 GUIDs
out there for whatever configs you have. Now the cool part to this is it's really easy to manage.
If I have 50 machines that need the same config, guess what I'm going to tell 50 machines LCMs?
(Audience comment)
Same GUID number. So I just have to have one out there and I can manage 50 machines with it, but it can be a
little bit confusing, so let's go ahead and take a look here.
First of all, the order or sequence I'm going to do this in is I'm going to start with the LCM of a
particular machine, so let's do this. Here's what I need. The LCM configuration, let me drop this down a
little bit, I need a GUID, so I've just got a parameter here where I'm going to pass the GUID.
Now I'm just going to generate one and pass it into the LCM. I also need something else.
I'm using a secured pull server and so I need the thumbprint for the certificate on that secured pull server.
So there's two things I need for this. Now down here in the settings, I'm going to do ApplyAndAutoCorrect.
I need to set the refresh mode to pull because by default it's push and this is where I'll put in the
ConfigurationID and here's the interesting part.
ConfigurationRepositoryWeb, this is how I tell it what web server to go to that's the pull server.
So take a look. The server URL is the URL of your pull server and you need to put in the thumbprint for the
CertificateID and set AllowUnsecureConnection to false.
Pretty simple, right? Not that hard. Not that hard. So I'm going to run this.
Oh let me show you down here. Now I got yelled at on Sunday. Here's how I make my GUID.
Who wants to yell at me? Who was here earlier that wants to yell at me?
Good because don't yell at me because I'm not going to. This is how I make my GUID.
There's apparently, I never looked, there's a new cmdlet in v5 called New-GUID.
So and here's how I get my thumbprint. I'm actually going to go to the pull server and this is kind of useful.
I'm going to look at the pull server certificate store and where the FriendlyName is,
whatever you FriendlyNamed your certificate, and then select ExpandProperty's Thumbprint.
That grabs the thumbprint for me, so it's real easy. Kind of cool, kind of cool, kind of cool, kind of cool.
So I'll run this. Woo! And theoretically, I'll get a MOF and there's the MOF.
I could show you the MOF, but we don't care what's inside the MOF.
It's a meta MOF, meta, meta, meta MOF. So I'm going to set server1.
I've got two servers that we're going to play with. Server-1, I'm going to set his LCM.
Now just to let you see here and I'll bring this up a little bit, you can get the information for the LCM and
look at all this. It doesn't open up your configuration stuff, so when you're trying to troubleshoot stuff
and you want to see what's in there, just expand property on that and it'll show you what's inside so you can
troubleshoot including the thumbprint and all that kind of stuff if you run into issues with it registering.
We good so far?
Okay, so I have a node that has now been told here's the GUID I want you to look for when you go to the pull
server I told you to go to. Are you with me so far? Now I need to make a config and name it with that GUID number.
So I got a simple config. This is just going to install the SNMP service.
It's not a, I'll show it to you, it's not a real big deal. So just something really simple.
I'll run that. I want you to notice the name of it is S1.mof. We don't want it to stay that way, so I'm going
to put it on a pull server. First of all, I'm going to get the GUID and a variable from one of the nodes
that I had set. Boink. And now I'm just going to rename that file to that GUID.
Boink. And I'm going to put it on the pull server, but before I do, I need you to understand something.
This is tricky. This is also something that throws off people when they're trying to troubleshoot this when
it doesn't work.
What's going to happen is the first time it's going to work just fine, but at some point, you're going to
modify the config, run the config again, rename it to the GUID, and copy it back out to the pull server and
then you're going to wonder why your changes never go to the node. Got it.
Here's the thing, we need a checksum file. So this will make a hash and no it's not Shaw256.
I don't care what Steve says. We're going to make a hash and so you always have to make sure that every time
you modify your configs, you make a new checksum for it and you put both of them up there.
The LCM will know that there's been a change to the configuration by checking that checksum, so that's the
thing that really throws people off when they do this. Now at that point, I'm just going to copy it up there
to my pull server. I only have one, but I'm just going to copy up the GUID stuff or all that stuff and I just
want to show you that it's on the pull server. Now this is the location where you put your configurations is
WindowsPowerShell\DscService\Configuration. You're not impressed, but okay fine, be that way here.
See them. See them? Oh, let me pull this up. Ahh. Okay, great you're applauding that.
All I did was copy a file, right. Now I could sit here and wait and the LCM will eventually pick this sucker
up or I can just kick him in the pants and that's what I'm going to do, so we don't have to sit here and wait
all day, well at least 15 minutes. So I'm going to update that configuration.
Nah, nah, nah, nah, nah, nah, nah. Now I can't that stupid thing out of my head.
I hate that. Oh and by the way, right now he's running the config.
Isn't that cool? So the node actually-- yeah. Yeah, okay you're not that impressed.
Okay, but you should be.