Now we're going to do it another way. A lot of people like this way.
I like this way because here's the thing, GUIDs are hard to manage because you can't tell what's inside the config.
In other words, you see a number and when you get 6,000 up there, well which one configures SNMP?
I don't know. Now it becomes really hard. Now most of us have created our tooling where we put the GUID
into a database along with a description of what it is and all that kind of stuff, so in other words,
we're kind of writing our own version of Chef, but it's really easy to---did I say that word Chef, yes,
I said that---but it's really easy to do your own tooling for this, it's just you're probably going to want it.
So let me show you another way. This is a new way. This came out last April in the previews stream of things.
I'm going to do the same thing I did before. I've got a simple config.
I'm going to run the config. It's going to say s1.mof. Here's what I'm going to do, I'm going to rename the
config, but I'm going to name it with
something a human can understand. See it's going to be---you don't look happy about this, but you should be.
So I'm going to rename it to RoleSNMP. I going to make a checksum for it because we always got to do the checksum.
And then, da, ta, da, na, na, na, na, na, I'm going to copy it up to the pull server again.
But now watch, looky, looky, looky, looky. Which one do you understand?
Yeah, see how cool this is? This also brings up a security issue because when it's a GUID, nobody knows what's inside.
When it's not a GUID and you use a human name, they know exactly what that config does.
That could be an issue. That's why you probably heard the team talking about this is why we're encrypting the
MOFs because of this right here.
So, but it's easier to manage. It's really cool. Now what we have to do is we now have to do something
kind of special. We need to teach
our pull server how to work with this technology called configuration names.
Now what Microsoft did is they're like, you can figure out what the configs are, so you can set any node to
pull any config because it's English readable, we're going to set up a registration key.
It's basically just a shared secret. We're going to put the shared secret on the pull server and we're going
to teach the LCM what the shared secret is. Only if you know the shared secret---how can you ask a question about that?
(Audience comment)
Oh go ahead.
I'm assuming that you do the name, the configurations, the pull server seem to be running on v5.
Oh, I should have mentioned that. Thank you very much. You are absolutely correct.
This has to be v5 deal. Config names, at least the last time I checked, did not work in v4.
So and then also, then I guess it applies that this node also has to be running in v5.
The node can be, as long as the LCM is version 2, so they updated v4 to have an LCM too.
So the LCM could be a version 4 that's been updated. Again, a really great question.
Guys, we need this registration key, so
I'm going to create a text file with a registration key in it. Of course, what we want you to put in here is a
GUID.
Good. I'm just using some numbers so you can see that it doesn't matter what you put in here.
So I'm just doing 1234567, I'll make this file, I'm going to copy this registration key up to the pull server
to a very specific location, WindowsPowerShell\DscService. This is the root folder for the configuration and
modules folders for the pull server and with that, thinking I don't have to prove to you that it's up there,
but let's go ahead and prove to you that it's up there. There's my registration keys.
Got it? So now all I need to do is teach the LCM and I'm going to pick on the computer too.
I don't need a GUID anymore in this LCM config, so I remarked it out, so you can see it's out, but what I do
need to do is teach him the registration key and the configuration name.
So if you look down here, I set the ConfigurationID to blank because we're not using GUIDs and down here,
RegistrationKey and what role or what config name do I want him to use.
Does that make sense? It's actually really, really easy.
(Audience question)
Some day. Also, I want you, great question, because I want you to also notice the word configuration names
and see my note that says there can be only one. Today, there can be only one.
Perhaps in the future, you could actually ask it for multiple roles and it'll munge it down to a single MOF.
(Audience comment)
Yeah. So I'm going to run this. Whoops. Hang on, hang on, hang on.
I screwed something up. What did I screw up? Connecting to remote server failed with username or password is incorrect.
What the hell are you talking about? My invoke-command failed? Wait a minute.
Wait a minute. Anybody see what I screwed up? Thumbprint because it's an empty string.
Yeah, I know. Oh, come on. Invoke-command Computer dc. I don't think my, wait a minute, I know my pull
server is running. Oh, I don't know why he's in the middle of a reboot, but he had, and the thing is, I have the
LCM set on him to reboot if needed and apparently he needed. So anyway, back to.
Sorry about that. Let's try this again. Hey, here we go. That's much better.
So I'm going to now set that LCM on machine number 2 with that information and if we did everything correct,
put the registration key up, name the configs, configure the LCM correctly, if we did everything correct,
oh wait a minute, did I get another red splat? The underlying error is attempt to register agent, oh don't you
do this to me. Seriously? Come on. I'll tell you what this is in a minute, what this error is.
If I run update, it'll suddenly work.
And mine's not and I'll explain to you in a minute why. Do you get the kind of concept though of using a config name?
I've got good news and I've got bad news with config names. The good news is it's pretty easy to manage because
now you can understand what the files are, it's easy to set up nodes with it, a lot of people really like this.
I'm going to get to the bad news in a minute. Look at the bottom of the screen, see.
So here's part of the bad news. If you want to use config names, you're pull server must be a graphical server.
I only work on Core servers. I only work on Core servers. I only work on Core servers.
I only work on Core servers. My pull server has to be a graphical-based server.
The reason is that when they wrote all this up, there's some dependencies still on the graphical desktop.
They are in the process of fixing it right now. As a matter of fact, the guy who is fixing it was here
yesterday morning going I'm fixing it. Because it's kind of embarrassing, right?
Your crap doesn't work on a Core Server from the team that made the Core Server and told everybody it's got
to be Core. Okay, you don't see the hilarity to that, but I certainly do.
There's another issue too. You are not going to reboot on me again.
Oh, okay. Just whatever. There's another issue. I built my pull server and when you build a pull server,
you need to get a module from the gallery called XPS Desired State Configuration.
Unfortunately, that module has changed version numbers as they're trying to fix this configuration thing.
Twice in the last few days. I have the latest one and the latest one is causing an agent registration error
and that's the red error I got from server 2. You will get that error if you use config names today.
Hopefully, 3.10.0.0 will ship soon and that will fix it all. Are you with me?
I apologize. It's just it is what it is right now.