Kind of, sort of?
Let's do resources real quick.
Now this is supposed to have my beauty demo, but my beauty demo might fail
because the one---I use config names and we'll see how it goes.
Huh, what?
(Audience comment)
No, I don't want to do that. I don't have that much time. Well we'll see.
We'll see the beauty demo is awesome. Some if it'll work. So let's go down here and let's talk about resources.
Resources are more challenging.
Before we go on, can I ask you a question? So is there any reason to use config names other than GUID?
No.
I like GUID names. I don't think they're a problem.
Stick it with GUIDs then.
Well here's one thing we all just now learned. GUIDs work, and quite honestly, like I said, Steve and I still
prefer GUIDs, other guys prefer, yeah you prefer GUIDs, use GUIDs.
All the GP guys always use GUIDs.
There you go, so yeah, there you go. There's no reason not to use GUIDs.
This was something they threw in because everybody was, you've got to imagine everybody that starts with DSC,
they were complaining about the GUIDs because they didn't know what the hell a GUID was and they couldn't
figure out what they were doing with it and there was no, they didn't think of, somebody said well let's make
an Excel spreadsheet. No, don't do that, but you know. So that's why they put in config names.
I like config names. It's really useful, but. Guys, I'm going to make a couple of, I've got a configure that's
going to make some cool web servers.
You're about up to here with DSC making web servers, aren't you? Yeah, I know.
If you came to my thing on Sunday, we made domain controllers and stuff like that, but I know, it's kind of irritating.
It's just easy to do. I'll show you this config here in, if you want to see it, I'll give you the details of it.
This is just one of my configs. I separate my config data. It's going to build two different websites.
I've got two different roles in here.
It's going to use web as one of the roles, which configures a base web server with only the components that
I want configured in it. Then one of them is going to do an open site, which is just a regular HTTP site on
one server and one's going to do a secured site with an application and a custom resource.
I'm pointing this out because you're going to be writing custom resources left and right.
You've got to make sure you package them correctly for your pull server.
So let me just kind of show you here.
I guess I should run that because I'm going to need it. Oh, don't you dare.
Oh. Alright. What was the problem with this the last time I did this?
Could not find XDNS server. Oh, I haven't put the resources out yet.
See this red squiggly line? that means my authoring box doesn't have the resources.
That's part of my demo was to show you that.
I saw that one earlier. I noticed the red squiggles.
Yeah, I didn't even read my own comment that says yeah, look at the red squiggle.
So here's what I'm going to do. I'm going to copy the resources to my authoring box.
It goes out to Windows PowerShell modules and now the red squigglies, let me close this, and guys this is
one of those things you have to close it and reopen it.
(Audience comment)
Yeah, yeah. It won't re, yeah that it's not refreshing. I saw that was getting voted up too, that's good.
So now hopefully, my come on make the red squigglies go away. No.
XWebAdministration multiple yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
This is the problem I had yesterday. Find-module xwebadministration.
By the way, this is something that will happen to you, so might as well.
AllVersions. NuGet, NuGet I am up to here with you updating NuGet.
Chocolatey NuGet. Oh. So here's the deal, a couple of days ago, a new version of this came out and that's what's
breaking my demo. I need to be on 1.9 and it's currently on 1.10, so let me get rid of on my machine has 1.10,
let me get rid of it and that's where I'm going to uninstall, uninstall-module -name xwebadministration.
Did I spell that right?
You did.
Okay, good. MinimumVersion1.10.0.0. Let's try this again.
No squigglies. Okay. Oh, don't. Golf clap. Anyway, so this is going to install.
Let me just run this, guys, so
we can start him off because he takes a few minutes to run and then we can kind of talk about him.
Notice I got two MOFs out there, s1 and s2. I'm going to show you another trick because I had my cute little
coding trick here and then Morawski yelled at me, so I'm going to show you, oh I'm going to change the names
of those files, so let me just rename them. I'm using a config name for those and let me make a checksum for them.
Ta-da. And I'm going to put them up on the pull server and here's the important part for this section.
I'm just going to put the configs up there, but now here's the hard part.
The resources have to get copied up there. Now they have to be copied into the DSC Service Modules folder,
but here's the challenging part. On your authoring box, your resources are PowerShell modules.
They have to be zipped and use a special name. The special name is the name of the module_it's version number.
If you screw this up, it'll never work. You can't invent your own format for this name or the version numbering.
Here's where you have to go for this. The version numbering is in the manifest of each resource.
Now let me
give you an example here. Here's one of my custom, this is my custom resource.
I'm going to go into the manifest, see the module number? However that module number is listed must be the
way that it appears in the zip name. People mess this up all the time.
And I'm going to give you an example. I want you to see this because I looked at all the modules and got
their version numbers. This one was 1.2.0.0. This one was just 1.0.
It didn't have the other two, so it's got to match exact of what's in the manifest.
Does that make sense?
Now here's the beauty of this. Because that version number is in there, you can have newer versions of these modules.
You can put them on your pull server. So you have version control on the pull server.
Maybe you have 50 machines using version 1.2 and you want to put a 1.3 version of the resource up, but you don't
want to break the 50 machines that are out there. You want to put a new version up and maybe put that on like
three machines you want to test. The beauty to that is just astounding in production.
There's only one small problem. How many of you know that class-defined resources, we don't have versioning
in class-defined. So here's the deal, I don't write class-defined resources other than to entertain myself
because I can't use them on a pull server because I can't version them, so I use standard resources.
Anyway, it doesn't matter. Actually, this PSWA authorization is a class-defined resource, but I'm not putting
another version up because it won't work.
So I'm going to zip this. Zip, zip, zip, zip, zip, zip. And you need a checksum for those zips.
That way we know if it's been changed. Yeah.
(Audience question)
No. You still have to put the version number in there that's in the manifest for the class.
So that's actually really important. It's just you'll never be able to put another one on there until they fix this.
(Audience comment)
Because it doesn't know how to, it doesn't actually, the LCM doesn't know how to look for it with a class-defined resource.
They know this is an issue and they're going to fix it, but this has actually been on UserVoice for quite some time.
This has been an ongoing thing. And the thing is that in production is where you feel the pain.
Literally, Morawski and I were going through this because we were yelling at each other back and forth
because over skype one day because I'm like use class, use class, and he's like every version of a class-defined
resource, I have to bring up a new pull server because that's the only way you can do it.
Yeah. Ooh, and I'm like okay you win. Anyways, so let me copy these up and we'll run this and give it a shot,
see how well it works here.