Alright, so how many of you have been to my other sessions? Okay, because if you haven't, you are really in
the deep end of the pond at this point. This is the end, so to speak.
And what we're going to do is we're going to talk about DSC. We've already in other sessions built pull servers.
I already have a pull server. Pull server. Pull my finger, oh okay, no you're not going to do it, are you?
And so, what we're going to do now is this is really the hard part that throws a lot of people off when they
start with DSC is how do I get configurations on a pull server and how do I get resources on a pull server so
that when a node goes ask that pull server says hey I want this config and the config needs additional resources,
then it'll just download the resources that it needs. So I don't deploy these resources, it just gets what
it needs when it actually runs. Now if
you don't know this, here take a, use your phone, take a picture of this, whatever.
Here's where all the code is. This is actually the entire code that I did for the PreCon.
So this is start to finish DSC stuff starting out with how to write a config, how to manage the LCM,
all that kind of stuff. Take a picture because I'm going to make it go away.
So I put together a ton of code for you. What we're going to do is the last two modules and we're going to
do it really fast because this is short session, so and also Morawski's little reading list on DevOps.
It's an excellent reading list. And I think that's all I need to show you.
So here's what it looks like when you get the code, you will get a zip of looks like this.
Underneath a make a Scripts folder if you want to play with this at home and then copy DSCPreCon right there,
and underneath DSCPreCon, these are all the folders of all the code
and a ton of stuff in there, so you have a lot of fun. What we're going to focus on is the last two,
so I'm going to go
into PackagingConfigs and we're going to give this a shot. Everything starts with a demo script that actually
walks you through everything one step at a time, so let's do this, shall we?
Oh, that's not what I wanted. What am I doing? I'm in the wrong, ah.
Now you have to do it all over again. There we go. Make this a little bit bigger.
Oh, that's good. You guys see that okay? Awesome.