So what questions do you have?
Come on, anything.
Partial configurations.
No, we're not talking about partial configurations. Next question.
No, go ahead.
Because with a partial configuration in pull mode, you have to use the friendly name and a configuration number,
so are you stuck using the friendly names in that case? As far as I've seen, there's no way to do it using
the pull mode right now.
No, you're right. You need both of them right now. So I'll be honest with you, I'd stick with GUIDs if you're
doing partials right now altogether and not use any config names.
(Audience comment)
And if I were you, and I was just about to say, if I were you, we have this whole big thing, matter of fact,
I was just, you all know who Bruce Payette is? The great god of the linguistics in PowerShell?
Okay, what we've been saying for days, we keep telling, we tell this to customers on it, don't do partial configs.
There's only one case scenario for it and it's because you don't have an HR department capable of firing people.
Don't use partial configs. They will hurt you. The right way is to use a composite config.
That also goes through your build pipeline correctly and doesn't screw everything up.
Partial configs, you will die a 1,000 cuts. So I was talking to Bruce Payette last night and I said what's the
real, what's your view on partial configs and he just turned to me and went we shouldn't have done that.
Thanks, Bruce. That's exactly what I wanted to hear. But yeah, so I know that there are case scenarios for
partial configs, but please avoid those. Use a composite config.
It just makes your life easier than running partials. What else you got?
(Audience comment)
Yeah, and you know what's funny is that is exactly the answer I was going to get.
Your MOFs have to be versioned control by a version control source. They're not putting version control numbers
in the MOF, so what you want to do is whatever your source control is going to be like Get, whatever in GitHub,
that's where that versioning gets done. And I would dare say that you do the same process with your resources.
That's going to be in version control. You just have to make the name of the resource follow that,
you have to understand that versioning for those. That's a really good question.
Are you guys going to use pull servers or are you guys going to come up with your own way of doing it?
(Audience comment)
It has.
Right now, I feel like it either has to be both or I need to…
Okay, so there's a lot of companies that do push, they build their own push environments.
You're one of those. There you go and there's nothing wrong with that.
They are working on this pull server. I don't know if you've looked at the Azure automation stuff.
An Azure automation DSC pull server is a little bit more refined than our current on-prem pull server and
they're going to make a concerted effort to get the on-prem pull server, they've just been focusing on Azure.
Are you with me? You can use an Azure based pull server and let me tell you one of the benefits is we've got
encrypted MOFs on the nodes. These MOFs aren't encrypted on your on-premise one.
So somebody could just go hack the, just look at the ones on your and see things like if you forgot to secure
your credentials and that kind of stuff. On the Azure automation one, that pull server has encrypted MOFs on both sides.
It automatically encrypts the MOFs on the pull server and on the node, so that's kind of a benefit.
If you can have that hybrid approach, that's a really good pull server option right now to use.
This one, I use this in production all the time. While I'm not using config names this week,
that was supposed to be a joke, but I use this all the time and they're working on improving it really rapidly, so.
Also because, and I just want to tell you this, in the process of fixing some of this stuff, they've changed the
database type from JET to ESENT. Does anybody know what ESENT is?
Do I have any Exchange people in here?
(Audience comment)
It went from an MDB to an EDB. And now here's the funny part because I was asking one of the team members
yesterday about
this. I asked them, I said any Exchange guy that goes out and looks at this folder, let me just, is going to freak.
Where do I have it? Dc\C$, Program Files, Windows PowerShell, DSC.
Notice the old MDB is still out there because when they made this change last week, they didn't want to kill
your database, existing one, but they made a new one. Yeah. Yeah, it's why you didn't notice it and I just needed
see those things called .logs,
here's what I don't know. Any Exchange guy looks at this, the first thing they go is
Oh my God. And I said to the team member yesterday, here's the first question that should have popped out of
somebody's mouth as soon as it, because mine did, was are you using circular logging?
If not, how do I truncate these because there's no backup for this that's going to truncate these logs and
every Exchange guy knows your Exchange Server crashes because your backups aren't working and wouldn't truncate
the logs and it filled up all the disk space and it's going to do it in a heartbeat.
So I'm trying to find that information out and I'll put that up on powershell.org when we have some more
details on ESENT and how they intend to use this. I don't know if it's circular logging or not and I.
(Audience comment)
Well they could set it for whatever they wanted, so and that's what I don't know, so I'm trying to find that out.
But this change has just occurred, so don't be surprised when you go out there and see.
Oh, come on somebody had to watch Buck Rogers.
Yeah.
It's stage data. Oh, it was funny. Alright. What else?
Have you tried exploring the contents of that?
Not yet. I haven't had a chance. Because believe me I'm going to next week, but I haven't had a chance.
Because this literally just happened last week and I went oh, I wonder if any of my demos are now going to work.
(Audience comment)
Yeah, that's another thing. Yeah, that's probably something else that we probably should get around to fixing
at some point, yeah, or at least telling everybody that they need to make sure they delete that stuff.
Yeah, that's really good.
So pull servers. They're great, but we need some more work on them, so have patience.
Play with it in your lab environment. Yeah.
(Audience comment)
I know. So was mine. Well because the engineer told me make sure that your web.config says ESENT instead
of JET and I'm like what? What just happened? (laughs)
Yeah, and I don't have many details on this.
I think it's going to be really cool, but I don't have any details on this.
The other thing is this makes high availability just a little bit more challenging because--
I don't think they have any block replication capabilities like a DAG set up for this. (laughs)
That's my other question too.
(Audience comment)
Yeah, yeah. I think this is, from my initial set, I think this is probably a really good idea and those are
really smart people on the team, so they don't do things haphazard, so I'm thinking this is a really good idea.
I just thought it was funny because my Exchange eyes just went--wahahaha!
Alright, guys. Well thanks. I'll stand up here if you want to ask any questions.
Other than that, go to lunch, have fun, and enjoy the rest of your day.
Thank you!