So I'm going to set the LCM for these guys.
What I have is this is the way I usually do my LCM configurations, I separate the config data.
You don't see this a lot on the internet. This is actually a really cool way to do it, so all the config
data's up here for the LCM and then I can just tell it how many machines, whatever machines, and what roles I
want them to have and I never have to touch this code down here again.
So I just think this is a cool way to do an LCM. It's going to do multiple machines and here's where, I had this
cute little line of code and apparently now in v5, you can just do this.
Instead of the two lines of code, I'm going to show you, I'm just going to go bump, bump.
Whoops. I did it to the wrong thing. I am a moron. This line of code.
You just give it the path to them and it'll, all the ones that it sees there, it'll just kick them out.
Well now I broke this update computername s1 and s2. Yeah, that's the one machine, yeah that stupid config name registration.
You telling me it's not going to work at all? S2 is working. I'm going to try and see if I can get s1 to work
because s2 just registered, so let's see here. It's going to take a minute for this config to run.
I'm going to re-run it again to see if it picks up s1.
But the idea here is besides the config name bug, we bundled and put the resources up.
Here's the cool thing. One machine needs all four of those resources.
The other machine only needs two of those resources, so we only bring down the resources that machine needs.
We don't just copy them all down. Now here's what's going to happen, the resources must be available on the
pull server when the LCM runs the MOF because the first thing he's going to do is look at the MOF and go what
resources do you need and then he's going to go do I have access to those.
So he's not even going to start jamming on it until he can get those resources down.
I'll show you here in a second. Oh, that was awfully quick for you.
That was way too quick for you. Cannot invoke, oh, it's still in progress.
Okay. I'm going to do something I probably shouldn't do. You're not going to let me do it, are you.
Well let me show you if the resources got out there and I can't believe this, but my beautiful, it worked fine
on Sunday before they updated the module. No, it's not put them out there yet.
Okay, let's do this. You're really messing up my applause line, man.
Yeah. Yeah. That's just a shame because I don't think either one of them got set up because it was way too fast.
Yeah, that's a shame. Well I'm sorry guys, but you don't get to see the pretty website.
Did you even care about the pretty website? Of course you cared about the pretty website and I can't get it
to work now! Ahh.
(Audience comment)
Well I'll tell you what. I want to make sure that we don't go over here, but maybe I can.
Let's do this real quick. Let me see if I can, let's do this. Remove-DscConfigurationDocument to CimSession
s1, oh he's only going to let me do 1, Stage pending. Now a lot of times you have to do this when you're
troubleshooting something that gets stuck. Okay, he doesn't have one.
Consistency check, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, okay. Now let's try to run it again.
Maybe I can get him to go. Come on, do me a favor, just work. You're not going to do it, are you?
Nope, there's something in that update that came down that he isn't going to do it.
Oh, this says the checksum failed. Oh, maybe I can fix this. Hold on, hold on, hold on, hold on.
Let's just make sure that I got everything zipped correctly and let's make sure I got some checksums.
We'll make new ones.
(Audience comment)
Yeah, the force is overriding it. If you don't use -Force, it won't actually overwrite your earlier checksum.
That's another little trick.
And let me copy them back up there. And let me make sure I've got them all copied.
You know, I may not have copied them up there, so we may still get to see a website.
Now I'm setting your expectations and if it blows up, I'm going to look like a moron.
Okay, there they are. There they are. On the pull server. Okay, let's try it again.
Let's try it again. Cross your fingers, right now, cross your fingers.
Oh well. Uncross your fingers. We're not going to get the website guys, but
the moral of the story is that the packaging of those modules is very finicky about the names and I want to
go back to this one thing on checksums. This -Force, nobody puts that in and they can't figure out why they
can't get their updated modules to work
because the checksum doesn't get updated. I think that by default, it should just overwrite it, but it doesn't.
So -Force is like saying overwrite the existing checksum because what it does is it goes oh, you have a checksum,
I'm not making a new one, which seems kind of ridonkulous to me, so -Force is very important right there to
make him go just do it and life is good.
Is it new? Because before I always deleted the checksum and then rewrite it.
Is -Force new?
Yeah.
I think so because I used to always delete them too. Yeah, so I'm thinking that that's new.
But I do know this, it doesn't work unless you have -Force. Ta-da!
Is that broke, an error?
No, it doesn't throw it because it's not an error. You say New-Checksum, it goes oh you already got one.
That's not an error in his mind. I think it's an error. So yeah, you end up troubleshooting it for like
three days because you can't figure out what's going on until you notice that the, you actually look at the
checksum and you notice it's not getting updated in there.
(Audience comment)
Yeah, or if you think to manually delete it and do it.
Oh yeah, in verbose you can see it. If you read the verbose output, yeah you can see it in there, yeah.