So when I think about the growth
areas in this, I especially look at DSC and PowerShell classes. Being able to create resources and implement
DSC and be able to leverage those relationship maps
in order to ensure consistency in the environment. Or the other way around.
DSC is setting the configuration and you just pulled the information from the DSC MOF files.
Because when you still have to go out and do things and identify what's happening and where it's going,
DSC isn't going to do everything at this point. We're going to get to a place where DSC is capable of
managing multiple layers of the stack, but I was only able to find
Cisco UCS that had a DSC resource outside of what Microsoft was delivering.
Are there any others that you know of that Microsoft has not delivered?
Yeah, so that's kind of what I thought too. And I also think from a growth standpoint, as we continue to see
people move away from snap-ins and go more towards modules, it gives you an opportunity, as I mentioned earlier,
to kind of extend this out a great deal, right, to be able to do more in the environment just directly from
whatever system that you want. You don't have this cumbersome installation process and managing all of those.
You just simply make sure that the module is loaded.