the concept I wanted to share today is something that I've been working on.
I'm very much interested in your thoughts on this as well. And it's what I
call the Application DNA. And when you look in an application and you think about all the different
relationships that are associated with it, the fact that there are multiple layers that must be delivered
consistently and accurately in order to have that application actually function.
In order for you to execute change, you have to understand this and let's just start with the reporting standpoint.
If you're reporting on
this, man that is a bear. I want to understand all of the virtual machines, actually you can't even say that, right.
I want to understand all the virtual disks that are associated with the data store that's associated with the
LUN that's associated with this file or this storage platform or this, right, because in today's world,
as everything moves to policy-based, it could be anywhere. So the concept that I've worked on and I won't
pretend like I've solved it, right, it's kind of why I wanted to have lots of time here so that we can talk
about it, is when you're trying to get that information and trying to do those things, when I was at Cisco,
we had a need for that kind of report. We wanted to understand all the applications that were sitting
on VMAC storage because it's expensive and we wanted to make sure that nobody was on there that wasn't supposed
to be on there. Are you kidding me? Right, like that's a significant undertaking, right, because not only
did I need to identify what virtual machines were there, I needed to understand what the applications were
and I needed to understand who the application belonged to, right, and I would run this report and it would
take about 22 hours. I was using Get-View, I was doing filtering, it just took time because you're still stuck
doing a lot of this, right. So what I ended up having to do, and this was one of the big challenges of scale,
is you end up having to break it out into multiple systems, so each Virtual Center Server then had its
own PowerShell Server, and that PowerShell server was specifically dedicated for executing things against
that Virtual Center Server. I created some trusts in there, but now I have to manage a dozen PowerShell Servers.
And of course, we did the one ring to rule them all. We have one PowerShell that would execute against all
the other PowerShell Servers. That sucked, but I was able to get it done in 6 hours instead of 22 hours.
And what dawned on me because like here's,
yeah, what dawned on me is that
there has to be a better way of doing this because not only did I get into that, but when there was an
opportunity that I needed to execute something or change something, maybe change a configuration,
maybe I needed to move all those virtual machines that weren't supposed to be there.
I have to deal with multiple layers of that infrastructure, and then guess what I end up having to do,
I have to do the same queries over again. That's just dumb, right, because it takes up time, it takes up memory
and that's time that the business would like back, especially when you start thinking about DevOps
organizations and you're trying to implement things in a fast reliable manner and you're trying to shave
seconds sometimes in your value string. Why? Because the faster that you can get through test and release,
the quicker you get value for your efforts. Okay? So the concept with the DNA is that what if in
the background, we kind of collect these relationship things. We find some efficiencies in how we collect,
but in the background we collect this information and store it and I've played with multiple types.
They're all ugly, so I'm very much interested in feedback on how to accomplish this, but I've kind of settled
on JSON because JSON is just really fast and you can collect the information into an object, pipe it out
to a JSON file and it's very easy to import it and it be object-based.
And so the way this would work
is you would go out and you'd collect that information just like I had said before, but you do it for everything.
Like this is just a single one, but you would do it for everything and you would get these mappings.
You pipe it to a JSON file, and when you start your session, you put in your profile to load the contents
of that file and you have this collection happen
several times a day, but here's the thing, most the time it's stuff doesn't change.
The relationship maps do not frequently change. The only time they really change is when you have to perform
maintenance event, right. And so, being able to collect this information and store it into a file and then
absorb it into an object, you can then reference that object instead of doing that cross-platform query.
You get away from doing the Get-AllVolumes and find the one that just does the SCSI with the SCSI Id.
What you do instead is
you just find the SCSI Id that's in that JSON or in that object that you imported and you have all the
information for that entire application stack that's associated with that.
Does that make sense? Am I off my rocker? If I am, please tell me.
Right, because this has felt a bit like a leap and it's a little challenging,