Alright, I was kidding. We're not going to talk about cmdlets. I was just kidding.
We're going to talk about some challenges.
So here's some core challenges that you have to deal with. Yeah, I got problems.
So a lot of the core challenges that you have to deal with are how to manage the different modules and tools,
and the snap-ins that are made available. The relationship mapping, which I've touched on, I want to get
into a lot more detail about, and then dealing with problems that are associated with scale.
So we're going to talk about like as you go to implement some of this stuff, these are some of the pitfalls
that you're going to run into.
So we'll start with multiple providers. Now there are two types of ways that companies will provide PowerShell capability.
Right. Traditionally, it's been PowerShell snap-ins. Well because that was the only way they could do it,
right, that was the only real option. Fortunately, most providers have moved over to delivering a module.
Now it's still developed in Visual Studio, still developed with C# .NET, it's compiled and it's provided out
to you, so it's kind of locked. You can't get into it, but it is a module, right, that you can load.
And
the thing that's really important to remember there is that with a module it can be transported, right, it's transferrable.
You can put that on any system, any system that runs PowerShell that needs to perform a task, right, so if you
have multiple layers of the stack, you can extract these modules, put them in a central location, or add them
as I describe here to the PS module path so that when the session loads, that module is available, right,
and you can then leverage it along with others at the same time.
So if you're looking at managing VMware in Cisco UCS, and SolidFire, or Pure or whatever, you can have all of those
in the same spot. Well this is really, really handy because it's transportable, you can put that on any
system and you can now do a level of reporting, right, an execution that you wouldn't have been able to do otherwise.
Because if you're having to deal with multiple tools in Windows, yeah everybody likes to talk about the
single pane in class. I think PowerShell's like the ultimate single pane, right.
It's the single pane of kick ass. I'm quoting that. It's going on a t-shirt.
PowerShell single pane of kick ass, right. So I'll show you an example of
that, right, so you have your storage and you're wanting to query for that information like we talked about,
and for this one, like with the VLAN MTU, your common piece of information is the MAC address, the MAC address
that goes from the Cisco UCS port that's being delivered to the ESXi host, you go out and get that, and as I
show it here, and I'd thought I had shown the full cmdlet, but you can go in and that information is
accessible, right, that's neat, it's straightforward, but you end up doing
what I had mentioned here, you collect it all, you filter, and then you grab the piece that you really want.
This is wildly inefficient, right. So the concept I wanted to share today, and I've talked way faster than I thought I would.