Any other questions? Thoughts? Funny stories?
So Josh. I noticed on your third slide you had a whole VMware stack and a very popular vRealize orchestrator.
Yeah. I'm curious. How do you use an orchestrator because we developed and raised PowerShell scripts that
makes all these decisions for us and I feel silly for bringing an orchestrator because I've just taken all
that logic out and I build it and I run _____ as something stupid like that.
Yeah. So how do you use it? Or do you use it and use the dev?
Yeah, so I use Orchestrator primarily if there's any decisions that need to make, if there's going to be any
branch like if anything will change as a result of a condition or I need to do things like it will change
due to a condition. It says that if this condition exists, go this way, if it doesn't, go that way.
I tend to use Orchestrator for that. But it also really comes down to with Orchestrator what you have plug-ins
for and what you have actions and workflows for and that's where you hit a point and you're like well time to
go to PowerShell and then you can call from that. So I've tended towards Orchestrator primarily, and again,
anyway I'll talk about the hammer like when you're hammering everything is a nail like I always start with PowerShell.
I force myself to use Orchestrator and other tools. The biggest advantage and
I didn't show it here, but right here is the same idea, yeah, so that's vRealize Orchestrator is also object
aware in the VStore WebClient and it's supported like fully supported.
So you can create the workflows right in that, so a lot of the stuff
that I'm talking about, you can do with Orchestrator as well. This is PowerShell conference.
But with PowerActions, I like it because it also allows me to do more things because Orchestrator doesn't cover everything.
And that's the part that I'm struggling with is that I want to expose something simple to people.
Yeah. I don't want it to let them... Yeah, and for me everything is if I can just give you an
opportunity to run it and you not care how it's built on the back-end.
I tend towards Orchestrator primarily because it's fully supported from VMware and it's not handing someone a
PowerCLI script, but if you look at my GitHub repos, it's all PowerShell stuff, right.
I haven't released the Orchestrator stuff yet. But we have some customers using it, I just don't, I help them,
but I don't publish it. (Audience comment) Yep, so the primary requirements you have to have a PowerShell
Server and when you do the install, you have to make some modifications to the vSphere Virtual Center Server appliance
and there's some files that you have to make a slight modification to and there's that modification is
just so it will show up in the UI. (Audience comment) I think it's 5.5 is the one with the newer VStore WebClient.
So I've run it in 6, I had it running in 5.5. I don't think it's supported in 5.1 because I just don't think
that the WebClient functions with it. And then from the PowerShell side, Server 2012, actually I can pull it up.
So it's labs.vmware.com/flings and their site was down the other day for maintenance, so I'm hoping it's back up.
It is. Good. (Audience comment) What's that? There we go. So look for PowerActions and it goes right in
system requirements, 5.1 is included, so that 1 is included. Alright.
Server 2003 or higher, .NET framework 4, and 4.5 and then all the PowerShell versions.
And of course,
whatever version that you have. And here's the thing. You have to have all the modules for the different
layers in infrastructure onto that PowerShell server, otherwise, it can't run.
(Audience comment) No. It'll be separate unless you were running the Windows version.
If you're running the Windows version of the Virtual Center Server, it can all be native.
I think VMware has made it sufficiently painful to run the Windows version.
I think a lot of people have, they've improved the appliance sufficiently that a lot of people have moved
over to that, at least that I'm seeing. Alright, well I guess I'll just close it out.
If anybody wants to talk with me after, you'll get a little bit of time back.
I hope that this kind of gave you some insight into how PowerShell's being leveraged across the stack.
I also hope that when you start thinking about some of the challenges of taking advantage of those, this kind of
gets you in that frame of mind. Like I said at the beginning, I don't pretend to have all the answers.
I just simply know some of the questions that you need to be asking and wanted to feed some thoughts into how
you might tackle those things. And so, once I get that repo out, I'll make sure that I hit the
PowerShell summit hashtag when I deploy that out and I'll let everybody know and I'll look forward to your contributions.
Thank you for your time and your feedback and your participation.
I appreciate it. And despite what my wife says, I don't really feel the need to talk for long periods of time
without people talking back, so thank you for that and I appreciate it.