Alright, so let's start with some of the tools. Well here's the thing, right, we're all PowerShellers and
when we look at the things that we're trying to accomplish, a lot of the things that I mentioned earlier that
we're seeking, the first thing that we think to do is
can I do it with PowerShell. It's not always the best tool for it.
I would argue that generally it's a fantastic tool for doing these things, but for us as PowerShellers,
that is our native first response, like can I do it with PowerShell.
And one thing
that is fundamentally changed over the last five years is that in our infrastructure we have more APIs.
More products are coming to market and we are hitting
refresh cycles in our data centers where we're bringing these products in, where there is more extensibility,
right, APIs are made available that will allow you to remotely manage and configure and take care of your
infrastructure, and as such, we're seeing a lot more growth in PowerShell
modules that support that. Now this is not all-inclusive, in fact, everybody take a minute, absorb it,
and then we're going to have a sharing session where you can tell me the things I missed so that I can
include it later. And to be fair, right, I work for SolidFire with NetApp, right, we're a storage company,
but I'll include competitors on here because I think it's fantastic that PowerShell has become so pervasive
in our data center that we're able to do so many things with it, right, and when you look at this, right,
you've got your PowerShell, and then you got the Hypervisor stack, and of course, Hyper-VM is in there.
I kind of consider that rolled into PowerShell. Right. You've got some server technology.
I think Dell has a little bit of stuff, right. You've got storage or you have storage and then you have
things from the community where people are producing things and the reason they're doing this is because
there's an API. There is extensibility
in our data center unlike what we've had in the past and it is allowing us to tackle these challenges and to
jump on new things and deliver new capabilities in our data centers, and in this, we're going to talk about
how these layout, right? So
this is the stack that we talked about and when you look, as I mentioned, PowerShell is everywhere, right.
Most of these layers can be controlled with PowerShell one way or the other.
I found the dead zone and I don't know why I put that slide in there twice.
I just thought you liked it and so there we go. It's a great slide.
So community involvement. What did I miss? Just speak up. Did I miss one that you use?
I have used Dell EqualLogic. Dell EqualLogic. Revel of Intentry. Revel of Intentry.
Excellent. Okay, so I did pretty well then. Excellent. Nutanix.
Nutanix. Yep, excellent. Dell. Dell. Yep. System Center. System Center.
Pier Storage. Pier Storage, got it. That's it. Yep. Azure. Azure.
That's right. Any others that you use? AWS. AWS. Excellent. Alright, so for those listening at home and
people that are here, there is a lot that is possible, right, but there are also a lot of challenges.
Well we'll start with use cases, right.
What do we do with this big toolbox of PowerShell capabilities?
I have a meming problem. It's a fun problem. First step is admitting it.
Alright, so when you talk about PowerShell in the stack, see I worked really hard on this graphic, it's not really
complicated, but I'm just really proud of it, so I just want it on every slide that I can, right.
When you talk about PowerShell in the stack, there are a few low-hanging fruits, right.
You've got reporting, right, everybody's reporting, and the interesting thing is when you talk about reporting
is there's a lot of different things that you might be interested in seeing from a report and we'll talk
about a couple of those in a second. Implementation is another.
Being able to go out into your environment and configure net new resources, looking at DevOps, how do you
reduce time in the value string. How are you able to improve the effectiveness of your development team and
the consistency of your operations team leveraging PowerShell?
Maintaining configuration, obviously desired state configuration is a great example of that.
And then also we're going to touch on extending tools and these are tools that you already use that are able
to take advantage of PowerShell in managing your data center stack.
So the first example we'll look at is from a reporting standpoint and from an implementation and configuration standpoint.
If you were running a data center today, there is a high likelihood that you're running multiple VLANs.
There's a high likelihood that you're running jumbo frames and if you or any, and I see some heads nodding,
so if you're in an environment where you're doing this, has anybody ever seen a good situation from a VLAN
not being consistent up and down the stack and being exposed. It never ends well and it's a bear to find
sometimes, like where is this traffic dropping? Why am I not being able to get access to this application?
Same with MTU, right, when you're looking at jumbo frames for storage or for whatever the application is,
if it's not configured consistently everywhere, you've got problems and
the challenging thing is depending on the architecture and the infrastructure that you have, you may not have
PowerShell up and down that, but look at how many layers are involved, right.
If you were dealing with a VLAN and it needs to be a specific VLAN for an application, that's a lot of
layers to have to check and you have to deal with that with troubleshooting.
And at the end of this talk, I'm going to share an idea that I've had on how to help improve this.
So another great example storage. Anybody have storage in their environment?
If you have virtualization, you have storage. Storage is fundamentally critical in virtualized environments.
It is one of the key things that enable virtualization in the first place.
The ability to have a shared resource that's accessible to multiple hosts, and when you look at that,
there are some significant complexities around identifying, especially if you're dealing with performance and
capacity issues, which let's be honest, those are the storage issues that we deal with regularly, right,
to be able to identify that
this application has got a problem and where is that problem? Like where in the stack do we identify that?
And when you're looking at your entire infrastructure stack and you're trying to
get gain visibility in what's going on, understanding the configuration, understanding the relationships that
the different layers of your infrastructure have and leveraging PowerShell to do it, the most important thing
that you can understand is
that right there, that relationship, right. What is that piece of information that connects one layer to the next?
And for most people when they're looking at managing their infrastructure as a whole, this is one of the
biggest challenges that they have. How do I identify
what correlates that data store with this volume, right, or that VMDK to that Datastore, that Datastore to that volume.
Alright, what is that? And then this, I used SolidFire for this one because I already wrote this code and I
didn't have to write new code. But what we're looking at here is I need to understand what the volume is
that's supporting that Datastore and this is the Lun, like this is the physical storage that's being
presented to the Hypervisor to be shared so that we can provide resources to that application.
And in doing that,
I have to identify what piece of information is important and available both on the PowerCLI side, the VMware side,
and the SolidFire side that makes the connection, and in this case,
it's the SCSI Id, right, the NAAdeviceID, and by going to PowerCLI, right, and we use the Get-ScsiLun
by going into PowerCLI, we know the Datastore that we want, we collect, we find the CanonicalName,
which incidentally matches the NAAID, right, for the SolidFire side, we get that, we do a little manipulation
with splitting it, we get that part of the array, and we store that.
And when I go to find out what the volume is, I'm doing a Where statement, right.
So Where, I'm getting all of the volumes and saying where this value equals that.
Now is there anything in this that just throws up a red flag of inefficiency it?
I would get them all. Exactly.
Right. Why? Because it's easy. That's why. Right, but and then also with some implementations,
and this is something that I really wanted to point out. Anyway, I mean this is
I guess you would consider a negative on the SolidFire side, right.
We don't have a strong filtering mechanism. Why? Because the API was not designed to do that, right.
The API just considers it sufficient. Like it's okay if you pull it all to get that, right.
That's not neither good nor bad, but when you're thinking about a large environment, think about what it
would take to do a report when you have 100 Datastores and how much time that would take, okay.
So another use case, and it's in the book, just for you Luc. Okay, so when I was looking at contributing to
that book, I was trying to think from a VMware perspective, why would I care about DSC?
Because at the time, the work that Luc Dekens has done around DSC and VMware did not exist.
There were no resources. There were no capabilities, and it wasn't at the time you ask the question,
well what would you want DSC to do. Right. Still very much in that exploratory phase.
So I have this little bit of a conundrum. Alright, so how do I demonstrate the value of DSC that would be
useful to someone who manages the VMware environment. And so how many was it that manage VMware environments?
You don't count. You said you don't raise your hand at sessions.
Okay, so what I came up with is this concept of the DMZ, right, now that's not the concept I created.
The demilitarized zone, this is where its
front-end, right, it's behind a firewall, so it doesn't touch your regular infrastructure environment,
it's virtualized, right, so it's sitting on ESXi, it's managed by Virtual Center Server, these are VMs,
they're on a VLAN that is dedicated to the DMZ, so they have isolation, right, maybe not air gap, but anyway it's
still isolation, right. And you don't want to open a bunch of ports because every time you open a port,
that's an opportunity for penetration from the outside, right. You want your firewall as locked down as possible.
So how the hell do you use DSC in this environment? Let's just say we've got hundreds of machines sitting
there servicing a web application that is critical to your business and your businesses success.
How do you deal with that? How do you implement DSC? Well, I'm mean you can put your pull server out there,
but that's a bad idea, right.
You talk about honey pot. Somebody gets a hold of that, you're toast.
Right. They can configure whatever they want, so you don't want to do that.
So this hurt my head. It hurt my head
a lot. Like how would I accomplish this? Okay, so we have the DSC pull server, it's sitting inside of our
network, but we don't want to open up the ports, so how do you get it to communicate?
Anybody have a guess? Except for Luc. Invoke VM script. Invoke VM script.
That is a great way of doing that. So yeah, you leverage the VMware tools.
Right. For those who aren't aware, PowerCLI and VMware vSphere, you know with the VMware tools that are on a
virtual machine, you can actually remotely execute through the VMware tools.
It goes through the ESXi host directly into the guest and it leverages the VMware tools to do things.
Alright. And so what I did
and this is all available on GitHub, right, if you want to see the full code.
I just pulled snippets to describe, right. What I ended up having to do is we create the MOF file inside of
the network, we copy that MOF file using the, what was it, Copy-VMGuestFile, right, we copy that file into that
and then we use Invoke-VMScript to execute DSC and to execute on the MOF file, right to get the configuration.
Now recognizing
that this doesn't allow that LCM to be able to reach out and say hey am I still good, right.
This definitely you're pushing it out to the application's system, but it does enable that capability, right.
You are able to go in, configure that, and get it out there without having to open up all the ports.
So the key thing
here is you have to use multiple different layers of PowerShell to accomplish this and I will point out that
the original idea and the concept was I would just put the code from building the MOF file and everything and
do Invoke-VMScript. Well you're only allowed to send one line of code with Invoke-VMScript, right.
You can have it call a script file and have it do other things, but you're only allowed to send one line of code
and that just doesn't work with DSC. Alright, it's not going to happen.
Okay. So this was an example of how to leverage PowerShell in an environment against multiple different layers
in order to solve a problem. Alright, and it was helpful because I'd already written a code, so I didn't
have to write a whole bunch of code.