My name is Josh Atwell and I am here to talk to you about managing your infrastructure stack with PowerShell.
Little disclaimer, I'm not going to show you a bunch of code. I'm not going to teach you how to use a cmdlet.
I'm not going to show you clever little things that I've done with PowerShell.
That's not entirely true. I'll show you a couple of little things.
But what we're going to talk about today and this is something that I very much want you to be engaged with me,
point out where I have gaps, and expand on this. This is a conversation starter and we're going to talk
about a lot of the challenges and the capabilities of PowerShell when you look at the total infrastructure stack.
Okay? If you're on Twitter, I highly encourage you to use the PowerShell Summit hashtag.
You can mock
me and heckle me all you want. That's fine. I'm accustomed to that.
Throw it on Twitter and we'll have some fun with it and I just thought POSHit was just a fantastic hashtag
for so many reasons, so I threw it up there. You can use it or not.
I'm good either way. But as I said, I'm Josh Atwell. I'm a developer advocate at SolidFire, which is now
part of NetApp.
And we have the big thanks to people. How many people were using PowerShell right at the very beginning?
Throw your hands up. Alright, how many started with version 2? And how many of you do not like raising your
hands during presentations? Excellent. I like to _____ my audience and make sure that I don't count any
of your lack of votes. You guys are boring. I'm just kidding. I'm not name calling here.
So thanks to those folks. So a little bit about me and I have two hours, so I'm going to talk about myself
as much as possible. I'm kidding there too. But there's some things that I think are really important before
we get started so that we can level set on why this topic was something I submitted an I thought we should talk about.
I started out my career working for a small civil engineering firm where I did desktop support and then server
support and started virtualization. It's where I got started with PowerShell.
My intent was to automate some tasks. It started with Exchange and I think a lot of people who got started
early on, Exchange was that first integration that they worked with, right, I mean
can I get an Amen? Right. That was when Microsoft really legitimized PowerShell as a tool that you should invest
time and energy in and I did that. And VMware then released the vi toolkit and we're going to get into a lot
of these integrations here in a minute, but as part of this narrative, it's important to understand that
once the VI Toolkit became a thing, now there was this opportunity to do something much broader and much
more impactful in the environment than simply managing my mailboxes and accounts and all that stuff, right.
So that took me into CARQUEST general parts where I was responsible for basically rearchitecting the virtual
environment and enabling the development team, right. How do I speed up their efforts?
We have this really interesting thing we call today called DevOps, right.
This was something, and Luc and I've had a conversation on this, DevOps isn't something new.
It's something that we've kind of already done. It's just we have new tools and new methodologies to talk about it.
I'll talk about that a little bit more in a little bit.
Going into Cisco IT from General Parts, I went from managing hundreds of virtual machines to tens of thousands
of virtual machines and in that process, there was an element where
the manager says to me we need to automate, so we don't have to have extra headcount and we need you to do that, right.
And when you start looking at an environment that size, you have to take things into consideration that you
don't normally have to consider because you have time and we're going to talk about a lot of those things in
this session about how you can leverage PowerShell for multiple layers of the data center, some of the
challenges that are associated with that, and then how you address them.
And then now I'm at SolidFire. We were recently acquired my NetApp and in my role as developer advocate,
I still write a little bit of code from time to time, but I'm primarily focused on getting people together who
develop and work with our integrations and work in the infrastructure stack that are trying to solve problems
whether it's DevOps, whether it's just LeanOps and trying to improve your operations regardless of what they're
doing and try to help make them more successful. So I share the things that they do, I elevate the
conversation, and I try to get people engaged, which makes doing things like this fun, except for I'm like
oh crap, I need to write some more code.