I don't want to teach you guys cmdlets, alright. Like you guys know cmdlets, you know how to use Get-Help right.
So the next thing that I want to make sure that you're familiar with and introduce and I thought I had a picture
on this, but apparently I don't. So I upload up a vin, I'll get connected, and show you how PowerActions work.
So PowerActions is a VMware fling and
if you go to labs.vmware.com/flings, search for PowerActions, what PowerActions allows you to do is you
install it in your vSphere WebClient, and once installed, it provides a PowerShell console in the vSphere WebClient.
Now it's powered and backed by a server, a Windows Server that's running PowerShell, but what it does is it
enables you to execute PowerShell directly through the VStore WebClient and the screenshot that I thought was
here was a beautiful representation of this, so we'll get that in a minute.
But the other thing it allows you to do is it allows you to create scripts and files, right, that you can
share, your create functions that you can share within the VStore WebClient that will allow you to be able
to execute against something. Use case for this would be, I don't know about you guys, but when I go into a
VStore environment and I see all the storage and there's Datastore, Datastore (1), Datastore (2), Datastore (3),
Datastore (4), Datastore (5) because every time you install ESXi, it just calls the local disk Datastore.
I'm a little OCD. This bothers me. Right. So there's a PowerAction I've created and put out where you
right-click on the Datastore and you say set the local name, and it goes out, it pulls ESXi hostname,
and renames the Datastore to that name-local. Alright, so now you have logical information.
Now that's just an example. You can also do things such as being able to select a network or select a
Datastore and be able to query and say what MTU is set up and down the stack, right.
It'll check the switch, it'll check the port, it'll check like Cisco UCS and the networking there and you
can have that send a report. So if you were in that troubleshooting situation and you remember we had that
full layer, that stack that we had to deal with, this gives you
an opportunity to go in and take care of that and get that information and have it embedded directly in the
VStore WebClient, which is a tool that most of us are already using anyway.
Alright, so you're not have to jump around.
Everybody going to go check that out? It's not supported, so be mindful where you put it.
It's not officially supported, but it's pretty cool.