It's not a good example when it's not working, is it.
Alright, well let me show you the PowerAction stuff as well while we're talking about that.
So this is PowerActions as I was describing earlier, so I'll go to Home screen real quick.
Once you install it, it allows you to create these scripts that can be accessed
directly through the VStore WebClient, and so I've got several of them that I see on a regular basis.
Now I'm not a big fan of storage, but I work in storage company, so I talked to a lot of people about storage.
So a few things that we run into are like changing queue depth and changing naming,
changing performance characteristics, and in order to do that successfully without reaching across silos,
if you will, going into a storage team, you have to make that relationship and to do that query.
And currently, it works fine. It just takes longer to actually get all these.
And since my other script didn't run, I can't actually show them in action, but I
can show you how it works. Here's a PowerCLI Console that I mentioned.
It's, well I'm not connected, but it's PowerShell like it just runs.
Alright, let's go to this and so when you right-click, say Execute script, and it will tell you what's there.
You select which one that you want to run and it will prompt you.
I don't think I can run any of those because the storage is disconnected, but yeah, and what
it allows you to do then is to be able to identify or execute things or report back and identify how this
relates to other things like you could have a report that says give me all the snapshot information, give me all
the VLANs that are being used that are associated with this host on the Cisco UCS or something like that,
make sure that those two match up. Alright, so we've got some customers that are working on doing that.
That make sense? I wish I could run it, but I can do the local Datastore.
I guess my PowerShell Server is broken. I'm sorry. That's what I get for updating it to version 5 and not
testing before the conference.
Sorry about that.