There we go. Alright. So this function is designed to go through and basically it will when I work with
customers, a lot of them have used NFS or Fibre Channel and they're looking at size SCSI and they're like ugh,
I've got to provision all of this storage into my environment. I'm like ah, it's a piece of cake.
Here's a PowerShell function. That'll do it. But what I did here is I didn't want to just
create a bunch of volumes and then tell the VMware administrator that they existed.
So I wanted to do some things that were dynamic and I think it actually
ran, so but so what we're doing is we go in and when you run the function, you identify that this is the cluster
and give it a cluster name, how many volumes you want, the performance characteristics of it, is this for an
existing tenant like an existing account, is this a net new account, and then how do you want those organized
on the storage system. And then provisioning it all to the VStore cluster.
And so, let me make sure I'm logged into VStore environment. I'm not used to everybody watching me type.
Alright, and so what it does is when we go to set up, right, I'm collecting information as we go.
I'm collecting cluster information, I'm collecting host information, I'm creating targets, I collect the IQNs
from the storage system and I present them over to the VMware environment, alright, so there we go.
I need to add the IQNs from the ESXi host to the SolidFire storage system so that it goes and trusts that it
can connect to that and I'm leveraging multiple levels. So now I'm working on also doing some stuff with
Cisco UCS where you can kind of configure like if they want a specific VLAN to connect to all the stores,
things like that, and then go through and rescans and it connects.
So here you're adding the Datastores, you do a scan, identify the Datastores exist.
We're going to pull the volume name from the storage system, so we can make the Datastore match the volume
name that is on the storage system so that
it's easier for you to talk with your storage administrator about which system that you might need to change.
And then it just adds the Datastore. You create a new Datastore.
So you're dealing with multiple layers of the stack there and the bulk of the work in this is really
identifying those relationships. Like when something breaks, it's because I didn't map something correctly,
which is kind of what got me down this path. Let's see. Alright, and so now yeah, it's all disconnected.
That's sad.