Alright, so this is kind of near the end of the talk, but I'm going to log into a lab here in just a minute
assuming the internet connection and we can kind of walk through
some of these different integrations, kind of talk about this a little bit if you want to.
If you don't, then we don't have to. It's totally up to you. But any questions thus far?
Because you've been way too quiet. (Audience question) Yeah, so I'm still trying to sort out.
I wish I had a whiteboard because whiteboards and me get along really, really well.
So the question was how do you do updates? What's the plan for updating the JSON or updating the information
because there is this opportunity for the information to become stale if something changes in the environment
and so what I'm working on right now primarily is identifying the situations where a change would occur.
In a typical environment, what type of things would make a relationship map change?
And some of those would be like a VMotion, like a virtual machine moves over, you add additional resources
that are tied to something else, you add disk, you add new network, adding things like that.
Removing things obviously would make a change. So from a data integrity standpoint, it's really what we're
coming to, right. Is this data going to be stale? Is it still going to be useful?
I've thus far found that the number of changes are relatively small and I think if we look at what
information we're collecting because like let's go back to
when you think about what information that you need to collect all the way up the stack, I'm not sure how
much change we really would expect and it's one of those I'm kind of unsure about how I want to deal with that
because I've also looked at maybe using SQL Server and just create our relational database of all this stuff
because I treat, at present, I'm treating network, storage, compute separately and pulling and collecting that
information separately because they are relatively tied to each other, and identifying where you have things
that cross across those three stacks. Because at some point, you just
kind of have to draw the line of how you're going to be able to collect the information and when I'm doing
this, I'm really focused
on these, right, those points, so I'm building functions that collect those points.
And so the intent is that once I build these functions and have all those relationships mapped out,
you could then just pick the ones that matter to you, that are interesting, put it in there, and run those individually.
And so, they can run on their own in the background at whatever frequency you want and update that data as you go.
So this is why I really wanted to leave time to talk about this because I don't pretend that I have all the
answers and I certainly don't pretend that I know how to solve this problem, but I do know that especially
in environments where there's scale, this is a problem
and it's a problem a lot of us are going to face as we start getting more and more layers of PowerShell.
Right now, in my poll, they said 33% of the people polled of I think there was 40 votes, were managing 7 plus layers
or items in their stack. I'm sure somebody in here is doing that, right.
Anybody would classify themselves as seven plus layers? One, one, going twice, two.
Okay. Let's go back to the.
Alright, so when we look at this, alright so how many would say one to two?
Three to four? Five to six? And then we already established a couple people doing seven or more.
So what's going to happen to everybody that's only doing a couple?
Here's what's going to happen over the next few years. One, you're going to refresh cycles on things in your infrastructure.
You're going to buy new things. And as PowerShellers and people who have influenced their organization to
automate and use PowerShell and get value, you're going to have influence in that buying decision.
You should. You're going to look for things that have PowerShell integration as a capability.
It's going to become valuable for you. And in doing so, you're going to then say alright, I've got a new tool,
I want to go in, I'm going to PowerShell this bad boy, and then you're going to run into all these things
about figuring out like how does this connect to that? How do I get this to happen faster?
And that's one of the things I found challenging because I put this poll out because I'm just like is this a
problem that a lot of people are facing yet and I feel like there should be, but I don't hear a whole lot about it.
So I'm either way off the reservation with this, but I think what we're going to see is that we're going to
see this problem creep up more and more because that increase in extensibility is going to expose all of you
to more opportunities to automate because the other side effect of greater extensibility is that consumption
model change that I talked about earlier. Alright, the way that we're consuming the resources that we buy
today is very different than the way we did it 5 years ago and it's crazy different than what we were
doing 10 years ago and I suspect it's going to be crazy different 5 years from now.
And I get the question frequently they're like well Josh you talk about PowerShell and everything and all
this extensibility, isn't there just going to be other tools that's going to do all this work and we just
won't script anymore? Does anybody in this room believe that in five years we won't need to script anymore?
Alright. You got one. It's good to have one. There's always one.
I'm usually the one. So we're not going to see this major drop off of this need to script and execute in the environment.
You're still going to have to do tasks that even if you have this very robust management plan that can just
execute all these things, there's just some things it can't do. Because if it did do all of that,
nobody would want to use the tool. It would be too cumbersome, too complex.
You'd look at it and you're like there's just too much here and we see that with vSphere and System Center sometimes, right.
There's things that you wish were there and there's things that you just wish would go away because you don't
ever need them or use them. So you can't, nobody should ever expect that there's going to be one tool that's
going to change all of it. What is going to happen though is that as those tools grow and you start implementing
them in your environment, they are going to have hooks where you can execute PowerShell, especially once it
goes to Linux, if it ever does. I hope it does. That would be fun.
I would love to have PowerShell on my Mac because then I would know how to use my Mac.
And so, as you are looking at your environments and the things you're doing, you're going to start seeing
that you have more accessibility, more capability, you know those silos.
I wouldn't say they're disappearing, but the focus is much more on how can we help one another.
How can we leverage PowerShell to do something on this side of the stack and I think we're going to see that
those relationship mappings are going to be critically important.
So here in about the next two weeks, I will have on my GitHub repo, I'm going to have the App DNA repo where
I'm going to start putting these functions and I would really love and appreciate anybody that wanted to come
in and contribute to that and engage in this conversation some more because I think it's, unless SAPIEN makes
a tool for this or somebody, I think it's just something that we're going to continue to see pop up on a regular basis.
You said you had the time down from 22 hours. So I was just wondering, do you use…?
I didn't at the time. It wasn't an option. Yeah, that was four years ago.
Yeah, so and that's the other thing, right, some of this, we're getting a lot new capabilities and tools to
help solve some of these challenges and improve the way that we're executing.
I haven't used them because I don't have a big environment anymore.
So has anybody leverage, are you doing that? (Audience comment)
Right, and so what he was saying is leveraging workflows to go out and collect information from different
places into a single location to execute creating a virtual machine and getting that time down.
So yeah, absolutely something you can do. You have a question? (Audience question)
So to repeat what he said, like in their environment on the Linux side, complete automation up and down,
on the Windows side, nothing. So why do you think that is? I think it's mostly, started with the silos.
So silos. (Audience comment) Right, exactly. Well I guess, so what he was saying is just educating
people and making it a priority to do the automation. I mean, think that's fundamental.
I mean this is it right?
Let's just show everybody this. Let's just posh it real good.
You've probably seen the image that's got the two people that are pushing a cart that's got square wheels,
right, and there's two people right behind them that's got round wheels and it said the guy's pushing like no
we don't have time for that right now. Just show them that and be like and so when you think about that and
this is how do you make that change, like how do you elevate that conversation, get them started talking about it.
I primarily just say quick wins. Little bits here and there, right, and that's like when I look at that DNA
stuff, I really want it to be modular and extensible enough that you just grab the little bits that you need.
You don't have to use every bit of it. You can grab little bits to do small parts.
Maybe get that build time from 12 minutes to 10 minutes or down to 8 minutes.
Every bit that you do helps and just kind of feeds because now you've bought yourself more time and now you
you can start looking at more opportunities. Do you have a question?
I kind of have like a comment actually. I'm a contractor. I work for a client on a big environment
orchestration project and one of the reasons why I came to this was because I'm one of the seven plus and
what I find is like whenever we provision a server, like you said, there's a whole lot of layers like when we
say we want a new SQL Server, we send a call, we do things with SolarWinds or we put stuff in our automation
database, we provision the VM, we configure all these silo on an OS level, but and there's probably like five
or six different actual appliances that we put, insert new records into, or read records from, that sort of thing
and what the good thing about the whole DevOps mentality is all that is essentially just an API.
So we make an API call to SQL data that quote/unquote an API call to a SQL database, an API call to the IPM service,
or an API call to after all that stuff and PowerShell allowed us to it's essentially like the glue that glued
all of that stuff together that allowed us to just, you don't have to know what all these appliances do.
We just have to make a quick API call, bam, bam, bam and PowerShell orchestrates the whole thing.
And I highly recommend that and the funny thing is that when I think of what this concept like it's doing
exactly that, but trying to store in a stateful manner where you're not constantly making the queries.
I haven't been able to test it in a large enough environment to be able to say how much impact it's going to have.
So I'm hoping later this year people will be able tell me. Go ahead.
So you're talking about how the six-hour process to refresh that state data, and then you're considering
well how often do I need to refresh it to make sure that it doesn't go stale even though those relationships don't change.
My suggestion would be why not run that six-hour process every night and then you can have the scripts that
you need now if something changes. If an unexpected change happens, wouldn't you want to know about it?
Yeah. I think that makes sense. My intent would be a scheduled task that would go at some regular interval
and then also adding little bits of code to do a query if that doesn't match up.
because depending on what you're doing, it doesn't have to be and here's the thing, when you look at how
applications are being built and developed and put out into the world, they're much more modular.
The monolithic app is becoming less. They still exist. They're still going to exist for a long time,
but it's much more going into little bits and chunks that do their little bit, right.
What's that? Micro Services. Micro Services, exactly. And I think by enabling it with multiple functions
that do very specific things and storing it into a central data set, you could probably keep it fairly real time, right.
Or you just don't do those processes and only check when periodic.
Yeah, like there's and I think that there is no right answer. There is no this is the way you have to do it
because I think everybody's environment is going to be completely different because when you talk about the
different use cases here, like he's talking about implementation, right, like that's the Day 0 activity.
That is creating those relations like leveraging relationships and creating a new DNA, like a new app,
like it's coming into the world with nothing just like a child. You have to give it everything.
And so that is going to be one operation, but when you look at how do you turn and lifecycle it,
how much does it change? Like I wasn't born with a beard. I got a beard right.
Sometimes the beard my go away, not frequently because it gets itchy when it's not there.
It just feels awkward. But when you start thinking about Day 0 versus Day 720 or 730, completely different needs,
but the same information. So the refresh on that, not sure. We actually use a system just like this on one
of our large clients and we use a SQL database to store and what wound up doing we developed kind of transactional
model into that database, so now we can have training reports, so I can show you what's our trend on the end fields?
Are we starting to fill up on workstations and how is that looking at the time?
So it's, I think there's a lot of potential behind this and having a community-driven solution for this is a huge idea.
Awesome. Well I'm looking forward to you contributing based on what you guys are doing.
Absolutely. Alright, you haven't thrown things at me, so I feel confident that I wasn't absolutely crazy here.
I appreciate that. Anything else? Alright, let me see if I can get into the environment now.