but what ends up happening is like
why would you do this? Well you're going to get quicker reporting.
You already have those relationship maps in place so that six hours can get down to more like 30 minutes.
Getting that information faster, being able to have quicker time to resolution.
So if you have an issue, you already have that relationship map.
And I know there's like some change management databases out there that have similar types of information.
There's products like Zenoss that do a similar type of thing from an operation standpoint, but that's not
necessarily helpful in a PowerShell script standpoint when you're trying to automate.
That's helpful from an operation standpoint and be able to get visibility, but.
PowerShell's free. And PowerShell's free. That's a really excellent point.
Like the cost and the barrier to entry of PowerShell is phenomenal.
It's the best value in IT. And then from here, you also can do faster implementation.
So let's say that you do need to make that type of change. You're able to go in and execute and find the
information and find those relationships and execute those cmdlets regardless of where you are in the stack
without having to do the query and the work that I'm doing, and again it's still early, if it's changed and
it's not accurate, it'll throw an error. Just handle the error.
Then you do your query. If in the catch, there is an error, do the query and see if it works that time and update.
And then you can just update the object, right?
Improving the value stream. From a DevOps perspective, being able to reduce time because
I'm not kidding myself, right. In some respects, this is only going to shave a little bit of time on things
that we do on a day-to-day basis, but when you start looking at things that you're doing frequently like
provisioning out environments and destroying them and moving your software development lifecycle,
seconds make a big difference, right.
So yesterday during the talk about dynamic parameter sets, I started thinking and I brainstormed with several
of you about the ramifications of things that you could do like when you're going to deploy knowing that
there's certain Datastores that would be preferred, certain capabilities, if you know it needs to be on a
VLAN and you want to keep it isolated to a specific server, since you already have the data collected,
you could prepopulate in your functions the, what do they call it again, it started with C, help me out here folks.
The dynamic parameters. Anyway. So it will prepopulate options so that when you go to choose, you can see
the ones that need up, so you can have all the networks listed with the VLAN associated or have the storage
with the percent free so that you're identifying something that has more resources available,
making it easier for the user to be able to do this automation without having to do all these queries and
lookups and understand everything that's happening in the background.
And then, when you look at the extensibility into other tools like vRealize Orchestrator, for instance,
or PowerActions, like I mentioned, or Microsoft Orchestrator, whatever, System Center, Service Now,
anything that can execute a script
being able to speed that implementation has tremendous value because there's a truism I've learned and you've
probably seen this in your environments as well. When you're delivering IT services to people, they will fight
against your processes if they feel like they can get it faster another way.
They will spend budget stupidly often to get something faster. And so, what we found was if you wanted
people to fall in line with your process and things like that, you make it super-fast and easy for the
preferred way and painfully difficult the other way. Take cost completely out it.
And so when you start demonstrating that not only are you delivering a service, but you can deliver it faster
and more succinctly efficiently, right, very consistently, you'll find that your adoption to those efforts
will go way up. Same goes for when you're sharing scripts. So when you look at implementing something with
PowerActions and vRealize Orchestrator and sharing code with others, I think most of us would tend to deliver a function.
Because I know in the environments I've worked in that I would create a script and I would tell them,
and I think we've all done this, I think we all still do from time to time, but at the very top you have some
documentation there and you then you say fill out these four fields that are associated with your environment
for running this script. And then go and dot source it, run it, and things like that.
Well as you look to increase adoption, you turn those things into functions and not only do you make it to
where they are filling out information, you could then extend the parameter set or the dynamic parameters,
you can extend that, pulling from that data, and you're now giving them an opportunity to do it faster with
less effort, and more importantly, they don't have to call you asking you how to use it.