So let's get into why we would PowerShell the stack, right. I
almost feel like it was challenge that somebody has like can you get Salt N Pepa into a slide?
Yes, I can. So we're going to posh it real good. Alright? And here's the thing, right, why would you use
PowerShell across the whole stack? In your environments, let me just ask real quick, in your environments,
do you have control over multiple layers of your ecosystem that you could automate with PowerShell?
Yes. Right. That's becoming more of the norm. We hear a lot of conversations about silos.
Frankly, I don't like silos. I mean, I like the fact that they hold corn and corn is a primary ingredient of
bourbon and I'm a fan of that part of it, but when it comes down to organizational structures, I really prefer
looking at it as disciplines, right, and when you break down that concept of there being some separation
between you and a peer or how you look at your infrastructure, you now have opportunities to share and
contribute with one another. And so I did this poll
on Twitter and if you're on Twitter and you want to, go to my profile, it's pinned.
You can go ahead and contribute and then I can pull that up at the very end to see how this number changes.
But what I wanted to know is how many layers of your infrastructure stack do you manage with PowerShell currently?
And I won't lie, I was a little bit surprised to have that many people claiming seven plus layers.
Think about that.
Seven layers of infrastructure, right. And we'll get into how I define that in just a minute,
but seven components, seven layers of your infrastructure managing with PowerShell.
You know ten years ago if you would have asked anybody that was getting started with PowerShell if we would
be seeing that kind of result, I think that people would be a little bit bearish on that.
Jeffrey Snover will probably be bullish on that, as he should be.
But I also noted that the majority of people only have about three to four layers that they manage and I
think the fundamental element of that is based on what they have access to, right, what they were able to
automate and engage with PowerShell because this is
what our environments look like, right, and I tried to be heterogeneous if you will and demonstrate there's
more than just because I think most everybody here is VMware vSphere, we've got some Hyper-Vs, maybe a couple OpenStacks.
Anybody running OpenStack in here? Okay. Have you used the OpenStack PowerShell?
Okay, so it exists. Some folks at Rackspace built PowerShell modules for OpenStack, right.
And when we look at our ecosystem now, we have a few things that are really prevalent that we have to identify.
The fact that we have more layers. It used to be your applications were directly on physical hardware.
Alright, and we still see some of that, but we now have a lot more layers, a lot more components and one thing
that's really important there is that in that complexity, there's a lot of interdependency.
Anybody carry a
pager? Right and there's something that goes wrong. What's the first thing you have to do?
You've got to figure out what was impacted. Right, you've got to figure out where it came down to.
You're doing your root, you're trying to find out the root cause and what is going on and there's lots of
layers that you have to consider before you can identify exactly where the issue is, well unless it's blatant like
storage going down or a network just going poof and disappearing, right.
But with these additional layers, you have that additional complexity, right.
You have dependencies that we didn't have in the past, and so it's really important for us to take advantage
of the capabilities from a PowerShell standpoint in order to deal with that.
And then finally, another thing that I see in the work that I do from day to day is that
our consumption models of our resources is changing fundamentally, right.
We are very quickly moving away from this world
where someone calls you and asks you to provision something, right.
We're moving more to a world where people are enabled to do their own provisioning, they're enabled to make their
own changes in their environment. We're delivering IT as a service, right.
So
what we're seeking now is opportunities to manage at scale and when I say scale, I don't necessarily mean
Cisco IT scale, right. Your scale is completely relevant to what you are doing in your environment.
So if you only have a 100 virtual machines or you've got 10,000 virtual machines, you still
have issues with scale, right. You still have your constraints and the things that you're trying to do and
what you're limited to varies, right. We all have our limitations and things that we have to work against.
And then you look at where you have opportunities where you want to implement DevOps methodologies and tools
and you're looking at
like this complicated stack and you're saying how do I even get started, like what can I do?
How do I start moving towards this and how can I leverage things that I already know?
And we're going to talk about that today as well.
And I've already touched on it, right. We want more IT as a service.
We want to give people an opportunity to be self-empowered to do the things that they need and not being
completely reliant on submitting a ticket for everything that they do.