So then in my calling script over here, what I did was I took these files and I copied them from
there and I just put them out in my own GoateePFE AzureRM GitHub.
This is public and it's out there for you guys to use. So all these files that I'm showing you right now are
right here on the screen. So if you go out to github.com/GoateePFE/AzureRM,
you'll find these files and you can use them and tweak them up for your own purposes.
You can create a copy in your own GitHub and modify the configuration however you want and tweak a few things
and you can start spinning up your own domain controllers all day long, or if you're kind of lazy like me,
just run this one and just change the domain name. It doesn't have to be Alpine Ski House.
You can call it whatever you want and you can go in and edit things however you like and just make your own.
So you've got here the data file and then inside that zip, you're going to have the actual script file,
the ps1 configuration file and the resources in there. Alright so, basically all I'm doing then is I'm
taking that data, I threw it up on GitHub.
Now really and truly, you should put it in an Azure storage account where it's really secure and you're the
only person that can see it if you're going to use this in any kind of production capacity.
But all I did was I had to say Install-Module using the PowerShell get to pull down the Azure resource module,
install that, install AzureRM, and it goes out and it installs like 28 modules for you in AzureRM and this
all documented out there already. Install-Module Azure, Import-Modules are optional commands and then I just
log in, so really this is where it starts. I log into my AzureRM account.
So this is where---how many of you have an Azure account. Alright, you got a MSDN, your enterprise agreement
from Microsoft has Azure benefits, you can go get a trial. So as long as you've got some kind of account,
you just log in here, that's it. You put in your name and password.
In the past, you had to do all the subscription IDs and this jazz to try to run PowerShell commands against Azure.
Now this is all it takes. Log into my account, it knows all my stuff. I don't have to mess with all those extra parameters.
And so now, what I do is I give it the URL to my GitHub account and that azuredeploy.json file that I snagged
and edited out of that template library. And then I just---you can change these up.
I called mine GoateePSH and then RG for Resource Group, SA for Storage Account, and then AD for the DNS name.
So you can just tweak up those names right there, whatever you want to call those.
They do have to be lowercase and then you test their availability and make sure there's no DNS conflict there
in Azure and then you just create the resource group. So really what we're talking about to get this all
done is three commands, log in, create a resource group, and then you've got your parameters here pretty well
already populated, and then you just do the resource group deployment.
So three commands and in less than 30 minutes later, you've got a full-blown domain controller ready to bang on,
so those three commands. Now let's see, is it done? Let's take a look here.
It is. So let's take a look at the verbose output here. So here's the play by play on building it out.
We started at 3:05 PM and we scroll down. We saw it's deployed all these pieces.
It ends at 3:33 PM. I've noticed it takes 27-28 minutes on average for me and then it shows me at the very end,
here's my Azure resource group name and here are all the parameters that we passed in, here's the VNETs,
all that stuff, so it's done. It's baked. I've got a standard D1 Azure VM out there called adDC.
Now how do I get to it? Well, what I'm going to do is I'm going to use this GetAzureRM public IP address
cmdlet and I just give it the resource group name, grab the first VM that comes back from that here,
and so I'm going to grab the IP and the FQDN of that domain controller that I just spun up in Azure.
Now, the other Azure cmdlets have this command called Get-AzureRemoteDesktopFile.
I haven't found the equivalent of that for the RM set of cmdlets, so I'll I did was just do a Start-Process
on the RDP client and pass it in either the FQDN or the IP, either one.
It doesn't care that I pulled out of that other information there.
So now, I'm going to log in here as alpineskihouse/adadministrator.
In Azure, you can't use administrator for your AD name for your administrator account, so in this case,
the template said let's call it AD administrator and I'm fine with that.
And I'll put in my super-secret password here, make sure I type that exactly right.
Now this might take a minute connecting in for the first time. It's a brand new virgin VM out there in Azure.
It might just take a minute before it knocks the cobwebs out of its head
and it gets ready to roll. Here we go. It's spinning up.
So what you're watching on the screen right now is a brand new pristine Azure domain controller spinning up
for the very first time with an RDP session to it.
And here it goes. Let's take a look here. AlpineSkiHouse logging in and now I've been talking this whole
time for 37 minutes, but really when we started this whole thing, I just ran three commands.
And now, less than 30 minutes later, I've got a fully populated Active Directory domain controller ready for
me to script and do whatever I want to do to test, so I'm not doing those things in production, right,
so I can test now out here on a clean VM. So it's spinning up
and as usual, it's taking a minute just the first time for the server to wake up.
So what are the things we're looking for now? We want to go see,
first off, is it a domain controller, did it really work, did it promote my domain controller, is the data
there, do I have the OUs, the users, and groups, is the recycle bin enabled?
Alright, I want to see if this thing is actually configured the way we defined it in the configuration.
So I'm going to go over here to tools. First thing you'll notice right here, remember the Active Directory RSAT
we installed in the configuration. The RSATs there. So now I'm going to go over here to Active Directory,
let's see, Administrative Center. There we go. And the Administrative Center comes up, I click on my Tree view
over here because that's my favorite view, I click on the domain and over here on the right, first thing you'll
notice is it's grayed out where it says Enable AD Recycle Bin, it's already done because the configuration told
it to enable the recycle bin. Now right here in the front list, you can see there's an Accounting OU,
there's an IT OU, a marketing OU, an Operations OU. Let's drill into one of those and there we go,
Computers, Groups, and Users exist. Now my Users OU, there's Debbie and Harriet, and if I look in the groups
there's G_Operations, which matches the department name in the OU there.
I open that group and I look at the members in that group and there's Debbie and Harriet.
So I've got an OU that has a group that has users, users in the group all with DSC out-of-the-box.
Alright, now let's go down and take a look at the users default container.
Down here, I have TestUser1, TestUser2, TestUser3, 4, 5, TestGroup1, 2, 3, 4, 5, and if I look in TestGroup1,
there's a member TestUser1.
What do you think? (Applause) Does that look handy for you? Yep.
Alright. So we've now in three PowerShell commands, you run those commands before you go to your morning
status meeting, you come back from your status meeting, you've got a domain controller ready to bang on.
Alright, just like that.
And then when we're all done at the end of the day, we've got a couple things here that we can do.
Number one, if you've been in Azure very long, you've already learned this lesson the hard way.
Shut down your VMs at the end of every day, right. So you want to run this command, Get-AzureRmVM.
This makes it so easy using the new resource manager cmdlets. Give me all the VMs in my resource group and stop them.
Done. They're stopped for the day or I can literally just run this one command, Remove-AzureRmResourceGroup,
I want to run that. Bada bing, bada boom. And if I come over here to my Azure view, all my resources,
you can see I've got two of these out there. I've got the PSH one and the AD one.
I built one just as a fall back last night. But if I keep refreshing this view, you'll watch these resources
start to drop off as it deletes them when I'm removing the resource group, and so it's performing that target right then.
It's going to remove it and then we'll be all done.