So here's your call to action, help us grow the xAD resource in DSC.
If you've got a little bit of AD scripting skills, even if you don't have any AD scripting skills, just go watch
my videos out on Microsoft Virtual Academy. Anybody watch those?
There's a full eight sessions, full day of teaching you how to do Active Directory with PowerShell and then
go start hacking away on these resources out there and help us grow the Active Directory resources.
Now try it yourself. There's the URL, github.com/goateepffe/azurerm.
You just go out there. You can download that
one calling script file, you can tweak the parameters, the names of things, whatever, and then just run it
and you're done. It'll spin you up an environment. Just like we did right here, you can do it yourself.
And then, once you've got those files, just start editing and playing with them and make it work for yourself.
Question? How do you set the holes cache on the second disk to _____?
I didn't have to because over here in my
azuredeploy.json, it does all that for me. Let's see if it actually, it doesn't show that.
Let's see if it's got adDataDisk and the adDiskSize, somewhere in this long JSON template, it's set all
that for me and that's the thing I like about these JSON templates.
I don't have to know all that Azure business, alright. I just deploy the template and it builds it all for me.
At the end of the day, I blow it all away and I don't care. So it's that easy.
Yeah. And let's see, we're
still deleting that group. And so now, one last
favor I have to ask. Did anybody have to beg your boss to come to this event?
Alright, so like, yeah I know it's like, you know, funding travel, budget, conference, all that stuff.
Training budgets are really hard to come by. Well I kind of have to do that with my bosses too, so if you
could send me a tweet
@GoateePFE and just let me know was this helpful. Is this something that you're going to use?
How can you see some impact in your environment? That'll help me sell my boss on coming back next year.
Alright, appreciate it. Alright, yes. Would you like a copy of the emails?
Oh yeah, I'll take a copy of the emails. Thanks. When they come in, I'll send them.
Alright. So we've got about two minutes left here for questions.
First off, was this helpful? Yes. Alright, good.
Alright, so now you've seen what DSC looks like for Active Directory, and on top of that, now you can spin up
a domain controller to bang on.
Now this is just the scratching the surface here. You can deploy multiple machines with this.
You can deploy 10 domain controllers and you know build it all out with different roles and all that and you
could even, you know, kick off some other scripts to configure your environment.
We don't have resources available yet to set FSMO roles and things like that, so we need help building those,
so help us with that. Yes, question. Is there a similar infrastructure to the AzureRM if you're hosting locally?
Like on Hyper-V? Is there a similar equivalent set of cmdlets like…
Right, like if you've got a DSC template that you want to spin off of a VM in Hyper-V.
For Hyper-V, not necessarily. We have some Hyper-V resources that you might be able to, but you couldn't
do it exactly this way. Now you might check, keep an eye on Azure Stack when that comes out for onsite,
you'd have your own private cloud stuff, see if that might work with the AzureRM cmdlets.
I don't know. I can't make any official statements. I don't know what's happening there.
Other questions. Yes. Do you know anybody using the Active Directory DSC stuff for like production systems
like for users and stuff like that? I haven't heard of anybody using this much in production systems yet.
It would be kind of one of those things you'd only want to set it once with just the install, right,
so apply only for your LCM, right? That's what I just offhand I'd heard somebody.
I don't know if it was at the summit last year or somewhere else and someone had said and referenced to
to Active Directory DSC for like user provisioning and some OU provisioning and stuff like that where it was apply only.
They weren't using it to build like refresher _____.
Yeah, you could do that, but I just don't know if that's practical.
I mean, you can just run one line of script to create a new user OU group anyway.
Why would you do that with DSC? And somebody was asking me this last night and I thought, well, you know for
me, I support Active Directory, so all day long I'm standing up AD test environments just to beat on and
script against, so for me, this is really handy. I could run this all the time now.
And for you guys out there where you need a test environment, you don't have to go through all your VM
requests, you know, act of congress, you could just spin one of these up and then destroy it at the end of
the day, so. Alright, we're out of time. Thank you all for coming and please fill out our email.
Thank you.