Here's what we're going to do. I'm going to go ahead and we are
going to do this live right here today. So I've got some code. I've done my Login to AzureRM.
I'm going to come back and show you how this works. I'm going to create a couple of variables here that are
going to define the name of my resource group and then I'm going to just do a quick check to make sure that
DNS name is available. There's no conflict. There shouldn't be, there aren't that many Goatee instances out on Azure.
And then I'm going to spin up my Azure resource group. That one takes just a second to run.
That's good. And just like that, I created a New-AzureRmResourceGroup.
Now I'm just going to define a couple parameters, which are mostly variables already done here, I want to
go ahead and run those and now the big line right here, New-AzureRmResourceGroupDeployment.
I'm just passing in the splat of parameters and let's go ahead and run that line as well.
This is the part, alright, it's going to ask me for my password, make sure I remember this, powershell5 thing.
Alright, password, got it. What? Man oh man. Provided value east us for the template parameter.
Guys, I have done this a million times and the only reason it's failing is because I'm in front of all of you right now.
Alright, what's going on here? (Audience question) Yeah, it is, but it's all lowercase.
Well, that one particular piece, yeah, you know what I've run this a million times just like it is.
Oh, okay, yep, it is because I did change one last thing last night after I ran my demo, east, East US.
You're right. I did change that little spot after my demo practice last night.
That was a bad thing on my part. Now let's try it again. There we go.
Alright. Come on, baby. Got the -Verbose in there, so it gives me the play by play.
Alright. So what's happening now is I'm actually spinning up. I've got a new Azure resource group that I created.
Now I'm actually deploying to that Azure resource group a single domain controller, all the storage and
network and everything that goes with it and it's going to have a DSC configuration that I designed that was
custom for Active Directory and for my domain controller, the data that I wanted to go in there and that's
what I'm going to show you now is how that works. There we go. Get my prompt here.
I want to make sure this gets off and running because---okay, now we're good.
So we're creating a template deployment now for AlpineSkiHouseForest.
I'm tired of using Contoso.com. Anybody else? Alpine Ski House is one of the other legal approved Microsoft
fictitious company names. So Alpine Ski House sounds like a lot more fun than Contoso.
So let's get back to the presentation. We'll come back and see this in a minute.
So you came to talk about Active Directory in DSC. This is the xActiveDirectory resource module that you
can get at PowerShell gallery or you can go look at it on GitHub.
And in that module, there are a number of resources. Now how many have used this in DSC already?
Anybody? Just a couple hands, okay. So the main thing to understand here is the difference between
xADDomain and xADDomainController. XADDomain is going to be the first DC in the environment.
Every other DC after that in the same domain is going to be a xADDomainController.
Alright. And then xWaitForADDomain says once I've done the install, I need to make sure that it's come up
and it's responding, so that's the wait. And then once that wait is successful, I can contact the domain,
then I can go ahead and do my other resources here like DomainTrust, organizational units, users, groups, and so forth.
So those are the resources we have today in that module. It's bare minimum at this point.
It's been out there for a year and a half or so. We've got a little bit of traction out there, but there are
some other things in process.
The last I checked on GitHub, there's a default domain policy out there that's getting ready to be released soon.
Also, we're actually looking for people to help build this out. So if you do some AD PowerShell and you'd
like to help us add some resources here, we'd like to do a resource for just a generic Active Directory object
or setting permissions on something in Active Directory, tons of things we can add to this, you know,
sites and subnets, all that stuff.
So feel free to go out there to GitHub, take a look at it, and see where you can jump in and help.
So there's one person I would really like to thank and that's Iain Brighton.
This is the stats off of GitHub. Iain has done the most work on this module in the community.
So a big shout out to Iain for all of his work helping us move forward with the xActiveDirectory resource module.
So what we're doing today is deploying a domain controller using what's called Azure Resource Manager templates.
How many have heard of that before?
Okay. Now basically, instead of going and clicking through the Azure portal to do your resource deployment,
your---you've got to spin up, compute, and storage, and unicorns, and fairies, and all that in Azure to make
everything work right, and you can do that with code obviously because we're all PowerShell people in here.
But it's really easy now with Azure templates. You just say give me one of these and it just gives you all that stuff.
It just does automatically all the storage, and the compute, and the network, and all that, just builds it
all up for you and that's what I've been waiting on. See, now we're there, so I don't have to worry about
knowing all the 1s and 0s of everything I have to set up. So we've got that we're using and I used---I cheated
like everybody else. Hey, you know, when you write a script, you go look on the internet, find somebody else
that did it, and then you start with that, right? So I just went out to GitHub.
There's an AzureRM
section out on GitHub where we've published these resource templates, and sure enough, there's one there for
a domain controller, so I started with that. And then I snagged the latest Active Directory module here,
xActiveDirectory from the PowerShell gallery, and then I went out and watched Trevor Sullivan's video on
doing Azure Template deployments with PowerShell, some presentation he did over in Europe.
Everybody know Trevor Sullivan?
MVP? Yep, alright. So he did a really good job on that video. And then I did the
phone-a-friend thing and all that and talked to some of my buddies and kind of put this, hacked this thing together.