Okay. Active Directory Desired Stake Configuration. How many of you have Active Directory in your environment?
Oh, nice. Alright, you came to the same place, alright? How many of you have an Active Directory test lab
in your environment. Nice, alright. That's better than average.
You guys are above average here. How many have Lamas in your data center?
Two, alright I'm not going to talk about Lamas in a data center.
Alright, let's talk about Active Directory in DSC. That's my stuff up there, GoateePFE.
If you search anywhere online you'll find me. Alright, let's dive.
And yes, thank you, applause to all the guys who made this possible for the last 10 years.
Okay, here's the problem. I'm a Microsoft Premier field engineer, and I visit premier customers and help them
with their Active Directory, that's kind of what I've done for years, and most of those customers do not have
an Active Directory test lab. So what I'm going to show you today is how to spin up your own Active Directory
test lab in 30 minutes. Alright, that's mostly just wait time. It takes you just a minute to run the script.
It's going to be about 30 minutes and you're going to have your own domain controller spun up in Azure that
you can just destroy, do whatever you want to against it, and then at the end of the day, just delete and you're done.
So you can have an on-demand domain controller to beat up anytime, just run the script.
That's what we're going to do today. Does that sound like fun?
Yep. Alright.
So that was my goal then. I wanted to be able to deploy an Active Directory test lab to Azure including,
because you know this DSC stuff, usually somebody just spins up a server, but I want to actually put OUs,
and in those OUs, I wanted users and groups, and I wanted to enable the AD recycle bin, here do some AD
configuration, and then I want it to be as simple as running a script and I did not want to have to open
Visual Studio
because I'm not a big Visual Studio person, right. I'm an infrastructure guy.
I don't do---I'm an ops. I'm not a dev on that side of that equation.