So here are the challenges I ran into deploying a domain controller using this technique.
Well, number one, the template that was out there on the Azure resource templates was kind of dated.
It used an old version, an old, stale version of the xActiveDirectory resource module.
It didn't have all the new bells and whistles.
It still was using the xDisk DSC resource module, which has been deprecated now and it's now in xStorage.
And then there's the xNetworking was out-of-date, so I basically, I found this template that I could use,
but it was way out of date. I needed to fix it up. The other thing I wanted to do is I want to put my own
domain controller DSC configuration in there. I didn't want to take the one that was in the template.
I wanted to write my own, put that up in there as well. And then what I also learned was that when I was
trying to pass parameters in, with the Azure template, it uses a JSON and when I was trying to pass an array,
I couldn't figure out how to get the array to go through in a JSON parameter.
Maybe some of you guys know that, but I couldn't figure that out.
So but it was better, it was cleaner, instead, if I could just put my configuration script in one file and my
psd configuration data file for DSC in another separate file, it has all of my AD configuration information in it.
So those two files, plus the Azure JSON stuff. So here's the process.
I installed that xActiveDirectory resource module on a VM to start testing with.
I wrote and tested my AD DSC configuration, how I wanted it to build.
I just tested that on a local VM just getting my configuration tuned the way I wanted.
And then I basically took the arm template that I found out on GitHub and I just mashed those two together and
this was a lot of mashing to make that stuff work right. But I basically took my configuration, mashed it up
together with that template, and
there are just a couple files there. So there's something on azuredeploy.json,
which is what the Azure Resource Manager cmdlet uses to go find the information, where to point things,
and what values you're going to pass in, things like that.
Then there's a zip file. How many have done the Azure DSC extension?
Have you worked with that? And when you publish a DSC configuration to Azure, there's this zip file that it builds.
All that is a PS1 script file holding your DSC configuration script and then zipped up in there are the resource
module folders that need to be installed on that target, that machine.
And then there's a configuration data file. How many have done DSC with a configuration data file?
Alright, or you used the -ConfigurationData when you build a DSC, right, you pass that in.
So this is just that, that's a hash table file. It's got all my parameters in there.
So those are the files that are hosted out on GitHub. By the end of this session, you'll be able to go out
to GitHub and take the exact same files that I published out there, download it, one file, out of that GitHub
repository to your machine and run it and build a domain controller 10 times a day if you wanted in your own
instance of Azure. You can also use that code as a reference template for just how do I do a domain controller
with DSC and that's what we're going to get into in just a second here when we start looking at the code.
So then I deployed this template to Azure and did it work the first time?
No. So it's fail, tweak, fail, tweak, fail, tweak, and bashing head on keyboard until finally it works, then success.
Yay, alright. So that's, right, that's how we script. Right, we just keep trying until it works and then we,
you know, fist bump, right. So yeah.
So let's take a look then at the actual files behind this. Let's get this,
let's get this going. So there's xActiveDirectory Resource Module.
You can do Install-Module xActiveDirectory. I've already got that done, so I'm not going to worry about that right now.
You can just slide this down out of the way. And so I can look at my resources in that module and so forth,
but I don't want to go into that. I want to spend more time on focusing on the DSC configuration script.
So here we go. I've got a configuration called CreateADDomainWithData, which is kind of the difference here.
There are a lot of templates out there for deploying a domain controller with DSC, but this one is actually
going to show you a fully populated OU user and group data structure.
So what we're going to do is, this is just a standard DSC configuration and this is the one that came with the
Azure resource template that I snagged off of GitHub. Let me show you where that is, by the way.
You need to see this place.
So out on GitHub, there's a github/Azure/azure-quickstart-templates.
There are, I haven't counted, I'm guessing dozens, hundreds of these, any kind of ready-made recipe you just
want to go
spin up some environment with multiple servers all talking to one another and happy.
In Azure, without having to do that manually, there you go. There's all
kinds of those quick templates right there. Well one of these is a domain, so that's what I started with.
And so this configuration came out of that and then I had to tweak it up.
I had to import the PSDesiredStateConfiguration default module because v5 complains now if you don't do that.
Importing the xActiveDirectory module, the xStorage module, and we're taking a parameter for the domain
credentials because when you build a DC, you've got to give it credentials in a couple places.
So now let's get into the actual DSC configuration piece. This is what you came for.
So LocalConfigurationManager. This is the v4 syntax for the LCM and DSC and that's okay, it still works in v5.
The reason we put it here is because in Azure when I spin this up, what happens is it's going to run this
whole configuration, it's going to spin out localhost.mof and localhost.mega.mof and it's going to configure
the LCM and then it's going to actually apply the configuration to the local box and Azure just makes all
that happen magically with the DSC extension. So what I did there is I said hey continue after reboot because
when you do a domain controller
promotion here, it's going to have to take a reboot and you want to make sure that the configuration
continues to apply after that reboot.
I am only going to apply it, though, I'm not going to keep checking it out later and then RebootNodeIfNeeded
and AllowModuleOverWrite. So when you're spinning up a domain controller in Azure,
does anybody know about disk caching with domain controllers. What do they prefer?
You don't want write caching, right? You don't want read/write caching on the disk for your database, logs,
sysvol, that kind of thing. So you have to---when you deploy a DC in Azure under IAZ, you have to actually
create a second disk, a data disk, assigned to that VM so that you can turn off that caching.
So that's what this is for. It's waiting for that second disk, that data disk to come up in the Azure VM
and that's all handled by the template. I didn't have to do any of that hard work.
All I had to do was just edit this configuration.
So Disk2 and there's a RetryInterval there that's already defined up here in our parameters for the configuration.
So I wait for the disk and then I use the xDisk resource to create an F drive on DiskNumber 2, that's going to
be our ADDataDisk in Azure. And you could just---it doesn't matter if you're doing this in Azure or not.
This is the same thing you would do on your local data center if you're doing this locally as well.
So when we're deploying domains with DSC, we have to install the AD-Domain-Services, right?
So we installed AD-Domain-Services and then we run
what used to be known as DC Promo. Now this is what we call DSC promo and it's going to call all the cmdlets
in the back-end to make that happen.
So I've installed the AD-Domain role here, also because I like to cheat and use the GUI tools from time to time,
I want to go ahead and put the RSAT in there for ADDS in there as well.
So that's going to give me my good old trusty ADUC and the AD GUI tools, AD administrative center, all that good stuff.
So now we're down to actually building the domain controller. And when I did this presentation last year,
this is essentially the same kind of stuff,
but this was also part of that downloaded template from the AzureRM template gallery.
So xADDomain is going to be my first domain controller. Here's the DomainName coming in from the parameters
to the whole thing, the DomainAdministratorCredential and a safemode credential.
Because this is just going to be a quick dev lab, I don't really care that they use the same credentials.
No big deal. Now notice I can specify here the Database, Log, and Sysvol Path.
That's kind of important. You want to put that on that F drive that has no caching on it.
And then it depends on the feature being installed and the disk being available.
If those aren't ready, then I don't want to proceed with building the DC.
So that's the dependency there. Make sure that all happens in the right order and then we're going to wait
for the domain. So what this says is domain controller is promoting here with this resource and that's going
to take a while and actually, it's going to force a reboot.
So what happens the next time that machine reboots, I've got the LCM set to continue configuring,
it's going to run down through, it says oh this is already done, and then it's going to check and make sure
that domain, alpineskihouse.com, is responsive, and once I know that the domain is up and online, then I can
proceed with configuring the domain. So there's an xADRecycleBin resource I wrote about 14 months ago,
so now I can enable the ADRecycleBin and it's going to be for this same domain and obviously I have to wait
for the domain before I can enable the RecycleBin there, so that's a dependency.
So now I've got the base domain stood up with DSC. Now
the next part of the configuration gets kind of interesting.
So what I want to do is I want to build out an OU structure and put users and groups in there.
So here's how I chose to do that. In DSC, we're used to the simple quick demo configurations, but did you
realize that you can actually put scripting and looping in the body of your DSC configuration script?
So now we can iterate through data. So what I did
was I have this psd1 data file here and this is your hash table with your AllNodes, here's the Nodename,
localhost, which you have to have in Azure, it has to be localhost, and then this property called
PSDscAllowDomainUser. Notice there's not allow, what is the unsecure password thing is not there,
because azure will encrypt a password automatically for me. But this little thing will snag you.
On v5, one of the last few iterations of v5 we introduced this safety, so we prefer that you not use domain
credentials for the credentials in your resources, and so there's this warning.
If you put Domain/Username, it's going to flag you that you're trying to use a domain credential in your configuration.
So you have to put this in there, PSDscAllowDomainUser = true to allow it to use a domain user account,
which you have to use in this case. Now this NonNodeData is just a section, of blob of data that I'm going
to use to build out the lab and here I've got a CSV script block or script, I'm sorry, a string, a CSV multiline
string that has comma-separated values for username, department, manager, and a plane text password there that
I really don't care about because this is my lab, alright. I'm not telling you to do this in production.
This is just for a lab. So I've got eight users that I'm going to spin up here with the username, their department,
and their title, and then I've got my OUs, RootOUs, ChildOUs, and then a TestObjCount.
So here are my RootOUs, Accounting, IT, Marketing, and Operations.
Underneath each one of those four RootOUs, I'm going to create ChildOUs, Users, Computers, and Groups.
That's going to be one technique that I demonstrate in how to populate the data inside the domain.
The other technique I'm going to use is called TestObjCount. So here I could put 5, I could put 500, I could put 5,000.
Whatever this number is, that's how many test user accounts and test groups it's going to build and just
throw like User1 into Group1, User2 into Group2, it's just populating just random data for testing in AD.
So this is the data then that's going in to my configuration script.
So now on my configuration script for each RootOU that's in that configuration data block in the RootOUs,
for each one of those, I'm going to create a xADOrganizationalUnit giving it a dynamic resource name there
and it's going to use that RootOU name, it's going to be in the DomainRoot, which I calculated right here.
Domain name is alpineskihouse.com. So now it becomes DC= Alpine, DC=COM.
So then my OU path, that's going to be the parent path for the DomainRoot, I'll give it a description,
use the credential that we did already, ensure that it's present, and that's going to have to wait until the
RecyleBin is done before it kicks in. So now that I've got the RootOUs built, it's going to loop through and
build each one of those RootOUs. After that, it's going to create child OUs under each one of those.
So here's my xADOrganizationalUnit and I'm just going to give it a dynamically calculated name inside the
configuration here, giving it a ChildOU, and then the parent is going to be that RootOU in the DomainRoot,
and in this case, I decided I guess I did in the previously as well ProtectedFromAccidentalDeletion and then
we'll give it a credential, Ensure that it's Present, and that's dependent on the parent RootOU being established, right?
So I've got to have the RootOU and then I can create all the ChildOUs under it.
And then finally, as I'm looping through here, I'm building a master dependency array of all the OrganizationalUnits.
Actually, this is going to have all the child organizational units because before I can create a user in the
user's ITOU, that OU has to exist, so I'm stitching together an array of all the configuration items that
are dependency before I start building users and groups inside those OUs.
So that array right there comes down next to my users section. As the dependency, it depends on that array
of OU configuration items that have to exist first. So now I take my UserData out of that CSV.
I love doing this in my scripts. I'll just take a big string block and pipe it to ConvertFrom-CSV and then
instantly I've got
a rich PowerShell object with all these properties now for first name/last name, and a department, and all that stuff.
So now I can create the NewADUser here with the User resource and I give it the DomainName, I give it the
User.UserName because now I've got the CSV data. There's the username, there's the title.
Now their Department is actually the RootOU.
The RootOU as we just looked at, Accounting, IT, Marketing, Operations, that's the department that they're in,
so it's going to drop them automatically into the right department.
The account is going to be enabled.
Now have you ever tried to enable an account in Active Directory that did not have a password?
It fails, right. You have to have a password and one that meets the complexity requirements.
So in this case, I have to have a
password defined here, which is using the old ConvertTo-SecureString from that User Password that was, again, in plaintext.
It's in a lab, I don't care. I never do this in production. So I'm creating credential property there and
the dependency and now I'm creating a new dependency for the users.
So before I can put those users into groups,
the users have to exist. So later, in my configuration when I get to the group piece, I'll list all these
user accounts as the dependencies before I start spinning up the groups.
Now the other technique I'm going to use to spin up user accounts and you could use either one of these is
the TestObjectCount. So 1..5 would be what the equivalent here is just the range operator there 1.. and
whatever number comes out of that configuration file, it could be a 1000 users.
I'll just go blow them all in there and build them all out. And so I'm going to create NewADUser1, 2, 3, 4, 5,
and give the test username 1, 2, 3, 4, 5. And then this one, in this case, I don't care if it's enabled it's
just going to be Enabled = false. There is no password specified.
I don't care for that. And again, that depends just on the RecycleBin being enabled.
They're not going into any OU. They're just going to drop into the default user's container.
Then next up are the groups. So I've got that list of RootOUs. Those RootOUs are the same thing as the department names.
So now I'm going to create a G_Department Name global group that's going to be Global, Security group,
give it a description, and then the members in that group are going to be that user's CSV data,
and I'm just using a simple PowerShell filter here where their RootOU was the department name for that user.
So if we flip over here real quick, we're basically taking this list of department, right here, for each one
of these user accounts and whichever username matches that RootOU, that's the OU we're going to drop them into
from that CSV data. And that depends on the user being created before we can actually create the group in
that path and populate the users into it.
And then the users are dependent on the OUs, so there's this nested dependency structure that makes
everything happen in the correct order.
Then down here is my 1 to infinity, however many I specify, however many I specify, how many new groups I want,
NewADGroup1, NewADGroup2, 3, 4, and then inside there, the member is going to be TestUser1, TestUser2, TestUser3.
So I just use ForEach loops
and a ConfigurationData.psd1 file. So you can take this, take that CSV block, put whatever you want in
there for users and parameters and just define and tweak this configuration, put whatever kind of OUs and users
and groups you want in your domain that way.
And this whole thing is just the script, so it starts out with configuration CreateADDomainData and then when
I jump to the very end, that's it. There's no calling code, it's just the configuration block here.
And then when the Azure DSC resource, the Azure DSC extension
we're going to pass in over here in the JSON file. Over here we're going to look for, we called that
CreateADDomainWithData, createaddomainwithdata. So over here, what we have in the resource, the JSON file,
is it says call this script file, CreateADDomainData.ps1, call that configuration name,
CreateADDomainWithData.
So in other words, Azure builds this VM, it copies the configuration files inside of it, and then it calls
this configuration function name essentially inside that file with that name.
And then it finds the resources that they need in this zip file.
The zip file is going to have the Active Directory, xActiveDirectory module, and that type of thing in it.
So that's the---there was some other bits that I had to hack up in the JSON file and I'm intentionally kind
of glossing over that part because you're going to learn this piece as well if you decide to play with the templates.
It's a lot of fun banging your head against the keyboard for two days, but you'll get there.  I promise.