Okay, I'll take this slide. So one thing I wanted to talk a little bit about is why we went down this path
of bringing kind of PowerShell into the cloud and what were the reasons we thought about as we went down this path.
And I think the first one was-- we've seen a lot of customers, probably a lot of you are starting to look at
adopting cloud technologies and it might be that most of your stuff is on-premises today, but you're also
trying to say how do I take advantage as I move some of my services and applications to the cloud,
how can I also think about moving my management?
And so there's kind of core capabilities that the cloud gives you and one of those is you need to be able to
integrate into all these different clouds now because you're not going to get rid of all your on-premises
stuff as you start to bring things into Azure or into AWS or even into your own service provider.
So you want to be able to like talk to all those systems and still Integrate them today just like you might do on-premises.
The other thing that's been going around for a long time in the automation space is how do you deliver self-service?
Most of us are involved in writing PowerShell so that we can kind of complete some process, either a small process
on our own server or large processes that go across an entire organization and we think about that and one
of the main goals we have around that is so that we can offer out that automation to our end users so that
they can actually accomplish their tasks when they need it. And so as you think about the cloud, it just drives
the self-service capabilities. That's really what cloud is about is I want on-demand virtual machines,
I want on-demand storage, SQL, it's really about that self-service capabilities and how do we deliver self-service
around PowerShell as well as we go forward.
And then the last thing that I think if you look at the conference and where everyone is focused right now is
a lot on DevOps. How do we really enable the kind of continuous deployment of our services and applications,
working with the development teams, with the operations team, and allow that to go seamlessly back and forth
as continuous development happens.
A lot of people call this like infrastructure as code or some other name around it, but the idea is how do we
have the common tooling so that our development teams and our operations teams can actually talk the same
language, use the same tools, and gain the benefits of kind of that end-to-end development and management.
And then the other trend I talk a little bit about is as people start to think about okay I want to take
advantage of the cloud because I gain all the benefits of scale out there, I don't have to worry about the
infrastructure, how does management also play into that? You know, why
would you want to move your management to cloud and it's really the same reasons you might want to move
anything to the cloud is you don't really want to have to manage the infrastructure anymore.
You want to take advantage of the capabilities that cloud gives you and focus more on those scripts you're
writing and the process you're trying to do and not managing infrastructures.
The other big trend we've seen and I don't know if you guys are seeing it as well is that the world is
getting more and more heterogeneous and we think about heterogeneous it's mostly around, we live in a lot of
a Windows space,
but most of the customers we talk with and probably a lot of you have other systems in your environments.
You probably have Linux in your environments, but for sure you have other management solutions.
You're probably not running all of the management stack. And so, how do you talk to all of those systems
as they start to grow and grow, and as you move to the cloud, they just grow more and more.
And so we really want to think about how do we go about solving that communication, that integration across
Windows, Linux, as well as all the different systems you have to talk to complete that process.
And then the last one is I think everyone here is committed that kind of automation in PowerShell is the way
to actually automate your end-to-end process, but it also starts to put a lot more pressure on the systems
because now we're seeing automation at scale.
Whereas before we might do some automation to complete some tasks, we now see it as a pillar for most organizations
as they start to develop more and more integrated management solutions across the environment, and so we
wanted to build something that says okay we can actually solve that problem and give you automation at scale,
so it can go from your small needs all the way up to the largest needs you might ever need because we're able
to bring it from the cloud. So that's kind of a lot of the reasons why actually started thinking about okay
all the PowerShell stuff that works today, how can we actually bring that to the cloud, solve a lot of the problems
that you're seeing today, but also set you up for success in the future as you start to think about moving
more and more assets towards the cloud.