Okay, so let me jump into a demo. So we got through kind of the core slides, but how many people have
actually seen the automation service? Good. We see two or three, so I'm going to jump in just spend five
minutes, try to level set everybody what it's about and then hopefully as we go forward, you'll kind of get an
idea of why we built it out and how you can start taking advantage of it yourself.
So if you go into the portal up in Azure, there's actually called automation accounts over here, so you can
go and create a brand new automation account. I think we showed that on Monday with Joe, so I just created
one and I might jump into some of the capabilities around that, but when you first create an automation
account, here's what you're going to see. So you'll see this basically the home page and this is kind of the
overview of what's going on inside the service and it has a set of things.
So what we call Runbooks are basically PowerShell scripts, PowerShell workflows, or graphical runbooks,
so we kind of have three types of language we support today. We may add more in the future, but all of those
are runbooks to us because they basically allow you to deliver a process.
From our assets perspective, I'll jump in here because it's kind of a set underneath here and this is really
where we try to solve a lot of the problems that PowerShell has today and some of them are the first thing is
we allow scheduling. So you don't have to kind of set up your own scheduler using task scheduler or something
else and manage that, we do all of that in the cloud. So if you have things you want to run on schedule,
it's available from the service. The other thing is all of your modules, so as some of you know, when you're trying
like to automate and do PowerShell, you kind of have to make sure the modules are the right system when
they're actually going to get deployed and actually execute.
And so what we do with our modules is you can centralize them all into our service and then we can distribute
those out to wherever you need them. They can run from in our service, but you'll see that we're starting to
bring it so that you saw with the DSC probably on Monday we download all the modules needed for that configuration
so that you can actually run it. And so you don't have to worry about the distribution of all of your
modules going forward because you can centrally manage them here.
From a certificate thing, it all really depends on what you do in certificates, but a lot of times,
certificates themselves to get deployed and managed, and so we allow you to do that.
it might be something as simple as setting up like a certificate auth between servers or it might be deploying
your certificate to actually use for authentication and security over in IS, so it really depends without all
of that inside of our service as well.
The connections I'll talk a little bit about later, but these are really an object that allows you to kind of
separate what system you're talking to into a connection object so that you can reuse that inside your
PowerShell going forward and you don't have to hardcode that into the system.
Obviously, variables are kind of the catch all, so again, all of this is trying to allow you to say I don't
have to put stuff into the scripts.
I can put stuff into a central location service and then I can reuse those across all of my PowerShell
as I go forward and it's kind of the goal of like we've seen it for years and most of you probably do it,
but don't hardcode anything into the PowerShell because then it doesn't really become reusable, and so if we
can allow you to pull all of that domain knowledge into a central store and then you just use it at runtime,
it really allows you to have a powerful, flexible, and shareable PowerShell scripts.
The most obvious one at that is like your credentials. You probably use credentials to connect to a bunch of
different systems, but when the password changes, you don't want to figure out do I have to go back to the
scripts or some other place. You can just set it once here and then all of the PowerShell you've written
just inherits that as it goes forward.
And then, I mentioned variables and here's our credential stores.
So I won't go into DSC configuration because I think you guys saw this on Monday, but obviously we have
full management of all configurations inside our service, so you can upload your configurations,
you can compile them into the MOFs, you can deploy them out to any server either in Azure, on-premises in AWS,
and it's a pull services, so they get all their configuration and all the reporting comes back to our service.
Jobs, again is how do you troubleshoot? One of the challenges when you run scripts on-premises today is how
do you know what happened if something goes wrong? Where is all your logs being stored, are you writing them
to some share, are you trying to put them in some folder? We'll centralize every single action that's taken
from the automation into our jobs. So if
you need to go back and troubleshoot, you get the full log of what happened, but you also get which PowerShell
script was used at the time, so you can actually say well it's only changed my PowerShell script and that's
why it's failing or is it because the script just started to fail now and move the error?
All of that is centrally managed inside the service, so you never have to worry about that going forward.
These are the nodes in management, again, I think you saw most of these on Monday, and here's the node
configurations that were actually available. Question, yes.
Hey if I'm doing DSC pull server on here and it's contacting my nodes local on-premise, am I going to be
able to tell from here what's going on?
Yeah, so there's full reporting. I won't, so you can, like one of these…
(Audience comment)
Yeah, you'll know exactly what's going on from inside of the OS, all of the reporting shows up here.
So because the pull service you'll see that, you know, I'll just jump in here to one that's compliant
because this one's running, but you'll see I have a configuration that basically installs the Windows feature,
sets up a website, probably some stuff from Azure storage, I do some file work, I get some stuff from remote
file, and I install the package, standard stuff you'd see in DSC.
But now, all of this is reporting back, so if one of these things fail like you couldn't set the website up
correctly, I can drill in and you'll see exactly what's going on.
So you can see here I took action against the default website, as well as I created a new website inside of
my configuration, so
you can basically do troubleshooting all the way from the top level down to the actual resource that might be
failing inside DSC.
So yeah, that's not, that's one of the major advantages you'll get to it's kind of the central management of everything.
Okay and I'll jump out of here because I know we have other stuff to show, but the last thing to show here
and obviously you get the overview of your jobs, plus we have source control integration directly to GitHub
if you're starting to go down that path. You can just pull all of your scripts directly from there and it
allows for kind of that source control. Okay.