Okay, so let me show you this. So bringing your investments into the automation service.
So now I want to tell you a story.
So Sunday night, we were there at the hotel, the scripting life is like downstairs talking to about 20 or 40
different people that were like hanging around the bar area down there, yeah, and I went up and I was having
like some issues, so I sent Teresa an email and I said hey, I need you to come up to the room.
I need you to help me with my demo. And she goes, huh? I said yeah.
So why did I need her to help me with her demo? Well because she is an MVP, which means that she has a free Azure subscription.
So I wanted her to activate her Azure subscription, I wanted her to set up an automation account, and all of that.
So she did it and I didn't help here because I was like busy working on something else.
And she did all of this and then of course, then she made the mistake after she put her credit card in and
made the mistake of giving me her credentials, so I said wahoo! So I'm lined up.
So that's why this actually, it is the scripting watch portal and Teresa is the automation account name.
Now one of the things that's really, really cool and we just introduced this recently, and so and I've got,
I'm going to be writing some OMST blog articles about this. So if you go back and you're looking at Azure
automation and some of the scripts and tried to automate some stuff, you'll see that there's a lot of stuff out there.
A lot of this stuff is kind of difficult to word I mean because it's using Azure cmdlets, it's using Azure
RM cmdlets, there's talks of different, talks about trying to get access to your particular subscription and
all of this stuff and all of that is pretty much a nightmare, especially if you're just trying to learn this stuff.
So what we did is we created a run as account and Teresa did this automatically.
I didn't even tell her to do this because the GUI, when you're setting stuff up, it's smart enough to say
hey do you want to create a run as account and she said yeah. Well once you create the run as account,
then it does three things for you. It creates a run as certificate, it takes your account that you use and
actually creates an account for that, it also saves your credentials as a credential object, and it makes a
connection to your default subscription. All of these things were issues before.
Okay.
It definitely solves a lot of that. I think if you tried this out, depends on your organization, a lot of times
you can't really use your user account because you might have to factor auth enabled, which won't work inside the service.
Whereas now, we basically take advantage of service principles inside of Azure ID and that's what we
create behind the scenes for you and then we do cert auth against those, so you can manage your certs and
then we add you as a contributor to the subscription, but you could go in and manage and change that
and do anything you want, but it just does all of this by default just by checking the box during creation right now.
Okay, so this is a little bit of code that Teresa did, yeah, and it's pretty.
So once you've done that, then you use Get-AutomationConnection and the name is the AzureRunAsConnection,
and then you add your Azure RM account, specify your service principle, you've got Tenant, the TenantID,
the ApplicationId, blah, blah, blah.
Now I say she wrote it. She wrote this probably the way that lots of you write code.
She found it and cut and pasted it, right. So the other thing that's really cool is that once you've set up this
run as account, it automatically does a demo test script---
It's a tutorial, yep---
to the tutorial and that's where this code came from. Okay, but now you just simply past this into all of
your other stuff. But you can see how easy it is to come over here.
So there's the code. She kind of cleaned it up a little bit, but so add your RM account, blah, blah, blah,
and that's all you really need. And then at that point, your scripts, you add this in and then your scripts
will just simply work. So let's go back over here and I want to show you two runbooks and these runbooks
are using this service principle and this one here. So this is it.
It's a workflow, okay. Workflows start VMs. Now the one thing is you're naming your workflow and the name
of your runbook, those names need to match, okay. You'll get an error message that'll be very obvious if
they don't work. So there's that code right there that Teresa wrote to make my connection and then the rest
of it, this is standard PowerShell. Basically, it's three lines of code 7, 8, and 9.
My VMs get the AzureRmVMs.
Now these are your new Azure VMs, not the classic mode ones. Okay.
If you're creating new VMs in Azure, you want to be using the new ones, not the classic ones.
The classic ones are stuff you created a long time ago.
So we get all of those stored in a variable and just simply use foreach, walk through the loop, VM,
and then Start-AzureRmVM, that's a tongue twister, and then give it the name and the resource group.
Okay, so Teresa created all of her resource servers in a resource group called server.
Make sense, it's servers. So this starts them up and then the one that goes exactly with this is called
Stop-VMs basically. It helps, if I can tell you this, it helps if you create within your company a naming
convention and kind of stick to it. You see this is a stupid name.
But because I was wanting to figure out how to stop them because they were already running.
And as they're running, they're tick, tick, tick, tick, tick, tick, tick, just taking money out of your credit card.
So I wanted to figure out how to stop them really quick and I didn't want to do a bunch of clicky,
clicky things because I'm a PowerShell dude, right.
So workflow stop all of these. Now that obviously if I have more than a few, I'll be using foreach parallel
because this is a workflow, okay, but I didn't want to get things too complicated here.
If you know workflows, obviously you want it to know that one of the advantages is doing this stuff in parallel.
Same code, exact same code, cut and paste, but instead of Start-AzureRmVM, it was Stop-AzureRmVM.
So there's your two runbooks. Schedule them. This will help you when you start or you're playing with this
stuff doing your development and everything else, these two are going to save you some money guaranteed.
Start them up, shut them down. Now
not only that, let me show you this because I really and truly mean it when I say I really don't like mices.
Okay, so look what I did. Stop. So this is the schedule. I stopped these at, okay, so this is stop on
April the 7th, I'm going to stop these at what is it 7 am, is that what it says?
Yep.
Ah, different time zone. Okay. Different time zone. Okay.
So we're going to start these things at one time, we're going to stop them at another time.
Okay and so they start up, I work, they shut down.