So today it's only GitHub that we directly integrate with. I have some sample PowerShell out there that allows
you to basically connect to local.get, to TFS online, and you could basically use any kind of source
control you want and it basically just runs and I can share that later if you like.
Yeah, I've been on the online system, TFS is already showing up with coming soon.
I know. It's coming I would assume is the keyword there. It is coming, but we don't have a date on it yet,
but there are some ways to do it today. I actually have a little script that just runs and does that automatically.
There's lots of ways to do it, especially with our web host. But yeah, we're going to try to make the integration tighter.
(Audience comment)
Yeah.
(Audience question)
So today we store them and it's kind of a similar type of thing to the key vault, but we have our own store,
a secure store in the back-end that we use, and then we put them out as needed at runtime.
You could use key vault cmdlets if you want to store them there and then at runtime pull them into your script
if you didn't want us to store them, but it's a very similar back-end security model we have on key vault.
(Audience comment)
No you won't. So the question was if you wanted to sync with your local.get or your local source TFS,
does that mean we have to open up a bunch of ports so that we can connect to it to pull out those committed
runbooks and scripts. And you don't and the one way you don't have to do it is I kind of showed it, but I didn't
talk about it while I was. We have a hybrid worker in our service, and so what the hybrid worker does,
you can deploy this into your own environment on-premises and then it reaches out for work, so it's only
outbound ports that it has to go, so there's no holes being punched into your firewall, it's just an outbound
port you have to open and then that's how you can actually sync everything up and then send it up to there.
Okay, so let me just kind of, I know I flew by a little bit on that, but I just wanted to level set everyone.
Hopefully, you got a view for what we offer, but it really comes down to these major areas.
I won't go through each one,
but obviously everything's through the browser, so you can access it anywhere so all of the user experience,
all the authoring you can do up there in the browser as well. I might show that later.
We have full role-based access control, so if you want to say only certain parts of your organization have
access and certain automation accounts, you can actually assign an operator role and they can just execute
stuff in there. They can't actually modify, look at any of the credentials, do any of that.
Similarly, you saw some of the source control versioning work that we we've done.
From the authoring, we have two ways, this is the PowerShell summit, but we also offer graphical authoring if
you want to use that, and you can use graphical authoring with PowerShell and vice versa.
But obviously, we have an authoring experience for PowerShell directly in the browser as well.
So if you want to do authoring in there and you're on the road and you need to fix something up,
you can directly do it inside the browser, and test it, and then deploy it.
I didn't jump on the gallery. I think we may show that later, but we have a gallery experience that we can integrate with.
This allows you to pull all of your modules from PowerShell Gallery.
Everything's going to PowerShell Gallery, so if stuff isn't up there that you need, either please right it
yourself and upload it or ask us and we'll try to upload it as well, but everything we're doing is building
upon PowerShell Gallery as the kind of the source and the community content that's up there, so we don't want
to trade another one because there's such a huge ecosystem around it already.
And he says modules on the PowerShell Gallery, but we also have scripts up on the PowerShell Gallery as well,
and so if you've just written kind of a quick script or workflow or something like that, you'll be able to pull
that down from the gallery as well.
Yeah, it just got added the script read to recently, so it's another way in.
We're going to kind of do first class integration with that very soon.
I won't go through the runbook engine. You can probably imagine, but everything is built, so we run all of this
security and isolate it in the back-end for you.
So we basically create a host that you can run all your PowerShell in the service and it can scale as many as
you want, it's resilient, it can failover, you can specify which regions, all of that kind of capability,
you just get for free by moving things to the service. And it has a because it's a service, you can integrate
it very easy. I'll show you some of the ways you can extend and integrate into the service because it has
REST APIs that you can integrate with, as well as obviously all of the cmdlets, which were the Azure cmdlets
that you can manage it.
The integration I talked a bit about, so I won't spend any time with that, but I mentioned earlier
that through the key value property of PowerShell is not just a great language, but it's because everybody
and a lot of our partners and competitors have really on boarded with PowerShell as the way to manage systems,
and not just Windows systems, but actually management systems and even clouds.
I don't know if any of you guys have tried the AWS module that's out there, but it's like it's pretty awesome.
They have like I think 700 different cmdlets for managing every single thing you could do against AWS and
all of that can be run inside of our service, so it really kind of shows the power of using PowerShell,
but the ecosystem around it, it really does allow the integration to take place.