Cool. I know we're running out of time, so I'm going to jump just into a last couple of slides.
One of the things that obviously there's real power in the service itself and that's where you can do all of
your automation, all your PowerShell, all your configurations inside of service, but you'll start to see
we've actually integrated it into a lot of the other OMS services as well.
And so as you're starting to do that monitoring and all that logging, it means you can actually now trigger
your automation so that if this action happens, which you're monitoring, maybe you want to escalate it to a
service disk or maybe you want to restart the VM. We're all depending on that process, you can now tie the
insides with the action together inside the services. Similarly, with site recovery, you can do pre-automation
scripts to run, some post automation scripts to make sure that failover actually happens and that's first
class integrated into the service.
And then there's a bunch of integration into Azure as well. So if you create Azure alert today, you can actually
say when this alert fires, I want to call a webhook. We didn't go into the webhooks, but we have webhooks
available on our service as well. That basically allows you to call them.
But then if you do anything on Azure VMs, we have rich integration where it says run this runbook.
It's not just a webhook, so we've kind of first classed that experience as well.
Obviously I mentioned earlier, it is because we're a service, it really makes it easy for you to extend it as well,
so you can write your own modules, they're going to work in the service, you can call our SDK,
you can leverage Azure resource manager, all of those capabilities are built into the service and allows you
to build on top of that and extend. So if you haven't tried it out, definitely do try out our SDK.
For the ISE add-on, I gave a link to GitHub here, so you can actually see where the source code lives if you
want to use it. I'll see if I can open that up.
But while I do,
let me just jump in real quick and show you what the ISE looks like because I think it's useful to see what it does.
So you can see here I've actually logged in to the service, I can pick my subscription if you had multiple ones
and this, if you remember my RM account is the one I'm actually pointing to here.
So that's my automation account and it just enumerates all of the accounts inside the service.
But inside if your now all those runbooks are available to you, and so you can just open up one and just start
to reuse it. Let's see if I can. So this is a very simple one.
I was testing some output, but these could be any PowerShell, so you get all of the benefits of this,
and so you can author inside of here, but then you can also throw in some key vault stuff.
There's almost anything you want to do you would just normally do in PowerShell.
Author it here and you can test it, but then you can upload it to the draft, so you can see this is updated
locally, so I can just upload it directly into the service. And now it's in the service, but I can test it
here obviously just running it, but then I can also test it directly up in Azure because we put it into the service,
and so the identical script you author and tested here, you can push it to the service and just test it
directly inside of here and just off it goes. One thing I mentioned is you can test it either in Azure or if
you have a hybrid, you can cut it there as well. Alright, so let me jump out of
here because I know we want to just finish up.