Alright, so we're going to talk about Windows PowerShell as a Service today, managing clouds, Windows, Linux,
on-premise, or public by using Microsoft Operations Management Suite or OMS for short.
I am Ed Wilson, and I'm sometimes referred to as the Microsoft scripting guy.
I also write a blog called Hey Scripting Guy that's read by quite a few people and I've started, as of January,
the OSM team blog and I'll show you a link to that at the end. If you haven't been reading that, that is the
absolute place to go to find out everything about OMS. And I am up here with my friend from the OMS team, Eamon O'Reilly.
Hi everyone. My name's Eamon O'Reilly. Thanks, Ed. I work on the automation of the service inside of
Operations Management Suite, and so we'll kind of walk you through what that looks like today mostly focused
on the PowerShell capabilities.
Okay, so what are we going to talk about today? We need to have some objections, not objections, objectives perhaps.
Alright, so our session objectives and our takeaways, we're going to talk about why you want to bring what
does PowerShell automation give to the cloud and we're going to talk about what the core capabilities are
that our automation services provide.
We'll show you a nice slide about that. It is Operations Management Suite and the idea there should think of
well hmm, it's a suite of product and it really is, and so what we'll talk about that how all that works.
We're also going to
yeah everybody in this room is probably familiar with the very famous PowerShell manifesto.
I was actually talking with a couple people from the PowerShell team right before I came in here and PowerShell
has been around for 10 years. It's amazing. What's really kind of trips me out a little bit is when I'm
reading some blog from somebody, oh well we're using this new thing called PowerShell.
It's like dude, yeah, but yeah so 10 years it's been around. Well one of the things that's really cool and
Jeffrey Snover actually republished the PowerShell Manifesto, I think, last year just kind of as a
retrospective, but one of the things that he laid out in that Manifesto is that we honor your investment in
PowerShell and they've continued to do that so that yeah stuff that you wrote back in what is PowerShell 1.0,
it still works today. Yeah, there may very well be some better ways of doing it, but it's still works today.
It's an amazing level of background compatibility back over 10 years, but not only we're talking about that you
can leverage or that we respect your investment in the code because to be honest, like oh man I don't want to
look at some of that code I wrote 10 years ago, it's embarrassing yeah.
But certainly, I mean, we always learn and I've written more than 5,000 PowerShell scripts and stuff I wrote
even last week, I think of new ways of writing it better today. But so what am I talking about leveraging that investment.
When we came out with your functions, and then we came out with workflows, we respected what you had learned
from writing functions and writing workflows. Then when we came out with DSC, we respected what you had
learned from working with workflows and from functions and modules and all of that stuff kind of respects each other.
Well with automation and with moving PowerShell into the cloud, we still respect that and allow you to
leverage what you've done. So as a very, very simple example, all that time you spent learning workflows
when we introduced it a couple of years ago, dude, it applies, and a matter a fact, dude, it applies big time,
so you did not waste your effort learning workflows. But anyway, I'm sorry, we're still doing objectives and takeaways.
So integrating automation in OMS, Azure, yeah on-premises environments, so we're going to talk about how we
tie all this stuff together.
We're going to talk about how we solve some very, very real problems.
Some of the problems that as a person that's been scripting for more than 25 years, questions that I've heard
over and over and over again for the last 25 years, we finally solved them.
So we've got some very, very real solutions yet to some of the problems, and so we're going to talk about that.
The key takeaway. We are deeply invested in PowerShell, in DSC, and all that effort that you have spent in
learning this technology, we're going to allow you to apply it. And as we all know, PowerShell automation,
we're heavily dependent upon the community. That's why we're here.
That's why we can have great people like Eamon take time.
On the OMS team, we ship about every three weeks. So he's in the middle of a release cycle, but.
There's always one now.
He's always in the middle of a release cycle. But yeah, so he's here to talk to you.
Definitely we want to talk to you, find out. I think that we've hit a home run with this stuff or at least a
good double, but a stand up double. But let us know. We're here, we want to hear your feedback.