Ed, do you want to talk about Operations Management Suite?
Absolutely. So this is showing Microsoft's IT management solution and if you look down here at the bottom,
we got System Center, and so system center has been around, it's very mature technology, and primarily it's
been used and focused for managing the on-premises servers, all those servers that are over their systems there
and talks to it and it helps to manage. And then a few years ago, Microsoft started getting into the cloud,
and so we've got Azure up there, and initially, the idea was hey we need to be able to provide the same kind of
management capabilities for the cloud that we've been able to have for our on-premises servers.
As we try to shift more of the load to the cloud, the need to manage it grows proportionally as well.
And so, that's kind of where Operations Management Suite, the idea for it came from is that we need to be
able to manage this up there on the top, but we're not in a total cloud world.
We're not a total on-prem world. It's a hybrid world, and so the need really is there for hybrid management.
We need to be able to manage both. And by the way, in case you don't know, Azure isn't the only cloud service.
There's also this little thing that's called AWS or something that some people use.
And so, we need to be able to manage that too. And not only that, as a lot of times, people have their stuff
in both places. They've got Azure, they've got AWS. So there are four pillars for Microsoft Operations
Management Suite and there's a suite, so you can think of these four things.
As we were putting the product together, we drew from different resources and we brought stuff together.
So a lot of people who have heard about OMS, they think it's all log analytics, analytics, monitoring,
and stuff like that, and that is a piece, but or people sometimes think yeah well it's automation and there
is a configuration and automation piece as well. On Monday, we talked about using the OMS automation in DCS
to solve a number of very real problems that we have with Desired State Configuration.
One of the simple ones to highlight out of that is setting up a pull server.
Setting up a pull server is kind of a pain. Setting up a pull server correctly is almost a shot in the dark.
We give that to you for free. As soon as you start doing OMS and automation, you've got that.
There's a backup in disaster recovery component. There is also a security and compliance component.
Some of the stuff that we have, we provide deep insights into your environment that allow you to pull this
information out and expose stuff that you might not have even known was there.
And so, all of this, so OMS sits right there in the middle where we're doing the cloud, we're also doing the
on-prem, and because of that, as we're initially looking at a lot of our customers or looking at stuff,
we've got system center and OMS and they actually wind up being better together, but
OMS is not a cloud-only solution. We can do cloud, we can also do the on-prem, we can do Linux, yeah we can
do the other things, it's not necessarily a lay on top of system center.
You can have OMS by itself or you can have system center with OMS on top.
So it is pretty much the kind of management that you need for your environment that allows you to take care
of these capabilities.
Great.
Yeah, so I think the area we're going to focus on today obviously is a configuration automation.
It's most tied with all the PowerShell capabilities around all your scripts belong to your DSC.
But the last slide before we kind of give you an overview of what's going on is I think everybody starts to
realize when they look at the kind of lifecycle of the infrastructure and the application that there's a
bunch of capabilities required when you're actually managing not just infrastructure in the application and
it goes all the way up from how do you do the bills to how do you configure that and all the way through the
monitoring backup and recovery, how do you make sure it's secure, the governance, all of that is going to be
required as you start to think about especially in an enterprise world, what does it mean to manage the
infrastructure and the application.
And it's been a real challenge. I think we've had a lot of good tooling in System Center to actually help
with that with PowerShell and all the other management tools, but as you start to expand that to the cloud,
how do you still have the same processes as your stuff moves to the cloud?
And I think at the core of this, a lot of core services will offer their own kind of built-in automation.
Like when you do backup, it backs it up for you, and you can say that's automation because it backs it up for me.
But a lot of times, you really need to connect systems together to really provide a solution and that's where
the configuration and automation servers can kind of he uses a core throughout your entire lifecycle,
not just the infrastructure and the application to make sure that the end-to-end works and at the core of
that is the PowerShell because of its ability to kind of connect into everything and deliver that service.
And so you'll see, as you start thinking about the whole lifecycle how automation configuration is actually
central to all of that. Obviously, when you do the configuration side and other things we have like built-in
capabilities itself like DSC that is required for that, when we think about the whole lifecycle,
I would also say at the root of it all, it is configuration and automation.