Okay, so I'm going to hand over to Ed and he'll talk a little bit about if you want to, how do you bring it over.
Okay, so I started off by talking about how we honor your investment in PowerShell.
Well then that makes us say well okay, well dude, so obviously the language by being able to use the PowerShell
language and stuff, but you've also got scripts that you've already written
and a lot of those scripts you can bring directly into our service to be able to run immediately.
Some of them, you're going to want to change a little bit. So how many of you ever remember that Don Jones
said don't use Write-Host that every time you use Write-Host, you kill a kitten right.
Okay, well not only that, it's going to kill your automation script.
Okay, you may not like kittens. I actually saw a picture of a dog sitting there typing Write-Host,
Write-Host, Write-Host. But so use Write-Output, it's simple. Write a PowerShell script that goes through
every single one of your PowerShell scripts and changes Write-Host to Write-Output.
Actually hmm, that might be a good scripting guy article. It'd be easy to do it.
And you're already set. Now the nice thing about Write-Output is not so much from when you're actually doing
your automation because, as Eamon said, we have great logging, but when you're testing, when you're testing
your automation to make sure that it wants to work, yeah it's nice if you have something that kind of comes out.
This is kind of like using Set-Debug preference or something like that where you use your Write-Debug,
but we just use Write-Output and I don't know what would happen if I used Write-Debug.
It may work, it might not. I just figured I wouldn't.
No, we suggest Write-Verbose.
Yeah, Write-Verbose. Okay, so that would be better. But yeah, or Write-Output just to throw you some little
status points up, as you're writing this stuff for the very first time.
And no Read-Host.
Yeah, absolutely. Don't Read-Host. Obviously, that's not going to work.
Don't use Get-Credential. A lot of stuff like that. I've actually got an article that's kind of in the
works right now that I'm going to have on the OMS team blog where I'm going to go into some much more detail
about the stuff that you want to clean out of your PowerShell script before you stuff them into automation.
Another thing you want to do is you're going to want to modularize.
That's actually a word I made up back for my step-by-step 2.0 book where you take your script and can kind of
break them into component pieces, okay. So you want to do that because
if you break your scripts up into component pieces, rather than having these great big old monolithic,
I call them Frankenscripts, break it up into small discreet pieces, that way you can reuse them.
So for instance, if you've got a script that sends, that calls SMTP mail because you want to send out an email
or something, that makes a nice little piece. You can just kind of store it up there and you can just simply
call it, bring it in whenever you want to. Although, we've got some stuff that's coming, you're not going to
want to do that because we're building in the email notification features, so you'll want to be able to try
to take advantage of that as well.
We have, we've got a scheduler that's really cool and so you can create multiple schedules and then just
attach that schedule to your script however you want. It's going to just run.
You're going to get all of the notification.
Anybody that's ever tried to use even the PowerShell scheduler, or the App command, or the Windows Vista
scheduler, we've got like three or four different schedule engines built-in to Windows, none of which is
perfect, yet each of which has major problems and issues around reporting credentials and all of that stuff
and then when you start trying to test these things, it takes forever because you have to schedule it to run,
you go to test it and you don't know if it was a credential issue, an access issue, a resource issue, or what that
caused, or just I forgot to close a curly brace. You don't know what caused that script to fail.
Well with our resources and logging and stuff, you're going to be able to figure that out.
Workflow. Workflow is the way to go around here and I'm going to show you that in a little bit.
Now this last thing here. Authoring in the ISE. I use the PowerShell ISE all the time.
I love the fact that it's expandable and we can do the add-ons and stuff.
I love the fact that we've got it up on GitHub now, PowerShell Gallery you can download new versions of it, yeah,
all that stuff. Joe Levy wrote an ISE add-on, matter of fact, that's going to be in tomorrow's OMS blog.
I'm going to talk about that. So he wrote an ISE add-on that connects automatically to automation,
allows you to pull in your runbooks, you've got IntelliSense right there in the ISE, it creates a local
store right in your profile, we use JSON to keep it in sync with the runbooks and stuff that's available in
your automation, and you can test it right there. That's what I say, so I can edit, I can save a draft to
the cloud, yeah, I can publish it to the cloud, yeah, I can test it from the cloud, I can run it local,
however I want. It is a very, very, very cool thing and it's only on version .2.
Yeah, can you imagine what it's going to be like when it finally gets to version 1.0?
It is
open source, by the way. It is published in the PowerShell Gallery, which of course also means that it's
back in GitHub. And so if you want to contribute, if you want to fork it and add some stuff to it yourself,
you're more than welcome to do that.
Yep. I can show later on too. I'll show you a link to it if you want to start the preview.