So here's kind of the last slide. It's really about just what were the session objectives.
Hopefully, you learned about what we're doing, kind of where we're heading, how you can bring a lot of your PowerShell forward.
But I did want to mention as well that we have some customer days going on.
Ed maybe can talk about those.
So we've got customer days where people can come in. We actually have two of them scheduled and if you're
within the US, yeah just send me or Eamon an email and we'll see if we can get you into it.
It's for US only, but if you're internationally and you're willing to pay for your travel, then we'll put
you up for hearing that as well. The last thing is the
OMS blog, so blogs.technet msoms and that's where a lot of this stuff is and where a lot of it's going to be going forward.
And so, thank you. And with that, I've got some stickers, if you guys want to slide by, grab these as we
clear out the room for the next people.
Alright, thanks guys.