So lastly,  I want to mention that we need volunteers for a usability study tomorrow at 4:30 PM, so this is right after
the lightning demo session. We need about 20 to 30 people to participate in a UI study for a possible new
feature for Windows Server. It's like a prototype that I've been working on.
We are looking mainly for beginner to intermediate people with PowerShell, but advanced users are welcome.
It doesn't if you're MVP or not. If you're not an MVP, well you can sign an NDA there.
If you're interested in joining, please talk to me or Mark Gray, who's a PM on the PowerShell team, to sign up
and we'll let you know more details tomorrow about what room it'll be in, that sort of thing.
So thank you very much for coming to my talk. Here is some details about myself on Twitter and GitHub and
also the link to
PowerShell Editor Services on GitHub as well. I think we have a little bit of time for questions if anybody
wants to ask questions. All good. (Audience question) It comes bundled with the VS code extension.
So whenever you installed the extension through VS code's extension installer, it has everything you need there.
So yeah. So basically, it's a dynamic application that is bundled and it just gets launched with the extension.
When did the interactive shell get derived? Last time I checked code out, it wasn't.
Yeah, so it's been there for maybe two or three releases. It's sort of hidden because you can't actually
type directly in it. It's actually an output pane where if you select some code and hit F8, it will run it
and show the output, (Audience comment) yeah, so the sort of hacky way to deal with that for now is to
just type something not Format-Volume obviously, but like Get-Process, and hit F8, and it will give you the output, but.
Will F8 just select the current line by default? F8 runs whatever you currently have selected.
I think somebody added the function where, this is not actually selected, it's just highlighted.
I think if you don't have a selection, it runs the current line.
Yeah, okay. I don't know why it failed at that point. (Audience comment)
Yeah, it runs up to where the cursor is. That's a little weird, but anyway.
Yeah so what we're waiting on is for VS code to add the console so that we can basically just wire this directly
into a console where you can type in commands, so that's coming.
I think that within the next couple of months it'll be there. Yeah, that would definitely change my whole
view on it. Yeah, that's like the one thing that's missing, I think, until this like way better.
But anyway, I think we're out of time, so thank you very much for coming.