So I'm going to show you how this looks in Visual Studio code. So let me see if I can make this look bigger.
(Clicking) That's too big. Anyway, so what you see here is a file that I have open and I have a function I've
defined, which does just really simple thing, it just writes output, and you see this cmdlet here this
Register-EditorExtension and basically this command is running your PowerShell session and it says I want to
register a new command in editor with this display name of My Command with function and also this Id,
which is useful maybe to identify the command from other areas. Also, you were saying basically that there's
a function called Invoke-MyCommand, which is this, which should be invoked whenever the command is launched.
So to access these commands, I'll go to the Show additional commands from PowerShell modules option.
And if I run that right now, it tells me that no extension commands have been loaded to the current session,
which is what we expect. So what I'll do is I will select this code and I'll run it with F8.
You'll see in the output console that I've actually ran the code and the command has been registered.
And now, if I go back to that same additional commands list, you'll see that My command with function now shows up.
So if I run that, you'll see that the right output, whoops, the right output is actually called and basically
just invoke my function directly and it's kind of nice because you can actually edit these things in real-time
and not have to like restart your editor to be able to see the updated functionality.
So now we can also do the same thing with ScriptBlock. So if I have another command registered here or able
to be registered, which actually just takes a ScriptBlock and writes an output as well.
I've run that one. And now let's go to the additional commands list and now we see My command with script block
is here, so run that, same output. So that's pretty basic, not really helpful.
You can do things like run Get-process or something, but yeah, maybe you could launch your build scripts or
maybe a deployment script. That can be kind of helpful, but the real helpful stuff comes when you start
actually manipulating the editor in real time. So to define this function called
Invoke-MyEdit and it accepts this context variable and this is a variable that comes from PowerShell Editor
Services and it gives you information about the current context of the editor at the time the command was invoked.
So we have things like the current file and we have information about like what the current user selection is
and where the cursor location is in the buffer. So this current MyEdit function actually will take the current
file and will insert text into the file and it will do it with the sort of the full range of the current file
meaning the entire file. So we're basically saying insert this string with this entire range, so it basically
overwrites the range that you've specified. So if I just type something like WHOOPS and I run this,
then I can go and type, whoops, additional commands, and then Apply my edit is available, so I hit that,
and basically it just replaces the entire buffer. So that's kind of cool.
I mean, another thing you can do is do some manipulation to the actual content that's already here.
So if I take this and say Context.CurrentFile.Contents.ToUpper and all I have to do at this point,
since the command is already registered is just reevaluate the function itself, and if I run it,
it basically uppercases everything in the file. So you can start to see where this can go.
You can just basically manipulate the code in place. So let's say if I wanted to actually insert some text
into the file, so let me comment this line out and uncomment these two lines.
So what I'm doing here is I'm actually creating an object that defines the range that I want to update.
This is not the actual desired way that I want people to do this.
I'll provide some overloads to this InsertText method, but for now, I'm just doing it this way.
So basically what I want to do is in the current file, I want to insert a line of text at, let's see if I can
get to the end here, at the Line 24, Column 1, and Line 24, Column 1, so that's like the start location
and end location. So basically what I'm saying at this cursor location, I want to insert this piece of text.
So if I go in, reevaluate this function and I should be able to run it and now it inserts this new line of text here.
So I'm basically going to format the C drive, which is nice. But anyway, hopefully that
shows you that yeah, we basically can do lots of stuff with this.
One thing you could do is have a command for your project where you automatically are able to insert comment
block headers for your files or maybe generate a certain type of function like you have a lot of code that
needs to be generated for your project, you could easily generate it using one of these commands.
Yep. But where's your plan just like going? Like are you thinking like in your profile or will that command
register just stay with this session? That's a great question. So one way is it could go in your profile.
Another thing I'm thinking is it would be great if there was a way that if a PowerShell module from the
gallery included something that registers a command like this, if we could actually identify that module as
having a command and load it automatically in the session, if you have maybe a command in your profile that
says automatically load extensions, maybe the way that happens is we have like an extra tag we put on that
is like a conventional tag we put on modules in the PowerShell gallery, so I can just do like grab all the
modules that have this command that you have, sorry, this tag that you have that are installed and just load them up.
For a person who writes a module who wants to actually add some extension commands from their module,
they can just check to see if the PSEditor object is available, and if so, they can just call the Register-Command function.
So I think it's going to be a little bit of both. Either people have their own sort of comment code that
they are going to run for registering commands or modules that you get from the gallery will have extension
commands that will be able to run whenever they're loaded into your session.
So does that answer the question? Yeah. Yeah. So yeah, I kind of want this to be the new way going forward
of providing new functionality to editors. The nice thing about this is that for an editor who wants to
provide the same extensibility, they just need to implement a few methods on an interface or potentially
respond to a few different messages in the JSON protocol for the host process.
So it should be available anywhere that the editor service is used, which is pretty cool.
So the first draft of this extensibility model is going to show up in versions 0.6, the next version of the
VS code extension, and I expect it will show up in the ISE preview probably within the next two to three months.
I'm going to do a little bit of work to get that started in the ISE preview for my next talk at the PSCompu,
but it probably won't be fully there yet before the next version of the ISE preview.
I've got one question. Yep. With the ISE, how do you intend to get the same functionality of it doesn't
have that little bar where you type it in and stuff. Right. Another great question.
Yeah, that's another one of the things I want to add to the ISE preview is that same kind of command palette construct.
So for people who haven't really used VS code very much, VS code has this really cool command palette where
it basically gives you every single
command that's available in the editor and you can type something like save and it will show you the save commands.
It also shows you the key binding for the command. So I would like to add something like that for the ISE
because I think
that it gives a way to surface all of the possible operations that are in the editor and allows you to add
your own operations at the same level as the built-in operations so that all of the functionality that's
in the editor currently, it's all sort of at the same level and it should be pretty helpful.
But definitely curious to hear if people thinks that's a bad idea or if they like it.
But. I'd like to see that. Yeah, yeah there's a lot of people on Twitter and I did a Twitter poll maybe two
months ago or something asking if people wanted to see it and generally, people seemed to be in favor of it.
So I'm going to give it a shot and if people don't like ultimately, I can take it back out, but I think it
will be helpful. Let's see. So in my mind,
the future of the PowerShell authoring experience is clear. Our short term goal will be to use the
integration of PowerShell Editor Services into the ISE preview as a way to flesh out its feature support
so that the same functionality can be used in many other places.
This should help make developer adoption of PowerShell go a lot more smoothly because developers can use the
tools that they already like, their editors that they already like to have a really good PowerShell development experience.
They don't have to go and learn VS code or the ISE or Visual Studio if they don't want to.
I'd also love to work with anyone who's interested in using PowerShell Editor Services in a code editor or
any other type of application. The project is open for contributions and other type of feedback on GitHub,
so if you just go check out our GitHub page, which I'll show to you later, then you'll be able to see all the
things that are happening. If you watch the repo, you'll see all the work in progress.
Usually it's just me keep talking on issues. Yeah, and the platform will get so much better with every new
contribution and integration, so any amount of interaction there is definitely helpful.