Alright. So good morning everyone. It's great to see you all here today.
I don't actually have anything planned to talk about today, so I figured we could all just go over to
Kirk Munro's session instead. Just kidding. So anyway, I'm excited to be here at the summit to spend some
time talking to all of you about the cool things that are going on to the whelm of PowerShell operating tools.
For those of you who don't know me, I'm David Wilson, and I'm a member of the PowerShell team, and I'm really
fortunate to get to work on cool projects like the PowerShell ISE, PowerShell for Visual Studio code,
and PowerShell Editor Services. And in my time working on the projects, I've been able to talk with many
members of the PowerShell community, so it's really awesome that I get to meet many of you in person this week.
If you see me around the summit in the next few days, please feel free to come by and chat.
So my talk today is titled
The Future of PowerShell ISE and Editor Services. So my goal with this talk is to
show how the future of PowerShell ISE will be defined by the integration of PowerShell Editor Services and
how this will improve the larger of PowerShell authoring ecosystem.
So let's start with an
overview of the current landscape of PowerShell editors just to show how our work fits into the bigger picture.
So for many years, PowerShell, I'm sorry, Microsoft has been focused on a single editor for PowerShell,
the PowerShell ISE.
The ISE is considered the standard PowerShell editor for many people
since it comes in box Windows and typically supports all the latest and greatest PowerShell features
as they appear. It's simple and understated, but it gets the job down.
Its add-on model has allowed for some nice extensions and customizations and integrations with other
Microsoft services like Azure agnation and PowerShell gallery. It's also been extended far past its original
feature set by the ISE Steroids add-on, which a lot of people seem to like.
Tobias Weltner has done a great job of turning the ISE into a much more powerful editor than what it was before
for those who needed it. So even though the PowerShell ISE has been serving people well for many years,
a new opportunity appeared last year that we wanted to sort of investigate and that is
Visual Studio code. So Microsoft announced Visual Studio code during build 2015
and spent a lot of time last year polishing it and improving it to something that's really useful.
Its biggest benefit over Visual Studio is that it manages to provide the same level of functionality or
close to the same level of functionality without all the extra bloat that Visual Studio has.
So around the middle of last year, we were alerted to the development of a new extension model that would
allow developers to plug in new language implementations and functionality like IntelliSense,
code navigations, linting, and debugging support and we decided that it would be cool to investigate to see
what it would take to actually plug in PowerShell to Visual Studio code.
It turns out it wasn't that hard to provide a pretty decent level of PowerShell support.
So in November of last year, we released the PowerShell extension for Visual Studio code during the
announcement where the Visual Studio team, Visual Studio code team announced their extensibility model,
and since then, we've had over 30,000 downloads of the extension and four updates with new features and a
wide variety of great feedback in the community. So this effort also spawned another project called
PowerShell Editor Services, which allows us to provide the same level of capability to pretty much any other
editor, but we'll talk about that later. So,
we also have Visual Studio and people were asking for a long time why Microsoft didn't actually provide
PowerShell support directly in Visual Studio.
Well they didn't really need to ask for long because Adam Driscoll came along and made poshtools in Visual Studio
and it filled a real need for really good PowerShell support in Visual Studio as demonstrated by the 340,000
downloads as received, at least for the 2015 version, and the utility of this extension was so obvious that
the Visual Studio team decided to include it as part of the Windows, I'm sorry, as part of the Visual Studio 2015
installer, so that was pretty cool. Now for those who need something a little different than what Microsoft
provides are our third-party editor's store is still pretty good. There's the PowerShell studio editor from SAPIEN technologies.
I think June's somewhere back here. It's a really nice tool
that seems to go beyond just in general development experience to user interface development, packaging,
and deployment and been hearing really good things about it on Twitter and I haven't really had much of a
chance to play with it myself, but I'm sure that June would be happy to tell you more of the cool things it does.
There's also PowerGUI, which was originally developed by a company called Quest and then
acquired by Dell and I think that Kirk and Adam had worked on this at some point in the past.
I've heard good things about it, but I don't really see much activity of risk development these days.
And we also have the wild and crazy world of open-source code editors.
So Sublime Text and Atom are both really popular for developers who primarily use open
source technologies and platforms. Their strings lie in their modern style and white ecosystem of packages that
give support for various different tools and technologies, pretty much anything that you can think of.
So for PowerShell, both of these editors provide packages that contain syntax highlighting, snippets,
and some really rudimentary IntelliSense, but no real integration with the PowerShell runtime.
And last year, I spent a little bit of time, maybe a couple days trying to get PowerShell Editor Services
integrated into Sublime Text to start to get some of these features online, but I still haven't got it fully
wired up yet, but hopefully at some point later this year, I'll get a chance to go back to these editors and
wire them up. However, over the last few months, I've noticed that a lot of people are starting to migrate
towards Visual Studio code, so that may sort of affect the prioritization of the work to wire up these editors.
So there's also Emacs and Vim and the common stereotype for Emacs and
Vim users is that they're old school UNIX and MIMS with scruffy beards, long funny tails, and stale t-shirts,
but the reality is that both of the editors are still widely-used today and there's a sort of resurgence in
their popularity based on some new tools for them called Space Max and Neovim.
Both of these editors have packages that provide basic PowerShell editing support, similarly to Sublime Text
and Atom, but they also lack the richer editing features like IntelliSense, etc.
And they also have the same sort of extensibility models that would allow those things to get added later.
So since I'm actually a fan of Emacs, I want to go and try to get that thing hooked up with better PowerShell support
sometime maybe later this year or next year. I know there's a couple of people on the PowerShell team that
are active Vim users, so I wouldn't be surprised to see some activity there as well.
So at this point, you're probably wondering why am I mentioning all of these editors.
Well it shows that there's value in having different options for different needs, basically.
So some people prefer the focus experience of PowerShell ISE, while others need a more complete development
experience like Visual Studio, which supports other languages as well.
Some people prefer the minimalistic editors like Vim or maybe modern highly-customizable editors like Atom.
The important thing to understand is that for each of the editors provide a standard PowerShell development experience.
They have to implement a fairly large amount of common code. So what we'd like to do is make it easier to
provide the standard experience across most of these editors so that each developer can work in the environment
that's most comfortable to them that works better for their workflow.
So a little later in this talk I'll describe how we'll be able to accomplish such a standard experience and
feature sets so that developers have a wide variety of tools to choose from.