So let's talk about ISE preview priorities if I can get back to where my presentation was.
There we are. So one of the first things I want to do as you may have seen is
address as much high value UserVoice feedback as I can. I've started this work, but there's still a lot more
work to be done. I mean there's a lot of
issues that have been voted up on UserVoice and some of them are definitely possible, others not as possible.
I mean there's probably not going to be the likelihood that we're going to change sort of the UI model of the
ISE where you can sort of have Docking tabs and stuff just because it's a lot of extra work.
I think that ISE Steroids may solve that problem already. But just anything we can do that will be a general
productivity improvement or something that the ISE is lacking that other editors just sort of have by default,
definitely file feedback for that. What about little things like maybe let's say like where you draw your
bracket or whatever and you can't enter it. You know what I mean?
It goes like double does the line indents for you. Is it going to be like that stuff?
We can definitely look into it. I don't really know how much effort it would take, but definitely worth looking into.
So I don't know if there's already a UserVoice item for that, but if someone files it, we'll definitely look into it.
(Audience comment) Yeah, definitely that. (Audience comment) Yeah, pretty much every editor has the sort
of automatic indentation functionality, so this is something that is a little annoying whenever you go into
the ISE and it just doesn't have things like this. So basically, my plan is to work on the highest value
improvements that will address long-term pain points and the goal really isn't to make the ISE at the same
level as other editors that exist because you can just use the other editors instead, but it's just we want
to make this like really solid core editor with a really good extensibility so that the community can come
and add more features as necessary. So also, for new
feature development in the ISE preview and the full ISE, I'd like to focus on what we can add through the
ISE's add-on model to enable new features
to be added using our add-on APIs rather than being added into the ISE code base.
This may involve just some tadpole improvements here and there to our existing extensibility points,
but the goal would be just sort of enable new things that people can do to extend the life of the ISE by
adding new functionality. This is in the area that I'd really appreciate getting some feedback on UserVoice
about what new extensibility points would be helpful. I'm looking for a high value, low cost improvements
that will enable new types of extensibility in the ISE. There's also a new extensibility model that's coming,
which is complimentary to the ISE's add-on model, but I'll discuss that a little bit later.
So the biggest priority for the ISE is a gradual overhaul that brings in PowerShell Editor Services as their
core implementation for all this editor features.
This integration will be rolled out over time in a way that should minimize disruption to existing scenarios
while allowing everyone to try out the new features and provide feedback.
So generally speaking, what this means is that ISE, sorry, PowerShell Editor Services will basically provide
the host environment for PowerShell so that all the things like IntelliSense and code navigations, etc,
will be coming from there, rather than from the existing code base in the ISE and this will help in some ways
because currently we've got some sort of problems with the ISE code base where you might see things like
when it crashes or hangs and stuff like that really shouldn't be happening and it's due to sort of a bad
throating design, etc, but we can get away from a lot of those problems by shifting to a different core and
sort of refactoring the code that's already there. So as I mentioned earlier, the ISE preview release
contains an experimental PowerShell tab, which will be the basis for this conversion and this new tab we use
editor services to basically provide all these features. And since editor services currently doesn't support
as many features as the PowerShell ISE does, we'll have to continue to improve that support over time before
we actually make the Experimental tab the default. So remote session is just one thing.
We don't really support remote sessions yet. There may be some other little things here and there that I
haven't thought about, so we'll have to figure those things out sort of as the migration happens.
But once we make the Experimental tab actually the default tab, then we'll keep the old tab, the legacy tab
around just to have it there in case anyone hits an edge case in the behavior of the new implementation
so that it can use the old style tab for whatever it is they need to do.
And ultimately,
these improvements should be integrated back into the build of the ISE that we ship with Windows, but we still
haven't decided when and how we want to
accomplish this since shipping in box of Windows requires some extra work around quality, localization,
and other types of work. But the current plan is to try integrating new stable features from the preview
back into the built-in ISE sometime after the next Windows Server and client versions have been released,
so probably later this year sometime, way later this year. We want to make sure that whatever we end up
shipping is of high quality and has been put through as paces by the community just to make sure that it's
not going to be a problem when it's actually in box and it needs to be shipped, I mean sorry, it needs to be
supported for years and years.