So by now, you might have realized that I've mentioned PowerShell Editor Services a few times in this talk,
but I haven't actually explained what it is.
So PowerShell Editor Services is a platform that can be used to provide a rich,
PowerShell development experience in any sufficiently extensible editor.
The benefits lie in four distinct areas, language intelligence features, interactive console experience,
debugging support, and other platform features, so I'll discuss all of those individually.
But first, it's good to sort of run through the set of common features that any PowerShell editor will need to implement.
First of all, it's going to need
a host implementation, which implements PSHost, PSHostUserInterface, and some and not of
PSRawHostUserInterface and for those of you who don't actually know what those things are,
it's probably better that you don't know, but these allow the host application to expose a PowerShell
runtime through the host application's user interface and they aren't super difficult to implement, but it's a
lot of common code that's just reimplemented everywhere. Basically, any time you want to implement a host,
you have to implement these things and it's kind of a little bit of a waste.
So when you start implementing a PowerShell host, it does more than just execute PS commands,
you'll quickly realize that you have to change the way you execute commands based on the state of the session.
Running a command in a local session is
different than running a command in a remote session and running a command while stopping a debugger is also
different than running a command just in a normal session. So this behavior isn't always straightforward to
understand or figure out and at some point any PowerShell host out there is going to have to learn how to do
these things if they want to have more advanced support in their host implementation.
Another critical element of a good PowerShell development experience is interactive console support.
So one of the biggest reasons why people tell me they'd still
rather use the ISE instead of VS code is that the ISE has an interactive console that's always available.
It's a really helpful feature if you're sort of really quickly developing script.
Implementing in such a console
isn't difficult, but it requires rewriting a lot of common logic all over again, for instance, like invoking the
prompt function to get someone's custom prompt or dealing with formatting of error messages,
just all this stuff that sort of has been done many times. More capable editors may want to provide debugger
integration, which requires a fair amount of work for walking the call stack, getting information about
variables that are in scope for each level of the call stack, and even managing the pipeline whenever you
want to execute commands while the debugger
stopped at a breakpoint. So generally, the point I'm trying to make here is that any editor integration for
PowerShell is going to need implementations of all of these items and it'd be great if we could use what
we've learned in implementing these things for the ISE and other editors so that we can make this logic
available to everyone else and we just so have created a platform that with the intention of solving this problem.
So let's talk about the features that it provides.
So for language features, one of the primary benefits is improved language feature support.
First of all, being the IntelliSense support, which is kind of like the core thing
you need for having a pretty good PowerShell development experience in editor.
It's the same IntelliSense that the ISE gets because we're using the same completions engine that comes from
the PowerShell runtime,
but we also had a new area of features called code navigations and these allow you to do things like find a
definition of a function or variable, find all references of a function or variable or cmdlet, and also
search across all the names of symbols in your workspace or the current file, which is kind of useful in VS code.
These features try to be pretty helpful whenever you're trying to navigate around a piece of code that you
haven't ever seen before or maybe a module, so they're kind of a value add that the ISE currently doesn't have.
We also provide rudimentary
symbol renaming support meaning that you can rename a cmdlet or variable and we'll
also change all the places where that cmdlet or variable name are used, so that's also pretty helpful.
So I know the really cool feature that we have
is that we've hooked up PowerShell script analyzer to provide real-time, rule-based script analysis in the
analyzer scripts rising type, so as you're writing your script,
you'll see little squiggle markers that say that maybe you're violating some best practice.
So basically, you're able to select which rules you want to apply to your scripts while you're editing them
and then you'll see all the stuff marked up in your file. In the near future, we'll also be able to provide
code corrections, which are based on the rules that you've sort of violated so if you have a squiggle marker
under something, you may be able to click it and see a little light bulb pops up to actually get suggestions
on how to fix it and then if you click the fix, it will fix it automatically for you.
If that's sounds interesting, I'm actually going to give a demo of an early version of this feature at the
lightning demos tomorrow afternoon, so be sure to see that. So once we make progress integrating editor
services into the ISE, I'm going to try to wire up as many of these language features as possible because the
ISE doesn't have a lot of these things, so we'll see if we can get some of these things actually built into the ISE.
So editor services interactive console experience is getting better with each release,
even though it isn't immediately visible within VS code. We're able to do the interactive script execution
and have a console experience, which supports custom prompt functions just like the ISE.
It even provides a choice and input prompt support even through the interactive console or natively through
the editor's UI, so in VS code if you run a command that causes a choice prompt to appear, you actually will
see a little drop-down that gives you the options in VS code's command pallet rather than get to showing up
in the command console, so this can be helpful for like nicer integration with the editor for various reasons
like if you have an extension or something.
It's also if you type in a command that you haven't filled in all
the mandatory parameters for, you need to be able to get prompted for those things, so we also the input
prompt support where this will show up in the UI. And I also just finished adding a
$profile support, which should show up in the next release of the VS code extension.
For those of you who aren't familiar with profile scripts, they are used to customize
your PowerShell session in a given host like the ISE or VS code. You can do things like load modules,
create commonly-used functions, set your preferred command aliases, define your custom prompt function,
stuff like that. This feature is really the most helpful whenever you are using interactive console from within
an editor, so just to make it a little more customized for your purposes.
We're only lacking a
couple of important features at this point, but I intend to have them done before we hit version 1.0 a little
later on this year. The first is the ability to accept credentials securely and that's only missing because
we haven't yet found a secure way to securely transmit the credentials you type from the editor to the language service.
So since we had this model where the editor is talking to the language service through some channel,
we want to make sure that once you type in the credentials in the editor that they're secured in the editor,
as well as in across the channel to get to the language service.
This is a little bit difficult, especially in VS code because it's a web-based application and if anyone is
sufficiently intelligent or crafty enough, they could probably intercept the things that you're typing in,
but I think that's just a general problem anyway, but that's sort of why that's missing at this point.
The other thing is support for remote in nested sessions. This is something that we just need to have time to do.
It's not very hard to achieve, so probably within the next two to three months you'll see remote session support
in the ISE so that you can connect to like a Nano server for script editing, debugging, that sort of thing.
We also
provide a pretty rich, local script debugging experience. You can set breakpoints on lines, commands, and arbitrary expressions.
You can also inspect the variables at each level of the call stack.
Our interactive console experience also extends to the debugger in which it allows you to
run commands while you're stopped at a breakpoint, so if you want to run some of the PowerShell's debugging
or if you want to sort of mess around with the values of variables in the running script, you can do that.
Keith Hill has done a
ton of work to improve the debugging experience that we're able to provide, so if you've never tried out the
debugging experience in VS code, you should give it a shot and then tell Keith thank you whenever it blows your
mind because it's pretty cool. So there are some other nice features
that the platform provides and we designed them in a way that allows you to only use the ones which you care
about if you're trying to integrate this with an editor. First of all, our APIs are designed in a layered
model where the core functionality is exposed through a set of classes, which are useable at any .NET applications.
So basically, you can just pull a NuGet package into your app, and I don't know, 20 lines of code and you're
set up and you're able to run commands and use some of these nice editor features.
The next layer above that
provides a way to host these APIs in a process, which communicate with non-.NET applications through any channel.
For now, this host process speaks Visual Studio
codes, JSON-based language, and debug server protocols and it does it over standard input/standard output,
so it basically VS code launches the process and just connects to the console in/console out and we're
basically communicating with JSON messages back and forth that way.
But we can also plug in different protocols, but it doesn't necessarily have to be a JSON protocol,
it can be something else and I might experiment with this a little bit in the future.
This also implies that the API can be
exposed both to other processes on the same machine or through a network-based channel like HTTP.
Adam Driscoll has helped get the ball rolling on providing a WebSocket support to make the JSON protocol
available as a web service that could be used either on the same machine or possibly a remote machine.
Once we have a chance to flesh out the support and add the appropriate WebSocket client in VS code,
then it would allow the users of code editors like VS code on OS 10 and Linux to edit their code from OS 10,
but have all the language features coming from a host app that's running within a Windows VM or potentially
like a service running in a cloud, so we'd give you the ability to do PowerShell development with full features
on those OSs without actually running PowerShell locally on the OS since we don't have that.
But there are a lot of possibilities here, so there's a lot of different ways to integrate this into other
things, so definitely see interesting things we could do. Another useful feature is PowerShell
gallery integration. This allows any editor to interact with the PowerShell gallery to list, install,
and manage PowerShell modules from any gallery repository, so not just the standard PS gallery.
Doug Fink helped to get the support started and I'm going to leverage the new code that you saw in the ISE
preview for doing module updates just sort of put that together into the editor services to provide like a
standard service for interacting with the PowerShell gallery.
And lastly, we'll be providing a new extensibility model, which will enable editor commands to be written in
PowerShell and to be used across all the editors that leverage editor services.
You'll be able to automate things in the editor like the editing text or launching actions in the editor or
maybe changing views. We sort of have to figure out what the common surface area is across different editors,
but this might be a pretty interesting way for people to use their existing PowerShell code from their modules
to provide new editor functionality, so that's a pretty interesting thing.
So this feature is actually currently in development, but it's in like its very early stages, so I've got a short
demo that I'll show you today about to give you an idea of what is possible with this.