So since this presentation is supposed to be about the future of PowerShell ISE,
let's talk about the ISE preview. We made an announcement a couple months ago that we
had shipped an alternative version of the ISE via the PowerShell gallery, which gives us the opportunity to
try out some new features and new ideas while keeping the built-in ISE stable.
Our intention is to ship updates with new features somewhere between a monthly and a bi-monthly cadence.
Having said that, you may have notice that it's been a little while since the first release.
I think that we released it in February and it's still lacking another release since then, but that's for a
good reason though. I've actually been working over the last few weeks to put together a new release that
addresses some of the most highly uploaded feedback on UserVoice and also a new feature that I think all of
you are going to like. So instead of just showing you a list of what these new features would be,
why don't I just give you a quick demo to kind of show it that way.
Let's see if I can pull that up. Alright,
so one of the first things you may notice that's a little bit different is that there's this little icon here
in the lower left-hand corner. So now we have the ability when the ISE preview starts up to do a scan for
any PowerShell gallery modules that you may have installed and to check if there's any updates for those
because currently there's not a really good way to see which gallery modules you have that may have updates
that you haven't installed yet, so I decided to put a little piece of UI here that will give you the
information for this. Alright, so when I click the icon, there's a new window that appears that gives me a
list of the modules that currently have updates and we can see here that the Pscx module needs to be updated.
Of course, this was released in 2015 so it's sort of contrive example.
Also, there's PSScriptAnalyzer, which has been updated to version 1.5.
So you can see that we're actually gathering the release notes and the version information from the gallery information.
You can see that sort of all the details are here. Also, you can select whether you want all updates or just
uncheck various updates that you're not interested in. And another interesting thing here is that the Pscx
module actually was installed system wide. It wasn't installed for just a current user.
So I'm not actually running the ISE preview elevator right now, so it's sort of interesting to see what
happens whenever we do this. So I'm going to go ahead and just click Update to update these modules.
So since Pscx needs admin level credentials, we actually see an error that sort of shows you.
It's basically just an error that comes directly from PowerShell from the cmdlet.
And also, you'll see that there's a prompt for the untrusted repository, but I think that should change soon.
But now since it's all in PSScriptAnalyzer and if I had other modules that needed to be updated, they would all
be installed as well, so pretty easy. Just install like all your updated modules.
It's nice for people who actually are module developers so that whenever you push a new version of your module,
people who are using the ISE will actually be able to install it, they'll know that it exists.
So since this functionality starts automatically with ISE, some people may not want to have like the initial
performance hit of having this sort of module scan and update scan happening, so we've actually
added a new option in the Options dialog, in the General Settings tab, so you can actually uncheck the Check
for module updates automatically option. So that will stop it from happening at start up.
And if you ever want to invoke the process, you can go to the Help menu and click Check for updates so that
will kick off the update process. So that's sort of the big new feature.
There's another thing that we're doing that sort of sets the stage
for future work on the PowerShell Editor Services integration and that is the
new experimental PowerShell tab. So if you click the File menu, you'll see that there is a new item for an
Experimental PowerShell tab, and right now if you open it, there's really nothing different.
It's the same functionality that we currently have, but the point is to have the separate tab so that we can
start to gradually do the integration with PowerShell Editor Services over time and not disrupt the core
PowerShell ISE experience. This also helps people like Tobias Weltner who have ISE Steroids and he sort of
reached into the functionality of the ISE a little too much and if I do anything drastic with the existing
PowerShell functionality, it's going to break all the ISE Steroids users, so don't really want to do that.
But in the future, you'll be able to try out new features that come from PowerShell Editor Services in this
type of tab, so as those things get developed, they'll be talking about it on Twitter probably and let people
know that new things are available there.
Alright, so there's one UserVoice issue, I think it was filed by Bartech and it was sort of an annoyance for
people and a lot of people expressed some interest in getting this removed or getting this changed.
Let me see if I can pull up the inbox ISE. So right now, if you were to type something like Get-Process, whoops,
and you see there's a lot of output and you want to scroll up in the output pane and sort of see what's going on
there then maybe you go into the script editor and mess around a little bit, then you come back and click in the
output pane because you want to copy something, but it jumps down to the end, which is a little bit annoying.
So now I've removed that behavior. So if we type Get-Process here in ISE preview, you'll see the same output
a little bit slower because I'm running it in a debugger. And if I scroll up here and click inside of the
script editor and mess around then come back, it doesn't actually jump to the end.
So there probably needs to be a little more polish on this to kind of deal with a
couple cases where maybe you do want to jump to the end or maybe if you click in here, you may want to like
hit a button and have it jump to the end, so there's a little bit more polishing that needs to be done.
But really what I'd like to do is just sort of ship this and see what they've been think and just get some
feedback from the community and see what people want it to do. So that's kind of helpful, a little less annoying now.
Also just in general, productivity improvements, for instance, when people want to like comment multiple lines
of code out, what they've been told in the past is oh just use multiple cursives, and that's not really the
ideal way to do this because most editors give you a way to select multiple lines and comment them out,
so I've been working on a feature that allows you to just do that.
So if you select a few lines of code and hit Ctrl+K, it just comments all of them out and also Ctrl+Shift+K
will uncomment them, but you may notice that the indentations a little bit different now.
I need to work on this a little bit, but I think that this is sort of a Windows Core
features for an editor that's really necessary that just wasn't there before and I think the reason why it
wasn't implemented before is there's little edge cases here and there like detecting whether there are spaces
between the comment character, etc. that maybe it just wasn't seen as worth the effort, but I think it's worth
the effort, so we're going to try to finish that and get it shipped in the next update.
Also, another big problem is if you have a file open in the ISE preview and for whatever reason, the file changes
on the file system outside of the ISE, there's no notification. It doesn't tell you that it's been changed,
so you might start editing your file here again and save it and then overwrite whatever the external changes were.
So now I've tried to get the .NET Framework's file system watcher hooked up to solve this problem, so let's see
if it works and doesn't crash and burn. So actually, I'll just go ahead and open this file in Notepad,
the same file in Notepad, and let's see. So I'm going to go and just make a change here in this file and
you'll, oh, let me just undo whatever I did here. So this file is unsaved at the moment, sorry, it's saved at
the moment, so if I go ahead and just add some text here, save it, then you'll see that it, okay, this time it
didn't work, but it crashed. So this was a good time to tell you that
.NET's file system watcher is a little unreliable and this crash may be my fault.
But the point is that when this first comes out, it's actually probably going to be a little flaky,
so we're going to have to do a little work to see what we can do to make it a little bit more reliable.
So actually, I'll give it one more shot and see if it works, and if it doesn't, we'll just move on.
(Running) It happened again. Well at least you can't edit it after it…
Yeah, yeah. That's true. Actually, maybe I'll just leave it like this.
Yeah, it's a feature, so we'll just
restart the session. It's great. We'll just reload the files, no problem.
That's right. You guys should all be my marketing team. I'll just let you guys explain all the problems
that we have. That's great. Alright, so let me---