So there's only one more thing that I really want to show you and that's authoring a package management provider.
Jennion, who's sitting over here, wrote this example back in November or thereabouts, October.
If you go out to github.com/OneGet, which is also oneget.org, you'll be able to find the MyAlbum-Sample-Provider.
If you take a look at that, what it implements is the ability to copy png files as a package, which is it's cute,
but what it does is it's a very good example of the things that you need to implement in order to implement
your own provider and why should you care.
We talked a lot about giving you control. Let's say you take the PowerShellGet package provider and you want
it to be just a little bit different or you take the NuGet package provider and you want it to be just a
little bit different. You want it to work with your own local repository.
You want it to use credentials that are available on your own local repository and required.
You would make a modification to that base code and update it to fit your needs.
So going back to my other window, the thing
that I'm going to point out here is there's a couple of required things that you have to implement,
and unfortunately, these things don't really do anything. These are the registration elements that are required.
You've got to implement them because otherwise package management doesn't know your package provider is there,
but that's not where you do the work. Okay. What you really need to take a look at in this example is this
set of optional elements that actually do all the work. The Get feature Get-DynamicOptions.
DynamicOptions are the things that are the optional parameters, the things that you can supply.
Everybody who is going to write their own package management provider will take advantage of this.
This is where you would maybe include something like credentials.
Most likely, if you're going to be building something around credentials, it wouldn't be optional, but you can
see where that fits.
The other thing that you're going to want to handle is dealing with a package source, so the add package source
and resolve package source are critically important so that you can know where to go from this package management
provider to get something. So you stand up your own internal repository.
It's a NuGet-based repository. You're storing stuff out there and you're going to require credentials.
You'll set that up in your own version of the NuGet package provider, you'll release it as
MyNugetPackageProvider, you'll resolve the package source to your internal NuGet gallery, and require the credentials, okay.