So take a look at this thing and I'm going to recommend that you go through this code.
It's actually pretty simple, straightforward, and easy to follow.
If I can, you can. Trust me. Okay.
So, last element, how these concepts relate to a CI/CD pipeline. And I've been running through this stuff pretty fast.
This whole week is primarily about how does this fit within DevOps.
Package management is here so that what you can do is you can say I know where to get the things that belong
on my box.
You can set up your internal repository, you can register as long as you understand what the package source
type is and you're not modifying it, you can take the existing package type, and say the source for all packages
of this type are here. Everything that I've validated is here.
All of my servers are only going to go here to fetch something. Then your release pipeline can make sure that
everything gets published there. Your DSC resources when they run will only get things from there.
Alright. So this is all about ensuring that you have the control to drive the system the way that you want to.
So now, what we're really going to do is we're going to dance here.
Raghu and I are going to swap out machines real quick. And I'm going to let Raghu show you how he put it all
together for the internal repository of private PowerShell Gallery repositories.