Good afternoon ladies and gentleman, and welcome to the Package Management in PowerShell discussion,
and we're going to talk about a number of things here today.
First, I'll introduce myself. I'm Keith Bankston. I'm a program manager in the PowerShell team.
My primary focus is on the package management, PowerShell Gallery, PowerShellGet and that area, and if you
to talk about WMI and WinRM, I can talk about that too some other day.
Not now. Also, up here we have Mr. Raghu Shantha. He's a senior developer, senior software engineer,
I beg your pardon, in the same team that I work on and he's going to show you some of the things that he did
a lightening demo on later and we'll do introductions about that.
Quick review of what we're going to cover. For those of you who are familiar with package management and
have an idea of the concept, put your hand up real quick. Wow!
I like that. This is a good audience. Tougher than I thought. So I'm going to run through the overview
material very quickly. It's just give you an outline of what it is and make sure that everybody is up to speed,
but I'm going to run past that very rapidly. If you have questions about that, you can catch me later.
Then we're going to talk about the things you know probably a little better.
PowerShellGet, PowerShell Gallery, and then go a little bit more into the package management improvements,
some of the things that we've done in Windows Server TP5 that's coming out, and some of the other changes
we've made since WMF5 RTM has happened and also an EMWF5 RTM. And then we're going to put it all together
and we're going to leave the majority of the time available for Raghu to talk through setting up a PowerShell
Gallery, a private PowerShell Gallery, and the code that he did the five minute too-brief demo on
yesterday. So what are we talking about when we say package management?
The goal is pretty simple. There is one command that you can use anywhere in Windows that says
install this thing, make it happen. A lot of folks are familiar with apt-get on Linux.
You do apt-get something and especially on something like Ubuntu, where they've done a really good job of
carrying in a list of things that's there, you say app-get foo, and if foo is in the list, you get foo.
Well you have to do sudo apt-get foo. Now because we're Microsoft, we don't do apt-get, we do something like
Install-Package because we think it makes more sense. Same concept, you've got the idea.
We want to make it easier for folks to get stuff of a variety of types of installation mechanisms,
use the same command approach to get it onto your box. Now
in WMF5 and TP5, we've created the ability to abstract a lot of the Windows components and get those onto
your systems and we've also added repository management, and we'll do quick demos of these things along the way.
Package management though is going to become a lot more important when you start talking about Nano Server.
You all have heard Jeffrey Snover's basic vision. Nano Server is this minimal box, and it by minimal I mean
I've got just enough to connect to the box and do Install-Package to get the other stuff I need and control
it that way. That's actually one of the key elements that we're trying to accomplish ultimately is by keeping
Nano Server under your control, the set of things that are going to be installed there.
So package management is central to that vision.
And when we talk about package management, a lot of you guys, in particular, are familiar with this in terms
of dealing with the PowerShell Gallery and we're pretty proud of it.
We've had a few uses since we released that officially back in last June.
But it's also about control and it's about giving you the control over where the packages are coming from
based on the package type and that's one of the elements that we'll talk through.