And yes, I'm running through this kind of quick and my apologies.
Package management improvements. Main things that we've added. Support for containers.
Nano Server optional packages are coming in TP5. Windows Server packages, again, coming in TP5.
The ability to deploy something onto the Nano box when TP5 ships in the next couple of months, you should be
able to try this out. We are very much looking forward to your feedback on how well that works.
Multiple package provider versions side-by-side. This is something that will start to count more as you write
your own package providers. A package provider is I'm going to take a blob of goo that is going to be put
onto my box, unpacked somehow, and run through some process at the end of which it's installed, right.
Blob of goo gets put on my box package, blob of goo. Alright, fine.
I can have multiple versions of a package provider that I use for different things and I do this with my own
PowerShellGet package provider because I have the internal gallery and I have the external gallery and I have
both of them registered and both of them tested locally so that I can work back and forth between them,
between the dev environment and the production environment.
Event Log Support.
Well if you're going to do something on a machine, it would be nice to know that you can
actually see what happened and we've also again we've gotten rid of this nasty -version thing.
We've created the ability to install the NuGet provider locally
and we've added credential support. So let's
here's the set of package providers that I've got on my local box and you can see that I've got MSI, MSU,
NuGet, a bunch of things that are present there and different package sources and this is where you start to
see I've got two package sources, don't write that URL, but the point is,
those package sources are there and this is one of the tools you can take advantage of.
A lot of people are asking when I create my internal gallery, how do I control and make sure that the systems
only use that internal gallery. Well the way that I do that is I register the package source for
PowerShellGet to be the internal repository and I remove the default PowerShellGet registration for PowerShell Gallery.
Now when I use PowerShellGet, all those cmdlets will only go to your internal gallery.
So package source, Set-PackageSource, and Get-PackageSource, this allows you to manage where you're getting things from.
One of the other things that you need to be aware of is we're not the only people who are publishing package management providers.
It turns out that there's a few other people who are putting things on the gallery as well.
You'll notice that the GistProvider is out there, and we've got an example that I'll show you here in just a minute,
that'll walk you through how to create your package management providers.
JQuery is one of the NuGet packages that's available.
The problem with jQuery is that it's available on more than one location.
Okay, so there's something I want to show you here and I'm going to back this up just a little bit.
If I do a Find-Package jQuery, the first thing that happens is I check all of the package locations that are
available that are registered on my box, okay. If I want that to run a little bit faster, I either use
the source or the provider name in order to find the one that I'm after.
Then, I can go ahead and save it, install it, and manipulate it.
So one of the other elements that I can do is I can take advantage of the fact that I can handle all of the
installed versions of a module,
so I installed two versions of Desired State Configuration from the gallery, alright.
I want to be able to say
make sure that I only have the right version of my module present-- Oh that's right, version's gone.
Gee.
We got rid of version.
Alright, you guys are all going to make the same mistake I just did.
You're going to try to use version. The reason we got rid of version is because I've got two versions of X
Desired State Configuration there. Right. I don't want to have version, treat it like minimum version,
and delete everything off my box. Use required version when you want to use that parameter.
Okay.
Now one other thing that people have been asking us for is the ability, can you see that font there or do I
need to zoom it in.
It needs to be a bit bigger.
Okay. Visible?
Yeah.
Alright.
So get the PackageProviders available on this box.
Well it turns out this box isn't connected to the internet.
It's not connected to anything. It' a little VM that's local. One of the things that folks have asked us
for is the ability to say how do I deal with packages and with a NuGet installation.
Every time you use PowerShellGet, the first thing that happens is I get this you need to install NuGet warning.
You guys seen this?
Yes.
Yes, you have. Okay. So
I have a local copy of this thing available right here. As of the latest version of the package management,
I can do Install-PackageProvider and it will go ahead and update it and put it on the local machine.
You'll be able to get rid of those warnings forever. So in your sequences for your installations,
you're going to be able to get the NuGet provider that you want, put it on a local share, treat that as a local
source, install it, you get rid of that nasty message so that now
I have 1, no more funny warning messages such as you saw before, right, all those funny warning messages are gone,
and 2, I have the package, the NuGet package available.
Okay.