Package management architecture. This is stuff that you all should be fairly familiar with.
There's a set of cmdlets. You can always use the install or the basic package management cmdlets to do this stuff,
you just have to supply more parameters. So you
can do the same thing that you can do in PowerShellGet, as long as you know all the stuff that we're feeding
into the parameter set or you can use PowerShellGet and say and go find DSC resource and not have to do the
filtering, but package management Install-Package will still accomplish the job for you.
The basic core. We do the discovery, go find stuff based on the sources that are registered on your local
box, then install or save it locally,
and allow you to do some kind of inventory so that when you say what are all the things that I've installed
from that type of installer, we can get a list of it for you. We have a set of package management providers already.
Windows Server apps, that's kind of like an appx package type, alright, kind of.
It's something that we need some differences from that in order to support Windows Server components,
PowerShellGet, Windows containers, NuGet, there's a bunch of them that are actually available for you.
And the package sources. Every one of those package types can support more than one package source and I'll
show you that in a minute. So
PowerShellGet. Is there anyone in here who has not used PowerShellGet?
Okay. We have developed the PowerShell Gallery in order to support people sharing stable code.
That's the goal behind it. It's not stuff where you put test stuff out there.
When you've got something that you're actually willing to share with the community, it's relatively stable,
we want it out in the gallery, but you don't actually download something directly from the gallery.
You use the gallery to go find things, to find out who did it, to find out information about the stuff that's there.
You use PowerShellGet and the cmdlets that are part of PowerShellGet to acquire that thing, you can also do
find, and we'll show you that in just a second, but you're going to acquire the package, you're going to put
it on your local box, save, take a quick look at it, always do a save first, investigate, in God we trust,
nobody else, then when you are comfortable that this is something that you want on your box, then you do an install module.
When you do an install module, we'll keep a list of the things that you've installed and we'll get rid of it for you.
This is all the PowerShellGet specific versions of
package management, and as a part of delivering this in Windows WMF5 and these previews, we made sure that we
supported side-by-side module versioning and dependencies, and those two go hand in hand.
Part of that is when I write a module and put it out on the PowerShell Gallery, and this gentleman here takes
a dependency on my module, he can build that into his module and say I want to be able to know that I can get
that version of that module to go with my code. And anybody see the article about MPM about two weeks ago?
When you put something out on the PowerShell Gallery, we don't let you delete it today and if you want to have
access to the article about MPM broke the internet, you can look that up.
People ask us about this. The point being, I can take a dependency and he can take a dependency on a specific
version of a module. But then what happens if I want the latest version of the module.
Well I have to be able to install the latest version side by side.
It's why we have support for both elements.
We've added script support, we've added support for internal galleries, which is what Raghu is going to show
you the ability to say I want to get all of this stuff from something I've tested and we've also made some other changes.
There was this comment out in the group that when you used PowerShellGet, we had a -version alias.
-Version works fine for install-package. Install-Package -version gets you at least the version
you specified it mapped to minimum version. The problem was that when you did the uninstall version,
it mapped to that as the minimum version, so it would also get rid of everything newer than that.
So we've made some changes, we've gotten rid of that alias, and now you get to specify minimum version,
maximum version, required version again. You guys told us this thing's evil, we fixed it.
We've added credential support, we've improved proxy support. People got to us, told us these things aren't
working, so we've make some changes in the system. Commands that are available in PowerShellGet,
well mostly it's about how you manipulate modules, how you manipulate repositories, and then also how you manipulate scripts.
There's a lot of concern about well we're going to open this door and everybody is going to put scripts out
there instead of modules. We're being very explicit, folks. We want you to put modules out there.
Why? Because modules include documentation, they include tests, they include examples, these are the best
practices for things that you need to put out into the PowerShell Gallery.
There is a place for putting scripts out there, we have support for it, but we prefer that you use modules.
Alright. So---