Little bit of commentary on how we've been doing with PowerShell Gallery, I said you all have been working
with it and adopting it fairly well. As of, I guess it was Mid-February, we passed 1 million downloads.
We're at 1.4 million now.
It's growing rapidly. The statistics page shows this hockey stick of growth and if you are familiar with it,
that actually says we're very stable. So as of about Mid-February, we realized we are stable enough plus we
had implemented the support for antivirus scanning and also we've built in script analyzer scanning to make
sure that the code that's coming into the gallery meets a basic bar, so people can trust it.
A lot of what we focus on is ensuring that the features that we're adding are about trust.
The people who publish, we have about 700 people who've registered to publish, okay?
We have about 700,000 people who are downloading. You guys can do the math.
We will focus our energies on ensuring that the people who are requiring content that experience is optimized
and so there will be times occasionally when you're going to come in say well that seems like you're putting
a little extra burden on the publisher that's because we want the things that are out on the gallery to be
something that somebody can look at and make a trust decision. Yes, I trust it, no, I don't.
Some of the lightening demos that you saw yesterday including the viewing scripts, including some of the
other things that we show here, those are being put into place so that people know I can trust this content.
We're also adding in integration with Azure automation and some improved filtering and I'll show you that UI
in just a little bit.
So real quick, let's do some demo because otherwise you guys will kill me.