Hi. So I'm going to talk about a couple of things about how do you set up your own private gallery in your enterprise,
for example, and how do you populate your gallery with the things you need, and I know how we can make sure
all the machines in your enterprise can point to this gallery and get all the work done.
So this will be mostly a technical deep dive of the configuration and the DSC resources and all the things
which make up the system.
So if people start want to I mean look at the code that's on PowerShell GitHub page, so if you go to
PSPrivateGallery, you can take a look at the modules of the configuration.
So there are a couple of high-level configurations, which are self-customer facing.
One is the ability to deploy our own private gallery, which is this configuration.
So essentially, what it's doing is it's setting up your front-end, which is IS, in this case, it's setting up
the database and it sets up all the Entity Framework later aspects.
So you could take a NuGet gallery code base and plug it in here under and it should setup a NuGet-based repository.
So it's got four high-level steps. So what I'm going to do is kick this off first, and then explain as to the
different components of the configuration itself. So let's go ahead and run this on the machine.
So if I look at my IS, I don't have any websites set up. And I'm going to run this configuration to set up
my gallery infrastructure.
Does ISE need to be installed first?
This does all that, so you can take a brand new VM auto machine and just run this configuration.
It's going to install all the dependencies, it's going to add on the Windows features, it's going to do
everything for you.
(Audience Comment)
Yes. So wherever you got IS, a set of magic cmdlets, and DSC configuration.
Then our composite resources some are class-based resources, so I'm going to go through the code.
So I just wanted to show you how quick and easy it is to deploy your own private gallery.
This is a just a deployment phase. We haven't gotten into the populating phase yet.
So let me go back, yeah, so in about 60 seconds, which is about a minute, I was able to deploy a private gallery.
So let me go back and refresh and yeah, it's set up your own private gallery and it's running under a user,
which is low privileged, in this case, it's a non-admin user called GalleryAdmin.
That's app that running on there, so let me go back to my browser and try to browse this gallery.
I set it up on Port 8080. So the first time it has to start all the IS servers and it takes a couple of seconds.
Yeah, so there it is. So I just changed the branding information to be more generic.
You could put your own branding.
Can we add certain communication to this?
Yeah, we can do that. It probably needs a couple of other steps in the configuration, but I think as we
evolve the project on the GitHub page, we will add all that capability.
So yeah, this was just a proof of concept to show you that you could set up a private gallery.
The only things I have enabled on this page is the ability to discover modules and publish modules and that
changed the branding information and the ability to set up local users, so this is the deployment phase.
I was able to set up a big blown gallery in about a minute and you should be able to use package management cmdlets,
the PowerShellGet cmdlets to actually interact with this gallery.
So let me go ahead and do that. So let's do all the part one first where I talk about how the gallery is actually deployed.
So this configuration is controlled by this configuration data and all we are doing here is we are consuming
a couple of credential files to set up the gallery itself for the app pool and you can also control the name
of the website and where you want to deploy it and where to pick up the branding from, and also the database itself.
In this case, it's a one box scenario. I'm installing SQLExpress on the same box, but you could change this
to use full SQL on a different machine and you can use a connection string to point to the box.
So part one is setting up of the web server itself and that involves a couple of things.
One is installing all the dependencies and installing the website itself and this is actually a composite configuration.
(Typing) And all of them are shipped in the PSGallery module and we make this available on the gallery soon.
And the configuration I want to show is the configuration to set up the WebServer, which is this.
And let's actually go and open that. So this is a composite configuration that sets up the front-end,
and as you can see, it actually does a bunch of things under the hood, things like installing all the dependencies,
setting up the users, and setting up the app pool, doing all your final copies for the branding and the
gallery content itself, setting up the website and all that. So all the complexity is collapsed into this
composite configuration and what you see on the front is just one single configuration to just do the WebServers.
It's similar for database. So I'll quickly go over the database resource, which is this.
So this is actually installing your SQLExpress package itself. So we can take an empty VM and kick this off
and it's going to do everything for you. It's going to set up your instance, it's going to set up your database,
and it's going to use the credentials you supplied in the manifest of the configuration data.
So these are the primary couple of resources to set up the front-end and the database.
There's also the migration part. It's called migration because the NuGet uses Entity Framework and we are
actually creating this key-minded database. We are populating with empty tables and all of that there.
And some of this is specific to SQLExpress and you could plug in your own migration logic if you want to deploy
a different kind of repository and those pieces are separated out.
Are we going to be able to figure out how to do that credential piece?
The credential in the database?
Yeah. Is there a way that you can do that, Clixml and that stuff?
I just use a credential object and that's where the Clixml…
Exactly, so before you kick this off, you can take a credential object, something like this, we can say
$cred =, so $cred will have your credentials and you can actually export this into a file basically serializing
it to a file. So the password is a secure string, and the username will be recorded as this.
And actually, in the configuration, we actually leave that file here.
We actually import it and then use it. This is one we are supplying configuration if you wanted to make it
more secure, you can avoid using the, you can use actually source.
Yeah, so let's go ahead with the rest of the things. So that's our database resource and not the migration part.
Let me quickly go over the migration part where we actually populate it with the schema.
And it uses actual connection string to the database. This is actually a MOF-based resource.
So this is part one where we bring up an empty instance of the gallery, which is this.
So now we'll kick off part two, which is populating the gallery with certain modules and then we'll talk
about what that's made up of. So in part two, what you're actually doing is you're populating your local instance
or your private instance. Okay, I don't have internet, that's why it's failing.
You're populating your private instance with the modules from the source gallery.
In this case, I'm actually seeing that my source gallery is the public gallery and my destination gallery is
one I created privately, and I also need to know what modules I want to put in the local instance.
So let's say you need in an enterprise you have dependencies on certain modules and certain _____.
You can call up all that here. Just an example.
And this publishing configuration is actually very interesting. It does a bunch of things.
It actually just starts your source and private galleries first so that it knows where to pick up things from
and where to put it to, and it sets up a user for your gallery, so you can do all your user management using
a DSC configuration. The user means this user here. So you can manage local users, so we will add that
domain resource later. And the last part is the publishing pieces where the configuration actually takes the
specified modules from the source and publishes it to the destination.
And we're actually using the latest and greatest features from WMF5 and Windows 10 to do this, so things like RunAsCredential.
So all this is running out of the context stuff, the app pool user, which is low-privileged user.
So none of these run as high-privileged or a system context. So we are very careful as to run it under.
And let's quickly go over the code for the publishing pieces. So for this, it's actually a class-based resource
and there are two resources. One is the gallery module, which does the publishing and one is the user
management resource, which is right here. So you can create a local user and you can manage it.
And for the publishing piece, we are actually using the public interfaces of the private gallery we just set
up, so they're actually using the package management cmdlets and PowerShellGet's cmdlets to accomplish that.
So we are using things like Find-Module to discover what you needed from the public gallery and actually
Save-Module to actually take the module and put it on the local machine.
We don't install anything on this machine. We save it in a temporary location and then we publish it using
the public interfaces of the private gallery, so we go to the publish interfaces.
Yeah, if I had internet connection, I would have showed you when you populate that, you can actually see these
counters going up, but I don't know if you have time for that.
(Audience comment)
Yeah, so
all of this is DSC-based, check it out. The whole code is on GitHub on PSPrivateGallery.
I already see a few issues being opened for requests, so we will take a look at them.
And this is actually a community-driven project, so if you guys have ideas, if you want to contribute, please do so.
We're taking full requests then. Thank you all very much.