So basic PowerShellGet functions, and boy that's just in a bad spot.
Sorry, folks, I've got to figure out how to use the mouse with this thing sitting here.
So Get-Command, this is all the stuff that's available in PowerShellGet and I've already done this.
Now one of the things that you will see here is you can do some filtering in PowerShellGet in order to find
the things that you're looking for and a lot of people don't know how to go about this, so
I thought I would spend just a minute and show you how to do that.
Right now, we have a number of things that are out in the gallery that talk about the ISE, right.
So which one is actually the one that came from Microsoft? Well, looks like that one is, PowerShell ISE preview.
So if you go ahead and you have to do the filtering the way that you guys are familiar with, it's Where-Object
and author, and I'll publish all this stuff. You're going to see a lot more of our documentation increasing
here, but this is one of the most commonly asked questions, how do I find things in the gallery based on the author?
Okay. How do I find something in the gallery where the author is Amazon?
So the point being trust, you can go ahead and you can locate the things that you care about in the gallery
based on who it is and whether or not you can trust them.
One of the other elements of trust is, okay, what are the things that this depends on?
I already told you that I can take a dependency on your module. Well one of the things that this HistoryPX
module, which by the way, seems like a pretty good module. I skimmed through the code the other day.
Did anybody in here write that?
It's Kirk right?
It's Kirk's.
I didn't see Kirk so alright. So he's got a set of dependencies that are available on that module, right,
and what we talk about is you need to know what it is that you are installing on your system.
I can do a save module and all of those dependencies will get installed onto my box and you can read through
that here as the verbose commands go by, you see SnippetPX right there is one of the elements that was a
dependency, and we will install those dependencies, just like I said I can take a definite dependency on
something somebody else wrote and it'll get installed using PowerShellGet.
So again, these are all about what can I trust and that's the main focus that we have for the gallery, alright.
So now let's take a look at what's actually in the gallery.
One of the things that you saw a little bit of UI about is we've had a number of questions in the last little
bit about where, how do I find all of the modules that don't have DSC in them.
Did you all see the lightening demos yesterday?
(Audience comment)
Okay, well this is one of my favorite pieces of UI because it responds to, I've got 181 items in this test
gallery, and know I'm going to try hard not to show you that URL because that's our test gallery.
Yes, it's live. Don't use it if you discover it. It's there and we will blow up your stuff if you put it there.
But if I want to see just the cmdlets and just the functions, the things that contain just the cmdlets and
functions, this new filtering UI, which will be out in the next few weeks is something that you can go ahead
and take advantage of. And again, it's trying to make sure that you can find what you're after, alright.
The only piece of searching that you can do, or the only way you can do searching for owner, and owner is the
actual person who published a package, is by using this UI today, okay.
you can't find it in the search functions in and you'll find module or find DSC resource, so this is a quick tip.
It's the only one of the demos that I'm going to show here now in the interest of time.
But if you want to find out everything from PowerShell team, or from Kirk, or from anybody else, the best way
to do that is in the gallery, you search for owner and then the owner name, alright.