I'm really excited to get that out and not have to think about it anymore.
I'll leave that up if anybody else wants pictures, but it's just aka.ms/thereleasepipelinemodel.
So this slide, I really put in for future presentations. We actually are going to make these slides public
and then continue iterating on them so that anyone from any organization can use them because I feel like I
need to weaponize everybody here to go back to your organization and be able to have this conversation.
So I want to make sure that this slide contains the information to do that.
So you probably are all familiar with configuration as code when I say that I'm talking about things like DSC.
The way that I talk about that with people who are new to the idea is that if you've been managing Windows Servers
or anything in IT, there's lots and lots and lots of APIs. So the way that you work with Active Directory is
different than the way that you work with WMI and the registry and the file system and DNS and then you've
got third-party software, you've got hardware devices and they're all different.
So the idea of configuration as code in the most simple concept is that I'm going to bring everything back to
just property value. And what's happening under the hood is all being performed by scripts written by people
with subject matter expertise. They are trusted and have given me good tools.
But at the end of the day, that file becomes my living documentation of how stuff is built.
So we all hate documentation, but whenever your documentation is functional, then it takes on a very different role.
It's something that I had to create in order to get things where I wanted them
and now I don't have to go write the paper with the tables that explains how the server was built.
So you're all familiar with DSC. I will mention that if you didn't go to other sessions that relate to this
Azure Resource Manager, I also look at that as configuration as code.
In fact, most of the examples I'm going to go through today are Azure Resource Manager deployment templates,
but this same model, and we'll discuss this more at the end, can apply to lots and lots of things.
So any time that you see an opportunity to configure something as code and put it through a release pipeline,
look at that as an opportunity, do an investigation, is this a way that I can make this work better.
And the very last bullet, I'll just let you take ownership of the last bullet.
Yeah, so there's a lot of great tooling that's being implemented in the DSC space and the ARM space, but at the
end of the day, none of that makes you a subject matter expert in the things that you have to operate, so
I can learn Chef, I can learn DSC, I can learn ARM, that lets me spin up a whole lot of things, but I still
need to know how to operate them, I still need to know what the settings mean, what the things are.
So nothing in this is going to replace knowledge about how these systems work.
If you have in-depth Active Directory experience and knowledge, that is a major plus moving into these things.
Even though we might not be clicking around in some of the familiar UIs, being able to deploy a resilient
Active Directory infrastructure as configuration as code is going to lean heavily on your experience.
Being able to understand how Windows services behave, especially in like Cross-platform environments.
You've got Linux guys come over and say hey I want to run this thing as a service.
No you don't. That might be what you wanted to do on Linux, but really you want to get this thing in Task
Scheduler or you need to create a new service that knows how to register itself and do some things.
You still need to have that platform knowledge, so none is that is being obviated by the configuration as
code space, though it may seem like it because it's kind of a simplified interface.
It's key value and whether it's ARM, whether it's DSC, whether it's Chef, it's oh I declare a resource and
then give it some properties.
But yeah nothing will really kind of step---