So we've been working on this since about December.
Yeah.
We were talking on the phone and said here's all the---we like to just chat about these are the things we're
seeing going on with all the different customers we visit and some patterns that are working and patterns
that are not working and I'm going to cover this a little bit, but
we really kind of decided we should write a paper that explains all of this in terms that IT pros will
understand because there's all this chatter about DevOps and the amount of into is just flowing so quickly
now that no one has taken pause to actually reflect on if you're coming from a background that's Microsoft
Core infrastructure, what does all this mean to you and lay it out in a language that makes sense and that's
comprehensive as to why it should matter to your organization, so that's what we decided to tackle.
So this is a presentation, but we're releasing a whitepaper today, which I'll show you, I'll give a link to you,
that's about 50 pages long. So
for 20 minutes now, you guys just go ahead and read that and then we'll listen to your comments, no.
But no, hopefully, it's valuable to you. I suspect that this will end up being the first edition and that
we'll come back and make changes and I'll put up my information in front here.
So before you get too far, who the heck are you?
Well let me pull up the next slide with a picture of my jeep. So I'm Michael Greene.
I'm a principal program manager here in Enterprise Cloud Group. I'm actually in the CAT team and I'm the CAT
PM for PowerShell and DevOps. CAT is Customer Architectures and Technologies.
It has historically been our job to drive customer feedback. So we run the TAP program, that kind of stuff,
go out and meet with customers. I'm kind of the hunter in many ways now, so if you think about as Microsoft
has become very customer focused,
the CAT team ends up, previously we were driving customer feedback, well now it's like an even more aggressive role.
It's go meet with as many people as you can and every time you find something interesting that we need to
know about, make sure that you're just funneling all of that back to the PM team and we're continuing to evolve,
so we did an Azure CAT team and an Office CAT team and more and more you see CAT team sort of working on the
very latest cutting edge of what has come out and going to customers who are doing it first and being that
on-site, I'm here from engineering so that when you run into things that we didn't expect, there's a direct
conduit for those first couple of deployments to help make adoption easier.
So it's like I'm from Microsoft and I'm here to help.
Yeah. I should get a van with a logo on the side.
I just wanted to put up, oh so I've been with Microsoft for 12 years, out of that, I spent from 2010 to late
in 2012 in operations in what was called BPOS, now called Office 365. So
Don Jones taught me PowerShell in version 1 and in 2010, I spent 3 years in operations PowerShelling everything,
so I've lived a lot of the experiences that have resulted in things like what we're talking about today,
so I've got a lot of hands-on experience of PowerShell.
If you want to contact me, you're better off sending me a letter than sending me an email this week,
so if you want a response, but you can hit me up on Twitter. I don't mind doing a little dance where you
have to follow each other back and forth before we can DM each other or you're welcome to just tweet at me
and we'll get in touch with each other. And my GitHub repo is Mgreenegit and we'll be referencing probably
some stuff there. But Twitter is a good way to get a hold of me.
When I come to this event and I walk around, for me, it's like walking amongst celebrities because I'm not
really like into Hollywood celebrities, but when I look at Twitter and Slack channels and blogs and stuff
like that, it's all of you guys that I'm reading every day, so coming here and looking around at all the
badges and seeing those names, it's like whoa, that was that guy that I see every day and I've talked to him
every week for the past 20, but I've never met him in person, so it's really my pleasure to be here.
Great, and I'm Steve Morawski. I'm a principle engineer at Chef on the community engineering team.
I do a bit of DSC in PowerShell and stuff for a few years and Michael and I just kept bumping into each other
a lot at community events and at customers and talking about these same challenges, and so he's like hey
here's eight pages I just kind of scrawled out on my thoughts on this topic and let's go and do stuff, and so we
started collaborating back and forth and I just kind of rode along on his coat tails to help get some
feedback into the paper and all. And for me, this concept is one of the most critical things as you start to
move towards more DevOps environment and workflow. If you do not seriously look at addressing some of the
concerns that we're going to walk through here, you will not realize all of the benefits from working with
things like Desired State Configuration or Chef, being able to, you will not approach some of the big wins
that you see in reports like the state of DevOps and things like that where you see these faster times to
recovery and reduced failure rates and things like that. And so, for me, this is a---