But,  there is actually, there is good statistical information that shows that peer review
of changes in source control is way more effective than any change control board that's out there.
So I'm going to demo this first with screen shots and then I'll walk you through it, but when you go to repeat
this presentation, and I hope you do, I can share with you how to recreate the environment, but in case you
don't have time, I want to make sure that you're armed with showing people what's it look like to manage
change if you're using source control. So
this is using TFS, this is TFS Express, so you can go to microsoft.com, look for Visual Studio under the
bottom of it, I think you can go to visualstudio.com, just go to the bottom, and there's a link for TFS Express,
which for five users or less is free. So the environment that I'm connecting to is this environment and it's
just a TFS Express instance running in a VM on Azure. Like you said, GitHub is a perfectly great place to do
this kind of thing or if it's personal information or private information for your organization, you could use
a private repo there, you could use GitLab, GitHub Enterprise, there's just a variety of different source
control platforms out there. TFS is nice because for everything we're going to cover today, it offers it all,
so it's a one-stop shop. So this is just what it looks like. That's a project that's checked in.
You can see the files, you can see when the last change occurred, you can see the comments on what changed.
If I go look at this in Visual Studio code, so this again is free download.
You probably used it for things like DSC and JSON and other projects, but you can see I'm looking at making a
commit, so I'm saying I'm going to retire 2008-R2 because I'm only going to support 2012 and 2012-R2 now,
so I'm just removing that from my allowed values for the incoming parameters and I'm going to check in that change.
So you can see it's showing me exactly what changed. Now that's kind of an easy one because it's just
changing parameter values. It could be adding a network adapter.
It could be changing the way that the network is configured. It could be adding a new virtual network.
The point is that you can go see this is what I had, but I removed the line and this is what I have now and
you can do that commit. You can actually also do your push from within Visual Studio code and a variety of different editors.
You can also go out to the command-line.
So in this case, I made my change, but before I submit it, I'm going to run tests on my workstation because
I don't want to embarrass myself by checking in a change that I know is going to fail.
So I just invoke Pester.
This is the weakest set of test scripts ever, but it's just a basic deserialize the JSON, make sure that
everything I expected is there. So I'm just going to run Pester and it's going to make sure that what I'm
checking in is not junk, right, that I didn't make a silly mistake along the way.
And then I do a git push, in this case, it just says, yep, you modified some files, great.
You own the repos, so no problem push them back up there.
At that point, I can go look at my source history. In the browser, I can see yep, I retired 2008-R2,
and so if anybody ever wants to find that, it's easy to search for and if I drill into that commit, I can see
once again in the browser that yep this is now stored forever. I can always go back and see exactly what changed when.
I was logged in as TFS1, so that's who, it was Tuesday, April 5 at 5:54 PM, so I can see when, and I can see
any comments I wanted to add. The next
thing happens is build.
So what did we do before?
We waited. After that change control meeting, right, and we came in on Saturday because we hate our personal lives.
We made sure that all of the servers that we were going to work with are docked in RDCMan
so that we can remote desktop into every machine where we're going to manually make change.
That was always my prep for going into the change windows. Do I have my RDCMan file all set up with the
password stored and stuff like that.
So I connect to all the servers, I make changes, and then I have to do a reboot, which is where I sweat it
out for 30 seconds or so or 4 minutes if I'm waiting for BIOS to go through all the checks.
Hopefully I get everything in order, and then after I do a little dance for good luck, then I go through and
manually make sure that everything still works the way that I think it should.
Can you show us that dance?
What's that?
Maybe at the pub crawl tonight.
Okay.
I'll break out the change window tribal dance. So that last one is the scariest part, right, validating that we
didn't break something.
And then if you did, that's probably a six hour or an eight-hour change window, so now the clock is running
and I've got to get it fixed, but if I don't know, maybe I'm not the expert on this, I was just told that
there's a 0 day, so I've got to make the change. At that point, now the clock is ticking until Monday morning
and users are going to come in and it's going to work or it's not going to work and that's how it goes.
Alright, that's the life that we put ourselves into week after week or month after month, so that's what we've
always been doing.
What do we do now? As we check in that change, there's a variety of ways that this can happen, but it's going
to run the scripts, the supporting scripts that we put in there. So it's going to start by just evaluating
quality using the tests that we wrote and checked in with that configuration as code.
That can happen as a web hook. If it's TFS, it's all one box, so it's all part of the same system, and I'll show
what that looked like to turn it on. Other platforms have agents that monitor a source control and look for changes,
you can also schedule it to happen, you can manually key you a new build, but when it says build, I mean especially
like if you took Computer Science courses in college, you think of build as I'm taking my source and creating
an executable, like that kind of a build. Yes, that's true, but in this case, the build service is just
running a PowerShell script to do these things. So build really just refers to there's a server somewhere
that's going to take care of running these supporting scripts to make things happen for me.
So all that gets stored in source and we're going to, go ahead.
And the reason it's called a build is at the end of that process, we're going to have some artifact.
It may still just be a PowerShell script, it may be a module, it may be MOF files, but at the end of the day,
there's going to be a result of that build process that we're going to move along to do some enhance testing
on or just to move into deploying in the environment. So it does map really well to the concept of build because
there will be some output or some result of that process.
Yeah. An interesting thing that I have learned from customers is that
yes, you could go create your build server and that's the central build server for all your things, but a lot
of people when a team creates a new project, they have their own build server and all these teams have their
own build servers. They actually have configuration as code to go build a build server and the reason for
that is once everybody's doing this, why have down time and releasing change just because somebody else's
machine is down and that kind of stuff, right. It's just performing a function.
You can all have one place that you go look for source. You actually want to get to the point, and we'll talk
about this in test, where that build server is doing stuff almost all the time and we'll talk about that more
in test, but think about that as you can really design this for yourself, which means you don't have to change
the whole world to make this work, right. You could have this as an instance that handles just one project
that you're working on. This is also a really good opportunity to look at JEA because now you're performing
everything automated, so why not have a JEA. If, number one, you're building a machine using configuration as
code, well that's how you put a JEA endpoint on something. And number two, why give that machine total access?
Why not have a set of commands or a constrained endpoint that only allows build to do what it needs to do and use that.
And at that point, you're delivering change using build, you could have constrained endpoints for doing
maintenance activities, so it's not to say, I don't want to confuse this with I'm only going to do this and
now if there's an emergency, I'm out of luck, right, so you do want to get to the point where you're not making
random changes because then it didn't have an opportunity to go through test, but there's still going to be maintenance activities.
There's going to be weird things that come up. You might have to go get information from boxes or go check
the state of things, so that's an opportunity to use things like Azure automation, use JEA on the machine and
build out this platform. And since I don't mention it later and I don't think Joe mentioned earlier in the week,
Azure automation can be managed using ARM. So you could actually check into source an ARM template that
includes a script that should run and when it should run using hybrid runbook worker in your environment.
So you can coordinate all of these things together.
We have a question.
Oh, sorry.
I was just going to say what you described it kind of fits in well with my experience in that this is the model
of what it looks like at the endpoint, right, where probably somewhere on the continuum or maybe at the very
beginning of this, so we're not going to have all these pieces. So as we start to implement one thing, right,
and then we get that working right and then we get, oh why don't we add Pester or why don't we add JEA,
and so over time you're evolving towards that this end goal.
That is exactly it and you start with these things pretty much in the order in which Michael is describing them.
You start with source control---