I can see the results of any one test and then I can create bugs.
So I can say, Steve you checked in junk, here's a bug back to you that this doesn't work right.
That never happens.
So I'm skimming fast.
Release is interesting because it's the most exciting thing to me, but it's the least interesting part of the
demo, so it's where I've been putting all of my thoughts lately, but as far as demo is concerned, if you're running
this, something got released, so it's not that exciting. But basically, something is going to go create the
environment if needed. If it doesn't already exist, it's going to manage any changes.
So as part of build, you might have in that script, go out and configure a load balancer or go create a new
volume on the SAN, something like that, right, so any environmental changes happen there.
What we did before obviously was go dig through all these things manually and that would include now that
I've built this machine, I'm going to go to Windows update and get it fully patched.
I'm going to make sure that antimalware is there. I'm going to onboard into our backup and monitoring services,
all of those things. It's why it took us three weeks instead of three minutes because we did all of those manually.
And then we announce a Go Live, right, which is
again where we get gray hair. So what do we do now? Build again.
Just that's another thing that it takes care of. So everything that we need to do to make that release
happen is stored in our deployment script in that source control and it's tested using Pester, we've tested it
locally from our workstation. As part of the build server doing things, you might have multiple environments,
so you might actually do a release to a quality assurance environment and then that's it for the automated
build and then you go back and trigger something else that goes into production.
I've seen a variety of things go through this and that's what we talked about promoting through stages.
You might have cut over scenario where you have a green/blue and you use a load balancer, so we're going to
deploy to green and then flip from blue to green, things like that.
Just to do a quick demo since
we're now out of time.
I'm huge fan of PSDeploy. So Warren is here. I think this project is absolutely awesome, and so we've been
working together on, he's just a champion with PowerShell and has been making some interesting changes to make
it work like Pester and PSake so that all of this is just one cohesive story, but I contributed an ARM plugin
so that it could work with this, which I think I broke last night, so my demo fails at this step,
but you can see it's the same concept, right, Deploy using ARM from that template to that resource group.
You can do tagging, so your tag might be production versus QA, which means it would just be a variable that
you could use from your deploy to say I'm going just set this for QA and then tell PSDeploy go run all the
deployments that are tagged for QA or that are tagged for dev or they're tagged for project name or whatever.
One of the things I can't wait to try is
use this because you can have these things depend on each other and have Azure and Azure Stack deployments
tied together, so I'm going to release a service onto Azure Stack, but I'm also going to have it go create an
Azure automation account, put my modules and configurations there, and then Bootstrap those machines to Azure,
and do a one-stop hybrid deployment. I can't wait to prototype that.
All of these tools make those really complex, mindboggling, new things very easy.
And I can now take the lessons I've learned in the past and bring them forward.