This is a super personal topic because this is what's going to help make your lives better.
There's a lot of learning to kind of get our heads around,
a lot of different terminology, so I'm going to get out of the way and let's dive in because we've got lots to cover.
Yeah.
So I'm going to start with this slide because this is how big of a mind-boggling change this is.
So I was talking about this subject with a friend and he reached up on his shelf and handed me a book.
I believe it's the Theory of Scientific Revolution. It's by Thomas Kuhn.
But then he spoiled it for me and he told me when you read this, all you need to get out of it is the following.
And so, I searched for that and read that page and I didn't read the rest of the book, but I'm sure it's good.
The point is in order for a scientific revolution to be an actual revolution, to have a paradigm shift,
you have to satisfy two things. There's a new set of problems. So you're thing came out and it solved those problems.
Great. You also have to solve all the existing problems.
So when a new thing comes out in the industry and we're looking at it and saying is this something that's
going to be huge impact, it's great, yep, all these new cloud adoption and deployment type stuff,
it really helps out with that, but if it doesn't help solve that, by the way, I'm going to have servers that
are not real, I've been supporting these things or that model for 10 years and I can't just do continuous
deployments and knock these things over once a day. I'm going to support them like pets even though we want
to support everything like cattle and that's going to happen for a while, it has to support both, right.
The paradigm shift has to make your life better for all of the scenarios in order for it to actually be a
revolution, otherwise, it's just more tools, right. So
when I go out and the only like universal truth I've learned in my life to this point is that there's usually
not an extreme, right. Usually, things sort of land somewhere more at a moderate place.
So everything starts looking like a spectrum. If I go meet with 10 customers, I'm going to find some that
are really on the cutting edge. I'm like oh the whole world must be doing this and then I'll go to the next
customer, it's like oh, no they haven't changed at all. So as we met with people, I really found two voices.
The first was, yeah, yeah, we've been doing DevOps, so thanks for showing up and having an interest in what
we're doing because that's neat.
What we've been trying to figure out is how do we bring Windows Server into what we're doing, so when we go
meet with those customers and help figure out what their model looks like and how Windows Server can be part of
that, and obviously, PowerShell takes a huge role for something like that.
On the other side of the spectrum, you meet with customers and you explain what you just learned from the
first customer, I don't know what just happened, there we go, and they say yeah, yeah, that sounds like
you're speaking a developer language and that's not really an IT pro thing.
So 80 or 90% of the people are in the middle and they're just trying to keep things from falling over, right.
So you can walk up and talk about hey there's this other way people are doing things now and it's really
interesting and I think it's better and they're like look, I will look at making my life better after I'm
done with all these things that make my life hard. So I love that animation.
There's like three or four different versions of it. So we wrote this paper and it occurred to me just a
second ago that I should prescribe a hashtag. If anybody wants to tweet about it, you're more than welcome to.
It's live as of this morning. That short code should work. It goes directly to the pdf,
and if you use that hashtag on Twitter, then I can search for it and I can tell my boss that lots of people were interested.