I was going to say I think I got a screenshot of that, yep, so if I go look at there's the history of my builds
and then we get the test, so everything that has happened in this environment, you can go back and see what it was.
So testing,
what do we do before? Create our VM, install the OS, probably installed an app or built a service of some kind,
we tried the change, it could be manually, it could be, yep sure.
Sorry, I've got a question on that last part. I kind of use AppVeyor a lot for my CI and one of my biggest issues
is trying to get AppVeyor to work, so I don't do any 48 builds just trying to get the AppVeyor configuration to work.
Yes.
Is there a way to in this product, I guess I want this product to just delete that build and be able to keep
rebuilding because I'm not really incrementing my code, I'm incrementing my test code just to get it to,
you know what I mean, there's really the environment building, you know what I mean all of a sudden like I
can't get modules to install from the gallery because they're NuGet versions and not up-to-date,
something like that, can I delete a build and just re-run the same version in this?
Most source control or most build-type environments have a way to expire out history because it's a database
somewhere and you may not care about it forever, in this case, I think I've got it set to like 10 days or
something because I noticed when I logged in last night that these builds from last week when I was playing
around, which I had like an embarrassing number of failed builds because I was just banging on it and banging
on it, but it does, you can do that or you can keep them forever.
It's configurable. But I do exactly what you just described, which is I think I got everything right and
then I have to figure out how to make everything work in this other environment that is generic.
But it actually leads to me having better quality in the end and solving more interesting problems,
but there's a lot of lessons learned as you go there.
Like with AppVeyor, like I don't have a way to get my hands into like their, you know what I mean,
their apps are spinning up, so I mean my last recent one was all of a sudden, yeah, I just couldn't install
modules from the gallery, so I was like yeah their NuGet whatever wasn't up-to-date and even though I spent
that much time trying to troubleshoot that, the only way to test that is to build.
There is a way, by the way, for AppVeyor that you can inject a stop and then remote desktop into their, yeah,
but we can talk about that.
We had another question coming up over here too.
So as part of build paths, one of the steps that we do before we do any deployments is to separate the artifact,
scan with a colon if you see any part where the applications that are open that are _____.
So we use some conference part, I would like to get some feedback on you guys any do this before any specific
tool feasible as part of the objective's plugin and would you do a ---validation?
So yeah, you can definitely inject all sorts of security testing into this pipeline.
This is just giving you different points as which you can inject various test phases, right.
So one of the things is with build we end up with an artifact and build is usually on like a per project basis,
so it might be how I manage my AB servers, it might a particular application, but at some point,
these things come together in like a test environment to where we can prove these things out and that's where
our configuration management in our applications kind of all land together and that's the environment that we
want to do a lot of that security testing in things. In the Chef ecosystem, we actually push that way
earlier with Chef compliance and inspect where you can do that security and compliance testing as part of the
whole dev process all the way up through the cycle, but where you get into a lot of the, we're going to test
how this looks deployed on a test server, maybe do some fuzzing of URLs and all that kind of fun stuff,
that's going to happen kind of after you get your artifact built and deployed into some kind of staging environment.
And so that's where we start coming into right after Michael gets through kind of just.
There you go. We should hit the accelerator
too.
Yeah, we're death five.
Yeah, let's not go there. That's not going to happen. So to shortcut this, your build is going to run all
the tests that you stored in source control. We're lucky that we're running PowerShell because script analyzer
is out there. It's a whole just volume of rules that you can get for free and it runs from the command-line
and you can automate it, so that works out really, really well and then you go all through Pester.
In the next, you're over there for the next time log.
Yeah, I think 2:00.
Okay, because he can show you what Kitchen looks like, so you can think about test Kitchen from Chef working
together in this environment with PowerShell, with Pester, but what if for this change you actually get to
test it against 2008 R2, 2012, and 2012 R2, not that anybody would have diversity of machines across their
environment and have to deal with something like that, but that would make doing that again back to just a
property value, what platforms, these three, okay cool. And then it's just going to go run those tests,
spin up a VM on whatever you want to spin up a VM on, run these tests, save the results, go to the next thing.
So all of these tools are all about making complicated things simple.
And then definitely go look at OVF, Operational Validation, it's under
github.com/powershell/operationalvalidationframework, I think, github.com/powershell and you'll find it.
But it's a project that's being spun up around how do you know that after you've deployed the change that
everything still works. Go ahead.
I was just going to say, and unfortunately this is kind of what, we're getting down to the wire timewise,
but this test phase, source control and this test phase when they did the statistical analysis of all the parts
of continuous delivery and what adds the most value, it's source control and the integrated testing and automated testing.
So the more effort you put into focusing on source control and all of the automated testing capabilities,
those are going to deliver your biggest bang for your buck as you start to adopt more continuous delivery-type practices.
And that's been proven out. That's definitely been a thing in the Chef ecosystem.
We are super heavy on the testing side of things because it delivers such great value, so definitely spend the
time looking at all the different test tools.
Yeah, I always tell people if there's one skill in 2016 that I would go learn, it's Pester because you're going
to be equipped for everything that comes at you after that. So if you only have time to go learn one new thing,
Pester is just hugely valuable.
TFS is nice because it goes and picks up those results. It works because Pester can output into an XML format
that's an industry standard for NUnit. So it just picks up those and brings them in.
I didn't have to do anything to make this reporting work, so it can say yep, for each of those builds,
here's your test history. It all
worked. You can obviously see if I had 1,000 test instead of 4 that this would be really of value.
There's lots of charts down that side--- I can drill in.