Step away from and take away that core knowledge of the systems,
the expert knowledge that you all have.
It actually becomes more important.
So these are the four things. In writing the whitepaper, we had to boil it down and every one of these has
eight things, but we wanted to get down to what are the core concepts if I'm looking at this for the first time
that I can categorize this information to pieces I can digest one at a time.
So we're going to go through each of these and the pattern in the paper is written in a similar fashion is
what is this and then what does this mean to me if I'm working in operations, right, because these things all,
I mean, especially if you have in-house developers, these are things that they talk about right, but these are
not things that we normally talk about in operations.
I'm not expecting you to read this slide, like I said, the slides will be available and this is obviously in the
paper as well, but we tried to capture what are the problems that this actually is trying to solve.
So we're going to dig into these a lot, but I hate just reading off a slide, so I'm going to dig in deep to those.
So if we talk about source first, that's the first big bullet.
What did we do before? Right, so I'm going to describe change management, even though we're talking about source control.
So I wanted to introduce a change, right, so I spin up a VM, I'm going to prototype the change there,
and then I went and I submitted the change form and then I went to my change advisory board and I present it.
I've tested this, I'm going to introduce a new policy setting, I've created a VM that looks like that server,
I created a sub OU, I moved the machine object into that sub OU, I applied the policy there, if all goes well,
then I'm going to also introduce that policy to the OU, to the policy that applies to the whole OU and cross
my fingers that things don't explode because I don't really understand what most of these servers look like,
right, because who knows if yesterday somebody RDPd into it and made a change.
I have no idea. So I need a rabbit's foot and a change form and I'm going to see how this goes.
When we get to change advisory board, we're going to argue because somebody's going to say why do you need to
make that change. It's probably going to break my stuff.
We're going to try to catch, if two of us are going to implement something that's similar and we might bump
into each other even possibly in the same maintenance window, so that's a little scary, and then, of course,
we're going to go to the build documentation for that server and update it because we always do that.
So the first that happens is we don't prototype in a VM and we don't update our docs.
We just show up, well we might submit the change form, right, and then we show up and present.
The next thing that happens is we're the cool kid because we're the expert, so we don't ever even submit the change form.
We just walk in, throw down our laptop, and say Saturday I'm going to make this change, deal with it,
and that's kind of change goes and then arguments happen. And then at the end, we just present an argue,
and then lastly, we just argue, and it's pretty much how change management actually happens.
That's what we did before.
So what do we do now? We start with configuration as code.
So instead of doing documentation at the end, which we never did, we just update the configuration file so
that is the documentation for how this thing is built. It's also how the machine, it's how the work is performed,
so if we didn't get it right, it didn't get built that way, so we know that this is right as we go.
Included in that source control, so when I say source control, I'm talking about things like TFS,
talked about subversion, git was the one that for some reason what not landing in my head and that's the most popular one.
Not visual source safe. Not SharePoint versioning.
It could be a file share, in fact, I talked to---
no, no, no---
it should not be a file share.
It is not a file share.
But I will relate it this way because it makes it a little bit easier to digest.
a lot of people in this room probably have a background where at some point you worked on desktops and you
probably had a file share full of apps that you deployed using something to those desktops.
Think about it like that, right, you had a folder structure and you had versions of those apps and you put
them there, and with those apps, you probably had a batch file that did a silent install.
We just want to start thinking about it that way, right, so we're going to take the way we're configuring
these servers, we're going to pair it up with a script that automatically deploys that file,
the Pester scripts that evaluate the quality of that and we're putting all that stuff together.
And then your release of it could be a web server, it could be Active Directory domain controller, it could be
an Exchange box, whatever, you're defining a version that's yours.
So that's you're, like you might be working on DNS Server version 7.4, and 7.4 doesn't mean that it's DNS
version 7.4, it means for you, this is your 7.4 release of that part of your infrastructure and that's kind of
how we can relate source control back into this. There's a version associated with how that infrastructure
is configured right now. So we make the change. We're going to talk about testing in a lot more depth,
but you're actually going to run tests locally on your machine to say yep, it looks like I've done this correctly,
and then you're actually going to do a push.
So if you're familiar with git, and even if you're using TFS, git.exe will be your front-end in most cases.
You're going to do a clone to your machine, you can pull changes that other people have made, you can push
your changes back, and if two teams are working on this at the same time, that somebody owns that repo,
they can do a pull request. It means that they can take DNS 7.4 offline, maybe they wanted to submit a
change to you, they can submit change .7.5, you review it, it'll show you line by line what exactly changed.
We're going to take a look at this. Here's what's most important,
as those things get checked back in, some people call it check in, some people call it a push,
there's metadata that happens. Who made the change? When did it happen?
There's comments to explain why did that happen and you can literally hold these things side by side and see
I can see right here that now we were static IP, now we're dynamic IP.
Like all of these things are side by side in a window and you can see exactly when that happened.
The state of DevOps survey that's been going on for the past three years, the fourth year of the survey is
going on now, Dr. Nicole Forsgren has been doing research on the statistics based off that survey.
One of the findings that they had was that change argument change control board thing there is way less
effective than source control and peer review of changes as they go out into your infrastructure, and so there's
a paper that's out there. I will be blogging the link to that probably later today if you want to dive into
kind of the science of it.