---because that ends up being your single source of truth.
Then you start adding your build process and that's where you can start plugging in a bunch of other stuff
like what he's going to continue talking about here so.
I'll show you what it looks like and then we'll get to the big one.
So when you go to demo this, what we're really going to demo is and I'll do a comprehensive live demo at the
end, but trigger a build, verify that things happened, look at the report, right, so that's basically what
we're going to do. So in this case, this is actually the script that we'd run.
This is formatted using PSake. In the live environment, I'm using a new version of PSDeploy to replace this
big code block, and so my live demo it's a little bit cleaner. But if you're familiar again back with
Computer Science type concepts, you've heard the command Make. On a Linux environment, you might be spinning
up a project from source and Run-Make, so PSake, pronounced Saki, but the concept is to use a DSL that's similar
to make or rake for Ruby and have that in PowerShell. So PSake is an awesome project to look at and it allows
you to chain together a lot of really complex tasks. It's a lot to just a glance, but it's definitely a
project to look at.
For my build definition, which just means what are the things that are going to happen whenever the build runs,
I just have a PowerShell script that I'm literally, just go run that, pass it arguments, and the arguments
are just coming from stored variables. So just like in Azure automation, you can store assets, store variables,
store credentials, things like that, same thing. So my build literally is just run a PowerShell script.
I have two steps because TFS understands how to collect published test results, so I have Pester output to XML
and then this will go pick it up and make it in a nice reports for me and that's like a free bonus.
What we'd want to get to and Mark Grey and I have been talking about this, we want to publish a project,
you should really be able to sanitize this to the point where you could take that project and just make it
work in any build system. It could be AppVeyor, it could be Jenkins, it could be Travis, it could TeamCity,
it could be Visual Studio, TFS, it could be locally on your machine, you should be able to just run build
that PS1 and not have to worry about it, right. You might have incoming parameters, but that's about as
complex as it should need to be.
I just wanted to show quickly for this particular project, I've got a whole bunch of stored variables.
That's just so that my scripts can become as generic as I can make them and then I really want that to be
scaffolding that I can just if I want to go create new project, I shouldn't have to reinvent the wheel when
it comes to what does that look like to check it in and have build run it and have tests run it and run a deployment.
We should pretty much just be able to pass it different parameters and it should just handle it on its own.
And TFS is a good example where you can encrypt information as its being stored.
This is where for triggers I can run it by clicking Q. If I check that box for Continuous Integration,
then whenever I do a push, it just runs.
And if I click scheduled, of course, then I can set a day and a time.
Yeah.
(Audience question)
Steve might know that better than I do.
Very. So just from a standpoint of flexibility or---so the question was what's the difference between PSake
and MSBuild and the answer is a lot and not very much. They're both build descriptor languages, but because it's
PowerShell and not XML, it tends to be a lot more readable, it's a lot more lightweight to write and kind of
dig through, but out of the box it doesn't have all the same steps and things as MSBuild.
MSBuild is really optimized for building .NET or .NET DLLs, executables, web projects, stuff like that where
PSake is a little more open-ended and just like Rake is going to be really good at building Ruby projects,
and Make is going to be very good for your C projects. PSake is a really nice easy addition to not only .NET
projects because you can call MSBuild tasks through it, but you can also easily do a lot of your PowerShell-type
testing, easily get into PS Script analyzer and Pester and because you're in PowerShell at that point.
I should call out for PSake, so you see task depends, so task test depends on clean, which just means run as
script to make sure. Because this is always running over and over again in the same box, clean up anything
that would have been there from the last build. And then deploy depends on test and then test depends on clean.
So when this runs, default depends on deploy. So if we follow this backwards, it means if your tests pass,
go ahead and deploy and that's why it's interesting to say if you check that box for continuous integration,
it means you edit the file on your machine, you hit Save, type in your commit, hit Push, it's going to go to build.
If all of you tests pass, you're going live, right, so you could literally just from your workstation go there.
Or you go into your dev environment or you're going, wherever that target is.
Exactly. I'm like that's the most extreme that I've ever seen it, in fact, I don't know of anybody that I've
seen go that quickly into production. There probably are for some projects.
Yeah, I think we've got some customers that do that.
Yeah, nice.
In most cases, you get to the output, so in this case, for DSC maybe you've got the MOF and then somebody eyeballs it.
What's interesting, so we'll look at PSDeploy in the last section, actually I'll come back to that section.
So I just want to come back to that point you said hey that's kind of extreme and I don't know a lot of
people that go all that route, but I'll bet every single one of you know somebody who's downloaded a script
off like TechNet or something and gone and run it in production and that's got even fewer quality gates than
what we've just demoed here.
That's true.
Right, so this is more rigor than what a lot of us are currently doing today in our environments.
Very true.
So it's not all that crazy.
Sure.
So I noticed that you have the test in the beginning, right, so would you consider like you talked about the
fact that after I do this deployment, right, now I've got to test maybe my apps and different things like that
afterwards and I'm not really seeing that as a step.
Is that part of my code in terms of my configuration code?
I don't know what's going on there, but it's hanging.
Does it need to have like okay here's the five applications test that you want to do?
Exactly. That's the next section. But that's exactly right. Your head is in exactly the right place.
In fact, that's the most important thing. I just
wanted to show real quick. I just love this that as you run the build when you click on Console,
there's a PowerShell window right there in your browser showing the scripts that came from source control and
everything is just running right there in your browser and you can watch it and it's like oh, this work that I
did is happening somewhere and I can do that all day long.
So you might have a build fail, no problem, you can see the output, so you can go back and look and you might
have it send you a notification, you might just go log in the website and see it, but now you can keep track
of okay this worked on my machine, why isn't it working somewhere else and help troubleshoot those types of things.
Let's see. You also obviously can have build succeed. What's nice is when you come back and look at this later,
you'll see each of the steps where it went and got from source, it ran PSake, and then it published test results,
so you can double-click on those and actually see the full log output in the history of these builds.