Just to start wrapping up, these are the, since we're at PowerShell Summit, learn Pester, learn PSake,
learn PSDeploy, go take a look at OVF. As you get further down the line, there are so many DevOps tools,
so as we update this slide, we'll continue growing this list, and in the whitepaper, we actually call out a wide variety.
Yeah, and one thing, I have a session on essential skills for DevOps world or something to that effect later this afternoon.
Michael is going to come join as well, so one of the things
we're going to talk about is build pipelines and the importance of continuous delivery and testing and all that,
so we can definitely have more time to dive into some of these concepts if you still wanted to.
We will make this probably my last slide.
Yep.
This is a huge point, so I just want to land this before we leave.
Coming from an infrastructure background, it's in our nature to say I found a new thing, this is my thing now,
and I'm going to focus on that and there's a couple of things that make this type of platform work.
One is you've got to get buy-in, right, from others in your org.
You can't do this alone because it only works if everyone agrees that the tests have to pass before we move forward.
The other is, keep your options open. So in the paper, we talk about things like how do you use this together
with ConfigMan and what's it look like to use this together with Group Policy because you're not going to cut
this over overnight and it's your job as you are the people, right, you are the people in your organization
that they look to as the lead architect that says how do we do this smart guy, right, and the answer is it's
not going to be a okay, well I stopped using this tool and now I'm using this tool and now we're a lot better, right.
That's just a tool change. It's the process change that makes this so valuable.
So we don't want to look like this with your precious. And now I've got my build server and now I'm just
linked to this stuff, it's all I care about now. Nope, you've still got all the tools you had before.
It's a process change and you can bring all of these things forward and that's how you be the hero for your
organization and help them get into this new world.
So yeah, we'll talk about this applying this same model to everything and making it visible and everybody
should be on success. So we'll continue onto this such thing then.
Thank you.
Great.