So, oh good, so we have some time.
I have 15 minutes. What I'd like to do is go from here to more, actually a real debugging scenario,
which with DSC resources. Let me just get back to the, if this is going to work.
So DSC class resource. The way DSC class resources execute, you see that all these things that we just
talked about can be used to debug those because it follows actually the same pattern.
DSC configuration is usually run on a remote machine, it's run in a host process, some obscure WmiPrvSE host
process, and inside of that host process, there's a runspace that's running your script, and so it would be really
great if you could attach a debugger to it when your script is not working correctly.
And just again, for a little bit of visualization, see how kind of complex it is, you have your machine on
one side of town, you want to connect to another machine or maybe a virtual machine, and inside that,
there is some process that DSC has created and is running your script and you want to attach to that and
debug that script.
I kind of wanted to take a quick second here and show something that's actually kind of cool.
In order to demo this, what I did was I've created a couple of virtual machines on this laptop, and on that machine,
I have a very simple DSC configuration that I want to run and that I want to debug.
As it turns out, when I was doing this in my office, all of the machines are domain joined, and so when I was
at home trying it, I'm no longer connected to that domain, and so I can't connect to it, so I can't do the
full demo that I would like to do, but I can do enough to show how to debug basically a DSC resource and just
kind of how that pattern works. One thing I just wanted to show real quickly though, which is kind of neat is
that even though I can't connect to my VM through WinRM because I'm not domain joined anymore, there is something
new called PowerShell Direct and
we worked with the, or actually I worked with the Hyper-V team and it's not possible to connect PowerShell
to a VM on your machine without running it all, and in fact, there's not a network enable at all because it
goes through a new socket layer that the Hyper-V team has created.
So you can do something like these are the VMs that I have and you can do Enter-PSSession now and give it a
name and then just try not to type quite so much.
You missed the R.
Did I miss the R? Okay, thanks. (Typing) So and then so now you can manage this VM what we would just kind of
need without having to go through WinRM remoting. And then on this VM here, I have a DSC class just for testing.
Just make sure that everything is set up. Yeah, just the way I want it to.
And so, how do you go about debugging this DSC resource class? So you start out and what the DSC team
created was Enable-DscDebug and you set it to BreakAll and what that means is that now when it runs,
it's kind of a big hammer. When you run DSC resource scripts, it's going to be in BreakAll mode, it's going to
be into the debugger and wait for a debugger attach, but to give you some information about that, so now you
can say Start-DscConfiguration, give it the class, you want to wait, Verbose.
So it runs and then it gets to a point and it tells you with a warning, the resource, which is test,
is waiting for a PowerShell script debugger to attach. Use the following commands to begin debugging this resource script.
And then it gives you a series of commands that you can run, and of course, they look familiar because they're
exact same things that we were just talking about and I'll just put it up here to see.
And again, you can do an Enter-PSSession if you need to connect to the remote computer.
A lot of times you don't need to because you might just have a remote desktop, and in fact, that's how I'm
going to do it, so you can skip that step. And again, this is something that we've seen before in our PSHostProcess
and the nice thing is that it tells you which process because there's probably a ton of WMI processes on there,
so it gives you the process. Another interesting thing is that it actually runs in a non-default AppDomain,
so when that's the case, you have to specify the AppDomain name, and then finally it gives you the runspace
that you want to debug. And of course, everybody sees this like well why do I have to execute three commands
and that's a good point and actually I have a prototype not released, not fully tested yet, but I will release
at some point where instead of executing all three commands, you just execute Debug-runspace with basically
a kind of a connection string. It's just a hash table.
That has all the information, so you don't have to type in three or four commands or whatever, you can just do one.
Something, again that I can't demo here because right now it's just based on connecting via WinRM and that's
not working right now on my laptop, but it's something that we'll get out at some point.
So okay, so anyway so the DSC configuration is stopped, waiting for a debugger attach.
What I'm going to do, since I can't remote in with PowerShell, I'm just going to go directly to, (Clicking)
why won't that maximized, there it goes, and what you can do is you can just copy and paste those commands or
it's pretty easy also to just do Get-PSHostProcessInfo and if we look, we can see like well there's really
only one WMI process that's attachable that's running a DSC worker, so we're pretty sure that this is the one
that we want. You do Post-Process, get same pattern, and then we can do a Get-Runspace and we see that
oh there's just one that's in breakpoint mode, so that's the one that we want to do.
So then we can do Debug-Runspace number 3. And now this is kind of interesting and the blog, actually I created
a blog about how to debug DSC resource classes. This is a little bit confusing because what's happening is
that we don't see any file, right, we kind of expect it to go into the DSC resource implementation,
but really what happened is when you say, when you set the runspace to BreakAll mode, it just says stop at
the very first script execution point and what happens is that each of these methods in the DSC resource class
is executed within a helper script, and so the debugger doesn't know that, it just stops in that helper script,
so it's a little bit confusing. So what it's doing is it's getting ready to call the Test method on the class,
but it hasn't yet, so in this case, what you need to do is you just need to do F11 and just step in until it
finally is executing the actual script and then ISE will bring up the file.
Now the good news about this, oh question.
(Audience comment)
So oh there was a demo yesterday about this?
Yes, that this problem was fixed.
Oh, I was just going to say that. Yeah, so I wanted to show this because it hasn't been released yet,
but the problem is fixed and I was going to demo it on my other VM that has the fix in it.
So yeah, a person in the DSC team very cleverly fixed it by before they execute the Class method, they get the
class file, parse it, and find out the line number, so it actually said breakpoints on the line numbers.
So the nice thing is that in the next release you won't have this problem, but I just wanted to mention it
so that when people see this, they're not too confused about what's going on.
So yeah, this has been fixed. And so yeah, we're just about done.
So I think this is probably about as far as I want to go right now, we can go, oh there is one thing we
could talk about real quickly. And again, we have some time for questions if you like, so I'll let you decide.
So we're going to talk about some of the gotchas and one of them we just talked about now and that is that the
Enable-DSC BreakAll stops in class in the calling script and that's been fixed, that's not true anymore.
Another kind of a downside to DSC debugging is that every time a new Class method is called, they reset the
runspace, but when you reset the runspace, also removes all the breakpoints, so all the breakpoints that you
put in are gone, so you have to put them in again and that's going to be a little bit confusing.
There's a bug on that and I think that can be addressed for the DSC team.
The LCM hosting process that you attach to, that can go away. That's not always a problem, but sometimes when
you have your ISE attached to it, you can do things like edit files through the remoting system,
but underneath it, they recycle the process regularly, so if you do something like try to save the file that
you edited, sometimes the underlying process goes away and then you get an error and that can be really annoying,
that's just something to keep in mind. And then the last thing is that just BreakAll is painful.
If you're running a number of classes, more than one class, it's going to stop in every one of those Class
methods each time, and if you're running like 10 and it's the 7th one that you want to debug, you have to go
through each one. And really, ideally, what you would like to do
is set a breakpoint, so I really want to debug this class file at this line and that's not supported in DSC
now, but I'm pushing the DSC team to add that. So it'd be really cool where you say Enable-DscDebug,
instead of BreakAll, you say give it maybe like a hash table of this is the file and these are the line
numbers and I want it to break at that point.