My name is Paul Higinbotham. I'm here to talk about PowerShell Advanced Debugging.
Welcome.
I'm a software developer on the Microsoft PowerShell core team, so there's my contact information.
Feel free to contact me. I've been working on the PowerShell team for almost six years now,
which interestingly makes me still kind of a newbie. PowerShell has been around for a long time.
A lot of people on the team have been there for 10 years or more.
One of my areas that I work on in PowerShell responsibility for is remoting, some of the debugging stuff,
workflow, actually a lot of different areas, but mostly PowerShell remoting and remoting related systems.
So what I want to talk about today is more advanced scenarios in PowerShell script debugging.
This slide is really just about motivation. When you have script that's just not working, there's a lot of
ways you can diagnose it and try to figure out what's going on and fix it.
A lot of times you get away with just looking at script output, verbose output, trying to figure out what's
going on with your script and sometimes you can fix it at that point.
But really, a lot of the times, what you really would like to do is just get a debugger on it, a script debugger
and PowerShell actually has a pretty nice script debugger that you can use to break into script,
step through script, set breakpoints, that sort of thing. But traditionally, it only works for interactive
scripts, scripts that you run in the ISE or in the console. But PowerShell is a pretty capable platform and
allows you to create and run scripts that are not being run interactively.
They can be run as background scripts, they can be run as part of an application that hosts PowerShell and
these are more complex scenarios where you can have complex script.
I think we'd like to debug, like have a debugger on it and be able to step through the script, but previously,
that just was not possible. You can only debug the script if you were running with an ISE.
So anyway, this talk about how to use some of the new PowerShell Version 5 features for debugging these more
difficult scenarios, and of course, one of the great examples is DSC script resources, so that'll be one of the demos.
So live debugging goal. What you want to do when you want to put a debugger on script.
Basically the script is not working, you want to find the issue that's breaking your script code,
fix a problem, and move on, and usually the first step is trying to get debugger onto your script.
And again, as I mentioned before, debugging interactive scripts is really easy and PowerShell, you open the
script file in ISE, set line breakpoints, you run the script, you step through it, you can see what's going
on, so that's really nice.
But debugging non-interactive scripts is more difficult, actually it was impossible until version 5,
and these kind of scripts are like background running scripts. PowerShell
has a rich set of APIs that let you create scripts that can run concurrently, that can run in the background very easily.
It's not running in the ISE or in the console, so how do you debug something like that.
Some examples of that are you can have like a custom management tool that's based on PowerShell and
PowerShell scripts, WinRM remote host when you do PowerShell remoting, WinRM creates a process that hosts
PowerShell, and within that, runs the script remotely on a remote machine for you, so that's just an example
of how PowerShell can be hosted in a process. And then, of course, the most complex scenario is the
DSC configuration scripts when they run. They run on a,
usually on a different computer in some kind of a hosting process inside a runspace, and if you have DSC
configuration script that's not working correctly, how do you debug that?
Preferably like bugger in the context on which it runs. I mean a lot of times you're developing probably your
configuration scripts in some kind of a mock up on your dev machine works fine, but then when you deploy it
onto another machine, it's not working. So what we would really like to do is be able to put a debugger on
that live session and debug that script in that context.
So the main concept for advanced debugging, I think, is redirection.
The whole idea is putting a debugger on the script that's running is basically you have ISE on your dev computer
and you want to point that or redirect that to where the script is running and debug it.
And there's like three cmdlets that conform to this redirection paradigm, one is Enter-PSSession,
that's actually a cmdlet that's been around since version 2 and that's how you do remoting, interactive remoting.
You would Enter-PSSession and you're basically redirecting the command-line to a remote machine.
So when you type in the command-line, it's being executed on the remote machine and then of course,
output's going back into the console. But what's new for v5 is two new cmdlets.
One is called Enter-PSHostProcess
and what that does is that allows you to redirect the command-line to a local process on your machine and
that can work within a remote session, so you can connect to a remote machine, and then on that remote machine,
you can connect to any process that's hosting PowerShell, and then when you execute commands,
it's actually executing in that environment.
And then the third thing is, third cmdlet, is called Debug-Runspace and what Debug-Runspace does is basically
redirect the debugger. It points the debugger at a particular runspace
that's executing the script, and so then you can debug that script in that context.