So yeah, so any questions? Feel free to interject. There's time at the end also for questions.
What runspace are these in? Are these under a user runspace or a system runspace?
The question is what runspace they're in, the user runspace or a system runspace.
Are you talking about the credential context of which they are running?
So I send the same context that the host process was created, so it's running in that context.
So if it was created with admin credentials, it's that, or any other user credentials, it's that.
So as you, the way it actually works is when you create, you saw the runspaces and then you execute script
in that runspace, PowerShell spins up a thread and is the thread based on the process context.
Any other questions? Ah, yes.
If the runspace that you were attaching to was multithreaded using the .NET classes to create a multithread
call, will you be able to attach to the separate threads?
The question is if the runspace that you created was multithreaded, could you attach to each of the threads.
And the answer is that each runspace can only run in a single thread, so you can't have multiple threads.
And so the way that PowerShell does concurrency is per runspace.
So multiple threads in script is really not supported. It's just a single thread.
Are you talking about just creating a runspace tool rather than just using Visual runspace?
So currently one of the pieces of middleware that I have running uses the .NET class to create a thread pool
and then
the value is group memberships in parallel for each one in the thread pool.
Gotcha, gotcha. I understand. So yeah, so what you're saying is that inside your thread using .NET API to
create multiple threads and then execute matters code on each of those threads, and in order to, so now you're
outside of this script debugging. So in order to debug that, then you have to use a native or manage debugger
to debug those threads. PowerShell script debug is only for debugging script execution.
Any other questions? Oh.
But in that case, if you have a runspace pool, you would see all the runspaces in the pool and theoretically
be able to debug those?
That's a good question. The question is if you had a runspace pool, which is a construct that collects and
manages multiple runspaces that you would be able to see all of those runspaces and debug script in each one
of those and the answer is yes. When you do a get-runspace, all runspaces are created whether it's within a
pool or separately is shown and it's shown in the list until all those runspaces, those objects are disposed.
And as well, on jobs because jobs usually have a child job that's actually doing the work, so you have a double
set into those runspaces?
So the question is, how would you debug jobs. And I think the assumption is that jobs are running in multiple runspaces.
Actually, PowerShell jobs run in child processes and inside those child processes are created runspaces,
so it's done that for extra isolation, it's fairly heavyweight. And so, in order to debug, there's actually two ways.
In order to debug a job like that is that you could actually attach to that process and then find the
runspace and debug it, but there's also a way from the original client console to do a debug job.
So when you get a job object back, there's actually Debug-Job cmdlet.
I'm not talking about it in this talk, but you can debug the jobs through that way as well and it actually
goes through the PowerShell remoting and then talks to the child process.
Interestingly, actually I've created and I think other people have created thread jobs and what they are
lighter weight PowerShell jobs that don't run in a separate process, but run in a separate runspace and if you
use my thread jobs, then yes, when you run those scripts what it does is it creates new runspaces in which to
run those scripts and you will be able to see those and you can debug them using this technique.
Paul, is that available in your thread jobs? Is that in the gallery?
The question is that thread job available. I've been meaning to put it up on the gallery and I can't even
remember if I did or not. I think I did a few months ago, but if not, I will do it.
There are other people have done, I mean it's a common idea, other people have done the same thing.
What I did was make them as similar to other jobs, the only difference is that instead of running it in a child
process, it runs in a thread. The nice thing about that too is that the objects that you're dealing with are
live to that process. You don't have that serialization layer going from one process to another, and so the
objects are live and plus it's much faster too. You don't have that overhead of creating the child process.
So if that's in the gallery, is it called thread jobs?
I think it's called thread jobs, yeah. Look it up in the gallery.
I just can't remember. It's something I've been meaning to do and then you forget about it and then a month
or two later, it's like oh I should do that, and then I forget about it, but I think I did, but I'll make a
mental note to check that. Okay.