So just take a second here. What are runspaces? And this basically says that every PowerShell script that
runs within a context called a runspace, as we call them internally, and what the runspace is basically the
context in which a script runs. It has the variables that you've defined, it has the functions that you've
defined, modules that you import, breakpoints that you set, everything is all kind of contained in something
called a runspace.
So when you talk about debugging script, it's kind of synonymous to say you're talking about debugging at runspace.
It's a runspace that's basically running the script and providing the context for that script to run.
So when you hear things like point a debugger to a runspace, what that means is it's really the framework in
which script is being run. And I just want to provide a diagram, just to kind of see it, kind of get your
head around it because it's fairly complex. You know over on one side of town you have your computer,
you have the PowerShell ISE open, but you want to debug script that's running on the machine someplace else,
and so the first thing you do is use Enter-PSSession so can connect to that machine across town, and then within
that machine, there can be multiple processes that are hosting PowerShell.
It could be a PowerShell console, it could be some sort of application process that you're interested in,
maybe like a DSC configuration, local configuration manager that's running script.
And so the next thing is you want to then point to that particular process that you're interested in and
that's when you use Enter-PSHostProcess cmdlet. Then within that process on that remote machine, there can be
multiple runspaces that are running script.
And then so one of those runspaces you're interested in is a script that you want to debug and then so you
want to use debug runspace to point to that particular runspace and debug that script.
So it's fairly complex. Either these cmdlets are not something that you're going to use every day because
this is kind of a complex debugging scenario, but when you need it, they're very powerful and it's something
that can really save you if you're just facing a problem. Scripts that aren't running and you're trying to
figure out why. It's just really nice to be able to debug it in a live session.
So from here, I want to pivot to the first demo. Basically, what I want to demonstrate here is the process
of redirecting to a host process that's running script that you're interested in, and within that process,
finding the runspace that's running the script that you want to debug and then attaching the debugger.
And actually what this demo is going to do is simulate a process that's running four simultaneous scripts.
One is going to be, actually I only have three here now, but one's going to be just a script that's running
in a continuous loop that's you're going to attach the debugger to.
Another one is called copy file script. It runs very quickly, and so this one's going to be set up so that as
soon as it starts running, it pauses and waits for a debugger attach so that you can debug it because it runs
in a few seconds and you want to debug the script. Third one is just a simple algorithm that extracts the
sub array from array, and in this case, it's going to use a new cmdlet called Wait-Debugger and what this does
is a cmdlet you put in the script and when it executes it puts the execution engine into a wait mode.
It stops execution and waits for a debugger attach. And the nice thing about wait debugger is that you can
put it anywhere you want inside the script, and so the debugger will stop and the script execution will stop
and wait for a debugger at a particular point, which is kind of nice when you're debugging.
And the fourth one I don't have listed here is set up a runspace, and again, it's going to run the copy file script,
but in this case, you're going to give it a line breakpoint and say I want it to stop at this particular line
and this script file, and then wait for a debugger attach.
So I've created a brand new console and pretending it's not an interactive console, but it is, and in it,
I have a script that's going to simulate what a PowerShell application, PowerShell hosting application would
do, which is basically create runspaces and then run script files.
I won't spend too much time on this, but I do want to show a little bit how this works because it's kind of
the same pattern over and over again on how to create a runspace and then execute a script inside it.
And then once this is running, and I'll show how you can attach to the process and then debug each of these
scripts that are running. And you can see it, okay good. So first one is basically a pattern where you
create a runspace and give it a name, creates a call to PowerShell object, you associate it with that runspace,
and then you say okay run the script file. And this is one that just runs continuously, so it's just going
to run in an infinite loop and it's going to have runspace and then call LogQueryRS.
The second one is the copy file. It runs very quickly, so again, we create the runspace, but this is a
little bit different. After we create the runspace, we use a cmdlet called Enable-RunspaceDebug.
What this does it sets up the runspace in debug mode and also sets a source called BreakAll.
So what
it's telling runspace is as soon as you start running script, stop at the very first execution point in the
script, and wait for a debugger attach. This is a little bit dangerous, something you definitely don't want
to have in a production environment because the script will look like it's hung, it's not running,
and that's because it's waiting for a debugger attach, so this is something you only want to do in investigations.
And the third one, and again, I kind of want to go through these because they're slightly different,
this one is the Max SubArray, again it's creating a runspace, adding in variables, and executing it.
The only difference is that inside the script, there's a Wait-Debugger command.
And so, it is also going to stop and wait for a debugger attach,
but there's nothing we did special to the runspace. We actually had to modify the source code.
So the Wait-Debugger is a very powerful, again something you don't want in your production environment
because it looks like your script is hung and the downside is that in order to use it, you have to modify
the script file, but it's very powerful for just saying I want the debugger to just stop at this point,
so I can investigate what's going on.
And then finally, the last one, again I'm doing a copy file. Again, the only difference is I am setting a
breakpoint in the runspace at this particular line in the file and one thing to keep in mind is again we have to
tell the runspace to be in debug mode because normally when runspace is executing script and a breakpoint
event fires, if there's no ISE debugger available to handle that, then it just ignores it, it just continues
running, but in this case, we don't want it to. We want it to stop and wait for the debugger attach.
Okay. So over here on my clean process, I'm just going to go ahead and run that script, get the process id 4112,
and then go back to here, and then I want to show a new cmdlet called Get-PSHostProcessInfo.
What this does is that a list all of the processes on your local machine that is hosting PowerShell and is
available for a connection and we see a bunch of them here because I have a few open, we see the ISE
obviously, the one I already forgot,
(Audience comment)
4112, thank you, is one that we're interested in, these are other consoles that are running.
So now we can use the new redirection cmdlet called Enter-PSHostProcess 4112 and we can attach to that process.
One thing I kind of wanted to show here and I think I'll just go ahead and do that now, just to back up a
little bit, that this Enter-PSHostProcess will work in a remote session.
So with just one laptop, it's hard to simulate all this, but I'm just going to pretend that this is running
on a remote machine, so I'm going to do an Enter-PSSession, actually it's a loop back to this computer,
and of course, for some reason my poor laptop seems to be really, really slow.
And if this is going to take too long, I can, okay there we go. So now we're, and again, we can do a
Get-PSHostProcess and we kind of pretend that okay we're remoting into a remote machine, we do get
PSHostProcess, we want to enter PSHostProcess 4112 and the thing to kind of look at is the command-line
because it tells you what's going on. It tells you that you're connected to the remote machine, localhost,
in this case, and within that, we're connected to the process 4112.
And then from here, we do a get, this is another important cmdlet, Get-Runspace.
What this does now is within this process, it'll list all of the runspaces after runspaces in this process.
And now finally, we see kind of what we expect to see. If we look at the first one, this is because this
process that we're in is actually a console host process and it always creates a default runspace,
so there's always a number 1 Runspace1 and that's been created so that when you type in the console,
that's what executes your command in your script. But then we see the runspaces that we've created and this
is what we expect, and of course, the first one the LogQueryRS, the availability is busy.
That's because it's running in continuous loops. Every time I look at it's going to show busy, but on the
CopyFileRS or these other three all show availability in breakpoint.
What that means is that they're not running script. It's stopped and it's waiting for a debugger attach.
Again, you have to be a little bit careful with that because if you're not aware of it, you just might think
that script is taken forever to run, it's not actually running.
And then the other one here is a little bitty string. This is called RemoteHost.
This is a temporary runspace that has been created when you run the Enter-PSHostProcess.
What that does is that executes the commands that you type on the command-line, so here like if you type in
your command, this is running in that RemoteHost process that its connected to.
When you exit the attachment to that host process, then that temporary runspace goes away.
So then I just show real quickly how then to debug these runspaces.
Each one is just a little bit different. So you do Debug-Runspace logqueryrs, that's the first one, and
what's happening is when you do a Debug-Runspace on script that's already running, it attaches debugger
and then it sets the debugger into step mode immediately, so it just stops at the very next execution,
and at this point, you can step through the code and do all the debugging
you want and you have the command-line here, so you can query state and machine state and variable and all the
things that you can debugging, so you have a nice live debugging session there.
What I'm going to do is a detach where you type detach at the debugger prompt, it detaches the debugger,
and so now if you do a Get-Runspace, we see that it's busy again, so it's busily running in that infinite loop.
Now if we do a Debug-Runspace on the first copyfilers and it did this before.
I'm not sure what's going on there, so we're going to skip that.
Oh, that's weird. So yeah, don't look at that. We're going to move to subarray.
I'll take a look at that later. This next one, this one is what we expect.
This is the code I was talking about. For the Wait-Debugger, what I did was if a global variable is defined
as true, then I go ahead and execute the Wait-Debugger, which means that it puts it in step mode so that the
very next line to execute is stopped and waiting for the debugger attach.
And now you can go through and do debugging as before until you're done.
And then if you want, what I kind of like about this is that it's conditional, so if you're done debugging,
you can do it, and this is in a loop, so if you don't want to do it in a loop anymore you can just, whoops,
set the variable to false.
(Audience comment)
I'm sorry?
You're missing a G on the debug.
Oh, thank you. It's these bifocals I can't see very well. And then you can just do an F5 to continue and
then it continues to run this very fast. One thing to keep in mind is that the debugger attach remains,
so you get this little warning that says command or script is completed, but the debugger is still attached.
So like if your new script started running, you can debug that if you want, but if you're done debugging,
then you can detach a debugger with just Ctrl+C then it takes you back to the command-line.
And let's go one more Debug-Runspace copyfilers2 and this is one where we set the breakpoint.
One thing to kind of keep in mind is that this one is still busy, this one has gone to available because it's
completed running the script, and so the runspace is available to run a new script, which is kind of
interesting to note. And this one is still waiting for a debugger attach.
And here is kind of what we expect, it's on Line 21, which is what we set, and so it can debug from that point.
And again, I'll just do a detach by typing detach at the debugger prompt.
So when you're done, you can just do an Exit-PSHostProcess Exit-PSSession and I don't know why that's taking so long.
I've been getting these weird pauses. Let's see if I can get back to the slides.