So that's really all I have. If there are any more questions, let me know.  Oh.
Instead of breakpoints changing every Class method call, if my Test method calls my Get method, does that reset
the breakpoint as well?
All the breakpoints that are set within that specific method call remain.
So like if you're calling helper functions or helper methods within like say the test or the set,
those all work fine, but the next time like if it goes from Get to, so like say…
(Audience comment)
Yeah, so I get, yeah, so the next time it's a new method call then I'll reset at that point.
Any other questions?
And that's actually because Get, Set, Test through the DSC Get call is there to send up, gets one call
and one of them it
creates a new runspace, that's why these don't affect us.
Actually sometimes it creates a new runspace. So the question is or the comment is that there's a new
runspace created for each of the method calls. That's sometimes true.
I know that they do create new runspaces, but mostly they recycle, and so there's actually a reset function
that you can call and part of that reset is to reset when you set reset runspaces, everything is cleared
including the breakpoints. I think it can be modified so that you say oh reset this runspace, but keep the
breakpoints because I'm running this in a context where it's the same class or something, so you know that
you want to keep the breakpoints. So I think that can be addressed and again there's a bug tracking it right
now, so I think it will be at some point.
Okay, well I think that's all I have then. Oh, contact information.
Feel free to contact me through MVP, or GitHub, or whatever. We try to keep tabs on all kinds of different areas.
I'm happy to talk to you, or after the meeting as well, or take any comments that you have.
Thank you very much.