Another thing that I started using quite early is I dropped all use of the PowerCLI cmdlets and I think I
mentioned it earlier I went immediately for the API methods. Okay, API methods.
Who of you is using the Onyx WebClients or has heard of the Onyx WebClients?
So there's a feature where you can see all these API calls underneath the PowerCLI cmdlets.
It's a handy feature if you want to write some advanced functions and don't know what they are actually calling.
So that is the kind of stuff that you will see appearing if you start using this Onyx WebClient,
so you see over the deep down APIs and properties. In this case, what I'm doing here I'm just adding a
VMHost and ESXi node to, or standalone server, or one to a cluster, instead the if statement at the end.
So based on what leaf type was returned, if it's a cluster that was returned, we can use the AddHost method
if it's not a cluster by definition it a standalone server, then we need to use this other method with
somewhat different parameters.
So a lot of the resources that you will see when I make this public, all of them, in fact, are real API calls
and API objects that I'm using. And the reason I'm doing that is like I set this for speed, but also to have more features.
But the API methods, I can do everything. There's a lot, there's some stuff with them, but the cmdlets
that is not possible.
What I also used as a guideline and I think I mentioned an example earlier, if you look at the cluster in the
VMware environment, the cluster has multiple components. We have high availability, DRS, DPM.
All of these in turn have a lot of parameters that you can use to configure these components.
On the other hand,
if you got to the WebClient or the vSphere client, you can just right-click on the datacenter new cluster
and it doesn't ask you a lot of questions. It just asks you, do you want HA enabled, DRS enabled, DPM.
That's it. So what I decided quite early on
in writing these classes is I would go for the same approach. If you define a resource, a new cluster in
this case, no not in this case, but if you would define a new cluster, you would get all the defaults.
And a configuration of HA or DRS or DPM would be a separate resource, but the dependency on the cluster,
of course, but I would separate the complexity that way, so that's why I called this slide, keep it simple.
So I'd rather
work with all these different resources with dependencies in between them, than making one big resource with
tens or hundreds of parameters, which is quite complex to code and manage.
So where am I now? At the moment, I have a number of resources that are tested and available.
Those are the ones that I will publish when I'm back home from this event.
It's the standard stuff, folder, datacenter, we have cluster, we have VMHost in there, we have datastore in there.
There's one component missing that you would need if you want to actually start using it, meaning start creating
VMs as your network part. VSS standard switches is quite obvious.
This one is under the development. Distributed switches is a bit further away in the future, I'm afraid.
That is quite complex object, but it's on my to do list. So what I'm working on at the moment is the networking part.
Like I said, I will publish this quite shortly after I'm back and since the environment is quite complex,
I can't do that all by myself, so what I want to do is publish this, give you an idea how it can be done,
so there would, by definition, need to be a lot of community effort to make this complete, to be able to
configure your complete vSphere environment based on DSC resources in this case.
Like I said also in the beginning, I'm not going to show you a lot of code.
I have my ISE editor open. If some of you want to see some of the code or have specific questions, feel free
to come up after this session or anywhere in the next coming days, I'm happy to run through it and discuss
with you what even, even though I prefer to listen to your suggestions on how some of this stuff should be done.
Quick question here. If you have available vSphere DSC resources, how many would consider actually using that?
And is that no problem with your environment that they say this is external or we don't trust it.
Would you have to do a validation? Would you prefer or would you require passive built-in tests?
Yeah. If a structure testing. So something that made available if it comes with infrastructure testing
that would be more acceptable than just the resources. Yes. Okay, great.
So that's new point on my to do list then or anybody else who wants to volunteer for that part.
In fact, that's what I wanted to say in this presentation. There's another one on Wednesday where I will
start looking or when I will look at the reverse part because a lot of you will have existing vSphere environments.
Now how do you get from an existing vSphere environment to a configuration file?
That is the interesting part. You're not going to write, I'm not going to write them from scratch,
so that's for Wednesday. And in fact, this brings me to the end of my session for today.