Then the modules themselves. Remember I said that I wanted to go for class modules, class base resources,
so I started in 5, one of the early previews in fact already, I started converting what I had,
a scripted resource to a class. Some guidelines that I, but not only for my DSC resources, I use this for all
my modules and scripts.
I love this region, hash region keyword in your code. It allows you to collapse and expand code, makes it more,
you can have a look from a high level on your code, so that's what I did here.
You see, for example, for my class folder, C, okay and I know that the C at the beginning is also under discussion.
I'm going to review that as well. That one I can understand that is perhaps a bit surpassed and that I should
just call it VmwFolder in this case. But what you see is that I have three distinct regions in each class.
First of all, we have the properties. We will open it on the next slide.
Then you have the standard DSC functions your classical Get, Set, and Test.
And then, what I try to do and you will see also that in the next slide is the Get, Set, and Test should be rather simple.
So a lot of the functionality I packaged in helper functions. That's the start region.
We'll have a closer look at those now.
Okay, I hope this is somewhat visible, but just because, okay the first part that's approximately to the line
no, it's to the Line 28, that's my attributes, my properties, parameters that I want, no the properties of
the class, in this case, for the Forward class. There's a number in there that you absolutely need that
ensure the path, the name, and so on. There's the hidden one. Everybody knows what a hidden property is in a class.
You won't see it if you use the IntelliSense thing. The intention of that one is remember I wanted to use
this corrected sessions. That's the one where the session id would go, in fact.
So for the moment, since it's not working, I'm not using it, but that was the intention.
Also notice that there are credentials in there and I know that
we should be at a good session earlier, no first session this afternoon on the encrypting your complete MOF.
This is definitely something that I should be looking at. I haven't done it yet, but we should start
encrypting this stuff because there's quite a lot of security in there.
You have your connectivity to your vSphere server, which you don't want to be seen in public or on the
network where everybody can snoop.
Then the next region is like I said, the Set, Test, and Get functions.
They are quite simple in this case. In fact, they only contain the functionality to return the correct result,
if they return the result at all. And then you have a number of helper functions at the bottom of the start
region that I used.
Okay, this is the part where I will set back, quite recently in fact, I had the multiple psm1 files that
didn't work out, so I had to go back and start using the RootModule in the manifest and put everything,
all my resources, all my classes in one psm1 file unfortunately.
I hope this is a temporary issue and that it will get fixed at some point because for source control reasons,
it's a lot easier if I have it in separate files if I work on the folder class.
Now I have to import and commit everything again, then I would just be able to do it on the part that I'm
actually working with. So if you start using it or if you start writing it, remember at the moment you can
only do it in one psm1 file unfortunately.