Okay. Welcome. I'm glad to see there are still people awake after this day of brain-melting sessions,
at least for me. I learned quite a lot of stuff. I hope this brings a bit of new stuff or gives you a better
insight in what we're going to talk about.
I'm probably a bit of the odd one out. Since you saw the title, I'm talking about VMware vSphere.
First of all, are there many vSphere users in the audience? Okay, oh wow.
Great. As you probably know, I'm quite keen on PowerShell and more specifically, on PowerCLI, which is the
snap-in and nowadays nearly all modules, but there's still a few snap-ins left to manage your vSphere environment.
Just a minute.
Okay, this slide this is a big thank you from the complete PowerShell community and users to the guys who
made all of this possible for it's now 10 years ago and without them, we wouldn't be here and we wouldn't
have this marvelous tool to automate and manage our environment, so thank you guys.
Much appreciated.
What am I going to do today here? First of all, it's 4:00, so I'm not going to show you hundreds of lines
of codes and I want to avoid the snoring in the room after 5 minutes in, so we'll keep it very light.
What I'm trying to go for is DSC, Desired State Configuration. This was something we're all looking at probably.
It's very interesting. There are a number of reasons why you would use that and my question, already some time
ago was why wouldn't we use this for our VMware vSphere environment?
Now unfortunately, at the moment, there aren't any public DSC resources available that will allow you to do that
and that's where I'm going to try and help or start at least because this is definitely something that will
be so huge once it is usable that it's not a one-person job. So what will happen is I will push some stuff
into the community and I hope there will be some participation from the community on setting up the DSC resources.
The agenda is very straightforward. I'll just tell you about the long and winding road that's in fact especially winding.
Although, I like
all the WMF5 previews, I've felt often like one step ahead and two steps backwards, so stuff that you thought
was implemented wasn't implemented or didn't exactly work as you expected it to work, but now with RTM,
I think we reached the stage where we can start actually using this environment, the 5 version I mean.
The 4 was already available long before that.
For those, this is a quick introductory stuff. Who is this guy on stage, that's me, look ridiculous.
I'm from Belgium, so I had a bit of a trouble to get here, but okay, we got here in the end.
I appear from time to time at VMworld. We have this PowerCLI reference for those of you that are busy with vSphere.
I suppose you know that book.
Second edition just came out last February, so the shameless plug, go, and get it, but okay it's up to you.
I'm most of the time, as you can see on the right I put some pictures with my partner in crime, Alan Renouf,
which is probably also well known. Who, by the way, is using his vCheck module here?
Okay, that's not as much as we normally, but okay great. If you don't know it, you should check it out.
It allows you to schedule reports of your complete vSphere environment.