Are there any questions? Yep. (Audience question) Sorry, can you? Have you gotten some extra VMs themselves,
CPUs, memory VA, just substantial things like that? If I write the resource for the VM, yeah, that will be.
Have you got there yet? No, that's what I said. I first need to network before I can actually create a VM.
I know and I think Brandon is in the audience, he has a resource where you can create a VM.
I wanted to start from the bottom-up, he started from top-down, so that's, but I hope that we can reuse some
of his code in this environment.
Anymore questions? Okay, yeah. Can you see this getting rid of the need for profiles completely?
Yeah, I know what the question is. I got this. Does this eliminate the need for host profiles?
We got that exact same question at the VMworld where the question was more painful than when I have it here, of course.
In my opinion, and since I'm not working for VMware, yes this will eliminate your need for host profiles
because this will do a lot more. But my good mate who works for VMware, he will tell you, ah no, not completely,
you still will need host profiles. (Audience comment) He's convinced of that, but he can't say that you
don't need host profiles. So yes, I think if this is working and it is working 100%, you could because with
host profiles it's a passive thing. If we get this working, that's an active thing.
That's why I would like this monitoring correct. I don't need to suspect a drift and then take action.
I want this stuff to discover the drift and correct it. For the correcting mechanism, would you be putting
host in a maintenance mode, moving VMs? That could be one of the options here.
In fact, what I'm looking at is just writing the resources that would give you that possibility.
It would still be you who writes the configuration files. Yeah. Who decides how far this correction of
drift can go. Yep. Anybody else? Okay. I thank you. I know this is the last session of the day and my brain
was melted with the previous one, so I guess some of you would also be very tired now.
Okay, thanks for coming and enjoy.