So these were a few of the concepts. I had to drop some temporarily, I hope.
But I started working on this thing and this is just a screenshot to give you an idea of my lab.
It's not a home lab anymore. It's sitting in the cloud nowadays, so I can access it here.
I can access it at home. It's a cloud lab. The setup is quite simple.
I have a very simple Windows environment, one domain controller, one pull server.
I have a workstation. I use 10 and 8 to be able to test both flavors of VMF5.
And then I have the famous vEngine and I have a very small separate vSphere environment, in this case,
it's a VCSA, a couple of ESXi nodes, and some storage. I use FreeNas at the moment because that's the
simplest to set up for me.
Okay, most of this is, I already mentioned in the previous slides, it was a bumpy road, so like I said I
often felt that I took one step forward, two steps backwards, but there was progress.
Ultimately, there was progress, especially when RTMF5 RTM became available or available again in February
that I could continue actually progressing on my DSC resources. Most of it what I mentioned here
is already mentioned on the previous slides.
Okay, the virtual, the vEngine box, I started configuring that with the RegistrationKey.
I think most of you know, or if you didn't, you heard it in previous sessions today how you can use this RegistrationKey.
I think the next slide will show you how it works with your,
okay, so you update your Web.config, you point to this RegistrationKey's text, there you put this
registration key, so it simplifies your registration, in my opinion, of your machine, of your DSC client with
the pull server. This is just background info. For the rest, it doesn't impart your DSC, vSphere DSC
resources normally, but that's how I set it up just to make it simple, what I think is simple in this case.
Then the partial configurations on the discussions as I said, but what I'm doing there is I tried, and that was
one of my arguments to use partial configuration, alright.
What we noticed or what I noticed in my environment that the people who manage your storage and the people
who manage your network, they start managing your virtual storage and your virtual network nowadays and they
aren't necessarily your virtual environment administrator, otherwise, your vSphere administrators.
I thought if we pull that apart, it would be easier than the network part how you configure your switches,
what settings are on there that would go to your network team, same for the storage part.
Same for the virtualization part, the virtual server itself, the cluster and so on that would go to your
virtualization administrator or whatever you want to call them in your environment.
So hence this separation. This is just a small sample where I have folders and datacenters and clusters in
separate part of configurations. And thanks to the DependsOn, we could then determine somewhat what should
be there, so you should have a datacenter present before you define a cluster if you're cluster is in a
datacenter, of course. So those simple dependencies can easily be configured in this way, so that's what I
was playing and still playing with at the moment.
This is once you launch this through your vEngine, this is the LCM configuration on that vEngine.
Nothing world shattering in there. It's what you saw several times today, I suppose.
It's a very straightforward standard thing configuring LCM.