Okay, first of all, okay, I saw that most of you are aware of vSphere and VMware.
Just a bit of history on one slide, nothing more than that. PowerCLI was something that they started in 2007.
I was very lucky to get on the early beta. At that time, I think they had about 60 cmdlets, in the meantime,
the last one that appeared to have over 600 cmdlets. One of my pet peeves is they still have three snap-ins in there.
All the rest is converted to modules.
And Alan Renouf's excuse, Alan has nothing to do with the remaining snap-ins.
That's above his authority, but it will come. They will go module all the way once I don't know when and I'm
not working for VMware, so I have no clue about road maps and so on.
One thing that is quite important and I was very happy that this thing was in there from the first release
that's this Get-View cmdlet.
Now Get-View cmdlet, most of you will know it because it is the one that if you're working in larger
environments and I mean thousands of VMs and hundreds of hypervisors, you're well off starting to use the
Get-View because it performs a lot better than the native to the standard cmdlets Get-VM and Get-VMHosts.
But Get-View has another advantage. It allows you to interface or interact with the complete API that
vSphere offers you. So that is the one that allows you to go directly to the objects and the API methods
that are available under the covers.
What PowerCLI is doing, it's doing exactly the same thing. It's packaging these API calls in cmdlets for your
easy use and it makes a selection of the properties that it returns to you.
There's a lot more available under the cover, but PowerCLI and the development team are trying to do there is
this 80/20% they try to cover 80% of your needs by implementing about, yeah what it is it, 20% of the methods
in the API, and I think they did a quite good job, okay. There's 600 cmdlets.
I think most of the stuff that you do on a day to day basis can be done with the cmdlets, but for this
specific environment that we are tackling, or I was tackling the DSC part,
I quite soon realized that I had to go to a direct API calls, and hence, the Get-View cmdlet preference.
Now to give you just a small example, what you can do with Get-View, if I hope it is a bit readable because I
tried to minimize my code and make it large enough. The first screen shot, what you see there is that we
extract information for one specific ESXi node and one of the properties that it returns in this case is the
number of CPU's in that VM Host.
Now with that information, you don't know if it is at one circuit with four cores or four circuits each with one core.
But that information is available. It's just not presented through the PowerCLI cmdlet.
Now if you get to the API, that's what the second screenshot is doing.
It's just a calculated property where we go into the API properties.
You can get that information and that's how we know. Okay, this is from a demo environment I was using.
It's a four circuit, one core box that you see there, so that kind of information, that extra information you
will find by using Get-View and diving deep into the APIs and the properties that it presents.
So Get-View is important
for many reasons. Another thing, a high level view, I didn't know there were so many VMware users in this
audience, but still I will talk briefly about the thing. This is a very high level abstraction of your vSphere environment.
The top item on the right, that is the famous PowerCLI icon, and what that does is that uses PowerShell, and
through PowerShell, it addresses this API. That's the box that I called VI API.
Underneath you have all your vSphere servers. Now one thing that you should remember, the vSphere server can
be all vCenter or that bare hypervisor your ESXi node. Both are called a vSphere server and for both you can
use the same APIs. That is a big advantage. So you can connect to different environments with the same API
methods and find back most of the time all of the same properties.
Once you're there, okay, your vCenter and your ESXi nodes they talk with the vKernel, that's where your
virtualized hardware is translated into physical hardware and your VMs are running also underneath all these vCenter servers.
Just a bit of background. It's important to know what we are talking to and who we are talking with,
so it's this VI API.
Now why would I consider even looking at Desired State Configuration for my vSphere environment?
I put a number of arguments out on that slide. First of all, vSphere is a very complex environment.
If you would just look at classic configuration. Classic configuration, you have multiple components,
you have high availability DRS, DPM, and so on. Each of these in ten has a lot of parameters that you can
configure to control that specific component. So it's a very complex environment and then we fall back into
same argumentation why DSC in general is there. It's to monitor these kinds of environments and to correct
autocorrect the drift that you would have
on such an environment. Somebody makes a mistake, everybody can make a mistake.
It's your junior or your senior administrator, they all can make mistakes.
So that thing would solve the problem of changes and building changes to your environment.
And then the next realization is if you look at DSC, DSC was introduced in 4 already, but it really expanded
availability and the possibilities in 5, so PowerShell is there.
On top of PowerShell, we have PowerCLI. So everything that we require to start using DSC in vSphere,
the toolset is there.
So that is already one big step in the good direction. And for me personally, and I think a lot of other people,
What is quite important with the DSC, you end up with this configuration files and these configuration files
are nothing more than flat text files, which
you can put under source control. So you can align your vSphere environment on a specific version,
put that under source control GitHub bit bucket, whatever you want.
We even use ClearCase for those who still remember what that is.
But you can do it and you can see changes between different implementations of your configuration.
So that was for me one of the bigger
arguments to go for DSC controlled vSphere environment.
Okay. The problem is we mentioned those vSphere servers. It could be a vCenter, it could be an ESXi node.
VCenter, the early implementation was quite easy that was hosted on the Windows box, but not anymore.
You now have the choice to go for an appliance, the VCSA is a Linux box.
Secondly, the ESXi node itself is a closed box. You're not supposed to put stuff on there anymore.
It's for security reasons, but also for support reasons by VMware.
So how would we fix that? We need ultimately we need an LCM agent somewhere.
So my idea was to put a box in between and that is what I call this vEngine, short vEng.
What we do there is we install PowerCLI on there and we install the DSC agent on there and that is the one that
will register itself with the pull server or push server, whatever you want to use in your environment.
That is the client for your DSC configuration and that one will be using PowerCLI, hence the icon at the bottom
there, to talk with your vCenter, vSphere servers.
So you avoid that you have to put anything on the boxes in your vSphere environment.
That's the first principle that I started off. So from there out,
okay, I recap here quickly the argumentation that most of this already was mentioned.
A standalone box rarely use PowerCLI to talk to the VI API, the lifecycle transparency.
If you update your vSphere versions, could be vCenter, ESXi, that's transparent from what you do on this
vEngine that is independent because ultimately, about the only thing that you have between those two is your DSC configuration.
What you and that is something that I try to implement from the beginning, but I had some setbacks,
but it's still on my planning. Most of you
have probably experienced if you run a PowerCLI script, the first cmdlet that you execute, it takes more time
than the second one consecutive cmdlet. That hasn't proved in the latest version, but the reason for that
thing is
this just-in-time compiler that they use. So there are options where you precompile and you do your engines
before you actually start using PowerCLI. And my idea was, PowerShell has an older, big thing that was
introduced in 4, if I'm not mistaken, disconnected sessions. What you can do is you can set up a session,
a remote session to your local host, in that session, you load your PowerCLI environment, you do the
connection to your vSphere server whatever be it an ESXi or a vCenter, and then when you're done,
your environment is set up, you could even start a dummy first cmdlet.
When that is done, you disconnect the session.
Now once your LCM receives the first configuration, it starts, it has to start doing stuff.
He has to start executing cmdlets. Now at that point, he just connects to that disconnected session and
everything would be already there. You would have your PowerCLI loaded, you would have your connection
through your vCenter or vSphere server already present, so you would avoid this over it.
Now I had it implemented, I even have a separate module to manage and control such disconnected sessions.
Unfortunately, we hit the problem where the first call it works perfectly, the first conflict that you arrive,
second conflict is a WMI editor popping up. I'm talking with some Microsoft guys here tomorrow, I think,
to look further into that problem, but it's still on my planning.
Okay. With PowerShell 5 and the DSC options in there and having lived through all the different previews
that we have until we arrived at RTM, I had a few targets that the DSC resources should apply.
First of all, it should be class-based. Last year at
VMworld in August, I already presented some DSC resources, but they were all skid-based, and first of all,
they are slower, and secondly, they still require the handling of this MOF file, which you would divide,
so we decided or I decided to go for a class base that was the first thing.
The second thing I wanted since there are a number of distinct resources in your VNC environment that you can
immediately recognize a datacenter, folders, clusters, and so on, I decided to have a resource module that
would be comprised of multiple files. Apparently, there is an issue with that as well.
At the moment, you can apparently for Java-based classes only use one file, the root module.
You can't use multiple files, multiple pairs and ones this apparently not available at the moment.
So I had to merge everything back into one big file. Not a big deal, but hard to maintain, in fact.
Then partial configurations was a target I set myself quite early, although, after yesterday and some
discussions I had in the corridor here,
there seems to be some doubt if that is still a valid concept to apply in your environment.
At the moment, I'm continuing with partial configurations.
I'm still not 100% convinced that it's always bad, so I think I'll stick with it until the opposite is proven.
But okay, I'm open for suggestions. And then the other concept that I wanted to apply, that's this famous
what-where separation. How you implement the cluster, that client, that part in your configuration files
should be standard filling in the actual values, the name of the cluster, what VMware, what ESXi node should
be in there that should be in a separate part, and that is the part that you could ultimately put under your resource control.
That is the part that will change between different runs of your DSC configuration.