Now one thing that gave me a bit of issues from the very early start is the,
if you look at your vSphere environment, there's an inventory tree, which comprises datacenters, folders,
clusters, resource pools, and so on. This complete hierarchy was conceived historical, so that means some
stuff was edited after the initial concept. So there are some things in there that are not that logical or
that not that obvious how you would reach. For example, look where you can define a folder.
You can define a folder, a yellow folder in this case, you can define a yellow folder on the root of your vCenter
environment, you can define it on the datacenter, yeah, on the date and you can go on like that.
Blue folders, on the other hand, which can contain only your virtual machines, you can only define in your
VM and template infrastructure. So there's a bit of complexity in there.
And before I forget, and on top of that, there are a number of hidden folders that you don't even see in your
WebClient or your vSphere client thinking of datacenters, VMHost, all these folders will pop-up if you do a
Get-Folder, but you won't see them in your hierarchy in the clients.
Now one question I had to answer. If you want to create a new resource, you have to give about where it
should create this new resource and the parameter in the classes, of course, obvious that's the part one,
but the questions I had to ask there and answer more particularly is will I include the hidden folders.
Am I going to indicate that home lab is a datacenter in this case or am I just going to give the name of the
part and let my function be intelligent enough to know that it should be a datacenter or look.
If it is a datacenter, is there a possibility that I have a folder with the same name?
So in the end, I succeeded in creating a function that can find whatever node in your vSphere hierarchy tree
just based on a path like that. First, let me show you.
I made a summary and this is of purpose complex because that's the reality of a vSphere environment.
If you look at all the objects in there and it starts at the top with the vCenter, datacenter, and so on,
but also all the connectivity in there, a one-to-end, end-to-end, folder can be there and there.
This is where all the complex, complex means hard to automate, hard to program in a script, so this is what I
used as a starting point to create that all-purpose find my node function that I included in the resources.
And this is the function, in fact. It uses some internal helper functions recursively, so
I will publish this. I'm not going to run through all these lines.
I know it's 4:00. I'm the one sitting between you and your dinner in half an hour, so I'm not going to torture
you any further. But be aware that these are all the complex function that can handle all these node retrievals
that you need, so it can resolve all these parts that you specify in your DSC resource.
And there's one other thing that is quite important and this was
a very helpful discovery feature that I used. What it does, in fact, when it finds the node or the leaf for
you in your path, it should return normally on an object or a point and the point in vSphere as some of you
may know is called a MoRef, Managed object Reference, which is a specific object type that comes with PowerCLI.
If I was going to use that in my basic Get, Set, and Test functions, I would have to be including statements
with using because they need to know how this object looks. Now the big thing is that you can convert such
a managed object reference to a string and the second big thing is you can use that string on the Get-View
cmdlet to retrieve the object.
So there's no need whatsoever to use a Manage Object Reference object in your basic class functions like
Get, Set, and Test. So this was a very
lucky feature that I could use to my advantage.
And that's the example, so this is from the VMHost resource. This is a helper function.
What we're doing is we had the path and the definition in the configuration file.
He passes this path to this Find-VmwLeaf function. He comes back with a node, if he finds a node, I need to
retrieve the object node as a point. If he finds a node, he needs to retrieve the object, and as you saw in
the previous slides, this is a string, but thank God Get-View with id can use a string instead of an actual
managed object reference object. So that was, I was quite happy that was possible.
Otherwise, it would have become a bit more obnoxious to code on.