But instead of going through that, I want to actually show you a way that you can, I call it abusing native
completers, I doubt, I mean it may be the case that native completers were intended to be able to do this.
It may also not be the case, so results may vary. But I think is kind of cool and in my session on Wednesday
I show kind of an actual use for it. So I've got a real simple, very rudimentary function that I wouldn't
trust outside of this demo that goes through the AST that's passed and tries to do like some fake parameter
binding like what the user actually passed in, right, and it will allow, it will look at the command metadata
if it's available, but it will also allow like a parameter that doesn't exist in that metadata to kind of be bound.
We do this---we're going to set up a little log over here and then what we're going to do is I'm creating a
command that has, it's just show native completer extra info. It's going to have two parameters and down here,
this is the important part, we're going to register our native completer for it and inside the native
completer, we are going to, you see command name is not available, remember that in the ParamBlock it's only
going to get three parameters passed to it, so the CommandName like in a normal completer is not available,
but we'll get that from the CommandAst.
And one thing to note about this, native parameters, so with a normal completer, you could register if an alias
is called, the normal completion engine will be smart to know like you called this alias, but you were
actually looking for this command and it will pull the right completer essentially.
With a native ArgumentCompleter, you're kind of stuck. If you make an alias after the fact, it's not going to
get called here. It's literally looking for whatever command you just typed, it checks the dictionary,
so it checks for the alias name and if it's not there, it doesn't run the completer.
You can register your alias if you'd like, but...
Next, it goes through and calls that Helper function, the parse parameters, and it takes the cursor position
into account because it needs to know what the current parameter name is as well.
Then we get the ParameterName from that and it's just what the helper function output, we get the fake bound
parameters, and then we're just going to output all that information.
So this thing doesn't do anything, except output information, so Show-NativeCompleter, extra in, did I not,
maybe I did not define that. Hold on. Alright, so we can come in and we can type -Parameter1 and you can see,
so we have that information, we have the CommandName up top, we have the ParameterName, the words are complete,
I can type that in. You could see earlier this is just for that little helper function, you see that it's
bound, it's true. It's treating it like a switch statement because it saw that there's a parameter name,
but there's no corresponding, no value that matches that, but what's neat, so you can do that, right,
we can come in and say Parameter2, which was something else so you can now see in the fake bound parameters
at the bottom that it knows something's there for Parameter1 and for Parameter2 and the logic could be changed
so that it, if it knows where the cursor is and nothing's been provided yet, it could just not put that in
the bound parameters. What's neat though, is you could say something like -fakeparameter and you can do that,
and so it'll do there and another one. And so you can see in the very bottom where it's treating though as
you're typing them, you could actually have your
completer go through and check for… Got a question. (Audience Question)
Oh, so that's just all I'm doing there is I create at
the very top here, I just create a file and then I do Get-Content -wait and I'm just doing it in a separate
process right here. But yeah, that's kind of neat. We're running, let's see what time we've got.
We've got a couple more minutes, so any questions about this? I actually do have kind of a use case for this
in my session on Wednesday and if anyone's curious about other stuff with this, you can use it.
And again, it might not be the best idea. I do a lot of stuff that's just playing around at first and then
hopefully good ideas come from that. Sure. Do you have any suggestions on how to parse the arguments for native commands?
Not really. So yeah, I'm not super familiar with doing with that stuff.
What I would say, the TabExpansionPlusPlus module. If you look into that, they have and it's on GitHub,
I've seen other completers that other people have made, so there's a ton of native command completers.
So yeah, I actually originally wasn't even going to cover native command completers and I was like well I
kind of need to do that and then playing around with it was when I discovered this.
This was like two weeks ago and I was like, oh that's pretty neat, I need to put that in.
And I was able to take it and apply it to something else I was working on, but unfortunately, I'm not---
it's just going to be---the CommandAst will tell you, you can easily---let's see.
Let's come in and modify this guy to, so we have access to that Ast outside of the completer.
So with any luck, so if we do what was it, Show-NativeCompleterExtraInfo, we'll treat this like it's net stop
wauserv, right, so when we do that, with any luck, yeah, so we have the CommandAst there.
So this is what we would have had access to inside that completer, so you can see that it's, GetType somewhere,
it's a CommandAst, and so on a CommandAst, you have there's a Get-CommandName, but you also could just take
this CommandElements, so you can see that there are three elements and that's right because we said CommandName,
the word stop, and then a ServiceName. So you could always say that the first CommandElement should be the
CommandName, the next one, if you were doing one for like for net.exe, you could check the next one and you
could see alright it stopped or it start, so I need to go in and start doing stuff.
I need to get a list of services
and you could say it stopped, so let me go get a list of services that are running, and you can get as
complicated as you want with that. The one thing you want to be careful of, anything that's expensive,
IntelliSense will time out after, I don't know, it's like a couple hundred milliseconds, so you don't want to
be the cause of it like hanging. Sometimes it times out and it's super quick and everything's responsive
again, other times it kind of hangs and has trouble stopping. So if you're doing something like expensive
that's going to take a little while to get results for, you may want to try to cache that somewhere.
What we didn't get into was how to tuck this away into a module scope.
If you have a module and you register your completers all inside of it, that part's easy, it should just work
if you want to do that after the fact. And also, if you want to use it with TabExpansionPlusPlus and this
is kind of in the notes on that last demo script. It'll explain that TabExpansionPlusPlus, will strip off,
if you're bound to a module, it will strip that binding and then bind it to its own module, so you have
access to its helper functions like New-CompletionResult, stuff like that.
So it kind of covers a way that you could, you can just call Get-Command, you can get the current command's
info and get its module scope and execute stuff in that. So I think that's about it.
Any questions? Alright, well thanks everybody. I really appreciate it.