So the next thing I want to show you is, it's the last thing we're going to do on ValidateSet, and it's really
a way to, it's really, in my opinion, abusing ValidateSet, taking it completely past what its intention or
what its use is for, but for the longest time before I knew about argument completers, what we're going to
talk about next, I always wanted a way to use a ValidateSet the way that argument completers are used the way
like when you're working in with normal PowerShell commands and they give you that IntelliSense, but you're not
forced to pick what's there. I used to always look for a way to do that and obviously argument completers
are the way to do that, but there is a way you can do it with ValidateSet, again, using dynamic parameters.
I'm not saying this is a good idea, but it doesn't use reflection or anything like that.
Essentially what we're going to do, if we look, so this function is going to do the same thing,
except it's going to allow, let me show you what I'm talking about like I want
Show-DynamicValidateSetExample. Maybe I want to be able to put in wild cards right there and have that
actually bring back those two values. That's not going to work when you're using ValidateSet the way that we
just did because pro* is not a valid folder on there. ValidateSet is doing its job and it's not allowing me
to input that. But if you want to do that, it would look something like this.
So here we're doing a dynamic parameter and this part right here is exactly the same as the previous one.
We get the list of folder names, we create the dictionary, we start to create an attribute collection.
This part right here is exactly the same where we create the parameter and we add the attributes to it and
add it to the dictionary. The difference is this part right here.
So a little bit of background,
when you interactively type a command in PowerShell, the completion engine in the background, to do its job,
it needs to know as much information about that command as possible.
So internally, it's essentially calling like Get-Command to get the metadata for the command.
So it needs, because it needs to know hey maybe they've provided like for Get-ChildItem, maybe they provided
a certificate path or certificate store path, so I need to know that code signing is a switch parameter
that's valid here so that it can actually complete those parameter names.
So when you're interactively typing on the command-line, when it's trying to get the metadata for this command,
it's going to internally call the DynamicParam block
multiple times potentially. I mean you don't really get to control how often it calls that.
So when you do that, the MyInvocation automatic variable, it has a property on it called CommandOrigin.
It has two possible values, it's either internal or runspace.
So when PowerShell's calling that on your behalf to try to Get-Command metadata information, it sees it as,
it was called internally. PowerShell itself called this to try to get some information.
So what we're going to do here is we're going to lie to the engine.
When it's doing it internally to try to get parameter completion information, we're going to tell it that you
need this ValidateSet. And then when the user actually, when you press enter and you submit your command,
that's when the command gets run for the last time. It runs the DynamicParam block.
It runs the begin, and your process, and your end blocks. And then in that situation, we're not going to add
the ValidateSet attribute. Now again, I'm not saying this is the best idea.
There may be reasons that I haven't even thought of that it's a bad idea, but it does seem to work.
So if we Show-DynamicValidateSetSuggestion and we come in---oh one other thing, notice on the other one to show
that end block was much simpler, I just told it to show the PSBoundParameters.
Well in this case,
because we're not letting ValidateSet do its job, we're actually on the hook for doing the validation to make
sure that the user puts something in that is valid. So of course, if you try to use suggestions,
it's going to be the same thing with argument completers. If you allow the user to type anything and you just
provide IntelliSense to help them out, you're on the hook for validating that they actually put,
that they gave you valid input. So anyway, let's come back down.
So it comes up with the IntelliSense. Now can I type in that? I can't.
So that's a way to, again it's abusing ValidateSet. It's not using ValidateSet for its intended purpose and
the way, if you have PowerShell V5, you really shouldn't try to use this for any reason.
PowerShell V5 offers argument completers an easy way for everybody to use them out-of-the-box without doing anything special.
So we're going to---I keep talking about these argument completers, I guess let's jump into them and actually talk.
Before I do that, any questions on using ValidateSet to get IntelliSense or…
No. Alright.