So argument completers.
So what is an argument completer? An argument completer is essentially, it's a ScriptBlock.
PowerShell is going to invoke it when it goes to look to see, when you're typing your command,
PowerShell behind the scenes is doing all kinds of completion events,
so when you start to type Get-Command, you know, as you're typing behind the scenes, there's a global
function called TabExpansion2 that's getting invoked that ends up passing everything you
just typed along with the cursor position and all that stuff into a helper function and that helper function
is pretty complicated, but it ends up figuring out whether or not the cursors on what's probably a command,
or parameter name, or parameter value, and behind the scenes, these completion events are occurring.
And so when you go to start typing, well that should have popped up something, there we go.
So at this stage, you know we could have registered what's called an argument completer and PowerShell would
have known that we've given this ScriptBlock the responsibility of showing the user what valid parameters are available.
And the completers themselves, they're actually just, they are just ScriptBlocks, so we're going to make a
very, very simple one real quick. And you register them, you tell PowerShell about them with this
Register-ArgumentCompleter command. So real quick, this presentation is mostly geared towards version 5,
but almost everything I talk about here does apply to version 3 and 4,
but you do have to do something special. That Tab expansion2 function, or yeah, the function that I mentioned,
in version 3, it doesn't provide an easy entry point into having these custom argument completers.
There's a module, the easiest way to get this available, there's a module called TabExpansionPlusPlus.
It's created by a PowerShell team member. I believe it's the same guy that made PSReadLine.
And essentially, so when I call Register-ArgumentCompleter here in version 5, this a native cmdlet,
but if you have that module, it's going to essentially do the same things behind the scenes.
It sets up, there are dictionaries of argument completers that all this stuff goes into.
So what we're going to do, we're going to register an argument completer for a command called DummyCommand,
which isn't a command yet, its definition is right here, and all we're going to do is output to strings.
Alright, a script, an argument completer ScriptBlock, it's supposed to return completion result instances and
we'll talk about what those are in just a minute, but it turns out PowerShell lets you do a lot of stuff,
sometimes it will get you in trouble and it turns out that a regular string can just be coerced into a completion result.
I'll show you why you probably don't want to do that in a minute.
But this is an argument completer that's just going to tell it that there are two strings that are available
and I just ran Register-ArgumentCompleter. That command has not been defined yet in my session and that's okay
because all Register-ArgumentCompleter did was put this completer into a dictionary and it was associated
with the DummyCommand, CommandName, and the Parameter, ParameterName.
So let's read that in and type out DummyCommand. When I type in parameter, I hit space, nothing happened.
If I hit Ctrl+Space to actually tell the completion engine to bring up the IntelliSense window, you notice,
I don't know if you've noticed this or not, but I'm calling it out so you should notice it in just a second.
There's no little icon right here, that's blank, and that's because we just let those strings get coerced
into completion results.
The completion results are what are used for CommandNames, for ParameterNames, for variable expansion,
all that stuff and you're supposed to tell it what type of completion result it is.
And so in this case, IntelliSense saw that this wasn't a parameter value completion, so that's why it didn't
automatically show it.
But let's go ahead and pick one of these. Now if you notice, I just picked that one.
There's no quotes around that, so it's kind of like what I was saying earlier there was like a bug in ValidateSet.
Well this actually is, in version 3 or 4 there was a bug in ValidateSet that would do this.
This isn't actually a bug though. You want to be able to, and you can and I'll show you in just a second how,
you want to be able to
control exactly what is returned to the command-line as that parameter value.
So it is on you if it's something that needs to be quoted, it's on you to get it quoted.
So another problem with this, I can type in gibberish, and I can press Tab, and it goes through.
So what's happening there, that ArgumentCompleter ScriptBlock, it's doing exactly what it was told.
Every time it's invoked, whatever it returns, that's what the IntelliSense is going to show.
So we told it to output those two strings. So it doesn't care what I have. I can start this with a G and
that should come back with the goodnight string, but when I hit tab, it goes Hello World in that order.
So every single time that ScriptBlock is invoked on behalf of PowerShell, it's going to output everything in that order.
So if we come in and let's first fix the quoting problem, right.
So here's that same completer. This time we're going to fancy it up some.
We're going to take each one of the strings that we wanted to output and for each one, we're going to do a
really bad check for how to whether or not it needs to be quoted.
All this is doing is taking spaces into account. There are other reasons you wouldn't want to quote a string
like parentheses and any other number of them, but for this instance, we're going to treat, we save that
string off and then we determine whether or not we need to quote it, and if so, we add quotes, and then we're
going to end up calling, creating a new completion result. And so, CompletionResult new, so it has two constructors.
We saw earlier that it will obviously allow just a regular string and when you give it just a single string,
it ends up for these three values that take strings, it just uses the same one for all of them.
But here's something really neat about them, they allow you to have different values, this first one,
this CompletionText, that's what's actually going to be put on, that's the value that will be put with the
command, whether or not that's up in the Script pane or down in the command-line.
The next one is what the IntelliSense menu is actually going to show you.
Next, we have the type of completion result and if you're using Register-ArgumentCompleter to do an argument
completer, you're probably always, I don't want to say you're always going to, but I can't think of a time
you wouldn't tell it it's a parameter value completion type. And then you get to provide tooltip texts.
So in this case, we're just going to put the word Tooltip in parenthesis, so you can see that it is doing something.
So we do the same thing, Parameter, and now you notice Hello World and Goodnight Moon, they don't have quotes
around them, but when I press Enter to select one, they do have the quotes.
We still have that problem though where it's not taking into account whatever we typed.
So in order to do that,
that ArgumentCompleter when it's being invoked, it has a lot of arguments that are passed to it to give it
information about the current command that's running.
So instead of just telling you what they are, I'm going to demo it real quick.
What we'll do,
we're going to run, just monitor a little log file here and we will create an ArgumentCompleter for that same
command that's just going to output stuff to this log file that we're watching.
And so, we can come in now and again, try not to override that, DummyCommand -Parameter.
And so, if you look up here, five arguments were passed into it. The first argument is a string and its
value is DummyCommand, so it turns out that first argument is the CommandName.
The completer is made aware of what command it is acting on behalf of.
The next one is a string and its name is Parameter, so that matches up with the parameter name.
The second argument is the current parameter name. The next one, this is blank right now, so if you come over
here and type in gibberish and then invoke that again, you'll see that the value for the third argument is
gibberish, so that's the word to complete, that's what the user has typed in.
The fourth one is a CommandAst object, so you're given the entire abstract syntax tree of the command.
So if you want to do something super crazy and advanced, you can have it.
It gives you all the tools you need to do make completers that depend on other parameters that the user has
typed in at the command-line or you can do lots of stuff with it.
The last one is a hash table and that's, you're going to see that referred to in a little bit as the fake bound parameters.
So you can see where it's got Parameter1 there. If I come in and give it, you know, we'll do OutVariable,
just one of the common parameters and call that again. You can see down at the bottom where it has those,
those are available. So I could do a check inside the completer to see, maybe I need, maybe I care what's in
OutVariable, so I can check and see that. Now it's called the fake bound parameters.
It's not truly, it's not doing everything that the real parameter binder would do once you submit a command.
If you were to try something like this, just put a command inside parentheses and call it, even though echo var
is going to do essentially the same thing as, or effectively the same thing as just putting a string out,
it's not going to bind that. It's not considered a safe value.
You could have anything in there. You maybe call a new item or something like that and you don't want to
actually do that until the user presses Enter, so it's not going to necessarily bind everything, but if you
look in the AST,
you would be able to see everything that was typed, so if you had to, you could still go in and do the hard
work of looking through that. So knowing that, let's now go back and modify our simple completer.
It doesn't look quite as simple anymore, but this is exactly the same as the last time, except we have this
ParamBlock now so that we can use the commands easily by name instead of having to do arg0, 1, 2, 3, 4.
And the only other difference is right here, we do a little filter because remember the ScriptBlock is going
to be invoked and whatever this ScriptBlock sends out, in this case we're going to construct completion results,
but whatever it sends out, that's what's going to be returned in that order.
So if we put a filter here to say these original strings, they need to be like whatever the user has said,
and we have a wildcard on there, so if the word to complete is empty, then it's just saying if it's like any of those.
So let's run that DummyCommand -Parameter and now let's see what happens.
Let's hit Escape. The test right here is, so it went straight to Goodnight Moon.
It didn't go to Hello World, gibberish. So I promise I'm pressing Tab, Ctrl+Space, nothing is happening because
that doesn't match any of the completion results and this is what I would expect to happen
with normal commands that have argument completion.