Yeah, I think we have a little bit of time for this.
Let's talk about the completion order precedence. So earlier I said you can override the completion behavior
of any command and any parameter. Well, I may have said any parameter.
If I did say any parameter, I was actually technically wrong. If a parameter has, if it's an enumeration
type or if it has a ValidateSet, you don't get to override that.
You can put an ArgumentCompleter, register one all you want, but it's not going to let you do it and if you
think about it makes sense because in those cases, you have to pick one of the valid values, and so there's
no need to even return a completion result. There's also next up after that, PowerShell will look for the
type and the attributes. After that, it will check the normal completer dictionary and whatever command
you're running, if there is an ArgumentCompleter that's registered for that command and that parameter
combination, then it will use that completer. If there isn't one registered for that, it'll check to see if
there's a completer registered just for the current parameter name.
If there is, it'll use that.
So after checking that regular dictionary, if no results are returned, it may have found a completer registered,
but if no results were returned from either of those checks, then it falls down to the next step here.
And the next step here is something I didn't talk about and this is a version 5 only thing.
I think they---well so
there is an ArgumentCompleter parameter attribute, so if you don't want to call Register-ArgumentCompleter,
you can actually put your ArgumentCompleter the exact same syntax that we were using earlier with the
ScriptBlock, just decorate your parameter with it when you're defining your function.
But if you have one of those set and you then you call Register-ArgumentCompleter later, it should be the
case that ArgumentCompleter you registered would win out
because this is a called after that. Next, there's the completion engine has some hardcoded completion behavior.
So earlier when we were looking at Get-Command and you saw how name and noun had completion stuff,
that was in there. If you ever notice like
when you call new object, it does type, name completion, all that stuff, there's essentially it's like a
giant switch statement that says well none of these other things returned completion results, so is the
CommandName Get-Command and is it this parameter, okay, then I know what to do.
If there's still by this point hasn't been any completion results returned, then it falls back to those
native completers that we just talked about,
so it checks that dictionary. So even for a normal PowerShell command, it'll check the native argument
completer dictionary for that. And then
if you still don't have any completion results returned, then it just kind of does the whole, let's see,
yeah, it'll just fall back to completing for the current file system, right.
And in here, there's some demo code that kind of shows registering multiple completers and then going in and
watching how they're called and it sets up the little log file on the side.