So let's take that kind of to the next level, alright. So now what we're going to do, I want to show that
you can actually
add argument completers to commands that you don't even own, to native commands if you want to.
I mean you want to be careful with that, but
so I picked Get-Command to kind of pick on. There's you know I---ignore the title, Improve_Get-Command.
It actually---Get-Command as what it does is amazing. Alright, there's nothing, I have no faults with that,
but it'd seem like it would be a command to kind of pick on to show how you could have completers that depend
on other parameters that are being passed in while you're typing on the command-line.
So Get-Command, you know, it obviously it has some completion that happens natively, right.
So if I type in module and bring this up, this takes a little while, it was able to complete that.
It knew the available modules. Now if I type in -Name and hit Space, now this one's kind of funny.
I had to hit Ctrl+Space to bring it up and if you look at that icon, that's not the parameter value icon.
But still, it provided completion for this and it is filtered on just that module.
If I didn't put any modules there, then it should have just had all the commands available.
I can do the same thing with -Noun. This time around it looks like its, the default completion isn't doing
parameter values, so again you have the blank there and I had to hit Ctrl+Space, but this is still filtered on module.
But you can't do something like -ParameterName and try to bring up completions for that.
That's not going to work. It doesn't provide ParameterName or ParameterType completions,
so we're going to try to fix that. Now we're going to skip over the one that's labeled First try.
You guys can look at that later and it's just going to be this exact same completer here, but just with not
quite as much. But what we're going to do, I want to, actually first, before I embarrass myself, we have some
helper functions, this wouldn't have worked earlier or later. We have one called ReregisterCompleter.
What this is going to do
every time we modify that completer ScriptBlock, this things job is to just go in and for every single
parameter or not every single parameter, but all of these parameters, it's going to register this completer
to the Get-Command command and to each one of these variables, so we'll be able to just, instead of having
this foreach, we'll just call Reregister, oops, command. NewCompletionResult, this is just going to be,
this is the helper function and you're going to want to do this
probably. Remember how that simple completer earlier turned into something that's not quite so simple,
it's got a whole bunch of lines. This makes it so that you can just take a string and send it to
New-CompletionResult. It'll figure out if it needs to be quoted.
In this case, this is mostly from the TabExpansionPlusPlus module.
I did that one thing. This isn't the best practice here. It saved a couple lives for the demo, but this is
actually going to take the word to complete into account from its parent scope, you know where it's being called.
Just be aware of that if you try to take this and use it somewhere else since you probably don't want to do
that in your real helper function, but we'll read that in. So now we're going to come down and here's kind of
the neat thing. Since the completer will know the command and the parameter it's working against,
you can do something like this where you use the exact same ArgumentCompleter code for something,
for one command you can just have the same completer code, and in this case, you know, we have a check in the
beginning, this isn't strictly necessary, but if this completer accidentally got registered to another
command, we do a little check to see whether or not we should just return without putting any results out.
If this accidentally got sent to another command, you don't want to confuse the output with completion
results that don't make sense. The next thing we're going to do, we're actually going to call Get-Command on
itself and we're just going to splat the fake bound parameters into it.
So one thing we're going to do though, whatever the current parameter that's being operated on is,
we're going to add a wildcard to that because otherwise, as we're typing a command,
if we type -Module and we type three letters of a module in, that's going to mess your completion results up
later when this gets splatted because that would actually splat those first three letters
to Get-Command. And then we're going to, depending on what the parameter is, we're going to do something,
depending on what the ParameterName is, we do something a little bit different.
So if the current parameter, remember Get-Command has a ParameterName parameter, if its ParameterName,
then we're going to figure out whether or not the ParameterType has been specified and if it has,
we'll filter on, I mean literally whatever Get-Command returned earlier is stored in this ValidCommands,
so we check the parameters dictionary for each one of those and then all the values, we filter them, we sort them
alphabetically and get them a unique value and then send it down the NewCompletionResult.
ParameterType is pretty similar. We're going to, just in that case, instead of getting the keys off those
parameter dictionaries, we're going to get the values and then take their types.
And then if it's any other parameter like verb or noun or name or module, we're going to take whatever those
ValidCommands results are, whatever the results from a call and Get-Command are, and we're just going to
select that property off of the commands. So what should happen…
Question. Sure. Do you have a recommendation or idea when you might want to do multiple completers inside
of one completer like you're doing versus first string multiple ArgumentCompleters?
Yeah, so the
question was do I have any recommendations on when to do separate completers.
In this case, we're taking the exact same one and registering. And it just depends.
You look at it by case by case basis. So in this case, if I were to make a separate one for each one,
there would be so much, all the code would be duplicated, except for this switch statement.
So in that case, it makes sense, they're all doing essentially the same thing.
They're going to call Get-Command with whatever else has been passed
and it's just if you look at it and it looks like you're reusing the exact same code over and over again,
I would put it into one completer. I don't think it would hurt anything to have a separate completer for each one.
I mean, in the grand scheme of things, this is putting everything in a global dictionary that it's not,
it's the same amount of work for the PowerShell engine when it goes to look up hey, alright, I've got this
command with this parameter, is there a completer available? So it wouldn't have hurt to do them separately,
but in this case because the amount of code reuse would be incredibly high, I just chose to throw them into one.
Sure. Another question? Is that okay? Yeah, absolutely. So what is that with
Microsoft.PowerShell.Core\Get-Command? So that's the fully-qualified command name.
I mean and
to be honest, it's probably, so Get-Command is something, so there's an order of operations or a precedence
for different commands, so if I were to make a function called Get-Command, that would actually kind of
shadow the real Get-Command because functions are looked up first and I think aliases are looked up before functions.
So in this case, this is just a way to say go to the real Get-Command cmdlet.
That Microsoft.PowerShell.Core, that's a way that you can access all the core _____?
Well so let's do Get-Command Get-Command and let's see somewhere in there, I guess we have to…
(Audience talking) Yeah, I see that. In the middle there. It may have been.
(Audience talking) I wonder if it would be, hold on. Nope. So it's available from Get-Command.
In a little bit right after here I'll show you how you can actually grab that information.
I don't want to embarrass myself anymore up here. So we'll take that completer ScriptBlock and we're going
to run the ReregisterCompleter, which took that ScriptBlock
and said for Get-Command register this to the Name parameter, to the Module parameter, all that stuff.
So now we should be able to come in and we can limit this to a module and we can do name.
Now remember earlier the name, this was coming back with command completions, that icon was a little bit
different, so this time the completion just popped right up so that shows that it is using our ArgumentCompleter.
Let's actually do like -Verb and Add. Now we can come over to ParameterName.
And so, if this is doing its job, any verb in the PowerShell access control module or any command that has
the Add verb in the PowerShell access control module, these are the parameters limited just to that.
And you can look, there's not that many of them. If we take this and change it and just do ParameterName,
you'll see that it took a little bit longer and there are a ton more that come up.
Same thing for ParameterType, so we can actually take ParameterName and let's say our Name -ParameterType
and you'll see that out of all the commands in PowerShell, again if this things doing its job, then if you're
looking at commands with the ParameterName name, then this says all the commands, there is a SwitchParameter,
at least one SwitchParameter that has the ParameterName, at least one scale or string parameter and at least
one Array String parameter. And actually let's get the counts. So I don't want to cover too much about
what's this is just a modified version we use group object under the ParameterName and ParameterType
conditions in the switch block, but for the sake of time, I'll just kind of demo what it does a little bit
more and you can take a look at it in a little while. But we're at, we're going to add counts to that.
So Get-Command -ParameterName, and so now it has counts in there and you know of course I didn't
show this, but when you press Enter, it didn't have the count information.
That was we could tell the list to show something different than
what was completed. And when you do look at this, it seems like it'd be kind of useful to be able to sort it
maybe on the count and you can do that. You can put whatever kind of logic you want in that completer.
So if I put logic in that said take a look at that word to complete.
Now I ended up doing an exclamation point here because if you do just the less sign, then the completer won't work.
But if I put that in, I told it to change the way you sort it, so now it's sorting by the count, the greatest number
of parameters versus the least number. So you can see that all these common parameters obviously show up the most.
And these counts should change as we add different things to filter on, -ParameterName and let's this time do
it from an ascending order, but you can see all the different parameters.
So instead of the 292 or whatever, it looks like we're down to like 24 that have that.
And that's just an example of a way to show completers that can take other parameters that are being typed
into account in real time.