Alright, so hey everybody. Welcome to the PowerShell Summit 2016.
My name's Rohn Edwards. Today, I'm going to talk to you about advanced parameter completion, so how to get
IntelliSense to help work for you for your commands, even for other people's commands, you know,
commands that you didn't design, how you can add your own completion in.
So I actually don't have any slides. I took the last one out this morning because I found they took too much
time and they were pretty boring and I cover the same stuff in the demo code.
So we're going to jump straight into it. But actually what I'm talking, obviously, I'm sure everybody knows,
but you know, I have just a little demo command where Show-DateTimeCompleter and to be able to get that
completion results to show up like that and to be able to dynamically change into really, really help add a
little bit of polish to your commands.
We're going to start, we're going to very, very briefly cover using ValidateSet to do this.
I'm sure everybody's familiar with that. In the old days, years ago, PowerShell V3 came along and one of the
nice things if a parameter had a ValidateSet attribute, you got tab completion in IntelliSense for free, kind of.
So it wasn't really what ValidateSet was, it's not its main purpose to provide argument completion like that.
It's really for data validation, but as a side effect of that, you got
IntelliSense. So all of this code is going to be available after we're done, so you're going to notice
there's a few regions and code that we just skip over, like I'm not even going to really cover doing a static ValidateSet.
I'll show you that, but I'm sure everybody's familiar, that's in this room, with creating a static ValidateSet
around a parameter. But if
in the past, the problem with static ValidateSets are they are static.
You have to know the values you're going to put into them at compile time, at your function or command
definition time and that a lot of times doesn't work so well. A lot of times you need to know that information
at runtime to provide dynamic ValidateSets to your users.
So the way to do that, of course, is with dynamic parameters. And by the way, can everybody see that?
Is that a good size? Alright. So we have just a real simple, this is what using dynamic parameters to create
dynamic ValidateSets looks like. It looks like a lot of code. It looks kind of scary, but if you've done
anything with dynamic parameters, you're going to recognize what's going on.
You start out, so what we're going to do is create a function that has a single parameter.
It's going to be called FolderName and it's just going to get the, it's going to list the folders at the root
of the C drive. Right, so in the DynamicParam block, we do a directory listing of the C drive and we pull
off just the folder names. And then a DynamicParam block in a function, its job is to return a dictionary
of parameters that have been set. Nor a lot of times you depending on
user provided values at the command-line, you may create a parameter that only makes sense in that, you know,
for like Get-ChildItem, you can directory and file or dynamic switches that are added if you're in the file system.
You get a code signing switch if you're in the certificate provider, stuff like that.
So in this case, we're just going to create a parameter that is created at runtime every single time.
Here's where we create the parameter dictionary that's going to be returned and here's where we actually
return the dictionary at the very bottom and then in the middle is where we define that parameter.
So before we define the parameter, we're going to have to tell it the attributes that we're going to add,
so in this case, we are, we create a collection, and then we add to that collection.
This is a little bit more verbose than it has to be, but I feel like this is a little more readable to
understand what's going on, so we create a parameter attribute. This is the equivalent of having a bracket
parameter, open and close parentheses, just an empty parameter attribute.
And then we're going to create a ValidateSet, so this is the equivalent of, you know, if you had a static
ValidateSet having the ValidateSet inside the brackets, and then in parenthesis, spelling out all the values.
And here's where we create the parameter and add it to the dictionary.
So and the only thing this function is going to do is just return the parameters that were passed to it.
So if we come in here, oops, and don't overwrite the function, but instead Show-DynamicValidateSetExample-FolderName.
So you can see this is the C drive is a little dirty. Actually, I have some random folders I created when I
was going to try to cover a bug that used to be in ValidateSet, but you have to take my word for it.
This was dynamically generated. If I went in and deleted a folder off the root of the C drive, this would change
with it as well. And if you add version 3 or 4 or early, early versions of version 5, then this part right
here might not have worked exactly as you anticipate. It wouldn't put quotes around anything in a ValidateSet
with a space. I do have a work-a-round. I can't really demo it here because it is fixed in the current version
of PowerShell, but what we're going to cover next uses the same type work around.
So anyway, that's what it looks like to create a dynamic ValidateSet.