Alright, so next I want to talk very, very briefly about a different type of completer.
Alright, so those were I'm going to call them normal completers or just completers.
There's also something called a native completer. Native completers are geared more towards external light executable applications.
So it's things that aren't PowerShell commands, but they still have arguments like the net.exe utility.
You can use it to start and stop services and to access shared drives and stuff like that.
So the big difference from the completion standpoint is it has different arguments that it receives.
So when you take a look, we'll do that thing again where we have a little debug log up, and this time we're
actually going to, so this is going to output to that debug log, but it's also going to output some completion results.
This is geared towards, this is for ipconfig. Its arguments are really, really simple, so I chose it.
But the way you tell it that it's a native completer, you call Register-ArgumentCompleter, you give it the
CommandName, and in this case, and then you give it a native switch.
So with normal completers, the ParameterName is what's required and the CommandName is optional,
so I did kind of skip over that. With normal completers, you can actually say anytime you come across a username
parameter, I want you to run this completer, and as long as there's not a completer registered for username
with a specific command, then that one will win out. It will end up, you can have it to where a certain
parameter is always, has a certain completer that gets executed with it.
Native completers, though,
they don't, it doesn't take parameter names into account, you register it to a command, and then you provide
this native switch. Let's take a look at, so now if we call ipconfig and I have to do Tab or Ctrl+Space,
but you can see over here, this time we got three arguments. So the first one is the word to complete,
which is useful, the second one is the CommandAst, and then the third one is the cursor position,
in this case, 17.
So you don't get the CommandName included there. You can grab it from the CommandAst.
You don't get the ParameterName, again you can determine that yourself, and you also don't get the fake bound parameters.
The CommandAst, like I said, if you want to take the time to look into that, you could get all that
information out of it.
So anyway, in this case, what I did was looking at the CommandAst and counting the number of elements that
were here and I don't want to spend too much time on this. Honestly and truly, if you're interested in these
native completers, the TabExpansionPlusPlus module, even if you have version 5, if you go take a look at it,
they have a lot of native ArgumentCompletion because it gets a little bit crazier because you have with
native commands you might have like for net.exe, you have the first parameter determines what your next set
of parameters is and you have all these trees of parameters that end up.
But I wanted to mention this because in just a second, we're going to use native completers for something
that they probably weren't intended for.