the future of PowerForensics
basically I want to move into multiple file system support, so why not be able to parse the extended file
system on Linux or the hierarchy profile system on Mac or the FAT.
I want to start writing parses for like the SQLite databases or ESE databases.
WinPE, so Matt Graver wrote
a WinPE wrapper module that allowed us to basically create a bootable USB drive that has PowerForensics
loaded on it, and so you could go up to a system, plug it in, and boot from that USB drive, and you would have
a clean forensic environment that's on a 1 GB USB drive, and so like for instance in my pocket underneath the
microphone, but it's literally right there. And then
PowerForensics portable, which is the ability to run PowerForensics on a remote system without dropping that
DLL to disk, and so I don't know if we're
going to be to
show this but, it's really a pain in the butt when that messes up there.
Okay, almost there.
Come on. Oh, man. Alright, so that's skills right there. Okay, so the idea behind this is that there is
a function called Get-ForensicFileRecordPortable. I think that's what it says.
I'll walk over here so I can see better. Yeah, and so the idea is that this encoded compress file is
actually the base 64 compressed encoded version of that DLL. We're loading that into memory and then there's
a basically an API for PowerForensics where you can just use the .NET classes.
So in this case, you could run Get-ForensicFileRecord on a remote system over like WinRM or PowerShell
remoting without ever dropping, without the dependency of that DLL being on the remote system, so you're only
touching memory, which is a pretty cool concept. So that's that remoting capability that we're
trying to build in there. Yep, and so that's the end of this. Unfortunately, at the end, everything kind of
got messed up with the display, but if you have any questions, please feel free to see me afterwards and I'd be
happy to kind of demo the portable version or the WinPE or any of those types of things.
Thanks, guys.