initial findings. There's some sort of brute forcing sqlmap.
If you look at the referrer, there's a bunch of sqlmap references.
These webshells were created. Probably didn't need to do that. One thing, another thing that I've found
that's kind of cool is this gourse is kind of a visualization tool, and so okay I've got to figure out where
that thing is, there we go. This is a pain in the butt. Anybody see where my mouse is, alright.
Alright, so gourse is a visualization, so basically, I took that timeline and created this visualization to
show us files that are being created, changes to the file system, and so as you can see, some stuff is happening
down there, right. Something happened that is probably not good.
That's that brute force with all the session files being created.
And then we see over here in this, we see like webshells.zip and c99.php.
It's just kind of a way to visualize the data as it's happening.
I've got to find my mouse again here. Hopefully, this
works. Oh, man. That's oh well.
We're going to do it from here just like this. Okay, so