Alright. Welcome everybody.
This Old Dog, New Tricks Digital Forensics with PowerShell. I'm Jared Atkinson.
I'm from Veris Group's Adaptive Threat Division. I used to say that I was the token defender at Veris Group
Adaptive Threat Division because I work with very smart offensives lines like Matt Graver over there,
but since we've started hiring some more defensive people, so I have friends that aren't just breaking things.
I'm the hunt capability lead there, so the concept of hunting is practicing the assumed breach mentality in an enterprise.
So the basic idea is you have a really large organization, there's somebody out there that probably wants
to gain access to their network, steal data, do whatever they need
to do, and if there's somebody that wants to get in, there's a very likely chance that they will be able to
get in, and so our job is to go in and look through the network as if they have been breached and try to
determine where attackers have been or if there is a presence of attackers.
My background is that I was in the US Air Force on the Hunt team there from 2011 to 2015.
Probably one of my more proud achievements is in last year I had Black Eye, which is a big hacker in
conference in Las Vegas, I won the Minesweeper championship. So before PowerShell was my Microsoft love,
Minesweeper was the original. I'm also the moderator of powershell.com security forum, which if you have any
security questions, please come visit and ask the questions. And I also developed PowerForensics upper IDS
and WMI event, eventing, which are two modules that Matt and I will be talking about Wednesday.
So if you're interested in that, we'll definitely be touching on it.
I also really love forensics artifacts, which is what led me to talk about PowerForensics, so.
Going forward, so I kind of want to set the stage for what PowerForensics was created to do.
When you're looking at forensics in general, forensics is a very touchy word because it's typically the like true definition
has to do with law enforcement, law enforcement process where chain of custody is very important and all these
different things that when you're responding or practicing the assumed breach mentality in a 100,000 node
network, you can't necessarily take the time that a traditionally forensic investigator would take.
Forensics has taken on kind of a colloquial definition that is doing hard drive investigation or analysis,
and so or even memory analysis. So originally back in the day or even today in more law enforcementy-type circles,
folks are actually doing the kind of the image methodology for forensics.
So they'll take a suspected infected system, they'll take DD or something along those lines, make a bit for
bit copy of that hard drive, they'll keep the chain of custody records.
This is very good because it has, it's kind of the gold standard for forensics for the past couple decades,
very repeatable, meaning that any analysis that I do, I can go back to the evidence and reproduce that
analysis for like a court case, things of that nature, and it allows for thorough analysis.
One of the problems is that a typical
forensics investigation is typically going to take around three weeks or so for a single system, so like I
said you have 100,000 endpoints, you don't know if there's a bad guy there, but you need to be able to
quickly determine, make a determination of whether there has been some attacker activity.
You don't necessarily have three weeks per endpoint and you also lose volatile data if you haven't captured that.
Then folks started going into this
kind of collection script concept, so the idea is that I write a batch script and then I'm going to script out
and use PsExec or something along those lines to script out a bunch of tasks.
So maybe
one of the tasks is collect all the prefudge files or make a copy of the national file table, things of that nature.
I'm going to pull it back and then do offline analysis. So you're not taking a full image because in a
terabyte hard drive not all, you know, however many bytes that are really valuable from a forensics perspective.
I'm just getting the files or data that's important for my analysis.
The problem with this is that it's often messy, not forensically sound, right Matt, so that's one of my kind of
big pain points and it often uses
third-party dependency, so things like accessing a file, parsing the artifacts, and support for report capabilities.
So you may use PsExec to get remote execution, you may use
raw copy to copy off a file like the MFT and then you have to use like Analyze MFT to parse the MFT,
so there's tons of different tools that you're using that have to be all strung together and they're not
necessarily created to be put together in that way. So then we kind of move onto this live response,
which is kind of
the concept that I'm pushing with PowerForensics. So the idea is that you're able to quickly triage key
systems in order to determine where you need to look next and determine if something has indeed happened that
you need to investigate. And so the pros are
that it's very fast, forensically sound in the manner that I'm going to be doing it, it's self-contained,
so PowerForensics, the remote access, the file access, and the parsing are all built-in and they all build
upon each other. The cons are that it's not repeatable, so unless you're taking a copy of that data,
you're not going to necessarily be able to use this investigation in court.
So this is more focused towards your advanced persistent thread to write nation state type of text,
so trying to hacks Company X, Company X isn't going to get China to extradite the hacker in order to press charges, right.
So ultimately, it's about stopping them exfiltrating data before they're able to reach their objectives.
Alright, so
my solution to this is PowerForensics. So this is a PowerShell module for live forensics investigation.
I chose to write it in C#, so it's a compiled
C# DLL binary module for speed and things of that nature.
Minimizes the use of Windows APIs, so that whole forensically sound
concept, so attackers can use root-cutting techniques to basically lie to you if you're using the operating system's APIs.
So let's say you want to look at the SAM hive, for example. If you're using the operating system to look at
the SAM hive, somebody can basically intercept that request and know they'll lie to you when you're trying to
get data from them, and so I'm trying to parse it all on my own and not rely on the operating system,
which can be tampered with. Currently, we're parsing NTFS
data structure, so the new technology file system, which is the base file system for Microsoft Windows,
and then Windows-specific data structures like the registry, the Windows event log, scheduled jobs,
pre-fetch files, so on and so forth.
A couple design requirements that I had when I first started is it needs to be forensically sound,
if you haven't noticed, that's kind of my thing, so meaning it parses the raw disk structures on its own.
So all the parsing
code is stuff that I've written myself, as opposed to using some third-party library or some built-in library and
it can't alter like NTFS timestamps, things of that nature, so you don't want to actually affect the data
that you're dealing with. It can execute on a live running host, so that's really important.
I don't want to make an image and then be able to have to investigate that image.
I want to be able to do it on a live host without taking it offline.
It needs to be operationally fast, which I hope I'll be able to show you that here soon.
Lee really helped me on that. So I was at DerbyCon, which is a hacker conference in Louisville, Kentucky.
Lee
sat by me in a class taught my Carlos Perez and we literally just kind of went through on the MFT parsing.
I think it started at like 10 seconds to parse an MFT and we got it down to 4 seconds, so Lee showed me a
bunch of ways to kind of speed up the way that the code was running.
Everything needs to be modular, and so things like, for
instance, I have an invoke forensics DD cmdlet, which is going to allow you to read from a raw disk.
That capability needs to be built upon in order to, for instance, parse the MFT and so on, and so forth.
So everything is built off of each other, right. And then it needs to be capable of working remotely,
which there is,
we're at the proof of concept stage with that right now, so we'll talk about that at the end.