So what? What does this all do for me, right?
Hey, got another demo. So there's a weird bug that I just found that one of these things doesn't work with
the ISE, so we're going to go through the actual shell. So what we're doing here is Get-ForensicChildItem,
so functions similarly to Get-ChildItem, but we're doing it in a forensically sound manner,
so we're using all that stuff that I just showed you behind the scenes, we're parsing all of it,
in this case, we're going to show the children of the C drive. And so in this case, we have, for instance,
Program Files, Program Files x86, Users, temp, Windows, but we also have the hidden files that you don't see
when you just use Get-ChildItem, right, so we add our $AttrDef, which is record number 4, and so remember we
had that $MFT variable that has everything. If we do $MFT and then look at the item adds or the object at Index
number 4, we would see the AttrDef file, so we can actually show that real quick.
And there it is, so C AttrDef, right. So now we're starting to kind of understand what's going on here.
Alright. This is my first time using this little fancy demo thing.
I just didn't want to type all this out, so bear with me. Okay, and so now we have
Get-ForensicFileRecordIndex and we're giving it a path, right, and it's going to do a lookup and determine
what that index is, right, and so,
I don't use this very often, but just to kind of show that we can take a path and determine what its index in
the MFT is. Alright, and then
so yeah, I'm going to kind of speed through this, but Get-ForensicContent is similar to GetContent,
but it does it in a forensically sound manner and we're going to basically read the contents and then encode
it in Unicode of the AttrDef file, right. Again, this we can kind of make out some strings here,
so $ATTRIBUTE_LIST, $STANDARD_INFORMATION, so on and so forth, but there's a lot of stuff going on that we
don't know what it is, right? And so
luckily, there's Get-ForensicAttrDef and we give it a VolumeName of C and it's going to parse it out and tell
us all the information, interpret the information for us. So the AttrDef file contains different attributes
that you're able to use within an MFT record, so things like Standard_Information or File_Name or Data, so on,
and so forth and there's a bunch of other ones that
aren't used very frequently, but they're allowed or defined. Alright, what is this doing?
Alright, so now we're going to do Get-ForensicFileRecordIndex for System32\config\SAM, right.
So we know the SAM has an offset into the MFT of 278072. Yes.
What is the SAM? Yeah, so the SAM is the SAM Hive, it's the registry hive that contains all the information
about users and passwords and all that kind of stuff. So I'm going to show in a second that it's a locked
file and you can't just randomly go and say hey I want to read the contents of the SAM Hive, but we're going
to then do that basically. Alright, so
oh this is kind of weirdly out of order, but Lee really liked this, so you can take Get-ChildItem and do like
the C drive, so we're listing out all the children in the C drive
and then pipe it into Get-ForensicFileRecord, and it will give you the MFT record for each one of those files
so it's kind of a cool thing to show how this functions correctly with typical PowerShell cmdlets.
Did you have a question? Okay. Alright, so oh I jumped ahead of myself, so right now what we're doing is we
want to get the MFT record for the SAM Hive and we're measuring how long that takes.
This is following kind of the directory structure, so that we only have to parse out the things that we need
to parse and that took 587 ms, so less than a second, about half a second.
And then we're going to do the long way, which is basically get every single file record and then we're going
to do Where object and it took 5 seconds,
so we're talking, I'm not a good math person, but 10 times as long to parse that out.
So if you're not actually following the directory structure, then it's going to take much longer to get to
where you need to go and this is using like the .where in PowerShell 5, which is significantly faster than
where object through the pipeline. Alright, so
now what we're going to do is use the built-in Get-Content to try to read the contents of the SAM Hive and
not surprisingly, it says hey this is being used by another process, you can't do that.
Okay, well if we can't do that, then we'll just do it a different way.
And so we'll use Get-ForensicsContent and read the SAM and there's the contents of the SAM hive.
Again, this might not mean very much to you, but things like if you're parsing, nk is like the header for the named
key property or like the vk is the value key. And so you have these, if you're familiar with the registry structure,
you at least see that this is representative of a registry file, so we're in the right track, we're on the right track.
So then we can do things like
we're trying to copy item. Well hey, same problem, you can't copy it, but what we can do here is
Copy-ForensicFile, just kind of showing that concept, and then if I Get-ChildItem, we've copied the SAM out to,
whoops I did get ChildItem on the wrong directory. Oh, come on. Oh, no, never mind.
So I showing that the SAM file is 65,536 bytes, the copy that we created was 65,536 bytes as well,
so we're copying the same size. I would do a hash, but you can't actually hash this in because it's
locked, right. So alright, so now building on top of that, we can do something like Get-ForensicRegistryKey
right, so now we had that whole blob of registry data, which doesn't mean anything to anybody, but we're able
start reading the content. So in this case, we wanted to look in a software hive, right, and this is the
root of the software hive, every key in the root of the software hive.
Then we can do things like interpreting a specific registry key to understand what it means, so a lot of people
are familiar with like
the run keys that autostart programs when you set them, and so we have Get-ForensicRunKey, which is going to parse
the MFT, determine where the software hive is, or the NTUser.DatHive, which is the HKCU hive or well,
there's one, there's a NTUser.DatHive for every user on the system that currently log in users
NTUser.DatHive is the HKCU Hive. But we're going to basically go through all of those and find any autoruns
set to autostart in the run or run once keys. This takes a little while because it's looking through,
oh, never mind,
it's looking through like seven different hives to get this data, but here we see, in this case, like I have
VMware user process set to autorun, so on and so forth. So now we've taken that and we're starting to
actually understand data on the hard drive that we can analyze and determine whether something's going on.
Okay, yep so just again showing the fact that everything that's being output is a proper .NET object where
we can manipulate house properties and methods, so on and so forth.
We also have like, for instance, there's a bunch of timestamps and those timestamps aren't just like strings,
they're actually DateTime objects, and so in this case, I'm showing the BornTime of the record for
the MFT record for the MFT itself and it's an actual DateTime object that you can manipulate the same way you
would manipulate any DateTime object, so that's the
end of that one. Alright, so.