we can look at all this data and start interpreting it, but what's that actually
matter if we can't perform an investigation.
So let's look at a situation. So there's a guy on Twitter, he goes by BinaryZone and he lives in the Middle East,
but he's produced a bunch of forensic challenges to where we has basically, had somebody come in and hack his
system, steal data, or do whatever they do, and then he puts them out there on his website, you can download them,
and then perform forensics or an investigation, kind of practice your skills, and so we're using one of his images.
And so, in this case, it's not technically a live system, but the same concepts would be able to be used
against the live system. For the demo purpose, I want it to be static so that stuff wasn't changing and my
code wouldn't get
jacked up. So in this case, the client does not provide us much information.
They believe a web server has been compromised and that's great.
That's probably more than you'll really get in real life. And they provide a forensic image.
The investigator must find a temporal starting point, so where do we think that the investigation needs to
start on a timeline and then determine whether the web server has in fact been compromised, and if compromised,
provide leads to incident responders.
Whoops,
oh that that's the findings.
Okay, so going back, that first demo with Start-Demo actually went okay.
Let me clear this out here. Alright, so one thing I like to do, so right now it's mounted as H.
We're just kind of showing that there's a bunch of stuff in the H drive.
One thing I would key in on in this, I didn't have this when I started, but the xampp directory is the like
directory that contains like an Apache server, so I might be particularly interested in since the web server
might be compromised and I'd be particularly interested in files in that directory.
Alright,
so we're going to basically store the MFT, there we go. So this is for volume H now, in particular, and then what
I'm doing now is I'm storing all MFT records that are in the xampp directory, right.
And so now that the MFT is a relatively small file system, but it has 62,400 files, and within xampp,
it has 19,473, so we already reduced
the scope of our investigation by 50,000 or so, right, so now we're kind of narrowing in because we have,
in the case of my VM, we had 305,000 records. I don't want to look through 305,000 records.
I want to look through like 100 records at the most, and so we need to start kind of narrowing in to figure
out where we're looking. Alright, so one thing we could do is we could take the items, all of the files that
are in the xampp directory and we could group them based on their DateTime, right.
So when I install an Apache server, a lot of times I'll install everything
at the same time and so we can look for files that were installed kind of out of order or at a different time.
And in this case, we see that 17,000 of those
files were installed on August 23rd and then we have on September 2nd and September 3rd, a bunch of other
files that were created, right, and so in this case, I'm going to store those in a variable real quick and
now I can start referencing like groups 1 is going to reference all files that were created on September 2nd,
in this case. I'm going to sort them by their FMModifiedTime, and so that's the modification time of the MFT record
itself, which is one of the more true indicators of when a file is created.
And then, so as you can see there's a bunch of session files. So a quick Google will tell you that every time
a session is established with that server, a session file is created, right.
And like if you look at the times, it depends on if this is like Amazon's web server, but if this is
just like an internal web server, people probably aren't connecting to this 200 times in 1 second, right,
and so that's kind of strange. Let's see what they did on the third.
So we see one last session and then we see stuff like webshells.php and c99.php, phpshell2.php.
In the incident response field, if you see webshell, that's probably a really bad thing, right.
So let's look at some of that stuff. So we're going to look at the session.
This is the session that happened right before all those files were created, and so we see that
the username here was admin, which might be interesting, and then we're going to read phpshell2.php,
so just for time sake, we're going to look at one of them. There's some weird stuff going on.
We see an IP 192.168.56.102, which might be something interesting.
We see port 4545. Kind of going on, let's go see what else is happening.
So we found an initial pivot.
Looks like something happened on the 3rd of September, so we're going to start building kind of a date window
around the 3rd of September, so
$start now represents the 3rd of September at basically 12:00:00 AM
and then we're going to create an endpoint, which is 1 day ahead of start.
And so this is really cool like one of the cool things about PowerForensics is that everything that's already in PowerShell,
you could leverage, right, so in this case, Get-Date, I'm just building a date window and then I'm able to
take the MFT, oh we already have that saved, but apparently we've got it again, and then I'm able to filter
down and say hey show me files that were, in this case, modified, oh boy, we've got to hurry up, around that time.
And so, in this case, we started with 62,000 and we went down to 22 files, right.
That's a lot better. So there were 22 files, which were created on that day.
So let's specifically look at those files, and so again, we basically don't see anything super new, but we see
that session was created and then we see some temporary internet files that have a reference to that IP address
that we saw. We again see webshells so on and so forth. I'm going to kind of speed through because there's
some cool stuff at the end. Another thing that we are parsing is the UsnJrnl.
So the UsnJrnl is the update sequence number journal, which keeps track of all changes on hard drive.
A lot of times this can be leveraged like by backup software to see what files have changed since the last
time you backed up or an antivirus to make sure that it doesn't waste time scanning everything and it only
_____scans files that were changed since the last time you scanned with antivirus.
But this gives us information about every file that was changed, or modified, or deleted, so on and so forth
over the past X period of time. Usually, a UsnJrnl will keep about three weeks of information,
so we've got to kind of be agile, but we have a little bit of leeway there.
Alright, so the UsnJrnl by default had 12,000 and we got it down in that window to 8,000.
Usually, it's a much more drastic number, but because this is some sort of group forcing going on, there's a lot
of files that are created within our window. Alright, so what we're doing is we're going to look at all the different files.
We're grouping by file name, so we see a lot of activity was associated with ServerManager.log,
so we might want to look at that at some point. We see these weird name files,
tmpudvfh.php. We can see all the phpshell stuff. One thing that I'm interested in because I haven't seen it
before is this guy, php3331.tmp, alright. I see that it's, I just happen to know this, I would show this,
but we're running short on time. This is the MFT record number for that file, so let's go check it out.
Alright, so I just read the contents of that file and its php script that does system and then takes a
variable and runs the command, right. Like that's the most simplistic web shell possible, alright.
It's just going to run any command that licensed to it. Alright, so this is something that I just added.
So there's
not a cmdlet associated with it yet because I've been super busy recently, but basically what we're doing is
we're taking the Apache access log
and we're parsing that out. So we're going to look at every time that somebody tried to connect to the Apache server.
And so this is what an Apache access log looks like. We have things like the timestamp, the method that was
used in the HTTP method, the status that was returned, you get the referrer, so on and so forth, the username.
That one's not a very good example, but. Alright, so now we're going to group them by HttpMethod,
and so in this case, post requests or the Post method is how you put data up onto the server, and so I might be
interested in looking at what data was added to the server, and so this is all the information.
So just down at the bottom, you see c99.php and then act=cmd. That might be worth looking into.
Kind of a cleaner way to look at this is, so we're just going to show just that request there, and so instead
of getting all of the entire object, we're just looking at the request and again we see like the cmd,
which means that somebody might have been executing something on a webshell.
So then kind of the crux of the whole thing, so I've been doing all that analysis kind of in a vacuum,
but I'm really interested in being able to, oh we're not there yet, sorry.
I really want to be able to like look at everything at the same time, right, and so I'm building a timeline
that includes all the different inputs, UsnJrnl, MFT, Registry, so on and so forth.
So what I do is I, in this case, I stored a file record object for
that c99.php and it's just in $record, right, but what I'm able to do is convert to ForensicTimeline and it
takes because there's two different timestamps that are up here, it's going to create two different timeline
objects representative of each timestamp that's associated and it's going to tell me, in this case,
it was modified and changed, in this case it was accessed and born, and so, we can kind of start to get
context around what's going on. So now, what we do is get ForensicTimeline.
Everything's been building to this point. And so, now we're building a timeline.
Right now, it's parsing the registry. It's parsing the MFT of the UsnJrnl, the pre-fetch,
something else that I can't think of, the scheduled jobs. I haven't added the Apache access log, but that would
be really nice to add into this. And then so like this is just going to show the different source types that we're getting.
So in this case,
like lnk files, which are those ShellLink or like shortcut files, MFT entries, USNJFNL entries,
REGISTRY entries were on this guy, and so now we're going to filter them down on based on that window that
we're looking at. Okay just showing how many timeline entries there were 244,000.
We filtered it down to 8,731, so that's a really nice thing.
And then I was just in New York at a conference and Doug Fink showed his import Excel module and so I thought
that was pretty cool. So timelines like 8,700 objects you're not going to be able to just go through like
on the console, so it exports Excel if you use the -shell option, it's going to, hopefully I tested this,
there we go, it's going to pop up Excel for you and now you can like start going through, you could sort
based on the
timestamp and then start going through and look at what happened in chronological order and start to build
context around that situation. You can see what registry items were changed.
So the, I think that's the end of this demo, yeah, okay.
So quickly,