Alright, so the first demo is the forensically sound demo, so I'm going to walk through kind of how you would
actually parse NTFS and how PowerForensics handles it. So the first thing that we
need to do is read from a disk or volume directly, right. And this is where the only Windows API is used,
and so the Windows API that we're using here is the CreateFile API, which allows you to create a read or write
handle, in this case, we're doing read
only, read handle to a physical disk or a logical volume, so think physical disk 0 or logical volume like the
C drive, for instance. And then we're using the
FileStream Read method to read from that handle. This is an example of the PInvoke signature that I'm using
for CreateFile and I'll kind of show that
as we go. The first thing that you're going to run into when you start reading from the physical disk,
it's kind of an eye chart, but just to show is the master boot record and we'll actually show how the code parses
all this inside here. The Master Boot Record is the key there is actually this partition table, and so,
by default, the master boot record has up to four partitions. There's an alternate partitioning scheme
called the GUID partition table, which is going to allow more than four default partitions.
There's also ways that you can make master boot record have more than four.
Ultimately, what we're looking for are things like the partition type
NTFS or the status, which is 80 bootable, meaning that's the bootable drive or the operating system drive.
And then we're looking at the things like relative start sector and total sectors, which are going to tell us
how much or how many sectors, a sector is 512 bytes, are taken up by this logical volume, right, and so now we
know where, in this case, the C drive is or whatever your operating system drive is.
After that, we're going to look at, in the case of NTFS, we're going to look at the Volume Boot Record,
and so this is going to have tons of information about how you should understand
the layout of that particular file system or that volume. And so we have things like bytes per sector,
which in this case, 200 hex, which is 512 bytes per sector, then you have sectors per cluster, which are
8 times 200 hex, which is 4096 bytes per cluster. Those are just helping you understand the geometry of the volume.
And then when you have things like a pointer to the MFT, so MFT first cluster number, that blue one right there,
that's going to tell us where the master file table is. And so if we follow that pointer,
we then find the actual master file table, right, and this is an example of a single master file table record.
The master file table is a metadata file, so it is a file that keeps track of all other files on disk, right,
and so there's an individual record. Each record by default is 1024
bytes. If it's not going to be 1024 bytes, the volume boot record is going to tell you that.
Inside of that, it's going to have a number of different attributes.
So they're not really shown here, but we'll talk about them in a second.
Each attribute, like for instance, the file name attribute, I'll let you guess what that keeps track of, right,
it keeps track of the file's name. A file in this context is either a directory or an actual data file.
In this instance, in this image, we have a data file, so there's a data attribute, which has either contains
the data for the file, if it's a relatively small file or it contains pointers to the clusters that contain
the data for the file and we'll talk about that going forward. Alright, so this is what a
data attribute looks like. This is for a relatively small file.
We're talking because so there are two types of ways that the MFT record keeps track of data.
It can either be resident or non-resident. A resident data record is going to have the data within that 1024
bytes, and so as you can imagine, a file needs to be around like 600 bytes or less in order to be resident,
and so in this case, it just says Hello World, so the data's small enough it fit within there.
In other situations, there's going to be pointers that show you
where that data is, and so this is an example of a non-resident data attribute to where there's these data
runs, which it took me a really long time to figure out how those work, but ultimately, what they're telling
you is that hey I offset 68DC04 for 21CO hex clusters there's data that's relevant to this file and this is an
example of a fragmented file, meaning that there's the clusters are not sequential, so they're spread out
throughout the hard drive, so you have to understand that and then read them all in order.
Then you have this
guy, so instead of so directories don't have data per say, but they have information about files that are
contained within that directory, and so that's what this Index_Allocation attribute is telling you.
It's telling you, in this case, you have let's see HelloWorld.txt contained in there and a file named Test.
And then you would have to follow it back and figure out what the directory's name is,
things of that nature, so we'll show that here in a second. Okay, so now we'll actually start going through this.
Okay, so one thing that I wanted to show, I meant to show this a few seconds ago, so WinDD.exe is a pretty
well-known DD.exe is like or DD is the Linux capability for disk duplicator.
It's supposed to be able to make bit for bit copies. WinDD is a Windows implementation.
One of the things that I wanted to show is that when we actually run Get-PE, which is part of PowerShell's
arsenal, something Matt wrote, we can actually look at the import, the function imports, and so it uses
CreateFile in the same way that PowerForensics is using it. So the idea is that although we're using a
Windows API to get access to the actual drive itself, you have to do that at some point.
So if an attacker is going to attack you, attack PowerForensics, they're attacking WinDD the same way.
So that's the one place where I think an attacker could kind of take advantage of the process, but it affects
pretty much everybody equally. Let me just run this real quick.
Alright. I've been practicing all the little shortcuts and stuff that I forget.