So now we're looking at this again
and we're taking that partition 0 and we're looking at StartSector and we're going to read 512 bytes.
So the StartSector is the beginning of the logic, the bootable volume, right, or the C drive in this case.
So when we read that, again, not very much stuff. What we do see up here is NTFS, which is a good indicator
that we're looking at NTFS volume boot record, but still, not very much stuff to go off of, right.
Let's go back to, luckily there's a Get-ForensicVolumeBootRecord cmdlet, and in this case, we're hard passing
it C: sorry, C: and then you just run that, and now we have the VolumeBootRecord object, and this is what it looks like.
So we have things like total sectors of this volume, the number of hidden sectors, bytes per sector,
bytes per cluster, we have the MFTStartIndex, which is going to point us to,
and this is relative to the beginning of the actual of volume itself, so the C drive.
It's going to point us to
the master file table, so we can start understanding what files are on the disk and start doing forensics on those.
So just for the sake of needing that later, we're going to store that, and then we're going to go down,
we're done with the volume boot record. Okay, now we're back at the master file table, so we're just kind of
doing the same thing, you know, expecting the same results, insanity.
And so, what we did here, let's go back up, so we're looking at the C volume now, so this is what June was
talking about, \\.\C: and then we have vbr.MftStartIndex, then we're multiplying it by the BytesPerCluster,
so because the start index is stored in
clusters, we want to understand how large a cluster is, and the we're saying hey we want to take
the bytes per file record and we want to read one file record, so this is the MFT record for the MFT itself.
Somewhere in here, you see $MFT is the name of the MFT file, so the MFT record for the MFT itself is always
at offset 0
within the MFT, so we always know it's the first record. And so, within that, let's go
back here, we can now interpret that with Get-ForensicFileRecord, right.
So now we see hey that's human readable, right. It makes a little more sense.
There's some timestamps in there. It tells you who the ParentRecordNumber is, so we see that its parent is
RecordNumber 5, which is the root directory. And then we're going to store that for use here in a second.
Okay, now I just kind of wanted to show the different properties.
So these are proper .NET objects, so we have PowerForensics.Ntfs.FileRecord object and there's tons of
different properties more than we're showing, so I have a formatter, which only shows default properties,
but you can see a lot more if you ask. So what we're going to do, for instance there's an attribute property,
which wasn't shown originally. Let's look at that and this is an array of different attributes.
So here's that Standard_Information attribute, the File_Name attribute, which has, whoops,
which has the MFT, the name of the file, and then we have this is one of those fragmented files, so we have
two data runs, which we have to follow in order to find the data within the MFT file.