Alright, so I'm going to be using splatting, which for those that aren't familiar, basically we have a hash
table, each one of these represents an argument that we're going to pass to a cmdlet, so in this case,
we have an InFile argument, which has a value of \\.\PHYSICALDRIVE0 and when we do the @ sign in front of the
props variable, that's going to just splat that out there and assume that each one of those items in the
hash table represent an argument. So just for readability purposes, we're doing it that way.
So Invoke-ForensicDD takes a few different arguments. So InFile is the file that we want to read from,
Offset is where we want to start reading from, BlockSize is how many blocks or how many bytes at a time we
want to read, and then Count is how many of those blocks that we want to read.
In this case, we're going to start at 0, read the first block, which represents the Master Boot Record,
and then we're going to output in text so that we can kind of see what it looks like.
So this is the master boot record for this hard drive, the physical drive 0 on this virtual machine.
You can kind of see down here there's some error messages, invalid partition tables, so on, and so forth.
This guy is the partition table, but that doesn't really make sense.
I don't know about you, but I don't really want to look at that, and so what we can do is we can take that
capability where we're reading that first
sector and we're just going to do Get-ForensicMasterBootRecord,
and so now I've interpreted it for you, right. You have a disk signature in there.
This is the code section. It's actual like boot code that's going to be running when you first start up your
system, and then there's three NTFS partitions on this hard drive.
Okay, so going forward, we can then do like, for instance, Select-Object -ExpandProperty PartitionTable.
There's a PartitionTable array, which is this guy. We just want to see the actual contents of that array,
and so there's partition objects. So NTFS we see that this one is bootable.
It starts at sector 2048, this is all decimal, and goes through to whatever that sector is 1026047.
Okay, so another way to do this same concept is there's Get-ForensicPartitionTable, so kind of skipping past
that select statement there and it does just the same thing as the one to show, we'll see, I don't know,
Ctrl+I, I think. Question here. Yes.
What's the best way to bind to enumerate all of the like physical drive strings?
Is there like a WMI class? Yeah, there's a WMI class. I forget what it is, like Win32 physical disk or
something like that. Yeah, okay. It's in the help File because I couldn't figure out how…
Oh yeah, it's in the help. When I started doing that, I have Jared and I said not all drives are callback, right.
I have CND. Yeah, and so to clarify the drive, right now we're looking at the physical disks, CND would be
the logical volumes, so we're going to get to that point in a second, but for the master boot record, in particular,
we're not dealing with the volumes yet because we're trying to figure out what those are.
Okay, so now I want to, I'm going to skip over this one command, but in general what we're going to do here
is we're going to, this was just showing, the command above was just
showing. We're going to take the bootable partition and we're going to save that to a variable, so that's simple enough.
Alright, so that's what we're doing with the master boot record, right, so we had a string of 512 bytes.
They're just garbly
GIF, we don't know what they were, but then we actually parse them out and so that a human could understand
what they were, right Get-ForensicMasterBootRecord.