And so that ends the Master File Table entry, right. So within that, we want to kind of start understanding
these data attributes, right, and so this is that data attribute just kind of showing that we have it there.
And so we use Where-Object Name as DATA and then we can go ahead and look at our storage.
And then this guy would be kind of a foreach loop, foreach data run
in the data run array. I want you to basically store this or write it all out to a file.
So Invoke-ForensicDD also allows you to output to a file, in this case, we're just going to write,
it's going to go through, in this case, two times and write each time to that file, so let's do that real quick.
It takes a little while. (Waiting) Alright, so now we can come back, and so I was writing out to a
C:\temp\MFT and if we play that, we see that the MFT has now been written
out to disk. So the MFT is a hidden operating system file, which you're theoretically are not allowed to touch,
right, you're not allowed to view the data within it. The operating system is doing that behind the scenes.
It's locked because there are some changes happening to it all the time.
What we just did is we found where the data that is associated with that file resides on disk and we read it
and then stored it in a file. So we never touched the MFT, we just touched the data that is associated with
the MFT, so kind of a roundabout way there.
Alright, so one thing that we've been doing this the hard way. Surprise!
There's a bunch of methods that are associated with the File Record object.
One of them is copy file, and so we could have or also there's also a GetContent, I think that's what we're showing here.
Let's see Ctrl+I. Okay, so now we're just going to GetContent and store that all to the byte variable.
And so a lot faster because we're not writing a disks. We don't have to worry about the I/O there.
And then I just wanted to kind of show the fact, whoops, oh nope, I put the wrong variable.
I changed the variable name and then didn't change it there. Okay, let's see.
Alright, so they're all the same size. So that's just kind of showing that kind of three different ways to
do or two different ways to do it and we're comparing it, we have the same data, well at least the same size
of data anyway. Just trust me this is the same data, I suppose.
Alright, so then I just want to store, so previously, we were looking at a single MFT entry, but if we
want to just grab the entire MFT, this is the thing that Lee helped me speed up.
So we're parsing the entire Master File Table
right now for the C drive. It takes about 4 seconds or so, and so just to kind of the wow factor, I guess,
there are 305,000 entries in the MFT that we just parsed in 4 seconds. So now we can start going through that.
We have all the data
stored in the variable there. Alright and then so one thing I want to show is that the index into the MFT array
is representative of the index into the MFT for that record itself, so for instance, if we look at MFT5 or
the MFT at Index 5, we see record number 5, which is the root directories MFT record.
So just kind of a way to quickly go through the MFT there. Alright, so now we have the root MFT record,
I just showed that, so we need to start being able to understand how the directory structure is built out so
that we can find, I don't want to just go through every single MFT entry to find where like the SAM hive is
because that's going to take forever. I'd have to pass all those through the pipeline, 305,000 records that
just takes some time. So it's better if we start parsing the directory structure to quickly be able to figure
out where like C:\\Windows\System32\Config\SAM is, right, then we only have to technically parse 5ish records.
And so I just stored this record into the root variable and so now we can look at the attributes.
We want to grab the attribute that's called Index_Allocation, so there it is.
It's another non-resident attribute, but this one is contiguous, so just to kind of show there's only one data
run meaning all the data is stored sequentially, and so that makes life a little bit easier, I guess,
and then we're going to store that. And now we can look at the methods here and again we have this GetBytes method,
so we're going to use that to read the contents. And so this is kind of a little hack, I don't actually know
why this is necessary, but PowerShell has a
weird thing to where sometimes it doesn't know that what you're giving it is an array, so this is just a
syntax to say hey I'm forcing you into being an array so that it works cleanly with format hex.
So we're going to run that.
So basically what we're running is index, which is the Index_Allocation
attribute, running the GetBytes method, passing it the \\.\C: so it knows what logically volume to read from,
and then we're going to pass the output, which is just a byte array to format hex.
And so this is what it looks like. Tons of data. The thing that I kind of want to point out is you have things
like Windows, let's see, Users, system, System32, System volume information, these are all records that
represent the files that are contained within that root directory, right, so if you parse that out,
then you'll start to understand what's going on with the file system.
Okay, let's see. And that's the end of that. So at this point, we've talked about how to get from the
Master Boot Record all the way down to the MFT and then started to figure out how we can understand what files are residing in
what directory, so we can start to kind of find our way around the MFT.
Alright. Okay,