So now we're able to monitor for ProcessStarts, for lateral movement, for registry, autorun additions,
but what if you don't have like Windows event forwarding working or you're a consultant like me and the
company that you're consulting for doesn't have the time to set up Windows event forwarding, right.
What we did is we decided to make this what I call the active script generic HTTP consumer, and so as you can
see lots of fun VB script. I never knew that to escape a quote, you had to use three quotes or there's some
weird thing like that. I have no idea. But generally, what we're doing is we're using, we're basically creating
an instance of the Microsoft XML HTTP comma object and then we're using that to basically post data to a
specific listening post or a CIM in some cases. So we've got it working definitely with Splunk, Elk, or Logstash
and we've got it working with QRadar, which is, I think, I don't know who makes that, IBM I think.
And so, what we're doing is we're taking that target event and the reason why it's generic is this works with
literally any WMI, well not every WMI, but all the ones that I've tested it works with and it will basically
create a JSON representation of that object and then post it out to your CIM, which is most CIMs are going to
have some sort of REST ingestion, rest API ingestion. And then basically, we create the
ActiveScriptEventConsumer with that script and tell it we want to use VB script as the scripting engine.
So going back.
Is there a reason you're not using like Invoke-WebRequest or anything like that?
Because we're not relying upon PowerShell whatsoever.
Yep. There's no reason you couldn't.
Yeah, so we want to avoid the like startup of processes and because like PowerShell startup is a relatively
expensive process when you're talking about monitoring every process creation and it will also create or even
a yeah, an infinite loop. Alright,
so what we're going to do is we're going to create a filter real quick.
This is that ProcessStartTrace filter, then we're going to create this ActiveScriptEventConsumer and it's
going to ask me my IP, so I'm just going to do it to localhost because why not.
And so now you see like the IP was filled in. That's pretty nifty.
And then we're going to create a subscription that binds those two together,
so AS_GenericHTTP ProcessStartTrace. Next what I want to do, so right now I am literally every process that's created.
I'm sending out an HTTP POST request to my localhost. This is really small.
Can you guys actually see that?
Yes.
Okay. It's not like the details of what I'm about to aren't what is it called PowerCat, yeah.
So a buddy of mine wrote PowerCat, which is a netcat implementation in PowerShell, and so we can listen on
Port 80 and then start some random process. And so now we see that consent.exe, which is that what is it called,
the UNC, I think, or yeah. That's the process that's associated with that, and so we see things like
consent.exe, we see the ProcessID, ParentProcessID, SessionID, Time_created, so on and so forth, so this would
literally work with any type of WMI class, in this case, we used the Win32_ProcessStartTrace class.
One thing that Matt eluded to is that you have to kind of when you're looking at intrinsic versus extrinsic
events, Win32_ProcessStartTrace is extrinsic meaning that as soon as a process is created, it's going to fire the event.
Win32_Process can be used intrinsically with the instance creation event, but it's, you have a polling
interval, so you could make that 1 second, but you could also make it a 100 seconds, and so you have a chance
that you might miss processes being created. The Win32_Process class has significantly more information like
the executable path and the command-line and things of that nature, so it's kind of a tradeoff which one you
want to use. Do you want the one that's definitely going to fire or do you want the one that's going to give
you more fidelity on the data. And so, maybe you might even use both.
And so, in theory, there's more going on in the background, but netcat or PowerCat only will capture one
packet at a time.
Alright. How am I doing on time? I'm over, but. Alright, we'll skip over this part.
In general, you can also enumerate WMI event subscriptions using WMI event, so you could do like
Get-WmiEventFilter, Get-NTEventLogEventConsumer, so on and so forth.
That's pretty simple. Okay, so we also created a Register-PermanentWmiEvent to where literally everything is
done from one cmdlet, and so if we show the help of this, again tons of parameter sets, so you've got to kind of
figure out how you want to use it and what.
(Audience comment)
Yeah, yeah. June, please help. And so what we're doing here is we're creating a, we're going to be splatting
again, so we have a Name and MyFirstSubscription, EventNamespace root\cimv2, Query SELECT* From
_InstanceCreationEvent WITHIN 1 WHERE TargetInstance ISA Win32_Process and then we're doing query language WQL.
In this case, we're using a LogFileEventConsumer, so Register-PermanentWmiEvent has access to use all
different event consumer types, and so we're going to write a file called temp\test.log and we're going to
anytime a process is created, we're going to write that TargetInstance to that log.
Does it automatically append?
Yes, yep. Alright, so that's been created all in one-fail swoop.
We can show that we have the event filter, whoops, there, let's see, and we have the event consumer.
So now what I could do is start some random process called Notepad, right, that's a good example.
We'll leave that running for now because remember this is an intrinsic event, so we need it to stay running
for a bit, and then hopefully this file has been created already, but we're just going to get content, and so here's
the contents, there's been a few processes created, right, and so Notepad.exe, scrcons.exe, which is an
artifact of that ActiveScriptEventConsumer run-in. So that scrcons.exe is going to actually execute that VB script
in the ActiveScriptEventConsumer and it does some work to like batch up those ActiveScriptEventConsumer hits.
And then like wmiPrvSe.exe was running as well.
And you could filter for those particular ones that you know were not a problem and are likely…?
Yeah, exactly.
Absolutely, yeah.
You could build that in too.
And so that's where you would want to like store off your filter so that you don't have to constantly remember
how to type that entire thing. Alright. So there's that. Alright, one last thing before we're done is so
when I'm deploying out let's say 20 signatures at a time, I don't necessarily want to sit there and type out
Register-PermanentWmiEventSubscription and let me do this and let me do that one, and so on and so forth.
So we created this concept called like Signature Files, and so what it is it's literally like a custom object
that's going to have a FilterName, a ConsumerName, and a ConsumerType.
This is assuming that in the filter's directory within the uproot module, you have a filter named
EXT-ProcessCreateMethod and in the consumer's directory in the Uproot module, you have an
Nt_ProcessCreateMethod, so there's a little bit of overhead here. It's not just going to magically do it for you.
But that subscription is already defined out. I think there's like 12 subscriptions and all I have to do is
say Install-UprootSignature -SigFile EventLog and this will, the SigFiles are in the Signature directory in
the Uproot module, and so I could, let's see, I have two Basic and EventLogs, so there's like a dynamic parameter,
which will look up your SigFiles for you, and when you run that, fingers crossed, oh well let me clear out everything.
Now you get to see Get-WmiEventConsumer and Remove-CimInstance, so this is how you kill off the ones that you already have.
I've done this a lot recently if you can't tell. Alright, and then we're going to re-run that, install, fingers crossed.
Okay, so now it all installed. It kind of looks like it didn't do anything, but we could do
Get-WmiEventFilter and there's 12-ish filters there, right, it's all just kind of magic,
Get-WmiEventSubscription and we see all see all the different subscriptions, so we can enumerate that.
And that is the end of my presentation.
If anybody has any questions, I think it's lunch time, so I'm really to stay around and answer any questions
anybody has and get in more depth.
Yeah, we'll take them offline. Thank you.
Cool.