Alright so, I'm Matt. This is Jared, and today we're going to be talking about Creating an Agent-less Host
Intrusion Detection System using PowerShell and WMI. So what do I mean by agent-less?
I mean we're not actually installing any software on our targets.
We're using effectively permanent WMI event subscriptions to trigger off certain events and then to use
built-in classes within WMI to respond to those events accordingly all without dropping any MSIs, exes, dlls,
drivers to disk.
A little bit about myself. This is my Twitter handle. Right now, I'm the R&amp;D capability lead with the Veris Group
Adaptive Threat Division. Previously, I was on the FireEye FLARE team doing malware reversing.
And then before that, I did some red teaming on a government red team.
Parts of that, I was enlisted Navy. I was a Chinese linguist. I'm a CDM MVP, although with my specialty
obviously being in PowerShell, although I wouldn't really call myself a cloud or datacenter expert, so it is
what it is. I'm also the creator of PowerSploit and PowerShellArsenal.
I've also got various other modules and repositories on GitHub that you're welcome to check out under mattifestation.
Cool. And I'm Jared Atkinson. I'm the Hunt technical lead. I just got a new job at Veris Group in this
Adaptive Threat Division as well. Former, I was in the US Air Force on the Hunt team.
I mentioned on Monday I was the 2015 Black Hat Minesweeper champion, so before PowerShell there was Minesweeper
and I was obsessive compulsive with that as well. I'm the moderator of the powershell.com security forum,
which if you have PowerShell security questions, please come ask them and we'll try to help you out.
And then I developed PowerForensics, WMIEvent, and Uproot IDS, which the last two we will be talking about today.
Alright, so generally, what is Uproot. I'm kind of setting the stage.
Uproot is a host-based intrusion detection system built on permanent WMI event subscriptions, so
permanent WMI event subscriptions allow you to monitor for changes in the operating system and why not
monitor for activities that may be associated with an intrusion.
That was kind of the thought process.
And it leverages this WmiEvent module to easily manage subscriptions.
What is WmiEvent you might ask? Well it's a PowerShell module that abstracts the complexities of permanent
WMI event subscriptions. So
WMI event subscriptions, there's a lot of background knowledge that you need to have in order to get them working,
and so WmiEvent is trying to kind of bridge that gap for kind of a new user of WMI event subscriptions to be
able to easily create and modify these subscriptions.
That's a CDXML module, right?
The base is built on CDXML, yeah.
Sweet.
Okay, so a little motivation behind our work here. In my previous job, we were investigating the group known
as APT29 and some of the techniques and tools that they used involved using permanent WMI event subscriptions,
both as a persistence mechanism, right, so their code would execute after boot every time and also as like a
covert storage mechanism, so they were using the WMI repository itself as a means of storing their payloads
and what that enabled them to do was both store their payloads, perform persistence, and also execute those
payloads entirely remotely using nothing but WMI, which is pretty cool.
So a buddy of mine during our holiday party was asking me because that they were, I mean they were kind of down
in the weeds investigating this really extensive breach that had occurred and he was already pretty experienced
with WMI permanent event subscriptions, but he was kind of curious like, so he asked me how would you go about
detecting the like WMI persistence, right, so in other words, the creation of permanent WMI event subscriptions.
So I started thinking and actually it occurred to me like you could use, you could create a permanent WMI event
subscription to detect the creation of permanent WMI event subscriptions.
So that's what kind of lead me down this path to think that there's like, there's all these built-in WMI methods,
or sorry, WMI events and classes that you could potentially trigger off of to detect all kinds of malicious actions.
And so it is actually kind of an interesting concept because before Matt and I actually knew each other,
we both came up with the idea of using permanent WMI event subscriptions as an IDS completely on our own and
then like the genesis of our relationship, I guess, was talking about this concept, so that was pretty neat.
The reason why I kind of came about it was I was in the Air Force and as you can imagine, the DOD in general was
very specific on what type of software can be added to their systems and there's a very long change process,
and so we were often running into issues with being able to push out continuous monitoring applications,
and so one of the reasons why I got interested in PowerShell is if you could script it, then it's not considered
a software change, and so you could literally script anything. And so, the idea
was to create a continuous monitoring capability that leveraged WMI and PowerShell as a mechanism to monitor
for adversary intrusions. And now as a consultant, I still have that same kind of idea, right, so as a
consultant, I can't go into a Fortune 100 company and say hey guys you're just going to randomly deploy this
software that I'm giving you. We could just go in and make changes to configuration as opposed to actually
changes in software deployment.
And the great thing about WMI is that it's been preset on every version of Windows going back to like Windows 98.
So theoretically, you could use like say the v3 CIM cmdlets to administer a Windows 98 box, although,
I think you'd have to install WMI, I think, by default it comes installed in like Windows XP and above.
Correct me if I'm wrong. But I actually use the CIM cmdlets very often to do WMI tasks in Windows XP where
PowerShell isn't even installed, so it's great. So If you have a capability like this, then all you need is
like your host machine with PowerShell on it to run like these WMI or CIM cmdlets onto and install these like
these signatures on remote systems all without needing to have PowerShell on any of them, just the WMI service listening.