Okay. So as you start thinking about what events you might want to create, think about the following things, right.
So let's say you want to start listing out the things that you'd like to detect, so service creation,
registry persistence, remember I showed you the Win32_StartUpCommand class, that's a great one.
Lateral movement, I'm going to be using this one as an example in a little bit.
WMI persistence, again we've already kind of talked about that, and so go down your list, start writing out
what you'd like to detect, and then start digging through the WMI repository and see what classes might be
able to match up the action that you to detect to what's in the WMI repository.
But before you go down that road, just consider that there might be other detection mechanisms already present,
so like I think it's like in Windows 7 and above, I forget what it was backported to, but you can enable
process auditing anyway, so that's all going to go the event log anyway, so that's all going to go to the
event log, so you may not need to use WMI for process auditing, but you could.
And then Command-line auditing, like Applocker. You can put Applocker into audit mode, like if you wanted to
track all modules being loaded, like all device drivers, executables and dlls that were being loaded.
That would already be logged to the event log if you have Applocker in force or audit mode.
So consider other options first
is what I'm saying. Now if you've determined that you really do want to use permanent WMI events,
consider the following. Go through and discover all of the extrinsic events that exist first because again
those are ideal. They will trigger immediately. And if not, then fall back to intrinsic events and just be
mindful of like the polling interval and whether or not you will miss events from firing.
Okay. Now how would you actually go about determining what classes are available, well we have PowerShell for that.
And then in the latter portion of my demo, I'll also be showing you how I test out my events using wbemtest,
the super old school tool with a terrible UI, but it's extremely useful, it works.
It gets the job done. Alright, so here's my first example. I'm just showing you a local events subscription
using Register-CimIndicationEvent and what I'm interested in is anytime a new volume is attached to my
computer, so by attached, I mean EventType 2 and you'd have to look that up in the documentation and the
action that it will perform upon that event firing is it will just print out the drive name.
Okay. And to register all these events like well especially permanent WMI events, you'll have to run from an elevated prompt.
Okay. I got my handy, dandy SAPIEN USB key here, so let's see if this fires.
Yep. Cool.
And now when I remove it, it shouldn't trigger anything because I've kind of filtered down on the event that
filter a little bit, so
where it will only trigger upon insertion. Okay. Alright, going on.
Here is an example of how you do a permanent WMI event subscription.
So here's what I want to trigger off of. It's the same query as before and then the event consumer that I
want to use is I want to execute PowerShell. Alright, and what I'm going to do is I'm going to pass the
DriveName here and this is how you specify it. So you're passing, an instance of this class is being passed
to the event consumer and here I'm specifying one of the properties of that class, the drive name, and I'm doing
something a little shady here. I'm Base64 decoding the Eicar string, which is like a test string for AV,
so as soon as this drops to disk, in theory, AV should detect it right away.
So I'm going to drop it to my USB stick without any user interaction.
Okay. So just imagine that this would be something like actually malicious that would infect this USB stick
that I'm going to insert.
One thing that we didn't really touch on is that those local WMI events are only persistent within, I guess,
the runspace or within that shell, and so once you close PowerShell out, those local WMI events are going to
just disappear, and so that's why the permanent WMI events, they're going to last through reboots,
they're just going to be there until you get rid of them, so that's why we're going that direction.
Yeah. Demo-ville. Oh.
Just to clarify, you said the intrinsic are volatile?
No, the local, so when you use Register-WMIEvent.
Just trying to think of how I can use this.
Yeah, no problem.
Okay. Alright, are we ready? So look in the bottom right of the screen and hopefully
when Eicar.text drops, Defender will catch it. Oh, come on Defender.
Oh, okay well it should have popped up, but it did actually catch it, so it won't even let me open the file
because it's quarantined. So
(Audience comment)
Yeah. Good job Defender. You catch the obvious. Okay, now I want to show you how I would go about
developing these signatures, so I wrote some helper functions to say I want to list out all of the extrinsic
events within every namespace in the WMI repo. And so I would literally just start going through these one by
one and see if anything sticks out to me. And there was one that stood out to me in the root\cimv2 namespace,
which was this WmiProvider_ExecMethodAsyncEvent, and in the interest of time, I'm not going to go through all
of this, but I will show you wbemtest and just show you that it's sort of my testing methodology here.
So I'll connect to the root\cimv2 namespace, answer a notification query, and so say I'm not quite sure what
is going to fire in here, but we'll just see what pops up. So I suspect that if I execute any WmiMethod that
some instances would pop-up that I might be able to get some interesting information from.
So I'll call the Win32_ProcessCreate method and also I'll pull a value from the registry using the StdRegProv class.
And let's see if we get some stuff that pops up, okay? Okay, so we got two things here.
Now I can double-click on one. There's a little bit of lag time between when you click on it and when you
get this pop-up. I'm going to hide these system properties, so I can see the actual properties of the class here
and what happened was, so here are some of the interesting properties.
So I was notified that the Create method within the Win32\Process class within the root\cimv2 namespace was
executed and what I found to be really cool was that it provides input parameters to that method within this embedded object.
So I can view that embedded object and now I get the raw command-line of what was executed.
So here's like ghetto, but super effective command-line auditing built into Windows, okay.
It's pretty cool.
One thing that we didn't mention also is that the Create method for the Win32_ProcessWMI class is one of the
top lateral movement techniques that are used by attackers,
and so, very frequently to get code execution on a remote system they will leverage that method, and so that's
why detecting it is pretty cool.
(Audience question)
Lateral movement is a, if I'm an attacker and let's say I am able to phish somebody and get access to their
system, I want to start spreading throughout the network to start enumerating and maybe get figure out where
the domain admin is logged is, so I can steal their credentials.
In order to get access to their system, I need some way to execute code on that system, and so that is that
process is called lateral movement.