So once you've grown accustomed to like rooting out these like defensive signatures, here's some examples of
what might be useful to defenders. So we just saw the first one here, although I'm going to filter it further.
So this is what would detect that lateral movement that Jared was talking about.
I'm interested in all method invocations of the Create method within the Win32_Process, so that'll give me
the command-line context of what was executed via WMI, alright. Here if I was interested in any like remote
WMI registry actions, this is what would trigger that. Now here I could do a Win32_ProcessStartTrace on
powershell.exe, but as I was just saying to a gentleman up here, PowerShell is not powershell.exe.
PowerShell could run in the context of any arbitrary process without it being powershell.exe.
So this is the detection that, the signature that I came up with so anytime a module is loaded, so module being
an exe, dll device driver, whose name contains system.management.automation.dll or .ni, which stands for
native image, .dll, then let me know because maybe in our enterprise like we don't have admins running
PowerShell everywhere so on those hosts where PowerShell should not be expected to run all the time,
maybe I would want to be alerted upon that happening.
Or if PowerShell is running an svchost.exe, then you probably definitely want to be notified about that.
Yep. When I was talking about what HT29 was doing using WMI as a covert storage mechanism, they were creating
their own custom classes. Here's a signature that you could use to detect that.
Now
you would eventually get some false positives say like you installed the latest service pack of Windows where
there's going to be a lot of new WMI classes anyway, but hopefully, you'd be able to filter through those
anyway because you're tracking when you're deploying updates.
Lastly, this one's kind of interesting. If you were interested in maybe the attacker doing process
enumeration using WMI, you would be able to detect that using this signature right here.
So yes.
Excuse me, on the left, I got them all, but on the last one, why is that important?
So I wouldn't consider this last event to be super important, but say you're like thread intel has indicated that
within your industry vertical, attackers really enjoy doing process enumeration using WMI, so this would be
able to detect that action. So just by the nature of the attacker running say Get-WmiObject Win32_Process,
this would trigger. Or if they use wmi.exe to do the same thing, it would also trigger, then you could be alerted.
And so from like an auditing perspective, being able to know that somebody, what specifically somebody is
using WMI for is very important. So like typically you'll see like wmiprvse.exe running when somebody's
using WMI, but you won't actually know what class they're enumerating or what method they're calling.
In this case, it would let you specifically determine what method or class is being utilized or enumerated.
That would depend, the utility of that would depend on method that the attacker happened to use or use frequently.
Sure, I mean you could make a very generic subscription and you would catch everything, but probably not
necessarily what you want to do.
Yeah, you don't want these signatures to be super loud. Again, you should filter as much as you possibly can.
Oh, hold on let me set this to.
So while Jared is setting up his portion of the demos, are there any questions that you have?
What's the performance impact?
So the comment was related to performance impact. So that's not something that we've like definitively
quantified in our testing. All we have are like the qualitative results of the fact that, so Jared has
deployed how many Uproot signatures in a large environment?
Yeah so, that we have a client that is a Fortune 100 company that has 60,000 Windows endpoints domestically
and we deployed Uproot to those, and so, and generally, we did some performance testing kind of like looking
at the system that it was deployed to. Let's say we had 16 signatures deployed out and there was very
minimal change from before to after, like literally we're talking like .1 MB of RAM being used and the processor
doesn't even spike at all. And so, I don't know a like specific like we haven't done tons and tons
of testing on performance, but from just like looking at it and kind of playing around with it, we haven't seen
any performance with that.
I can tell you one class to be extremely careful with is CIM_DataFile, so you will experience a performance
hit with doing queries related to that, unless it's an extremely specific event filter that you're using.