Alright, so building on Matt's use case for that lateral movement detection, he showed how we would use
wbemtest in order to kind of detect what's going on for method calls.
We want to go ahead and probably create a permanent WMI event subscription, and so the way that we would do
that by hand, kind of like the old school way, I guess, is that we would have to go onto MSDN, figure out what
the properties that are associated with an EventFilter class are, and then we would by hand create our event filter, right.
And so in this case, I'm using a property hash table in order to allow me to pass arguments to the
New-CimInstance cmdlet, and so, in this case, we have a name, which is EXT-ProcessCreateMethod.
The EXT stands for extrinsic. We want the EventNamespace to be cimv2 and then this is our query, the same query
that Matt was showing where we're looking for Win32_Process and the method name over here is going to be Create.
And then the query language, in this case and most cases, is WQL WMI query language.
And then we're able to store that filter once it's created in the filter variable.
Alright, so that's been created. Next, we'll go, in this case, we want to write events to the event log.
That's the ideal situation because you have things like Windows event forwarding to be able to centralize
your event log. And so, why do some kind of like duct tape solution when you can just write to the Windows
event log, which is the supported login mechanism for the operating system.
And so, what we're doing here is we have an array called the template array and that's going to have the
actual data that will be written into the event log, and so in this case, we want to have an alert that says
lateral movement detected and then we want to store like hey the namespace, the object path, the method name,
and the command executed and then we have the actual properties that the NTEventLogEventConsumer class needs.
And in this case, we found that the WSHEventLog source is the best one and if you use EventID 8, in particular,
you can write arbitrary data to the event log, so that's like the one EventID in a source that just allows
you to write whatever you want, and so Matt I don't know how you figured that out, but.
I was really confused by that. I never really knew how like event sources worked under the hood and I had a
buddy who's really good forensics who kind of dug into that and explained it to me.
So the EventID refers to a specific like template string entry within that event source, so that event source
corresponds to, it's usually like a resource only DLL that within one of its resources is just a huge array
of these template strings, and
NWSH like the eighth string is just basically like a %S format string, which allows you to write any data
that you want using that source and EventID. So that had been documented on the internet like this is what
you would use to write arbitrary data to the event log, but it was never explained why, so that's why.
Thanks Willy.
Yeah, so while he was doing that, I basically showed the contents of the filtering consumer variables just to
show that this is an instance of a filter, event filter class, and this is an instance of an NTEventLogEvent class,
NTLogEvent, I don't know, I can't think of it off the top of my head.
I'm now confused. Okay, and then what we need to do is we need to create the FilterToConsumerBinding and
we're going to pass a reference to the filter and a reference to the consumer.
And so, alright. And so, voila, now we have a FilterToConsumerBinding or a Permanent WMI Event subscription
is the term that we're using for that. Okay, so now what we should be able to do is call the
Win32_ProcessCreate method and we should get an event that's written to the Windows event log.
And so, we're going to try that. Fingers crossed. This has given me some problems a couple times,
but and it's a live demo. Alright, so now what we're going to do is we're going to read from the Windows
event log using the source WSH looking for a message of lateral movement detected.
There should be a couple examples because I've practiced this recently, but here is that cmd.exe.
And so, in general, what we could do is Get-EventLog to kind of show that I didn't have those prestaged
or -LogName Application -Source WSH and then we can do, what is it, Newest 1.
And so that just got written at 18:34 and it's 18:35 on this system, so just showing that actually did in fact
write to the event log just now. Alright, so we have now detected probably the most common lateral movement
technique out there. Obviously, there's tons of lateral movement techniques, and so this is just one of them,
but it's a really good start and there's not a detection mechanism for that I'm aware of in public.
Right, exactly.
Alright. So we're going to move on. Alright, so that was kind of painful, right, and in theory I would have been
going back and forth to MSDN to figure out the different properties and things of that nature, so we wrote
the WMI event module in order to kind of simplify this and extract out some of the complexities, and so we
have things like New-WmiEventFilter, New-WmiEventConsumer, New-NTEventLogEventConsumer to be more specific,
New-WmiEventSubscription. So let's take a look at this.
It's also worth mentioning that Trevor Sullivan wrote the power event or power events module a long time ago
and that's also a great utility. It also has an extremely useful whitepaper that shows you like how to register
these things, how to use wbemtest, and use those notification queries for testing your event, so that's highly
recommended as well.
Alright, so what I'm doing now.
(Audience question)
It's just empty. Don't judge me.
(Audience comment)
Oh good. Yeah, no it's just empty.
Classic June Blender question.
I know, gosh.
June, I have another module that I would like your help on in a little bit.
So yeah, what I was trying to show before I got in trouble was
that now what we have is we have the new WMI filter and there's a specific parameter for every property that
you're going to need to pass to it, right, and so in this case, it needs a name, an event namespace, a query,
and a query language, so I'm just kind of typing those out, Win32_ProcessStartTrace, so this is going to
basically capture every time a process is started. And we've kind of gone away for this example from trying to
do something fancy just to try and do something that we could trigger very easily, and so WQL will fill in automatically.
There's that filter, it's called testfilter, in this case, so then if we do Help Get, this is a fun one,
so whoops, not Get, sorry, New. Alright, so New-WmiEventConsumer.
Like we said, there's five different types of event consumers that you could create and within each or
different event consumers, there are multiple ways to call them, and so there's like 37 million parameter sets
in this situation, and so you can filter through these and try to determine what you want to do.
In this case, we know that we want to use the NTEventLogEventConsumer, so we can do
New-NTEventLogEventConsumer, whoops, whoops, that's not what we want.
Does anyone else know the pain of parameter set common notorial explosion?
Yeah, that cmdlet or that function has I think like 400 lines of parameters, so yeah, that was a pain.
And so in this case, NTEventLog has two different ways that you can use it.
The first example is if you want to do it locally or use the computer name variable or parameter.
If you want to use a CIM session in order to push it out to a remote system over CIM, then you can use the
second parameter set. And so in this example, we want to use a name, a Category, an EventID, an EventType,
InsertionStrings, which are what we want to actually write to the event log and then the number of insertion
strings and the source name, right, so that's a lot of stuff that we would have to remember if this didn't tell us.
Yep, that didn't work. Okay, so name, we're going to call it testconsumer -Category, we'll say 0, EventID.
The things that actually matter in this case are the EventID has to be 8, and then EventType we'll say 2 I
think as a warning. InsertionStringTemplates, I'm just going to write, what did I do, let's see.
ProcessName, so we're going to say ProcessName Started. And so that should be written to the event log.
Let's see what else we need here.
The length, right?
SourceName, yeah, WSH and then NumberOfInsertionStrings is a 1. So I just ran that.
Now I have a test consumer, which is going to write ProcessName has started to the EventLog.
And then, whoops, then what we can do is help New-WmiEventSubscription and this tells us how we're going to
do this, how we're going to create a binding. I just kind of renamed it as subscription because that makes a
little more sense. And so, we can do New-WmiEventSubscription. We're going to give it a FilterName
testfilter ConsumerName or ConsumerType, it's an NTEventLogEventConsumer ConsumerName, and it's going to be a testconsumer.
And so there it is. Now the subscription has been created. So let's go back, well actually, we just start
our random process. Calc. Okay, so calc has been created, so now we can do Get-EventLog -LogName Application.
It's not a security-related talk if calc isn't popping.
Yeah, exactly. Source WSH. And so, there you see in the message, calc.exe started, so now we're monitoring
for process creation. Process creation is obviously going to be a very loud signature, so you've just kind of
got to take that for what that is. Let me go back here and kind of clear everything out.
Okay, so that is the Generic WmiEvent module. Obviously, you don't necessarily for more complicated filters
and things of that nature, you don't want to necessarily remember all of that, and so we've kind of made a
mechanism for storing your filters and consumers and things of nature.
And so in this case, we basically take that hash table and we store it in a file, and then we .source it,
so now once we .source it, $props represents what's in that file.
The caveat here is that you should before you .source a file,
you should probably
know what's actually in that file because you're running arbitrary code.
So yesterday, the PowerShell team talked about how they're coming out with a way to like signature an entire module.
That would be a very good use case here is that you're signaturing that none of the filters have been changed, basically.
Or none of the filters or consumers.
Alright, so then what we can do is we can just splat props, and so now we've created that filter,
so we're kind of trying to make this a little bit easier.
So Uproot has a bunch of these built-in signatures in the form of a hash table, which is then splatted to the
functions that he just showed you.
And so everything is known as props in the way that we've done it so far, so now I just created an event filter
with significantly less typing and then we're going to, actually let's just copy this entire thing,
and we'll run that, and now we've created the consumer. And so what this consumer is doing in particular is
we're monitoring for a Startup command creation, so this is an intrinsic event.
I believe right now it's pulling within 10, so every 10 seconds, it's going to pull and look for a new Startup command.
And one of the reasons why 10 is okay is because if it's a persistence mechanism, then it's probably
going to be there for longer than 10 minutes, if that's what we're worried about.
And so now we can go ahead and create a value in the run key. And so, we're going to create a value called
Jared with an argument of cmd.exe. So as soon as the system rebooted or in the case of the system starting
up again, a command shell will be popped, and so I don't know if that's super cool, but it will get the point across.
And so that was created and now we can check to see that it wrote, and as you can see, I've practiced this
a few times before we did this, but in general, it writes out to the EventLog and says hey an autorun entry was added.