Alright so a quick refresher into WMI eventing. There's really like two event classes.
There's extrinsic and intrinsic classes. Extrinsic are my favorite because they trigger immediately.
Alright so if you've worked with WMI events before, you may have noticed that sometimes you need to add like
a polling interval, so that's a requirement of intrinsic events.
You don't need those with extrinsic, although, you're not getting quite the flexibility per say for extrinsic
events just because there's not as many available, whereas, you can get really creative with intrinsic events.
I always prefer to go to extrinsic first because I know they will fire.
Whereas with an intrinsic event, say you wanted to trigger off of process creation, so if you had like an
InstanceCreationEvent that triggered upon a creation of a Win32_Process class instance, there's a chance that
you might miss that within that polling interval if that process started and stopped within that polling
interval timeframe, so that's why I'm always hesitant to use those, but if I have to, then I have to because
I mean, there's not an extrinsic event for every conceivable event in existence.
So a good example of an extrinsic
event would be like the registry key chained event. So like you would specify the hive and the registry key
and then if there's any change within that immediate key, so like it doesn't work recursively.
It would trigger. And then like I said like with the InstanceCreationEvent as an intrinsic event, you'd have to
specify that polling interval, but you can get super creative. So like there's thousands of these WMI classes
built-in by default in the WMI repository, so really just like use your creativity to think about the possible
events that you might be able to trigger off of using intrinsic events.
Alright there's, using PowerShell, there's really like two ways to register WMI events.
The first would be local events, so using the older WMI cmdlets, you would use a Register-WmiEvent, and then the
newer CIM cmdlets available in v3 and above, you would use Register-CimIndicationEvent.
And most of the examples that I'll be showing you today will be using those CIM cmdlets.
And the great thing about the CIM cmdlets, at least from my perspective, is that they make deployment of
these WMI events and signatures so much easier because they give you the flexibility of being able to use
either WinRM as a transport or Legacy DCOM, right, so if I wanted to use the CIM cmdlets to deploy signatures
to Windows XP, I would just specify the CIM session option to use the DCOM protocol.
And then there's permanent WMI events. So what you need to use for the older cmdlets will be Set-WmiInstance
to create new instance of a set of classes I'll show you. Otherwise, using the CIM cmdlets, you would use New-CimInstance.
With the CIM cmdlets,
there's also like Set-CimInstance, so it's a little confusing, but actually it makes more sense with the CIM stuff.
Set-CimInstance will set the properties on an existing object, whereas New-CimInstance will instantiate a new WMI object.
Whereas, Set-WmiInstance kind of does double duty doing both.
Okay, so in order to set a permanent WMI event, you need the following.
You need an instance of an event consumer class and there are five standard event consumer classes I'll cover briefly.
So the EventConsumerClass, sorry that should just be EventConsumer.
This is the action that you want to perform upon your event filter triggering.
So the event filter is comprised of just AWQL event query and I'll show you some examples of those.
And then
to install the permanent WMI event, you just bind the filter and consumer together using an instance of a
FilterToConsumerBinding.
Alright, so let me run through a few examples here. So on intrinsic events, can anyone tell me what this is
interested in catching. I mean, it should be self-explanatory, I guess.
(Audience comment)
Yeah, so this will trigger anytime a service changes into the running state, so I emphasize changes by using
the instance modification event class. Now if you're interested in a new service being created, then you could
create a query using InstanceCreationEvent where TargetInstance is a Win32_Service.
In this case, the polling interval is 5 seconds that's set within 5.
Yep. So if for whatever reason this service went from a running back to a stopped state, there may be an instance
where you wouldn't catch that, although, I think in this case you probably would.
But again, intrinsic events can be kind of tricky with those polling intervals.
Alright, this one I really like. I love the Win32_StartupCommand from a defensive perspective, it's great.
So this will just monitor for any instances of new Win32_StartupCommand classes.
So what this class is it covers all user and system runkeys and user and system start menu items, so I don't
know if Microsoft had the intent that this would be great for defensive purposes for catching attacker
persistence actions, but that's what we love to use it for. Alright, some extrinsic events.
This one's kind of cool. I'll be demoing it shortly. This has nothing to do with the like volume on your
speakers, rather like disk volumes. So what I'll show you is I'll trigger an event upon inserting removable
media into my laptop.
What's EventType 2?
So I have it pulled up here. The question was what is EventType 2.
So I just pulled up Win32_VolumeChangeEvent in MSDN and EventType 2 is device arrival, so insertion of
removal media or any fixed or removable media.
Okay.
How is that going to care like if I were to dock my laptop on my docking station, would that detect all the
USB-based devices that are already plugged into that docking station?
So the question was would this extrinsic event trigger off of say like you attached your laptop to a docking
station, would it trigger for all of the new devices that were attached thereafter.
The answer is probably no. Unless you had like some like a removable drive plugged into the USB port on there.
I think if it gets registered as a logical volume, so like it gets a drive letter per say, then it will be
registered regardless of how it's attached.
All of the other devices that are registered would be registered as like a plug and play device and there are
WMI classes for plug and play stuff, so you could certainly trigger off like new device creation and what not.
Again, you can be very creative with this stuff and there's a huge WMI repository at your fingertips to
create some of these cool event filters.
Okay, and the last one is Win32_ProcessStartTrace. I really, really like this one again because it triggers immediately.
So let's say I was interested any time Chrome started up, I would be notified immediately with this event.
Okay. So the event consumers, you have five built-in event consumers provided by Microsoft, thank you.
So one is LogFileEventConsumer, so upon an event filter triggering, write some data to a file, and you can
actually pass the arguments provided from the event filter to these event consumers, so you can have like
contextual data provided to the event consumers that you would likely want.
So like in the case here of the ProcessStartTrace, if you wanted to
log the name of the process and the process Id to the log file, you would be able to do that.
ActiveScriptEventConsumer, this allows you to execute any WSH scripting language, so that includes VB script
and J script, sorry no PowerShell.
So Jared's going to show you a case where he uses this to make a call to make an HTTP Get-Request out to like
CIM and report some like security-related information.
It's for the people that like pain, the ActiveScriptEventConsumer.
Yeah. Attackers really like ActiveScriptEventConsumer too. They also really enjoy the
CommandLineEventConsumer, so say you have PowerShell present on the operating system and then you have some
interesting like attacker created event filter and then once that triggers, it would say execute something
like powershell.exe-encodedcommand and then some basic C4 encoded, super evil thing.
There's NTEventLogEventConsumer, so it creates an event log entry and I really like this one because the
event log already captures so much like security-related stuff anyway, but what permanent WMI events allow
you to do is supplement the event log.
For everything that the event log doesn't capture say like the creation of permanent WMI events, you would be
able to write those actions to the event log because those would otherwise never be detected.
And then NSMTPEventConsumer shoot out an email if some event occurs.
Yeah, don't do that when you're like monitoring process creation.
Yeah. Yeah, and as I kind of go through the methodology that we have for creating these signatures or really
when I refer to a signature, I'm referring to a WQL event query, you'll want to be very targeted in how you
create your filter so that they're not firing all the time or that they're extremely high fidelity such that
they only trigger when you know that something really, really bad is happening.