Okay, so we've got four VMs that we're working with that are running on this laptop computer.
They all have PowerShell V5 on them. We've got a domain, the servers, the three servers are running Windows
Server 2012 R2, Server Core and no GUI, which is what you really should be running.
GUI's don't belong on servers. If you do want to use a GUI to manage your environment or somebody on your
team does, that's fine, but manage it from the desktop, don't RDP into the server.
So PC01 is a Windows 10 machine that's, they're all in the same domain.
So for the purposes of this demo, what we're going to be working with is an SMB pull server and for those of
you who haven't worked with DSC, there's two modes of configuration delivery.
Even if you haven't worked with it, you probably know this, but push mode and pull mode, and push mode is the
default and it enacts the---it results in immediate delivery and the then next the configuration.
This script is heavily commented
and this script here is actually already on GitHub, and my presentations, repository uploaded it last night.
Now I have some bonus content. I may not get to that, but I've got to re-upload that one tonight.
So I want to show you, we'll just look at the root of the C drive on DC01.
We've got one SMB file share already and we've set the security on that as well, so Domain Admins has full
control and domain controllers has read access.
Now at one time I was setting my SMB shares for my DSC configurations and my resources, I was setting that to
so domain computers had read access, but believe it or not, not every computer in your domain is a member of
domain computers, and specifically, domain controllers are not a member of domain computers.
So what I've done here, I've actually separated the environmental configuration from the structural
configuration and I'm not going to dive into that topic very much.
It's what I recommend, but if you have questions about that, I actually have a very detailed blog article
that I wrote for PowerShell magazine. You'll find a link in the code here.
And then also there's a good article, there's a lot of PowerShell documentation now on GitHub, if you weren't
aware of that, you can actually contribute to that, but there is a specific article that shows you how to do
this as well.
Now they're actually using a different AccessControl DSC resource than I'm using.
I'm using a SmbShare DSC resource. I've got the links to GitHub, but the AccessControl DSC resource was
written by Rhon Edwards and he spoke on that on access control last year at the PowerShell summit, so you can
find details about it on the YouTube videos. So what I'll do, I'll go ahead and define my structural
configuration, which is the logic. And the environmental configuration, I'm going to store that in a psd1 file.
I do want to show you something here. I'm going to change this just to something else, psd2 because I've seen
that, I've actually seen this written in some books that they say hey you could store this in a different file type.
That's not true.
So if I try to store the data in something other than a psd1 file, I mean you can store it in a variable,
and there are some benefits to shorten a variable instead of a psd1 file.
So if I try to run that and actually that did work, so maybe my testing was not valid.
So let's do text or actually text. (Working) Yeah, so that did work.
So maybe it was PowerShell V4 I was testing that on. Okay, for the purpose of this demo, we're going to
stick with the psd1 file. And see that's one of the things about PowerShell, if you think you know,
nobody knows everything about it, but if you think you know everything about it today, then just wait until
tomorrow because they'll change something.
Okay. What I also want you to notice is how all this code I've showed you so far is formatted.
So format your code for readability. Your future self will thank you for it, as well as your coworkers.
And if you're looking for help online you're going to paste your code, to be honest with you, me, or nobody
else, if we can't read your code, then you're probably not going to get any help, but if it's really easy
to read your code, you're much more likely to get help.
Okay, so I'll just show you the psd1 file that we created. That's what it looks like.
It's actually a hash table and then it's an array of hash tables for each of the shares I'm going to create.
One of these shares already does exist. Okay, we'll create the MOF configuration document and we'll try to
apply the configuration with push mode. You'll notice we got an error message.
So I was in Kirk Munro's session last and he brought up a good point that read the message.
You know, a lot of people they'll call somebody else over to get help from them or even they'll run the command
again and they'll get the same error. Read the error message because generally, it'll tell you exactly what
the probably is. And here, does anybody know why we got this error message?
(Audience comment) Okay, I'm actually highlight it. Yeah, that's better.
There you go. Okay and I'll just go ahead and tell you
it's because we don't have the DSC resources on the domain controller and remember we're running PowerShell V5 here.
So what are my options for getting my DSC resources on the domain controller?
I'll open this up. So you can see those are the default modules, not necessarily DSC resources, but that's the
location I recommend putting your DSC resource in. It's not the only option, but it's the all users module path.