Okay, so we've got a few more minutes, so I've got some bonus content.
What I also do when I do a demo, just so you guys know is I actually write code to undo everything I just did,
so I can actually just highlight this region and we are done with this, so I can just run this and with
Desired State Configuration, I can actually
put it back in the state it was before I started so that way my demo is clean and I can run it again.
Okay, so I'm on my base machine now, so this is live stuff here.
Let's go ahead and import this module. It'll take a second and we'll set our, we'll increase our font,
so people can actually see this. Okay, so the way I designed my tools, I want to show you this MrDSC module.
So what I did I ran a directory of Get-ChildItem on the directory that contains this module.
So what I do actually break down all the functions into their own ps1 file
and the ps1 file is named the same thing as the function. I'm going to show you what the module and the
module manifest looks like and there's some issues you can run into with this.
So I have, I created a Pester test, but it's not a standard Pester test.
I actually wrapped inside a function and parameterized it because it's a Pester test I want to run on any
module and I don't want to duplicate that code. So
when I run that test, it's actually going to go out and test and make sure that all the files in that folder
match the functions to export on the module manifest. So I'll show you what that, so this is what the Pester
test looks like. It's actually a function and I can feed it a module manifest path and all it does, I can give
it modeable, so I can use my like entire Get-Repository and have it go through every folder in there
and it'll make sure that I haven't left out any ps1 files that are functions that should be exported and that
everything lines up, so create tools to create your tools with.
So what my module manifest, this is what my psm1 file, so this is where you would normally have your functions,
so the only thing I'm doing is going through and .sourcing all my functions and I know June Blender recently
wrote a blog article that's somewhat related to this on the SAPIEN blog, so definitely take a look at that.
So if you look at my module manifest, what I found is you actually have to specify all the functions in the
module manifest when you're doing this
because if you use some sort of logic, although it'll work if you manually use import module and import that
module, it won't auto import if it's in the PS module path, the cmdlets won't be available.
And also if you upload it to the PowerShell gallery, it won't show the cmdlets in the list.
Have you thought about writing some things that just build that module every time you update that formula?
Yes. (Audience Comment)
So what I have here, I'm actually going to copy a command from an old version of my Get-Repository.
And by the way, in September, I'll be doing a tech session webinar from powershell.org on Get and using get
with PowerShell and you can do all your stuff right from one interface in the PowerShell ISE.
So anyway, now that I've copied another ps1 file, notice it fails because we're expecting, and you can't see
that, so we're expecting eight functions to be exported and only seven are imported because I copied a ps1
file in there. So I actually have a function that I can run that will give me a list of all the base file names,
which by the way are the functions names. There's a problem with Update-ModuleManifest in PowerShell V5
where I could automate the entire thing, but what I can do, I have to do a little bit of copy and pasting,
but I can pipe that to clip.exe and then I can open the module manifest and I can actually paste it right
here in FunctionsToExport because that's kind of a pain in the butt to update, so then I can save it and I can
run my test again. What my test does, my test actually does a force on importing the module to make sure you've
got the current one.
(Audience question) My tools, I normally don't have any private functions, but what I've see some people do
is create two subfolders and they'll have private in one folder and public in another and then that way they
can control how what's
exposed. Now one thing I am doing, and I'll just tell you what I'm doing, I'm actually when I do
Get-ChildItem to get the list, I exclude Pester test and profiles because I had an issue one day where I had
a problem with a profile and it's because I kept importing the profile.
So you'll notice that's here, so I'm excluding those. So now if we run our test again and we actually that's
where we're at, we just ran that. So I want to show you one more little issue here.
It's really common when you're writing functions, you'll say -Modules PSDesiredStateConfiguration or whatever
the module is. I cannot type. So I don't type in the notes. We'll get it here in a minute.
Okay, so it's really common to do that because things I'm doing are going to require the
PSDesiredStateConfiguration module. So if I go back and import that again, now I want you to notice that
I've got some cmdlets listed. I don't have any cmdlets in my function.
Well the thing is when you write your code like this, you'll end up with anything that you're telling,
I'm going to run this test again, notice the test failed again, but you don't want to use required modules in
your functions if you're breaking them out. You actually want to use, if you go up to the module manifest,
(Scrolling) That's it. I've actually got an example here and we're just about done.
As you can see my cleanup is there. So in my PowerShell toolkit that I have, I'm actually using required modules,
so I have Hyper-V, Pester, PushKit, and PowerShell Community Extensions, so that's what you want to do instead.
So you'll notice in all my functions,
I actually say hey if you're using this separately, then add this line and I put that in as a comment because
somebody can come grab one of my functions and add it to their toolkit without having to grab the whole module.
So we'll jump back to the slide deck real quick and then we'll be done.
Okay, I'd like to thank everybody who has been on the PowerShell team for the past 10 years.
We wouldn't be here today and we probably wouldn't have as good as job as we have if it wasn't for the PowerShell team.
We'd still be a click-next-admin.
Okay, I've got a slide of resources here. This slide deck is on GitHub already as well.
So powershell.org, that's why you're here today and there's a whole list of stuff.
And there's my contact information and that's the last slide. Thank you, guys.