Hey, welcome. So welcome to creating a DSC or welcome to creating a PowerShell Toolkit to Demystify DSC.
For those of you who don't know me, I'm Mike Robbins. I go by Mike F Robbins online.
I'm a Microsoft MVP on Windows PowerShell, a SAPIEN technologies MVP, leader and co-founder of the PowerShell
user group, the Mississippi PowerShell user group, co-author of Windows PowerShell TFM 4th Edition,
author of Chapter 6 in the PowerShell Deep Dives book, winner of the advanced category in the 2013 Scripting games.
You're not here to learn about me, but if you want to know more about me, see my blog site.
I blog every week. I've got about 400 blog articles out there. I've been blogging since 2009 and get most of
my hits from Google searches or Bing searches and I get about 2,000 hits a day, so that should tell you what
type of content I have.
Okay, so I've got some questions for the audience. This one thing of
the sessions I've seen this morning, I'm not just going to get up here and preach to you because I want to
know what level you guys are at before I start that. I don't want to talk over your head, but I don't want
to talk underneath you as well.
So how many IT pros do we have in the room?
Okay. And how many developers? Okay, looks like we've got a mix of people in the room.
So okay, so how many people are using PowerShell V4 or higher?
Hopefully, that's going to be everybody in the room. So hopefully everybody here is writing functions.
Okay and modules? How many people in the room are using Desired State Configuration today?
Okay, good. I'm glad I started with some questions because I probably would have been talking over your head.
I would have assumed that everybody in the room is using Desired State Configuration.
It looks like we've probably got less than half of the room who's using it.
Okay and how many people are familiar with Public Key Infrastructure?
Okay, if you're not familiar with that, you're going to use DSC, that's something you want to invest some
time in learning because that's how you're going to prevent putting passwords in your MOF configuration
documents that are in plaintext and that was a capability that was possible in PowerShell V4,
but in version 5, you can actually encrypt the entire MOF document.
So how many people are placing their PowerShell code in some type of source control system today?
Good, I actually see more hands than I expected.
Okay and how many people are using Pester or some type of unit testing for their PowerShell code?
Good. These are things if you're not doing today and definitely invest some time in doing them,
it'll save you a lot of time down the road.
So what about your---I want to talk a little bit about job responsibilities.
You're here at the PowerShell summit this week, so who is back on site doing your job this week?
You know, if nobody has to be doing your job this week, then are you really needed, you know?
And my question too is do you really trust the people that are there on site doing your job.
Now hopefully, you've automated the majority of your job and I don't know about you guys, but I don't worry
about automating myself out of a job because if I do, then I'll just find another one and do the same thing again.
So anyway, what this session is really about is when you figure something out, create a tool to accomplish
that task and then maybe you want to create some documentation. My documentation is my blog site.
I left early Friday to take my wife out to dinner since I was going to be here this week.
Well my boss calls me after work. He says, hey you know that code you wrote to do X, where can I find a copy of that?
I said I'll give you one even better than that. Just go to my blog site, put in this key word.
It'll be the only article that will come up. You'll not only find the code to do what you want to do,
but it'll walk you through it step by step. So that was the end of the conversation and I was able to enjoy
the rest of my evening, instead of having to get into the system remotely or spend usually most of these more
complicated things, you can spend twice as long on the phone with somebody trying to explain to them than just
do it yourself. But once you figure out how to do something right, a tool to accomplish it because if you
don't do something for six months, unless you're a lot smarter than me, then you're not going to remember the
details of how to accomplish that task. But you write a tool, you figure it out once, you write a tool,
you never have to figure it out again unless things change like from PowerShell V4 to 5 with DSC,
there are some differences. And I've got some tools that it, I try to make my tools version agnostic
so it doesn't matter what version you're using.
Okay, so the content we're going to cover in this session will briefly touch on all this, so we'll talk about
DSC, Desired State Configuration, we'll talk about the Local Configuration Manager, Push mode, Pull mode,
a little bit about DSC resources, some new features in PowerShell V5 as far as DSC goes, we'll talk about
functions, modules, toolmaking, automation. It's not a deep dive into any one of those topics, but we'll touch
on each one of those. So it's time for the demo.