I've got a question. Sure, go for it.
The SMB share for your DSC resources on the pull server, in a push mode is there a way to specify alternate
credentials to get those resources? I'm not sure to be honest with you.
With the LCM, you can configure them. You can configure the credentials on the LCM, but I'm not sure it'll
use those in push mode. So if you're in pull mode, I mean, you can do that.
What I'll do, I'll actually test that after the session, and we'll find out.
Quick question. So if you're using partial configuration to kind of separate which department is handling
which configuration aspect on the system, is there any way to define like an order of operation or handle
conflicts if they were to rise, like set a precedent for like, okay, I have this server admin portion
configuration for always trump whatever conflicts… It depends because if it finds a conflict, it just stops.
(Audience discussion) Yeah, that's what I would think too. I haven't actually tried that, but that's what
I've been told as well. (Audience comment)
Okay, so let's talk a little bit about pull mode. There are some new features in pull mode as well.
So we have a SQL Server, we have all the default settings. What we're going to do is set the Local
Configuration Manager so that it will be in pull mode. This is actually compatible with version 4 and higher,
although, there is a new way to configure it in version 5. And the reason you need to know that is because
when you're querying the Local Configuration Manager, if you're designing a tool, you need to check both
locations if you're going to make your tool version agnostic. You want to check it to say, okay, is it set here,
and then if it's not set, then go ahead and check it somewhere else too.
Check it in the new location because the way you can configure this in V4, it's compatible with V5, so the machine
could be set one way and you'll---my point though will be a little bit clearer once we get this configured.
Okay, so we create the MetaMOF, we go ahead and create it on SQL01, we take a look at the Local
Configuration Manager, now we're in pull mode and we have this DownloadManagerName and we have a SourcePath
up here as well. Usually, you have to expand these properties to see what's really set so you can see what's
it's a UNC path, but it's in a different location on the Local Configuration Manager.
So let's take a look at the modules that the DSC resources that are installed on SQL01.
So you'll notice that I've got one that I wrote probably a year ago that's called cMrSQLRecoveryModel.
I'm going to remove that, so now you see it, now you don't. We're going to define a structural configuration
for both DC01 and SQL01. This is the same thing we did earlier, except we're defining one for two different
servers, two different types of servers. I've got a lot of comments in here that we're going to gloss over.
But like I said, this code is available already. I just want to look at---I want you to be able to see a
specific settings and I think this is actually the same thing I showed a couple of minutes ago.
So we did set a configuration id and we set it to refresh mode and the SMB path, as well.
So what we want to do now, we want to create a tool to automate the deployment of MOF configuration files to
the SMB share. So what needs to happen with that is the MOF configuration document needs to be renamed to
the configuration id on the Local Configuration Manager and then we have to create a checksum, which I already mentioned.
So we'll have a Publish-MrMOFToSMB tool. So if I take a look at that, it actually goes through, it checks several
things, it checks to see if it's in pull mode. If it doesn't, it generates a meaningful error message.
It checks all these different locations that can be defined in V4 and V5.
That way, whoever's using this, they don't have to worry about oh well do this if it's V4 and do that if it's V5
because especially if you're talking to a junior level engineer, the last thing, this is confusing enough as
it is without having to know all the manually know if it's V4 do this and V5 do that.
Okay, so if we look at the SMB share for the SQL servers, the neat thing about this one, it'll actually read
the Local Configuration Manager settings,
so it'll get the configuration id, it'll do it all for you, so you don't have to put anything in manually.
The only thing we're doing is
running the configuration to create the MOF files just like you would normally do, but then you just pipe it
to the command I've created an it's going to do everything for you and put in on the SMB share with the checksum
and all of it.
And if you give it more than one computer name, which I've actually given it two here, if you give it more
than one computer name, if one is not in pull mode, it'll give you a meaningful error message, but it will go
through like 50 servers, and if it's got different settings to find in the LCM settings on the servers,
it'll put it on the different shares.
So when I run this and you'll notice we've got a meaningful error message and I know you can't hardly see that,
but that's for DC01, it's because we're still in push mode, so it stops and it gives the user of it, it says hey
DC01 is not in pull mode, so instead of them spending half a day troubleshooting this.
But now we have our MOF configuration documents for the SQL Server and I'll just highlight this again,
so you'll be able to see it. So the other thing we need, I'll show this one more time, so we use the same
command before and this actually doesn't read the LCM settings, the command, we have to give it the SMB path,
but my thought process with that is normally, you're going to have a MOF configuration document per server
and I know you can have a group of servers and you can actually use the same configuration for multiple servers,
but with the resources, you probably don't want to publish the resource for every single server because
those are going to be, I might be using the PowerShellAccessControl module for multiple servers, and I don't
want to constantly be publishing that out.
So I'll go ahead and publish the required DSC resource out to the share,
I'll take a look at the module folder on SQL01, in addition to that, I'll take a look at the configuration
folder on SQL01 where the pending MOF is going to end up. So you'll notice we have a previous MOF,
we're going to end up with a pending MOF here in a second. We'll pin that folder as well.
So we'll run Update-DscConfiguration for SQL01 to force it to pull the configuration and the DSC resource.
So you'll notice now we have a pending MOF, which will become current MOF once the configuration is successfully applied.
In the background, this is having to load the SQLPS module because I'm setting a recovery model in some SQL
Server databases with this resource, so that's why it took a little bit longer than normal.
But now you'll notice the current MOF was updated. So if the configuration failed to apply it, it would still
be called pending MOF. But also the DSC resource was sent to the server.
Okay. It's going to share the same thing in the event logs, the same thing as before, so there's nothing
really new here to see. It's putting the resources in the temp folder again.
So with PowerShell V5 for a pull server, there's a new location to configure the pull server settings for at
least an SMB share. Well I believe for the web server for HTTP or HTTPS, there's a new location as well.
(Audience question) I know at least the way I just showed is I know that I could actually run, what is it,
Get-DscConfiguration and here on CimSession, you can actually just give it a computer name, you actually don't
have to give it a CimSession. So you can run that. You can also run Test-DscConfiguration, and in V5,
you've got a I believe a detailed parameter on Test-DscConfiguration that'll show you all the details,
not just the tree falls. (Audience question) It's magic. What…
(Audience comment) I don't know the answer to that. That's a good question.
I've got two things. I actually really enjoy blogging. It's probably one of the things I enjoy doing,
so I've got two really good articles I'm going to write from questions in here, so keep them coming.
I think it doesn't need the CimSession because the computer name in front of it.
So if you don't need your credential… So you can see actually it says SQL01 is it says it's false.
Let's look at, let's say detailed. Hmm, that's interesting. (Working)
We'll run this one more time. Yeah,
so I'll have to research that as well because it says it's not in the desired state.
Okay, so what I want to show you now is the DSC settings for an SMB pull server on PowerShell V5.
Not sure where I left off, but it won't hurt if we run this again. So we'll create the MetaMOF,
we'll apply it, and we'll actually, it's called ConfigurationDownloadManagers, we'll take a look at those settings.
So what I'm going to do here is query all three servers and show the LCM settings and I've kind of created
custom properties here, so you'll see these are what I would call it, and actually, we've got WEB01 in there twice.
So I didn't get an error message, so I'm going to run the command again.
I don't know why we had WEB01 in there. I've got gremlins today.
You'll see there's like three different paths you would have to check and we've got this pull mode for two
of them and then we've got a push mode for another one. So if you're pushing out like DSC resources,
you would have to check all these different locations on the Local Configuration Manager.