So with PowerShell V4 and push mode, if I was running PowerShell V4, my only option is pretty much copy and paste
those modules out there. But with V5 and push mode, you can actually automate the distribution of resources
just like you can with pull mode.
Okay, so we'll take a look at the Local Configuration manager settings for DC01.
You notice we have a LCM state of a PendingConfiguration and that's because we tried to apply our MOF configuration document.
I've also noticed that sometimes when you're in that state with PowerShell 5, you'll get this warning message.
There's a cmdlet called Remove-DscConfigurationDocument, so we'll go ahead and run that.
We'll check the state of our LCM again and the main reason I wanted to show you this is that all our settings
are the default, but you'll notice now it's actually idle and we don't get that message since we've removed
that configuration we tried to apply. So what we're going to do, we're actually going to configure the LCM,
the Local Configuration Manager on DC01 to pick up the DSC resources from an SMB file share.
And one thing, there's actually a bug in this, you actually have to set a configuration id, even though it's
not needed for a push mode. So we'll apply the MetaMOF. When you go to configure the Local Configuration
Manager, you actually get a MetaMOF file and I don't know if you saw that here, but it says MetaMOF.
So I'll query the LCM again. We'll actually query it here. So you'll notice we've got this
ResourceModuleManagers property now. So we'll drill down into that, we'll expand that property, so we can
see exactly what was set. So this is what was set. And then we'll take one more look at it, just grab the
settings that I really want you to see. So DC01, we had to set a configuration id because of a bug in
PowerShell 5 and we have it set to a UNC path and we're still in push mode.
So what we want to do, like I said this is about toolmaking, so what if while you're here, your coworker
needs to make a modification to your configuration management system?
Do you trust them to take a DSC resource and put it in the proper file name and the file name is going to be
the name of the root module, it's going to be the version of the module, and then it's going to be zipped and
it's going to be .zip. So that's usually than me, if I didn't have this created, if I haven't done this for
like six months, I would have to look up, okay, what's the details of that.
Or what I would do is go look at it and say, okay, what's one like today?
How did I previously do this?
So the information that you need to create this is actually really simple.
You can run Get-DscResource and I'll specify the two resources that we're using.
So that one command will actually tell us the module name. It'll tell us the version and those are the
resources we're using under name. I'm not a 100% sure in PowerShell 4 that it gave you the version because I
actually used Get-Module to get the version with. So now let's---
in PowerShell 4, there wasn't a compressed archive cmdlet, which they added in 5, and I've actually read in
several places where you couldn't use the .NET framework to zip the file, but I've been doing that and I've
had no issues and you can actually use common object as well and I have an unzipped file function that'll
actually check and see if the .NET Framework is up-to-date, and if it's not, it can use com, so it's down level
to like PowerShell V2. But anyway, I'll just show you this function real quick.
I'm not going to walk you through all the details of these functions.
This one here, of course, it's got comment-based help because if you don't have help, then how are people
going to know how to use your functions. It requires a certain version of PowerShell.
It includes a parameter validation and so on. So now if you're running PowerShell V5, you don't have to
resort to something like that. So to get the file name I was just telling you about is fairly simple.
I want to show you what the file names would be for these two DSC resources and there they are there.
They're ModuleName_theVersion.zip. So all that information is very, very easy to grab.
But trying to figure that out manually is a challenge, especially this week while somebody else is trying to do it.
So you also have to create a checksum for the zip file and that doesn't matter if you're putting the MOF
configuration document out or if you're putting the DSC resource out on the file share or on a web server.
You have to have a checksum and the checksum is actually how it knows that an update is available.
So I can't tell you how many hours that I've spent that I've updated a configuration or a resource and then I
didn't regenerate the checksum. What happens is the server has a copy of the checksum, so it compares the
two checksums, says oh the configuration is the same.
I have a couple more functions here. So I've got one that publishes the DSC resource to the SMB share.
You'll notice all my modules and all my functions I use the prefix administer for Mike Robbins just so you
know why that's there. When you scroll down this one, you'll notice I'm using the New-MrZipFile function.
You could very easily use the compress archive and then also I'm using the New-DscCheckSum command,
but what I try to do, I try to break, I showed you the New-MrZipFile command, I try to break my commands down
so that I'm not writing 500 lines of code in 1 file and I'm not duplicating that code between functions.
I put it in a module and then if I call it with another function, then it just loads that function and uses it.
So I consider that, if you're duplicating data, that's real bad because you're creating technical debt for yourself.
Now redundancy of systems like you want to have more than one domain controller on site, of course,
but if you've got 50,000 copies of basically like the same database, that's really bad because one's going to
get updated and then all the other ones are going to be out of date.
So it's kind of the same thought process with
these PowerShell functions. And I have another one called Get-MrDSCResourcePath that gets the path to the root module.
So for creating a Guid, in PowerShell V4, you didn't have a cmdlet for creating in Guid.
In version 5, you've got New-Guid. So I'll show you the one that I created.
It's very simple. So I can use this, and notice I've got comment-based help, even though it's very simple, that's it.
So and I'll show you this. You know, a lot of times you find commands like that, so let's take one while
actually we can still see it on the screen. Notice the built-in one in PowerShell V5 is a function.
So what that means is it's not compiled, so we can see what the command looks like that they wrote.
So mine was written before they wrote theirs, but of course, we've kind of accomplished the same thing the same way.
So what we can see is we can see exactly how they wrote their command.
Let's make this a little smaller. So this is the SMB file share that we have defined for DC01.
What we're going to do, we're going to publish the resources to that location.
So we're going to run this command and you'll notice in the window they're going to show up.
It's going to be zip files. It's going to be the right name and it's also going to have a checksum.
Wasn't that easier than figuring all that out manually? (Clicking)
Okay, so now we'll look at the domain controller. This is the location and let me make this larger so you can see.
So it's the C, Program Files, WindowsPowerShell, Modules folder.
We're going to pin this open so that we can run a command behind it and still have that window open.
We're going to run the same command we ran before to apply this configuration to DC01.
So what's going to happen this time is it's actually going to pull those resources down from the SMB file server,
even though, we're in push mode and that's, like I said, only available in PowerShell V5.
Okay, so I have another command that I wrote. I don't want to have to figure out how to get the
which event log, there's only one event log enabled by default on DSC and there's a couple other ones that
are not enabled. So I just wrote a command that's a wrapper to a Get-WinEvent to get the commands from the
remote machine
and it has a, I'm using invoke command. So we'll go ahead and run this.
One of the things I like about grid view in PowerShell 5 is you can do a Ctrl+ and make it larger.
It'll tell you exactly what happened, that there's resources. You can see here are the
PowerShellAccessControl when it was successfully installed and it'll tell you the location,
and with PowerShell V5, you have a side by side versioning, so it puts it in a version folder,
but the same command I could run on a V4 machine and it would actually put it, it wouldn't create a version folder.
One thing I want you to notice
here is that it says the PowerShellAccessControl module was downloaded to this location C:\Windows\TEMP,
whatever this temp file is,
so every time you run this, you're resources that are being downloaded are being downloaded are being
downloaded into a temp file and that's not being cleaned up.
So if I go look at the temp file folder on the domain controller, you'll notice local time for me is 1:23 or 1:25 PM.
Two minutes ago, we had this temp file show up and you'll notice that I've got like 50 million of these
because I've run through this demo like 50 million times.
So unless I go up there and manually clean these up, then they're just going to keep building.
Okay, so what did we accomplish with that configuration? We actually created the SQL and the web SMB file share.
Not only did we create those, but we also set the security so that we have a SQL Server's global group in AD
that contains our SQL servers and that one has read access and then we also have a SQL admins group that
contains our SQL admins that can configure those servers.
So in this scenario, just imagine that we have three groups of people.
We've got the main admins who are doing the domain controllers, we got SQL admins that are doing the SQL servers,
and we've got web admins who are doing the web servers.