So yesterday, I saw Jeff's session about building, coming up with code to help you build other commands and
he had a really, really neat one where he took, he had a little GUI that you could create a command based on
you give it a CIM class and you could go in and pick the different properties that you want and it would spin
up a command for you that would just be easier to use than Get-CimInstance and with the CIM class and telling
it all the properties that you wanted.
So what we're going to do and this should look very familiar, so it's going to be almost exactly like the
previous one, except the reference scriptblock will actually be, well first let's look at, it might be easier
if we take a look at how we're going to define the command, so this will give you an idea of what the domain-specific
language will look like. So we're going to create a keyword. Instead of DynCommand, we're going to have
CimCommand and CimCommand will take a name and that's going to be the name of the function that we will create.
These probably aren't very good because it kind of looks like Get-CimInstance and all that, so you would
probably want to rename these. But we will allow inside the domain-specific language, you can give it 0 or more CimParameters.
So when you don't define any CimParameters like down here, it's going to actually use Get-CimClass to figure
out what all the parameters are and it'll allow all that stuff for you or it'll do all that work for you.
But if you do give it parameters, Get-CimService should only have two parameters that it will allow you to
filter on and two properties that come back on the objects that are output.
But you also tell it which CimClass you want, so the first two are going to use Win32_Service and the last
one is going to use Win32_Process. So that's what the domain-specific language is going to look like,
so we'll very, very briefly talk about what the---implementing the domain-specific language again looks very, very similar.
We make a CimCommand function that's going to act like a keyword.
We have a string and a scriptblock. When you look down in the process block, you'll see where just like with
the previous command, we take, we create a new parameter dictionary and then we invoke the definition and the
only things that or really would be valid inside the definition, well besides other valid PowerShell commands,
but the other domain-specific language constructs that would be valid inside there would be the CimClass and
the CimParameter keywords. CimParameter is going to do just like the previous parameter from last time would do
and CimClass is just going to take it and it'll optionally take a namespace, but this will take that
CommandInfo and add the CimClass and CimNamespace information there.
So after we've invoked that definition, we do a little bit of error checking.
You need to make sure that a CimClass was specified. If not, write an error and the command just won't get generated.
If it was, go ahead and, this is kind of, this has two purposes, we're going to Get-CimClass on and we're
going to check against that namespace and that actual class. We'll make sure it's valid.
If it's not, it's going to give us an error. But we'll use this CimClassInfo just in case the user didn't
give any parameters. So if there are no parameters, then we'll go through and call the CimParameter keyword
here for each parameter that Get-CimClass is aware of. And then of course, we define the function and export
the module member, so that leaves explaining what our ReferenceCommand does and this is where all the work
is going to happen whenever you use this method. So now, you notice our DynamicParam block is still really simple.
All that work was done when we built the command. But now if you look inside the process block, what this is
going to do, I'm not going to go line by line through it, but essentially what this does, we're going to create
a hash table that will be splatted to Get-CimInstance and we're going to take a look, I forgot to mention
that the reference command now has a parameter that we're defining, it will be on every one of the commands
generated from this called ComputerName.
This isn't a very good parameter to use because there probably are some CimClasses that have a property
called ComputerName, so you would, so I'm seeing, so maybe that's not a bad name to use.
(Audience comment) What's that?
We'll likely use the name.
Okay, so but that is something to think about. You may want to confirm that it's not going to be in a case
where you're allowing almost any kind of property, this could cause some kind of a conflict potentially.
But this is proof of concept code,
so we'll let it ride. But you can provide a ComputerName, so every one of these commands that get generated
will have that ComputerName. Think of it as a common parameter.
And so, we create a hash table and we take a look and then at that point, we also get the information out of
the CommandInfo hash table that's living in module scope, that should have a reference to every one of the
dynamic commands we created. And again, we use the key for that is the current command's name.
So we get that CimClass and let's see, then we go through each one of the parameters and we know that everybody
has a ComputerName, so if the parameter we're looking at is ComputerName, then we had ComputerName to those
Get-CimInstance params. We're going to end up splatting that hash table back to Get-CimInstance.
So if there's no ComputerName specified, it'll just run on the local system.
Then we go through every other parameter and we're going to just build a dynamic WQL statement.
And so, we have a little bit of logic there that checks to see the type of the parameter, if it's a string,
this is something you would definitely want to work on more. It's not going to be very resilient,
but right now it just looks, if it's a string, then it's going to quote it and it's going to change the
operator to like and then it'll end up, and this is to build the WHERE clause, so if the user doesn't provide
any parameters, then it's just going to call it without any WHERE clause, there would be no where conditions.
So then down here is where it actually takes, it looks at all of the parameters that are valid for this thing
that are all of the dynamic parameters and then it ends up just building a select statement and from the
CimClass and it does not, so yeah I just now realized this, this isn't taking the namespace into account.
So yeah, don't do anything outside of Root CIM v2 right now. But then it takes our CimInstance param hash
table that we defined earlier, it adds this to the query parameter and then it just splats that to Get-CimInstance.
So let's read this in and see if it works. So if we Get-Module or Get-Command -Module $DynamicModule,
you can see that we have our three commands. Remember Get-CimService, the first one, Get-Command
Get-CimService -Syntax, the first one only had we told it we wanted the state and the name, so that is all that's there.
If we call Get-CimService, you'll see. Now what's happening here, and as a matter of fact,
let's actually filter this real quick, so State is running. So you can see that we were able to,
it's working and it really is only returning name and state. It's PowerShell's formatting system is kicking in
and for a service if you did a normal Get-CimService or Get-CimInstance on Win32_Service, all of these
properties would be returned by default. We could very easily go back in and add these if we wanted to,
but the neat thing is Get-CimService2, that was the one that we actually we told it to just let it put all
the valid parameters in there. So we should be able to come in and do something like where -State is stopped,
oop, hold on, something else you might want to do is transform the parameters as they're put in so that you
replace asterisks with the WQL and SQL wildcard. But you can say where it's stopped and start mode is auto select,
so and let's actually take that and run it against local host. And so you can see that you can take this
command that we spun up with just a few lines of code. I mean behind the scenes it took a decent amount of work,
but we were able to with just, what was that three lines of code for the actual command definition down here,
with that we were able to have a command generated that we can perform filtering, we can perform it against
any number of machines that we would like. And there is one more thing I wanted to show before we move on
and that is if we come back in this reference scriptblock and this is just to kind of, this is like an idea,
maybe you get an idea of you want IntelliSense to be added for some of the properties, so that kind of gets
back to that idea of you make improvements and you want to use them so that every command gets to come along
for the ride. So when we look somewhere I define the CimParameter, there it is.
So inside the CimParameter, I have this commented out because it's actually pretty inefficient because
there's not very many properties that fit on this, but what we're going to do is every parameter that comes
through, we're going to add an argument completer attribute on it, and inside the argument attribute,
it's a whole bunch of, and to be honest, it's only going to work on certain properties.
What we end up doing is using Get-CimClass to look up whatever the current class is and it looks for any
properties that have a qualifier, a value map, which I think and it appears to work.
It's kind of WMIs way of having, telling you what the valid values are.
So we just uncommented that. That kind of mimics adding that functionality and now we can call Get-CimService
and we look at State and you can see that we now have IntelliSense added to it.
So that was Get-CimService. It's the same way with Get-CimService2.
State, well status has it as well, I guess. Let's see the StartMode, I don't remember, yep, StartMode.
So you get IntelliSense for, this made it essentially for anything that has that value map qualifier and we
never did look at Get-CimProcess, but it's there too. So anyway, I don't know, does that look like it could
be useful for anything?
Yeah.
Alright.
Absolutely.