The very first thing we're going to do is we're going to make a little module that will allow us to just build
dynamic commands that don't do much of anything, but we will go over how to, that concept of building a
reference script block
and then having all the other command and having that reference script block be smart enough to know to do something different.
I mean, obviously if you make two commands that have the exact same definition, it sounds like they're going
to do the same thing, and so why is that useful?
So our first module we're going to make, we're going to set this up, let's see, can everybody see that?
I'll zoom in a little bit. Alright, so first thing you're going to see, we're not going to actually create
modules that are on disk, but this is going to behave exactly. If you were to write all this stuff that's
inside these braces to a file and then call Import-Module, it does the exact same thing.
There's nothing special about this. This is just an in-memory dynamic module.
But again, if you were to take this, write it to a file, and call Import-Module on it, it's going to do the
exact same thing. This is just so I don't have to switch between files.
Alright, so our first one you'll see that inside this module we're going to define our reference command and
this is going to be the thing that we'll go in and tweak as we want to add more functionality.
And our, this is kind of our Hello World example. All this is going to do is call Write-Host and it's going
to say I'm the whatever the command name is command. Useless function, but the more important part here is
how we're going to spin these commands up. So we're going to create a little, like a little miniature
domain-specific language. We're going to have this function called DynCommand.
It will act as a keyword, right. So you see that it will take a CommandName in and it's going to take a
scope right now. This is more to kind of, I'm going to show you one of the pitfalls to doing this.
At first, when you create this, you're probably not going to want to play with the scope on this, but all DynCommand
is going to do is take the CommandName and then it's going to take that ReferenceCommand, it's going to
create a new function and it's going to use whatever scope you have there.
By default, is going to use the script scope and that's honestly and truly the one you do want to use,
but again, I'm going to show you one of the early pitfalls I came across.
And then it's going to call Export-ModuleMember. So this function, well let's import this real quick,
and we have DynamicModule, so we should be able to call, whoop, no I guess we can't do that.
Get-Command -Module. At some point IntelliSense will kick in. Yeah, so you can see it has one command
that's exported right now that's called DynCommand. So if we call it and try to create a command called Command1,
let's do this, so if you take a look at the exported commands, you can see Command1 is listed and then you
have, we still have remember DynCommand that was also exported, but there is a problem.
If we call Get-Command on command1, you'll see that it can't find it.
So if we create a command and put it in the global scope, again, you're not going to want to do this,
but and I'll explain what's going on here in just a second, and then take a look at the exported commands,
you'll see that this Command2 isn't listed in the exported commands from this module, but if you call
Get-Command, you do see it there, right. Now Command1, remember we don't have it here, but if we were to
actually call inside that dynamic module scope, it is in there. It did truly create a function, but it was
in that script scope. So what's happening here
is when the module is imported and when we're calling new module there, it's the same steps that are occurring.
When the module is imported, there's some special logic that it comes through and realizes hey, I have this
list of commands that need to be exported and it's smart enough to realize whether or not it's a nested
module and those need to be hidden from global scope or whether or not it's a, those functions are supposed
to truly be exported into global scope and it handles that for you.
If you try to go in like we did a second ago
and do this, you'll see that it wasn't listed as an exported function from the module and it is truly in the global scope.
If you tried to call this as a nested module, it would come out into the global scope and you probably don't want that.
So the whole point of that exercise there was to show that we probably, you'll probably want to keep that
dynamic command keyword inside the module scope and not expose it and as long as you call it inside the
module, you're fine. So that's why in the database examples that I was showing you saw that inside the module
I was calling the commands there. It's not if you, this doesn't really work very well for allowing someone
to at the command line create something, and to be honest, I don't know that there's much reason to do that.
So we'll look at this and this is exactly the same. We had the exact same reference command.
The only difference between this module and the previous one is that we call the DynCommand keyword inside the module.
So we'll import this module. So we'll import this module in. If we take a look at what's exported,
instead of Command2, I created one called AnotherCommand, but you'll see that those are both exported, so that's good.
We can call Get-Command on it. That works. If we actually call these commands, that works too.
But again, this doesn't do anything useful. They do technically do something different, but they're not
doing anything that is useful. And as a matter of fact, they're still very similar.
They have the same command syntax, which is they just take common parameters.
I would show you the other command, but it's going to look just like that.
There's no point. So the next step on here and then after this, I promise we will do something that has potential use.
The next thing I want to do is show how you can make the ReferenceCommand scriptblock smart enough to
actually present itself as a command with different parameters and how you can make it actually do something
so that the commands can differentiate themselves. So if you look here, we have our ReferenceCommand again
and the difference here, so we still write to the screen and say which command we're coming from, we're also going
to output the BoundParameters. So other than that, the process block is exactly the same.
The big difference is, oh and I did skip over one thing. One thing that's different between this module and the
previous one is that we're going to create a hash table that will live just in module scope and this is going
to contain whatever command metadata that we want to have and the reference scriptblock is going to be smart
enough to go look into that and figure out how it needs to behave differently.
So the easiest way to get the syntax to be different and to have different parameters is to just use dynamic parameters.
It's not the only way that those database readers weren't using dynamic parameters, but that's going to be
the easiest way to do it. And all this is doing is this is looking into that CommandInfo hash table up here
and it's just depending on a dynamic parameter dictionary to already be present and to be returned.
So we will make a change. Now we're going to actually change our dynamic command function here, so we'll still
take a CommandName, but we'll also take a scriptblock that's going to be the definition and all we're going
to do is end up invoking this, but we need a way to, when we create the command, we need a way to tell it to added
parameters to it. So inside here, we're going to create just another function and this way you can't
accidentally call this parameter keyword outside the scope of the dynamic command.
But all this thing is going to do is it will take a ParameterType, a ParameterName, and a set of parameter attributes.
And then it's going to do what the work you normally you have happen inside a DynamicParam block and create
a dynamic parameter and it will put it into this same CommandInfo hash table that was defined above.
It's going to add the dynamic parameter into the dictionary up there and in the process block of the dynamic
command keyword, this is new, so this is where when it first starts to execute, it's going to create an empty
runtime define parameter dictionary, then it's going to execute the code inside the scriptblock,
which is where the parameters will be defined. Alright, so now if we have our Command1 and Command2,
what we're doing here is telling it we're going to create a new command, we're going to call it Command1,
and Command1 is going to have a single parameter, it's going to be a string, and we'll name it Parameter1.
Dynamic command. Then we'll make another dynamic command. We'll call it Command2 and it's going to have 3 parameters.
The first one is going to be an integer. It's going to be called Id.
It will have two attributes. One is a parameter attribute. We're going to make it mandatory and put it inside
of a ParameterSet and the other one is a ValidateSet. Then we will have a name parameter that's a string.
It's going to be in a different ParameterSet, and this is just to kind of show you can give it any attributes
you'd like, and then we're going to create just a generic object parameter that's going to be an object of,
it'll take objects and it'll be named object. I'm simple. Oops.
So we'll read that in and if you take a look at the syntax, you will see in just a second that Command1 and
Command2 do indeed have different syntaxes. Command1 has our first parameter, just the single parameter,
well, hold on, along with the other common parameters, but you can feed something to it, and Command2 has 2
and you can see up there where it does have 2 ParameterSets, so the syntax is showing correctly.
And again, this doesn't do anything, let's do Id because it had a ValidateSet, but shows that we were able to
spin up two commands that do completely or that have different signatures, I guess.
So let's take that and actually try to apply it to something that could be potentially of use.