So my name's Rohn Edwards, and today I'm going to talk about Building Modules using Metaprogramming.
So what do I mean when we're I say we're going to be talking about building modules with metaprogramming?
Actually, I don't quite know what that means, but it sounded like a really good word, but.
Now metaprogramming if you look up the
definition, I think it's the writing of computer programs that have the ability to treat other programs as their data.
It's also known as programs that write other programs, right. So what I'm mostly going to focus on is kind of
a method of making modules that I started using to improve some old commands that I had where there was a lot
of code reuse. We're going to, to get the concept, we'll talk conceptually what I'm talking about in just a second,
but before we actually get started talking about that, I want to demo what I'm talking about.
It's kind of hard to wrap your head around, so we will start with a very quick demo.
So if I look, if I Get-Module, I have two modules here called, one called the AdventureWorksReader and one
called the NorthwindReader. And so these modules have, they just have three commands.
The first one has one command that's exported Get-AwDemographics, the other one is NwCustomer and Get-NwEmployee.
So the Northwind and AdventureWorks databases obviously are just like database people use when they're
learning how to read SQL statements or create SQL statements to read out of a database.
But if we take a look at the syntax of, let's look at the AwDemographics one.
So you can see we have some parameters here. It looks like first name/last name and if we take a look at
NwCustomer, so we have different parameters from there. This will be important in just a second.
We can take a look at the help on Get-NwCustomer and if you take a look, it actually has a synopsis and a description.
They don't mean anything to you. I put it in just to kind of demo that we're getting help out of these
commands and again this will make sense in just a minute. We have some parameters that have help.
There were a lot of parameters. I didn't want to put help on all of them, but you can see CompanyName
and ContactName have help associated with them. So if we go to use these, the purpose of these commands is
to generate dynamic SQL statements to read out of the database, so we can do something like for the
AwDemographics, FirstName starts with an a. Let's just select the first 5, I guess.
So we're pulling data out of the AdventureWorks database. I don't know if it's actually anything that's
completely useful, but we can filter on multiple things, things like let's see Education, I think high school
is something that you can filter on there. We can come---you know there's---I don't know if you noticed
there was a GroupBy and an OrderBy common parameter between the two modules and the functions we were looking at.
So we can---you notice we have some IntelliSense here and we can do a GroupBy, let's GroupBy the Education
and Gender maybe. So you can see that behind the scenes it's generating this dynamic SQL and that's not a big deal.
There's a log of modules that can do this kind of stuff. What is, I think, kind of neat is if we look at the
way these modules were actually built. So here's the NorthwindReader and you can see that it's calling
another script, but here's how these commands are actually defined.
So this first one's about 50 lines it looks like. So you come in, you can look that that's where that help
we were looking at is coming from, but all this has is a param block.
Actually, let's do this. The only thing that this, and you notice instead of function, we have this keyword,
I guess, I put that in air quotes called DbReaderCommand, this little domain-specific language, but we give
this keyword and we give the function name and then you'll also see these fake attributes.
Right now they just say magic in front of them so that I can tell that they're fake, but that combined with a
real param block with help mixed in with those parameters and that's it.
That param block is enough to build that command that we saw, oh and we didn't actually, I did not demo Get-NwEmployee.
So if you look here, we actually have formatting in there. If you take a look at, send that to format list,
you'll see more is coming across than what we get by default. So let's go back and look at the Get-NwEmployee.
You'll see that mixed in with these fake attributes, you have this FormatTableColumn.
So putting one of those in is enough to tell it that we're going to want this in a view and we want that
and behind the scenes it's generating some formatting ps1 XML files and adding all that.
So this isn't, I'm not really so much
trying to demonstrate these modules. It's more the concept behind why what we're going to kind of cover is useful.
Alright, so
why would you want to do that? Hopefully, after demoing that a little bit, it starts to kind of become a
little bit clear. Right, so what those commands were doing, let me start with the precursor to this module.
Years and years ago, about four years ago, I started making commands to look into the SCCM database at work.
SCCM has an amazing amount of information and so I started out, I think the first command I made was like
Get-SCCM computer so that I could look at relevant information on a computer.
I could search by a name, by an IP address, by a specific model number.
I could look for computers that hadn't checked in a certain amount of time.
And so, I spent a lot of time, I made a nice param block and inside the function I made logic that I could
map all that stuff together. I spent a good amount of time and I made what I thought was a very useful command.
And then I wanted more information out of there. So I came up with another SQL statement that I thought was very useful.
I chopped it up. I copied the original command, generated a new command, based off of that, I went in and
changed everything that I needed to do. Within 10 minutes, I was able to have another very useful command.
Fast forward 10 months, a year, and I have 20 commands that I've built up, but over time, each one of those
commands are a little bit different and I added more functionality to some of them.
As you saw there, we had the ability to do a GroupBy and an OrderBy.
So maybe the first command I didn't think of that and I didn't think of the ability to do a negation, to be able
to negate a specific parameter that came in. But 20 commands in, maybe I have added that functionality.
And now I have 19 commands that I have to kind of go back and port that functionality into and I don't have time
to do that kind of thing. So I had on my to-do list for a very long time a way, I needed to come up with a
way to make it, that I didn't have to go back and do that. I wanted to make kind of an engine so that I could
use the same exact code for each module or for each function and have it, by doing that, I was able to,
if I came across a bug, I could fix it in one place, and then reimport the module, and all the bugs were fixed.
If I wanted to add functionality, I could fix it in one place and all the commands could come along for the ride.
And the only work that's left after you do that is to come up with that the command definition that we had,
which as you can see there again, that was just essentially a param block.
That was very, very, very easy I guess you call it a domain-specific language.
So anyway, it takes code reuse kind of to the extreme and instead of having commands that generate static
code that I can then save, I can just edit things on the fly and then import them.
So it's definitely, it's probably really only useful in certain scenarios.
I have a couple of code examples. We're not going to kind of cover how all that works because honestly and
truly, the behind the scenes of that is pretty ugly right now. It's really big and clunky, but I do have a
couple of examples I think that could be useful. They're very, and I think they're simple enough that we can
kind of go through how to build the first one so because I'm sure somebody else can kind of take these same
techniques and come up with something better than, you know I can.