Next, I'm going to move onto doing this without a domain-specific language.
This was an idea I had. I was trying to think of different uses for this and
I came up with something that I don't know how useful this would actually be, but a lot of times I've tried to
create little bitty miniature WPF user interfaces and first of all, there's a module, I think, that kind of
does this stuff, Show-UI. I haven't used it myself and this almost definitely is not going to be better
than that, so definitely go check that out. But what I've done because my interfaces are pretty simple,
I'll use the XAML, and I'll have it read that in, and then I'll have to go in, and find whatever controls I'm
looking for, and attach whatever events I want and I was wondering if there was any way
you could use this to build a module that would allow you to make WPF user interfaces.
So we're going to try that. Now again, this should look pretty similar.
In this instance we're going to have, here's our hash table for command names.
This is going to kind of be like the command info before, but we're going to actually just let PowerShell use
Reflection to try to take a look at the different parameters to use for our WPF commands that are generated.
So in this case, we're going to have, let's take a look at the reference scriptblock.
This time around, the DynamicParam block isn't quite as simple and I'll go ahead and spoil this for you.
What's it's doing is in a little bit I'll show you where it's going to write, it's going to look for every
single WPF UI element, which I believe is the base class for all of the visual, the elements in WPF that you would use.
It's going to take every one of those and create a new function based off of those and inside that CommandName,
it's just going to store whatever name you used and whatever the type is.
Now that makes it so if you want, you can add prefixes to your CommandNames or something like that.
Then it's going to come through and here's where it uses reflection.
It takes that type and it gets a list of all the public properties and then it ends up taking a look and if
the public property has a public setter, then it's going to make that, that's going to be a valid parameter
that you can use. It also takes a look to see if that property has an Add method attached.
If it doesn't have a public setter, but it does have an Add method and that Add method takes a single argument,
then it will allow that to be a parameter as well and we'll have logic inside the process block that will fix all that.
Here's where it actually generates the parameter and then it does the exact same thing for public events.
So what we should end up with is like if we have a WPF window, we'll have a command called window and we're
going to have a whole bunch of parameters, anything that is a public property or a public event that can be
set, we will have that available to us as a parameter. And then here's the actual code that's going to
happen when everything's run. It's going to, it will go through each one of the properties that you've defined.
First it will create an instance of itself, let's see that must have been up here or right there.
Yeah, so it's aware of what its type is, and so it will actually create an instance of itself and then it's
going to go through each one of those properties and we already checked to make sure it could have some,
it could be set or if it's a collection it could be added to. So then the big foreach block here,
goes through each one of the properties, and does that. And here's the part where it takes that reference
scriptblock and associates it with each one. So let's see, we have, we'll take a look at the amount of code
this is, so from Line 11 to 175, so a little over 160 lines of code, we'll take that and first, let's take a
look at how many commands we have. So with a 160 lines of code, we made 181 commands.
So things like, well let's take a look at Button and this isn't going to be pretty.
I'm going to warn you. So yeah, this isn't something where you're going to use the help system to try to
help you take a look. Yeah, I mean, you're going to want to go to online help for this, but what's neat
about this, if you've ever written anything in XAML from PowerShell without help, which is actually not that bad,
but it's, I'm going to just kind of retype what we have here because I want to show you that as you're writing
you get should be IntelliSense title, so you can do all that stuff.
So we have something here that it kind of resembles XAML without all the extra XML stuff on it.
Now what this is saying is we're going to create a window and inside the window, now this is I don't like
this part right now. We have to know that the actual property that contains the, in XAML you would just have a
window opening tag, a window closing tag, and in the middle you would put the stuff you want.
Right now, we're having to say Content, then we create a stack panel, and for stack panel, instead of content,
we're having to say Children. But one thing that's kind of neat with that very, very simple code we're able
to, this is kind of a weird syntax right here, but what I'm telling it is create a text box, assign it to the
text variable and then output that. So you can in PowerShell if you were to do something like a = 1 and wrap
that in parentheses, it will do the assignment and then also output what it is.
So what this is saying, this is like saying create this text box, but we're also getting a handle to it so
that we can, and here for the button, oh and I need to fix that, I was supposed to go in and show you how in
the module, right now the events don't have a prefix. There was a little variable at the beginning of the
dynamic module where I could add a prefix, so right now we have Button -Click somewhere, but anyway.
So we're able to add an event handler in line in PowerShell like this.
Again, the only way I've known how to do this if you do everything from PowerShell before is you create your
XAML, you have to read that in, and then you have to kind of walk through, you could assign it a name,
but then you have to go search for that and get that and attach the event later.
So with any luck, hopefully this won't crash because that does happen occasionally.
All this is doing is set up so you can say put a message here, you can type Show Message and you can see that
it did truly, it was able to read that and we could attach that event handler in line.
Now, the biggest problems I kind of have with this right now are the fact that I had to do that.
Normally, when you're using XAML, you can just give it a name and then you can reference everything by that name later.
So we're going to try to make it so we can do that. The other problem is I don't like how we have to know
again that I would rather just be able to say window and then at some point have an open curly brace and a
closed curly brace and have all that stuff in the middle. And WPF is really, it's really kind of cool.
There is metadata associated with all of these different elements, so you can come in and look at the window
type and go to Get-CustomAttributes and we'll tell it that we want to look at the attributes that were inherited.
So you can take a look, oh actually we're running low on time. So what we're going to do now, we're going to
make a couple improvements to that, alright, so the two big improvements are going to be we're going to make
it so we can use the name parameter and it will automatically make a variable for us and we don't have to
worry about it. And we're also going to make it to where you don't have to know about that content in that.
If you still want to use that syntax, that's fine. So I won't bore you too much with the details.
I'll just show you that it definitely is possible. Our code, we have several more lines of code, except now it's
over 200, but now we can, I do want to show one thing here. Let's copy this instead of running it directly.
Let's do this and before, so text box is still yeah, so text box is there because we did that earlier.
Alright, let's run that again, and so now if you look here, so we called text box and we didn't have to do
that weird assignment thing. We were able to just say the name is going to be text box.
And if you come and look, text box is not in the global scope. We don't want it in the global scope.
That's going to get real noisy and real messy. If you look, what I was able to do there is to add a dynamically,
like a dynamic module that's attached to that window object and if we try to run this, you'll see that the
text box lives inside that scope, so it shouldn't affect anybody and it should still, ShowDialog,
this should still work and it does. So now you can have events that are completely in line.
You define text box there and then you can use it down here. Also, if you looked, we didn't have to do the
content, it was aware of. It knows that a Windows default content property is called content and it lets you do that.
The next problem with this is if I try to add like something with a grid, so in XAML you have to have,
there's a concept of something called an attached property. A stack panel, or so like if you have a button
inside of a grid, that button doesn't have a concept of the row or column it belongs to in a grid or in a dock
panel which one of those it belongs to, so you use what's called an attached property.
So right now, I can't really specify one of those. If I were to come in and try to type Button -grid.row,
which is kind of what the XAML stuff would look like, it's not going to let me do that.
I can't create a dynamic parameter to do that. It turns out though with a little bit of trickery with that,
you can end up, if you create a parameter, like a catch-all parameter that will allow all that stuff to come
through, and we're just going to skip to the very, very end and run this.
Oh, let's see. So you can end up with something that looks like this.
This will work, hold on, the big thing I want to demo, so this is attached properties, right.
So Grid.ColumnProperty, ColumnSpanProperty, right. So we're able to with a couple of extra lines of code,
now we can start doing attached properties. You have this is what is called an attached event, so we have a
combo box and a combo box itself doesn't have a text changed event, but it does have a, it comes from
somewhere along the line I think it inherits from a text box base, which does have a text box event or a text change event.
So anyway, just to show that this kind of works we can run that and hopefully it won't crash, don't crash.
There we go. So and this was, I didn't really describe what it was going to do, but it's a silly thing just
to show that it did assign everything to the right columns and again we had inline events that we were able
to attach, so we can come in and grab something from here and it should change what's in that right span over there.
Yep, because so. Anyway so that's it. Thank you. Any questions?
When's your code going to be available?
I will put it up right after this. It's going to be on GitHub, Rohn@ as a matter of fact, hold on,
get this captured. So github.com/rohnedwards and if you need to contact me, Twitter @ magicrohn.